<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Aggrenox" setid="938ab0b5-8377-404a-8f61-5c630bda5932">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
Hypersensitivity to any product ingredients (4.1)  Patients with known allergy to NSAIDs (4.2)  Patients with the syndrome of asthma, rhinitis, and nasal polyps (4.2)           AGGRENOX is contraindicated in patients with known hypersensitivity to any of the product components.          Aspirin is contraindicated in patients with known allergy to nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drug products and in patients with the syndrome of asthma, rhinitis, and nasal polyps. Aspirin may cause severe urticaria, angioedema or bronchospasm.          Do not use aspirin in children or teenagers with viral infections because of the risk of Reye syndrome.</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
AGGRENOX is not interchangeable with the individual components of aspirin and dipyridamole tablets.    The recommended dose of AGGRENOX is one capsule given orally twice daily, one in the morning and one in the evening. Swallow capsules whole without chewing. AGGRENOX can be administered with or without food.       One capsule twice daily (morning and evening) with or without food (2)  In case of intolerable headaches during initial treatment, switch to one capsule at bedtime and low-dose aspirin in the morning; resume BID dosing within one week (2)  Do not chew capsule (2)    Not interchangeable with the individual components of aspirin and dipyridamole tablets   (2)  Dispense in this unit-of-use container (16)           In the event of intolerable headaches during initial treatment, switch to one capsule at bedtime and low-dose aspirin in the morning. Because there are no outcome data with this regimen and headaches become less of a problem as treatment continues, patients should return to the usual regimen as soon as possible, usually within one week.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
Co-administration with anticoagulants, antiplatelets, or NSAIDS can increase risk of bleeding (7.1)  Decreased renal function can occur with co-administration with NSAIDS (7.1)            Adenosine Dipyridamole has been reported to increase the plasma levels and cardiovascular effects of adenosine. Adjustment of adenosine dosage may be necessary.  Angiotensin Converting Enzyme (ACE) Inhibitors Due to the indirect effect of aspirin on the renin-angiotensin conversion pathway, the hyponatremic and hypotensive effects of ACE inhibitors may be diminished by concomitant administration of aspirin.  Acetazolamide Concurrent use of aspirin and acetazolamide can lead to high serum concentrations of acetazolamide (and toxicity) due to competition at the renal tubule for secretion.  Anticoagulants and Antiplatelets Patients taking AGGRENOX in combination with anticoagulants, antiplatelets, or any substance impacting coagulation are at increased risk for bleeding. Aspirin can displace warfarin from protein binding sites, leading to prolongation of both the prothrombin time and the bleeding time. Aspirin can increase the anticoagulant activity of heparin, increasing bleeding risk.  Anticonvulsants Salicylic acid can displace protein-bound phenytoin and valproic acid, leading to a decrease in the total concentration of phenytoin and an increase in serum valproic acid levels.  Beta Blockers The hypotensive effects of beta blockers may be diminished by the concomitant administration of aspirin due to inhibition of renal prostaglandins, leading to decreased renal blood flow and salt and fluid retention.  Cholinesterase Inhibitors Dipyridamole may counteract the anticholinesterase effect of cholinesterase inhibitors, thereby potentially aggravating myasthenia gravis.  Diuretics The effectiveness of diuretics in patients with underlying renal or cardiovascular disease may be diminished by the concomitant administration of aspirin due to inhibition of renal prostaglandins, leading to decreased renal blood flow and salt and fluid retention.  Methotrexate Salicylate can inhibit renal clearance of methotrexate, leading to bone marrow toxicity, especially in the elderly or renal impaired.  Nonsteroidal Anti-Inflammatory Drugs (NSAIDs) The concurrent use of aspirin with other NSAIDs may increase bleeding or lead to decreased renal function.  Oral Hypoglycemics Moderate doses of aspirin may increase the effectiveness of oral hypoglycemic drugs, leading to hypoglycemia.  Uricosuric Agents (probenecid and sulfinpyrazone) Salicylates antagonize the uricosuric action of uricosuric agents.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
AGGRENOX increases the risk of bleeding (5.1)  Avoid use in patients with severe hepatic or renal insufficiency (5.2, 5.3)  Can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman, especially in the third trimester (5.4)            AGGRENOX increases the risk of bleeding. Risk factors for bleeding include the use of other drugs that increase the risk of bleeding (e.g., anticoagulants, antiplatelet agents, heparin, fibrinolytic therapy, and chronic use of NSAIDs) [see Drug Interactions (7.1) ].   Intracranial Hemorrhage  In ESPS2 the incidence of intracranial hemorrhage was 0.6% in the AGGRENOX group, 0.5% in the extended-release dipyridamole (ER-DP) group, 0.4% in the aspirin (ASA) group and 0.4% in the placebo groups.   Gastrointestinal (GI) Side Effects  GI side effects include stomach pain, heartburn, nausea, vomiting, and gross GI bleeding. Although minor upper GI symptoms, such as dyspepsia, are common and can occur anytime during therapy, physicians should remain alert for signs of ulceration and bleeding, even in the absence of previous GI symptoms. Inform patients about the signs and symptoms of GI side effects and what steps to take if they occur. In ESPS2 the incidence of gastrointestinal bleeding was 4.1% in the AGGRENOX group, 2.2% in the extended-release dipyridamole group, 3.2% in the aspirin group, and 2.1% in the placebo groups.    Peptic Ulcer Disease  Avoid using aspirin in patients with a history of active peptic ulcer disease, which can cause gastric mucosal irritation and bleeding.   Alcohol Warning  Because AGGRENOX contains aspirin, counsel patients who consume three or more alcoholic drinks every day about the bleeding risks involved with chronic, heavy alcohol use while taking aspirin.          Avoid aspirin in patients with severe renal failure (glomerular filtration rate less than 10 mL/minute) [ see Use in Specific Populations (8.6) and Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ].          Elevations of hepatic enzymes and hepatic failure have been reported in association with dipyridamole administration [ see Use in Specific Populations (8.6) and Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ].          Because AGGRENOX contains aspirin, AGGRENOX can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. Maternal aspirin use during later stages of pregnancy may cause low birth weight, increased incidence for intracranial hemorrhage in premature infants, stillbirths and neonatal death. Because of the above and because of the known effects of nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) on the fetal cardiovascular system (closure of the ductus arteriosus), avoid AGGRENOX in the third trimester of pregnancy [ see Use in Specific Populations (8.1)  ]. Aspirin has been shown to be teratogenic in rats (spina bifida, exencephaly, microphthalmia and coelosomia) and rabbits (congested fetuses, agenesis of skull and upper jaw, generalized edema with malformation of the head, and diaphanous skin) at oral doses of 330 mg/kg/day and 110 mg/kg/day, respectively. These doses, which also resulted in a high resorption rate in rats (63% of implantations versus 5% in controls), are, on a mg/m2 basis, about 66 and 44 times, respectively, the dose of aspirin contained in the maximum recommended daily human dose of AGGRENOX. Reproduction studies with dipyridamole have been performed in mice, rabbits and rats at oral doses of up to 125 mg/kg, 40 mg/kg and 1000 mg/kg, respectively (about 1½, 2 and 25 times the maximum recommended daily human oral dose, respectively, on a mg/m2 basis) and have revealed no evidence of harm to the fetus due to dipyridamole. When 330 mg aspirin/kg/day was combined with 75 mg dipyridamole/kg/day in the rat, the resorption rate approached 100%, indicating potentiation of aspirin-related fetal toxicity. There are no adequate and well-controlled studies of the use of AGGRENOX in pregnant women. If AGGRENOX is used during pregnancy, or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking AGGRENOX, inform the patient of the potential hazard to the fetus.          Dipyridamole has a vasodilatory effect. Chest pain may be precipitated or aggravated in patients with underlying coronary artery disease who are receiving dipyridamole. For stroke or TIA patients for whom aspirin is indicated to prevent recurrent myocardial infarction (MI) or angina pectoris, the aspirin in this product may not provide adequate treatment for the cardiac indications.          Dipyridamole produces peripheral vasodilation, which can exacerbate pre-existing hypotension.          AGGRENOX capsules are not interchangeable with the individual components of aspirin and dipyridamole tablets.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
The antithrombotic action of AGGRENOX is the result of the additive antiplatelet effects of dipyridamole and aspirin.          Dipyridamole  Dipyridamole inhibits the uptake of adenosine into platelets, endothelial cells and erythrocytes  in vitro and  in vivo ; the inhibition occurs in a dose-dependent manner at therapeutic concentrations (0.5–1.9 µg/mL). This inhibition results in an increase in local concentrations of adenosine which acts on the platelet A2-receptor thereby stimulating platelet adenylate cyclase and increasing platelet cyclic-3',5'-adenosine monophosphate (cAMP) levels. Via this mechanism, platelet aggregation is inhibited in response to various stimuli such as platelet activating factor (PAF), collagen and adenosine diphosphate (ADP).  Dipyridamole inhibits phosphodiesterase (PDE) in various tissues. While the inhibition of cAMP-PDE is weak, therapeutic levels of dipyridamole inhibit cyclic-3',5'-guanosine monophosphate-PDE (cGMP-PDE), thereby augmenting the increase in cGMP produced by EDRF (endothelium-derived relaxing factor, now identified as nitric oxide).            Aspirin  Aspirin inhibits platelet aggregation by irreversible inhibition of platelet cyclooxygenase and thus inhibits the generation of thromboxane A2, a powerful inducer of platelet aggregation and vasoconstriction.            The effect of either agent on the other's inhibition of platelet reactivity has not been evaluated.          There are no significant interactions between aspirin and dipyridamole. The kinetics of the components are unchanged by their co-administration as AGGRENOX.          Dipyridamole    Absorption  Peak plasma levels of dipyridamole are achieved 2 hours (range 1–6 hours) after administration of a daily dose of 400 mg AGGRENOX (given as 200 mg BID). The peak plasma concentration at steady-state is 1.98 µg/mL (1.01–3.99 µg/mL) and the steady-state trough concentration is 0.53 µg/mL (0.18–1.01 µg/mL).   Effect of Food  When AGGRENOX capsules were taken with a high fat meal, dipyridamole peak plasma levels (Cmax) and total absorption (AUC) were decreased at steady-state by 20-30% compared to fasting. Due to the similar degree of inhibition of adenosine uptake at these plasma concentrations, this food effect is not considered clinically relevant.   Distribution  Dipyridamole is highly lipophilic (log P=3.71, pH=7); however, it has been shown that the drug does not cross the blood-brain barrier to any significant extent in animals. The steady-state volume of distribution of dipyridamole is about 92 L. Approximately 99% of dipyridamole is bound to plasma proteins, predominantly to alpha 1-acid glycoprotein and albumin.   Metabolism and Elimination  Dipyridamole is metabolized in the liver, primarily by conjugation with glucuronic acid, of which monoglucuronide which has low pharmacodynamic activity is the primary metabolite. In plasma, about 80% of the total amount is present as parent compound and 20% as monoglucuronide. Most of the glucuronide metabolite (about 95%) is excreted via bile into the feces, with some evidence of enterohepatic circulation. Renal excretion of parent compound is negligible and urinary excretion of the glucuronide metabolite is low (about 5%). With intravenous (i.v.) treatment of dipyridamole, a triphasic profile is obtained: a rapid alpha phase, with a half-life of about 3.4 minutes, a beta phase, with a half-life of about 39 minutes, (which, together with the alpha phase accounts for about 70% of the total area under the curve, AUC) and a prolonged elimination phase λz with a half-life of about 15.5 hours. Due to the extended absorption phase of the dipyridamole component, only the terminal phase is apparent from oral treatment with AGGRENOX which, in Trial 9.123 was 13.6 hours.   Special Populations     Geriatric Patients : In ESPS2 [ see Clinical Studies (14)  ], plasma concentrations (determined as AUC) of dipyridamole in healthy elderly subjects (&amp;gt;65 years) were about 40% higher than in subjects younger than 55 years receiving treatment with AGGRENOX.    Hepatic Dysfunction : No study has been conducted with AGGRENOX in patients with hepatic dysfunction. In a study conducted with an intravenous formulation of dipyridamole, patients with mild to severe hepatic insufficiency showed no change in plasma concentrations of dipyridamole but showed an increase in the pharmacologically inactive monoglucuronide metabolite. Dipyridamole can be dosed without restriction as long as there is no evidence of hepatic failure.   Renal Dysfunction : No study has been conducted with AGGRENOX in patients with renal dysfunction. In ESPS2 patients [ see Clinical Studies (14)  ], with creatinine clearances ranging from about 15 mL/min to &amp;gt;100 mL/min, no changes were observed in the pharmacokinetics of dipyridamole or its glucuronide metabolite if data were corrected for differences in age.            Aspirin    Absorption  Peak plasma levels of aspirin are achieved 0.63 hours (0.5–1 hour) after administration of a 50 mg aspirin daily dose from AGGRENOX (given as 25 mg BID). The peak plasma concentration at steady-state is 319 ng/mL (175–463 ng/mL). Aspirin undergoes moderate hydrolysis to salicylic acid in the liver and the gastrointestinal wall, with 50%–75% of an administered dose reaching the systemic circulation as intact aspirin.   Effect of Food  When AGGRENOX capsules were taken with a high fat meal, there was no difference for aspirin in AUC at steady-state, and the approximately 50% decrease in Cmax was not considered clinically relevant based on a similar degree of cyclooxygenase inhibition comparing the fed and fasted state.   Distribution  Aspirin is poorly bound to plasma proteins and its apparent volume of distribution is low (10 L). Its metabolite, salicylic acid, is highly bound to plasma proteins, but its binding is concentration-dependent (nonlinear). At low concentrations (&amp;lt;100 µg/mL), approximately 90% of salicylic acid is bound to albumin. Salicylic acid is widely distributed to all tissues and fluids in the body, including the central nervous system, breast milk, and fetal tissues. Early signs of salicylate overdose (salicylism), including tinnitus (ringing in the ears), occur at plasma concentrations approximating 200 µg/mL [ see Adverse Reactions (6) and Overdosage (10)  ].   Metabolism and Elimination  Aspirin is rapidly hydrolyzed in plasma to salicylic acid, with a half-life of 20 minutes. Plasma levels of aspirin are essentially undetectable 2–2.5 hours after dosing and peak salicylic acid concentrations occur 1 hour (range: 0.5–2 hours) after administration of aspirin. Salicylic acid is primarily conjugated in the liver to form salicyluric acid, a phenolic glucuronide, an acyl glucuronide, and a number of minor metabolites. Salicylate metabolism is saturable and total body clearance decreases at higher serum concentrations due to the limited ability of the liver to form both salicyluric acid and phenolic glucuronide. Following toxic doses (10–20 g), the plasma half-life may be increased to over 20 hours. The elimination of acetylsalicylic acid follows first-order kinetics with AGGRENOX and has a half-life of 0.33 hours. The half-life of salicylic acid is 1.71 hours. Both values correspond well with data from the literature at lower doses which state a resultant half-life of approximately 2–3 hours. At higher doses, the elimination of salicylic acid follows zero-order kinetics (i.e., the rate of elimination is constant in relation to plasma concentration), with an apparent half-life of 6 hours or higher. Renal excretion of unchanged drug depends upon urinary pH. As urinary pH rises above 6.5, the renal clearance of free salicylate increases from &amp;lt;5% to &amp;gt;80%. Alkalinization of the urine is a key concept in the management of salicylate overdose [ see Overdosage (10)  ]. Following therapeutic doses, about 10% is excreted as salicylic acid and 75% as salicyluric acid, as the phenolic and acyl glucuronides, in urine.   Special Populations    Hepatic Dysfunction : Avoid aspirin in patients with severe hepatic insufficiency.   Renal Dysfunction : Avoid aspirin in patients with severe renal failure (glomerular filtration rate less than 10 mL/min).  AGGRENOX  Drug Interaction A dedicated drug interaction study was conducted in 60 healthy volunteers to evaluate the effects of omeprazole 80 mg administered once daily on the pharmacokinetics (PK) of dipyridamole and the pharmacodynamics (PD) of acetylsalicylic acid when co-administered with AGGRENOX twice daily. Dipyridamole exposure (Cmax and AUC) at steady-state were similar with or without omeprazole co-administration. The pharmacokinetics of acetylsalicylic acid was not characterized. However, the antiplatelet activity as measured by arachidonic acid induced platelet aggregation was similar between the treatment arms at steady-state.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="7880" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Hypersensitivity to any product ingredients (4.1) Patients with known allergy to NSAIDs (4.2) Patients with the syndrome of asthma, rhinitis, and nasal polyps (4.2) AGGRENOX is contraindicated in patients with known hypersensitivity to any of the product components.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7881" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Aspirin is contraindicated in patients with known allergy to nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drug (NSAID) products and in patients with the syndrome of asthma, rhinitis, and nasal polyps.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7882" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Aspirin may cause severe urticaria, angioedema or bronchospasm.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7883" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Do not use aspirin in children or teenagers with viral infections because of the risk of Reye syndrome.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7884" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>AGGRENOX is not interchangeable with the individual components of aspirin and dipyridamole tablets.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7885" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommended dose of AGGRENOX is one capsule given orally twice daily, one in the morning and one in the evening.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7886" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>AGGRENOX can be administered with or without food.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7887" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>One capsule twice daily (morning and evening) with or without food (2) In case of intolerable headaches during initial treatment, switch to one capsule at bedtime and low-dose aspirin in the morning; resume BID dosing within one week (2) Do not chew capsule (2) Not interchangeable with the individual components of aspirin and dipyridamole tablets (2) Dispense in this unit-of-use container (16) In the event of intolerable headaches during initial treatment, switch to one capsule at bedtime and low-dose aspirin in the morning.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7888" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Because there are no outcome data with this regimen and headaches become less of a problem as treatment continues, patients should return to the usual regimen as soon as possible, usually within one week.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7889" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Co-administration with anticoagulants, antiplatelets, or NSAIDs can increase risk of bleeding (7.1) Decreased renal function can occur with co-administration with NSAIDs (7.1) Adenosine Dipyridamole has been reported to increase the plasma levels and cardiovascular effects of adenosine.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M1" type="Trigger" span="68 8;266 7" str="increase | effects"/>
<Mention id="M17" type="Precipitant" span="277 9" str="adenosine" code="K72T3FS567"/>
<Mention id="M3" type="SpecificInteraction" span="68 8;251 22" str="increase | cardiovascular effects" code="111970001: Abnormal cardiovascular function (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M13" type="Trigger" span="68 13" str="increase risk"/>
<Mention id="M5" type="Precipitant" span="23 14" str="anticoagulants" code="N0000175980"/>
<Mention id="M15" type="SpecificInteraction" span="85 8" str="bleeding" code="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M8" type="Precipitant" span="39 13" str="antiplatelets" code="N0000175578"/>
<Mention id="M10" type="Trigger" span="100 9;116 8" str="Decreased | function"/>
<Mention id="M14" type="Precipitant" span="57 6" str="NSAIDs" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M12" type="SpecificInteraction" span="-1 24" str="decreased renal function" code="76114004: Decreased renal function (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M16" type="Trigger" span="220 26" str="increase the plasma levels"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M1" precipitant="M17" effect="M3"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M13" precipitant="M5" effect="M15"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M13" precipitant="M8" effect="M15"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M10" precipitant="M14" effect="M12"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M13" precipitant="M14" effect="M15"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M16" precipitant="M17" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7890" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Adjustment of adenosine dosage may be necessary.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M18" type="Trigger" span="0 10;24 6" str="Adjustment | dosage"/>
<Mention id="M19" type="Precipitant" span="14 9" str="adenosine" code="K72T3FS567"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M18" precipitant="M19"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7891" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Angiotensin Converting Enzyme (ACE) Inhibitors Due to the indirect effect of aspirin on the renin-angiotensin conversion pathway, the hyponatremic and hypotensive effects of ACE inhibitors may be diminished by concomitant administration of aspirin.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M23" type="Trigger" span="163 7;196 10" str="effects | diminished"/>
<Mention id="M24" type="Precipitant" span="174 14" str="ACE inhibitors" code="N0000175562"/>
<Mention id="M22" type="SpecificInteraction" span="134 12;163 7;196 10" str="hyponatremic | effects | diminished" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M25" type="SpecificInteraction" span="151 19;196 10" str="hypotensive effects | diminished" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M23" precipitant="M24" effect="M22"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M23" precipitant="M24" effect="M25"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7892" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Acetazolamide Concurrent use of aspirin and acetazolamide can lead to high serum concentrations of acetazolamide (and toxicity) due to competition at the renal tubule for secretion.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M26" type="Trigger" span="135 11;167 13" str="competition | for secretion"/>
<Mention id="M31" type="Precipitant" span="44 13" str="acetazolamide" code="O3FX965V0I"/>
<Mention id="M28" type="SpecificInteraction" span="135 45" str="competition at the renal tubule for secretion" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M29" type="Trigger" span="70 25" str="high serum concentrations "/>
<Mention id="M30" type="Trigger" span="118 8" str=" toxicity"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M26" precipitant="M31" effect="M28"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M29;M30" precipitant="M31" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7893" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Anticoagulants and Antiplatelets Patients taking AGGRENOX in combination with anticoagulants, antiplatelets, or any substance impacting coagulation are at increased risk for bleeding.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M38" type="Trigger" span="155 14" str="increased risk"/>
<Mention id="M33" type="Precipitant" span="78 14" str="anticoagulants" code="N0000175980"/>
<Mention id="M40" type="SpecificInteraction" span="174 8" str="bleeding" code="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M36" type="Precipitant" span="94 13" str="antiplatelets" code="N0000175578"/>
<Mention id="M39" type="Precipitant" span="112 35" str="any substance impacting coagulation" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M38" precipitant="M33" effect="M40"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M38" precipitant="M36" effect="M40"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M38" precipitant="M39" effect="M40"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7894" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Aspirin can displace warfarin from protein binding sites, leading to prolongation of both the prothrombin time and the bleeding time.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M47" type="Trigger" span="69 12" str="prolongation"/>
<Mention id="M48" type="Precipitant" span="21 8" str="warfarin" code="5Q7ZVV76EI"/>
<Mention id="M43" type="SpecificInteraction" span="69 12;119 13" str="prolongation | bleeding time" code="123789000: Blood coagulation disorder with prolonged bleeding time (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M44" type="Trigger" span="12 8" str="displace"/>
<Mention id="M46" type="SpecificInteraction" span="12 44" str="displace warfarin from protein binding sites" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M49" type="SpecificInteraction" span="69 12;94 16" str="prolongation | prothrombin time" code="409674002: Prothrombin time increased (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M47" precipitant="M48" effect="M43"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M44" precipitant="M48" effect="M46"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M47" precipitant="M48" effect="M49"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7895" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Aspirin can increase the anticoagulant activity of heparin, increasing bleeding risk.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M50" type="Trigger" span="12 8;39 8" str="increase | activity"/>
<Mention id="M54" type="Precipitant" span="51 7" str="heparin" code="T2410KM04A"/>
<Mention id="M52" type="SpecificInteraction" span="12 35" str="increase the anticoagulant activity" code="10191004: Anticoagulant effect (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M53" type="Trigger" span="60 10;80 4" str="increasing | risk"/>
<Mention id="M55" type="SpecificInteraction" span="71 8" str="bleeding" code="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M50" precipitant="M54" effect="M52"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M53" precipitant="M54" effect="M55"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7896" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Anagrelide Patients taking aspirin in combination with anagrelide are at an increased risk of bleeding.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M56" type="Trigger" span="76 14" str="increased risk"/>
<Mention id="M57" type="Precipitant" span="55 10" str="anagrelide" code="K9X45X0051"/>
<Mention id="M58" type="SpecificInteraction" span="94 8" str="bleeding" code="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M56" precipitant="M57" effect="M58"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7897" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Anticonvulsants Salicylic acid can displace protein-bound phenytoin and valproic acid, leading to a decrease in the total concentration of phenytoin and an increase in serum valproic acid levels.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M62" type="Trigger" span="35 8" str="displace"/>
<Mention id="M66" type="Precipitant" span="58 9" str="phenytoin" code="6158TKW0C5"/>
<Mention id="M64" type="SpecificInteraction" span="35 22" str="displace protein-bound" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M68" type="Precipitant" span="72 13" str="valproic acid" code="614OI1Z5WI"/>
<Mention id="M65" type="Trigger" span="100 35" str="decrease in the total concentration"/>
<Mention id="M67" type="Trigger" span="156 17;188 6" str="increase in serum | levels"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M62" precipitant="M66" effect="M64"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M62" precipitant="M68" effect="M64"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M65" precipitant="M66" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M67" precipitant="M68" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7898" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Beta Blockers The hypotensive effects of beta blockers may be diminished by the concomitant administration of aspirin due to inhibition of renal prostaglandins, leading to decreased renal blood flow and salt and fluid retention.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M71" type="SpecificInteraction" span="125 34" str="inhibition of renal prostaglandins" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M79" type="Precipitant" span="41 13" str="beta blockers" code="N0000175556"/>
<Mention id="M78" type="Trigger" span="161 10" str="leading to"/>
<Mention id="M74" type="SpecificInteraction" span="203 24" str="salt and fluid retention" code="43498006: Body fluid retention (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M75" type="Trigger" span="30 7;62 10" str="effects | diminished"/>
<Mention id="M77" type="SpecificInteraction" span="18 19;62 10" str="hypotensive effects | diminished" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M80" type="SpecificInteraction" span="172 26" str="decreased renal blood flow" code="764268008: Inadequate peripheral blood flow (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M71" precipitant="M79" effect="M71"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M78" precipitant="M79" effect="M74"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M75" precipitant="M79" effect="M77"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M78" precipitant="M79" effect="M80"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7899" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Cholinesterase Inhibitors Dipyridamole may counteract the anticholinesterase effect of cholinesterase inhibitors, thereby potentially aggravating myasthenia gravis.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M81" type="Trigger" span="134 11" str="aggravating"/>
<Mention id="M85" type="Precipitant" span="87 25" str="cholinesterase inhibitors" code="N0000175723"/>
<Mention id="M83" type="SpecificInteraction" span="134 29" str="aggravating myasthenia gravis" code="91637004: Myasthenia gravis (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M84" type="Trigger" span="43 10;77 6" str="counteract | effect"/>
<Mention id="M86" type="SpecificInteraction" span="43 40" str="counteract the anticholinesterase effect" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I29" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M81" precipitant="M85" effect="M83"/>
<Interaction id="I30" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M84" precipitant="M85" effect="M86"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7900" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Diuretics The effectiveness of diuretics in patients with underlying renal or cardiovascular disease may be diminished by the concomitant administration of aspirin due to inhibition of renal prostaglandins, leading to decreased renal blood flow and salt and fluid retention.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M87" type="Trigger" span="171 10" str="inhibition"/>
<Mention id="M97" type="Precipitant" span="31 9" str="diuretics" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M89" type="SpecificInteraction" span="171 34" str="inhibition of renal prostaglandins" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M96" type="Trigger" span="207 10" str="leading to"/>
<Mention id="M92" type="SpecificInteraction" span="218 26" str="decreased renal blood flow" code="764268008: Inadequate peripheral blood flow (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M93" type="Trigger" span="14 13;108 10" str="effectiveness | diminished"/>
<Mention id="M95" type="SpecificInteraction" span="14 26;108 10" str="effectiveness of diuretics | diminished" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M98" type="SpecificInteraction" span="249 24" str="salt and fluid retention" code="43498006: Body fluid retention (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I31" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M87" precipitant="M97" effect="M89"/>
<Interaction id="I32" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M96" precipitant="M97" effect="M92"/>
<Interaction id="I33" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M93" precipitant="M97" effect="M95"/>
<Interaction id="I34" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M96" precipitant="M97" effect="M98"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7901" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Methotrexate Salicylate can inhibit renal clearance of methotrexate, leading to bone marrow toxicity, especially in the elderly or renal impaired.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M99" type="Trigger" span="69 10" str="leading to"/>
<Mention id="M104" type="Precipitant" span="55 12" str="methotrexate" code="YL5FZ2Y5U1"/>
<Mention id="M101" type="SpecificInteraction" span="80 20" str="bone marrow toxicity" code="127035006: Bone marrow disorder (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M102" type="Trigger" span="28 23" str="inhibit renal clearance "/>
<Mention id="M103" type="Trigger" span="92 8" str=" toxicity"/>
<Interaction id="I35" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M99" precipitant="M104" effect="M101"/>
<Interaction id="I36" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M102;M103" precipitant="M104" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7902" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Nonsteroidal Anti-Inflammatory Drugs (NSAIDs) The concurrent use of aspirin with other NSAIDs may increase bleeding or lead to decreased renal function.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M114" type="Trigger" span="98 8" str="increase"/>
<Mention id="M109" type="Precipitant" span="0 36" str="Nonsteroidal Anti-Inflammatory Drugs" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M116" type="SpecificInteraction" span="107 8" str="bleeding" code="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M111" type="Trigger" span="119 7" str="lead to"/>
<Mention id="M113" type="SpecificInteraction" span="127 24" str="decreased renal function" code="76114004: Decreased renal function (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M115" type="Precipitant" span="38 6" str="NSAIDs" code="N0000175722"/>
<Interaction id="I37" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M114" precipitant="M109" effect="M116"/>
<Interaction id="I38" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M111" precipitant="M109" effect="M113"/>
<Interaction id="I39" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M111" precipitant="M115" effect="M113"/>
<Interaction id="I40" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M114" precipitant="M115" effect="M116"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7903" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Oral Hypoglycemics Moderate doses of aspirin may increase the effectiveness of oral hypoglycemic drugs, leading to hypoglycemia.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M126" type="Trigger" span="49 26" str="increase the effectiveness"/>
<Mention id="M121" type="Precipitant" span="79 23" str="oral hypoglycemic drugs" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M128" type="SpecificInteraction" span="49 53" str="increase the effectiveness of oral hypoglycemic drugs" code="51798006: Decreased glucose level (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M123" type="Trigger" span="104 10" str="leading to"/>
<Mention id="M125" type="SpecificInteraction" span="115 12" str="hypoglycemia" code="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M127" type="Precipitant" span="0 18" str="Oral Hypoglycemics" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I41" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M126" precipitant="M121" effect="M128"/>
<Interaction id="I42" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M123" precipitant="M121" effect="M125"/>
<Interaction id="I43" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M123" precipitant="M127" effect="M125"/>
<Interaction id="I44" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M126" precipitant="M127" effect="M128"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7904" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Uricosuric Agents (probenecid and sulfinpyrazone) Salicylates antagonize the uricosuric action of uricosuric agents.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M135" type="Trigger" span="62 10" str="antagonize"/>
<Mention id="M130" type="Precipitant" span="19 10" str="probenecid" code="PO572Z7917"/>
<Mention id="M137" type="SpecificInteraction" span="62 32" str="antagonize the uricosuric action" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M133" type="Precipitant" span="34 14" str="sulfinpyrazone" code="V6OFU47K3W"/>
<Mention id="M136" type="Precipitant" span="98 17" str="uricosuric agents" code="N0000009896"/>
<Interaction id="I45" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M135" precipitant="M130" effect="M137"/>
<Interaction id="I46" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M135" precipitant="M133" effect="M137"/>
<Interaction id="I47" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M135" precipitant="M136" effect="M137"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7905" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>AGGRENOX increases the risk of bleeding (5.1) Avoid use in patients with severe hepatic or renal insufficiency (5.2, 5.3) Can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman, especially in the third trimester (5.4) AGGRENOX increases the risk of bleeding.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7906" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Risk factors for bleeding include the use of other drugs that increase the risk of bleeding (e.g., anticoagulants, antiplatelet agents, heparin, anagrelide, fibrinolytic therapy, and chronic use of NSAIDs).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M156" type="Trigger" span="0 12" str="Risk factors"/>
<Mention id="M139" type="Precipitant" span="145 10" str="anagrelide" code="K9X45X0051"/>
<Mention id="M158" type="SpecificInteraction" span="17 8" str="bleeding" code="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M142" type="Precipitant" span="99 14" str="anticoagulants" code="N0000175980"/>
<Mention id="M145" type="Precipitant" span="115 19" str="antiplatelet agents" code="N0000175578"/>
<Mention id="M148" type="Precipitant" span="183 21" str="chronic use of NSAIDs" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M151" type="Precipitant" span="51 40" str="drugs that increase the risk of bleeding" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M154" type="Precipitant" span="157 20" str="fibrinolytic therapy" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M157" type="Precipitant" span="136 7" str="heparin" code="T2410KM04A"/>
<Interaction id="I48" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M156" precipitant="M139" effect="M158"/>
<Interaction id="I49" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M156" precipitant="M142" effect="M158"/>
<Interaction id="I50" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M156" precipitant="M145" effect="M158"/>
<Interaction id="I51" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M156" precipitant="M148" effect="M158"/>
<Interaction id="I52" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M156" precipitant="M151" effect="M158"/>
<Interaction id="I53" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M156" precipitant="M154" effect="M158"/>
<Interaction id="I54" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M156" precipitant="M157" effect="M158"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7907" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Intracranial Hemorrhage In European Stroke Prevention Study-2 (ESPS2), the incidence of intracranial hemorrhage was 0.6% in the AGGRENOX group, 0.5% in the extended-release dipyridamole (ER-DP) group, 0.4% in the aspirin (ASA) group and 0.4% in the placebo groups.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7908" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Gastrointestinal (GI) Side Effects GI side effects include stomach pain, heartburn, nausea, vomiting, and gross GI bleeding.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7909" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Although minor upper GI symptoms, such as dyspepsia, are common and can occur anytime during therapy, physicians should remain alert for signs of ulceration and bleeding, even in the absence of previous GI symptoms.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7910" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Inform patients about the signs and symptoms of GI side effects and what steps to take if they occur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7911" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In ESPS2, the incidence of gastrointestinal bleeding was 4.1% in the AGGRENOX group, 2.2% in the extended-release dipyridamole group, 3.2% in the aspirin group, and 2.1% in the placebo groups.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7912" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Peptic Ulcer Disease Avoid using aspirin in patients with a history of active peptic ulcer disease, which can cause gastric mucosal irritation and bleeding.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7913" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Alcohol Warning Because AGGRENOX contains aspirin, counsel patients who consume three or more alcoholic drinks every day about the bleeding risks involved with chronic, heavy alcohol use while taking aspirin.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M159" type="Trigger" span="140 5" str="risks"/>
<Mention id="M160" type="Precipitant" span="160 26" str="chronic, heavy alcohol use" code="3K9958V90M"/>
<Mention id="M161" type="SpecificInteraction" span="131 8" str="bleeding" code="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M162" type="Trigger" span="8 7" str="Warning"/>
<Mention id="M163" type="Precipitant" span="0 7" str="Alcohol" code="3K9958V90M"/>
<Interaction id="I55" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M159" precipitant="M160" effect="M161"/>
<Interaction id="I56" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M162" precipitant="M163"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7914" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Avoid aspirin in patients with severe renal failure (glomerular filtration rate less than 10 mL/minute).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7915" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Elevations of hepatic enzymes and hepatic failure have been reported in association with dipyridamole administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7916" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Because AGGRENOX contains aspirin, AGGRENOX can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7917" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Maternal aspirin use during later stages of pregnancy may cause low birth weight, increased incidence for intracranial hemorrhage in premature infants, stillbirths and neonatal death.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7918" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Because of the above and because of the known effects of nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) on the fetal cardiovascular system (closure of the ductus arteriosus), avoid AGGRENOX in the third trimester of pregnancy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7919" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Aspirin has been shown to be teratogenic in rats (spina bifida, exencephaly, microphthalmia and coelosomia) and rabbits (congested fetuses, agenesis of skull and upper jaw, generalized edema with malformation of the head, and diaphanous skin) at oral doses of 330 mg/kg/day and 110 mg/kg/day, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7920" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>These doses, which also resulted in a high resorption rate in rats (63% of implantations versus 5% in controls), are, on a mg/m2 basis, about 66 and 44 times, respectively, the dose of aspirin contained in the maximum recommended daily human dose of AGGRENOX.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7921" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Reproduction studies with dipyridamole have been performed in mice, rabbits and rats at oral doses of up to 125 mg/kg, 40 mg/kg and 1000 mg/kg, respectively (about 1½, 2 and 25 times the maximum recommended daily human oral dose, respectively, on a mg/m2 basis) and have revealed no evidence of harm to the fetus due to dipyridamole.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7922" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>When 330 mg aspirin/kg/day was combined with 75 mg dipyridamole/kg/day in the rat, the resorption rate approached 100%, indicating potentiation of aspirin-related fetal toxicity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7923" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There are no adequate and well-controlled studies of the use of AGGRENOX in pregnant women.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7924" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If AGGRENOX is used during pregnancy, or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking AGGRENOX, inform the patient of the potential hazard to the fetus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7925" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Chest pain may be precipitated or aggravated in patients with underlying coronary artery disease who are receiving dipyridamole.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7926" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>For stroke or TIA patients for whom aspirin is indicated to prevent recurrent myocardial infarction (MI) or angina pectoris, the aspirin in this product may not provide adequate treatment for the cardiac indications.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7927" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Dipyridamole produces peripheral vasodilation, which can exacerbate pre-existing hypotension.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7928" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>AGGRENOX capsules are not interchangeable with the individual components of aspirin and dipyridamole tablets.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7929" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The antithrombotic action of AGGRENOX is the result of the additive antiplatelet effects of dipyridamole and aspirin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7930" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Dipyridamole Dipyridamole inhibits the uptake of adenosine into platelets, endothelial cells and erythrocytes in vitro and in vivo ; the inhibition occurs in a dose-dependent manner at therapeutic concentrations (0.5–1.9 µg/mL).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7931" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This inhibition results in an increase in local concentrations of adenosine which acts on the platelet A2-receptor thereby stimulating platelet adenylate cyclase and increasing platelet cyclic-3',5'-adenosine monophosphate (cAMP) levels.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7932" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Via this mechanism, platelet aggregation is inhibited in response to various stimuli such as platelet activating factor (PAF), collagen and adenosine diphosphate (ADP).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7933" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Dipyridamole inhibits phosphodiesterase (PDE) in various tissues.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7934" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>While the inhibition of cAMP-PDE is weak, therapeutic levels of dipyridamole inhibit cyclic-3',5'-guanosine monophosphate-PDE (cGMP-PDE), thereby augmenting the increase in cGMP produced by EDRF (endothelium-derived relaxing factor, now identified as nitric oxide).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7935" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Aspirin Aspirin inhibits platelet aggregation by irreversible inhibition of platelet cyclooxygenase and thus inhibits the generation of thromboxane A2, a powerful inducer of platelet aggregation and vasoconstriction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7936" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The effect of either agent on the other's inhibition of platelet reactivity has not been evaluated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7937" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There are no significant interactions between aspirin and dipyridamole.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7938" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The kinetics of the components are unchanged by their co-administration as AGGRENOX.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7939" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Dipyridamole Absorption Peak plasma levels of dipyridamole are achieved 2 hours (range 1–6 hours) after administration of a daily dose of 400 mg AGGRENOX (given as 200 mg BID).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7940" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The peak plasma concentration at steady-state is 1.98 µg/mL (1.01–3.99 µg/mL) and the steady-state trough concentration is 0.53 µg/mL (0.18–1.01 µg/mL).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7941" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Effect of Food When AGGRENOX capsules were taken with a high fat meal, dipyridamole peak plasma levels (Cmax) and total absorption (AUC) were decreased at steady-state by 20-30% compared to fasting.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M164" type="Trigger" span="104 4;142 9" str="Cmax | decreased"/>
<Mention id="M171" type="Precipitant" span="56 13" str="high fat meal" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M166" type="Trigger" span="84 18;142 9" str="peak plasma levels | decreased"/>
<Mention id="M168" type="Trigger" span="132 3;142 9" str="AUC | decreased"/>
<Mention id="M170" type="Trigger" span="114 16;142 9" str="total absorption | decreased"/>
<Interaction id="I57" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M164" precipitant="M171" effect="C54606"/>
<Interaction id="I58" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M166" precipitant="M171" effect="C54606"/>
<Interaction id="I59" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M168" precipitant="M171" effect="C54609"/>
<Interaction id="I60" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M170" precipitant="M171" effect="C54609"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7942" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Due to the similar degree of inhibition of adenosine uptake at these plasma concentrations, this food effect is not considered clinically relevant.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7943" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Distribution Dipyridamole is highly lipophilic (log P=3.71, pH=7); however, it has been shown that the drug does not cross the blood-brain barrier to any significant extent in animals.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7944" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The steady-state volume of distribution of dipyridamole is about 92 L. Approximately 99% of dipyridamole is bound to plasma proteins, predominantly to alpha 1-acid glycoprotein and albumin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7945" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Metabolism and Elimination Dipyridamole is metabolized in the liver, primarily by conjugation with glucuronic acid, of which monoglucuronide which has low pharmacodynamic activity is the primary metabolite.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7946" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In plasma, about 80% of the total amount is present as parent compound and 20% as monoglucuronide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7947" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Most of the glucuronide metabolite (about 95%) is excreted via bile into the feces, with some evidence of enterohepatic circulation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7948" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Renal excretion of parent compound is negligible and urinary excretion of the glucuronide metabolite is low (about 5%).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7949" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>With intravenous (i.v.) treatment of dipyridamole, a triphasic profile is obtained: a rapid alpha phase, with a half-life of about 3.4 minutes, a beta phase, with a half-life of about 39 minutes, (which, together with the alpha phase accounts for about 70% of the total area under the curve, AUC) and a prolonged elimination phase λz with a half-life of about 15.5 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7950" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Due to the extended absorption phase of the dipyridamole component, only the terminal phase is apparent from oral treatment with AGGRENOX which, in Trial 9.123 was 13.6 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7951" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Special Populations Geriatric Patients : In ESPS2, plasma concentrations (determined as AUC) of dipyridamole in healthy elderly subjects (&gt;65 years) were about 40% higher than in subjects younger than 55 years receiving treatment with AGGRENOX.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7952" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Hepatic Dysfunction : No study has been conducted with AGGRENOX in patients with hepatic dysfunction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7953" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In a study conducted with an intravenous formulation of dipyridamole, patients with mild to severe hepatic insufficiency showed no change in plasma concentrations of dipyridamole but showed an increase in the pharmacologically inactive monoglucuronide metabolite.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7954" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Dipyridamole can be dosed without restriction as long as there is no evidence of hepatic failure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7955" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Renal Dysfunction : No study has been conducted with AGGRENOX in patients with renal dysfunction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7956" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In ESPS2 patients, with creatinine clearances ranging from about 15 mL/min to &gt;100 mL/min, no changes were observed in the pharmacokinetics of dipyridamole or its glucuronide metabolite if data were corrected for differences in age.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7957" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Aspirin Absorption Peak plasma levels of aspirin are achieved 0.63 hours (0.5–1 hour) after administration of a 50 mg aspirin daily dose from AGGRENOX (given as 25 mg BID).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7958" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The peak plasma concentration at steady-state is 319 ng/mL (175–463 ng/mL).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7959" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Aspirin undergoes moderate hydrolysis to salicylic acid in the liver and the gastrointestinal wall, with 50%–75% of an administered dose reaching the systemic circulation as intact aspirin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7960" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Effect of Food When AGGRENOX capsules were taken with a high fat meal, there was no difference for aspirin in AUC at steady-state, and the approximately 50% decrease in Cmax was not considered clinically relevant based on a similar degree of cyclooxygenase inhibition comparing the fed and fasted state.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M172" type="Trigger" span="157 16" str="decrease in Cmax"/>
<Mention id="M173" type="Precipitant" span="56 13" str="high fat meal" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I61" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M172" precipitant="M173" effect="C54606"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7961" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Distribution Aspirin is poorly bound to plasma proteins and its apparent volume of distribution is low (10 L).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7962" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Its metabolite, salicylic acid, is highly bound to plasma proteins, but its binding is concentration-dependent (nonlinear).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7963" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>At low concentrations (&lt;100 µg/mL), approximately 90% of salicylic acid is bound to albumin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7964" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Salicylic acid is widely distributed to all tissues and fluids in the body, including the central nervous system, breast milk, and fetal tissues.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7965" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Early signs of salicylate overdose (salicylism), including tinnitus (ringing in the ears), occur at plasma concentrations approximating 200 µg/mL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7966" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Metabolism and Elimination Aspirin is rapidly hydrolyzed in plasma to salicylic acid, with a half-life of 20 minutes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7967" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Plasma levels of aspirin are essentially undetectable 2–2.5 hours after dosing and peak salicylic acid concentrations occur 1 hour (range: 0.5–2 hours) after administration of aspirin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7968" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Salicylic acid is primarily conjugated in the liver to form salicyluric acid, a phenolic glucuronide, an acyl glucuronide, and a number of minor metabolites.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7969" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Salicylate metabolism is saturable and total body clearance decreases at higher serum concentrations due to the limited ability of the liver to form both salicyluric acid and phenolic glucuronide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7970" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following toxic doses (10–20 g), the plasma half-life may be increased to over 20 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7971" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The elimination of acetylsalicylic acid follows first-order kinetics with AGGRENOX and has a half-life of 0.33 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7972" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The half-life of salicylic acid is 1.71 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7973" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Both values correspond well with data from the literature at lower doses which state a resultant half-life of approximately 2–3 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7974" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>At higher doses, the elimination of salicylic acid follows zero-order kinetics (i.e., the rate of elimination is constant in relation to plasma concentration), with an apparent half-life of 6 hours or higher.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7975" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Renal excretion of unchanged drug depends upon urinary pH.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7976" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>As urinary pH rises above 6.5, the renal clearance of free salicylate increases from &lt;5% to &gt;80%.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7977" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Alkalinization of the urine is a key concept in the management of salicylate overdose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7978" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following therapeutic doses, about 10% is excreted as salicylic acid and 75% as salicyluric acid, as the phenolic and acyl glucuronides, in urine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7979" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Special Populations Hepatic Dysfunction : Avoid aspirin in patients with severe hepatic insufficiency.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7980" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Renal Dysfunction : Avoid aspirin in patients with severe renal failure (glomerular filtration rate less than 10 mL/min).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7981" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>AGGRENOX Drug Interaction A dedicated drug interaction study was conducted in 60 healthy volunteers to evaluate the effects of omeprazole 80 mg administered once daily on the pharmacokinetics (PK) of dipyridamole and the pharmacodynamics (PD) of acetylsalicylic acid when co-administered with AGGRENOX twice daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7982" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Dipyridamole exposure (Cmax and AUC) at steady-state were similar with or without omeprazole co-administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7983" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacokinetics of acetylsalicylic acid was not characterized.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7984" LabelDrug="Aggrenox" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>However, the antiplatelet activity as measured by arachidonic acid induced platelet aggregation was similar between the treatment arms at steady-state.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="adenosine" precipitantCode="K72T3FS567" effect="111970001: Abnormal cardiovascular function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="adenosine" precipitantCode="K72T3FS567" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="adenosine" precipitantCode="K72T3FS567"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="anticoagulants" precipitantCode="N0000175980" effect="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="antiplatelets" precipitantCode="N0000175578" effect="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nsaids" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nsaids" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="76114004: Decreased renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ace inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175562" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="acetazolamide" precipitantCode="O3FX965V0I" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="acetazolamide" precipitantCode="O3FX965V0I" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="any substance impacting coagulation" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="warfarin" precipitantCode="5Q7ZVV76EI" effect="123789000: Blood coagulation disorder with prolonged bleeding time (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="warfarin" precipitantCode="5Q7ZVV76EI" effect="409674002: Prothrombin time increased (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="warfarin" precipitantCode="5Q7ZVV76EI" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="heparin" precipitantCode="T2410KM04A" effect="10191004: Anticoagulant effect (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="heparin" precipitantCode="T2410KM04A" effect="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="anagrelide" precipitantCode="K9X45X0051" effect="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="phenytoin" precipitantCode="6158TKW0C5" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="phenytoin" precipitantCode="6158TKW0C5" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="valproic acid" precipitantCode="614OI1Z5WI" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="valproic acid" precipitantCode="614OI1Z5WI" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="beta blockers" precipitantCode="N0000175556" effect="43498006: Body fluid retention (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="beta blockers" precipitantCode="N0000175556" effect="764268008: Inadequate peripheral blood flow (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="beta blockers" precipitantCode="N0000175556" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cholinesterase inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175723" effect="91637004: Myasthenia gravis (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cholinesterase inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175723" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="diuretics" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="43498006: Body fluid retention (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="diuretics" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="764268008: Inadequate peripheral blood flow (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="diuretics" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="methotrexate" precipitantCode="YL5FZ2Y5U1" effect="127035006: Bone marrow disorder (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="methotrexate" precipitantCode="YL5FZ2Y5U1" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="76114004: Decreased renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="oral hypoglycemic drugs" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="oral hypoglycemic drugs" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="51798006: Decreased glucose level (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="oral hypoglycemics" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="oral hypoglycemics" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="51798006: Decreased glucose level (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="probenecid" precipitantCode="PO572Z7917" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sulfinpyrazone" precipitantCode="V6OFU47K3W" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="uricosuric agents" precipitantCode="N0000009896" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="antiplatelet agents" precipitantCode="N0000175578" effect="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="chronic use of nsaids" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="drugs that increase the risk of bleeding" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="fibrinolytic therapy" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="chronic, heavy alcohol use" precipitantCode="3K9958V90M" effect="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="alcohol" precipitantCode="3K9958V90M"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="high fat meal" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54606"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="high fat meal" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54609"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>