<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="AGGRASTAT" setid="fe0ced75-ccbf-4d2e-bd0d-b57e60ab913f">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
AGGRASTAT is contraindicated in patients with:  Severe hypersensitivity reaction to AGGRASTAT (i.e., anaphylactic reactions) [see Adverse Reactions (6.2)]. A history of thrombocytopenia following prior exposure to AGGRASTAT [see Adverse Reactions (6.1)]. Active internal bleeding or a history of bleeding diathesis, major surgical procedure or severe physical trauma within the previous month [see Adverse Reactions (6.1)].        Known hypersensitivity to any component of AGGRASTAT. (4) History of thrombocytopenia with prior exposure to AGGRASTAT. (4) Active internal bleeding, or history of bleeding diathesis, major surgical procedure or severe physical trauma within the previous month. (4)</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
Administer intravenously 25 mcg/kg over 3 minutes and then 0.15 mcg/kg/min (or 0.075 mcg/kg/min for patients with serum creatinine ≤60 mL/min), for up to 18 hours. This is not the regimen that was used in studies that established effectiveness of AGGRASTAT [see Clinical Studies (14)].    The instructions by weight and creatinine clearance are tabulated in Table 1.   Table 1 Dosing by Weight and CrCl          Weight   (kg)     First 3 minAll Patients (mL)     Maintenance Infusion Rate(mL/hr.)      CrCl &amp;gt;60 mL/min   CrCl ≤60 mL/min      30-37    17   6   3      38-45    21   7.5   3.75      46-54    25   9   4.5      55-62   29   10.5   5.25      63-70   33   12   6      71-79   37.5   13.5   6.75      80-87   42   15   7.5      88-95   46   16.5   8.25      96-104   50   18   9      105-112   54   19.5   9.75      113-120   58   21   10.5      121-128   62   22.5   11.25      129-137   66.5   24   12      138-145   71   25.5   12.75      146-153   75   27   13.5       Important Administration Instructions    To open the container, first tear off its foil overpouch. The plastic may be somewhat opaque because of moisture absorption during sterilization; the opacity will diminish gradually. Check for leaks by squeezing the inner bag firmly; if any leaks are found or sterility is suspect then the solution should be discarded. Do not use unless the solution is clear and the seal is intact. Suspend the container from its eyelet support, remove the plastic protector from the outlet port, and attach a conventional administration set.  You may administer AGGRASTAT in the same intravenous line as atropine sulfate, dobutamine, dopamine, epinephrine hydrochloride (HCl), famotidine injection, furosemide, lidocaine, midazolam HCl, morphine sulfate, nitroglycerin, potassium chloride, and propranolol HCl. Do not administer AGGRASTAT through the same IV line as diazepam.  Do not add other drugs or remove solution directly from the bag with a syringe. Do not use plastic containers in series connections; such use can result in air embolism by drawing air from the first container if it is empty of solution. Discard any unused portion left in the bag.         Administer intravenously 25 mcg/kg over 3 minutes and then 0.15 mcg/kg/min for up to 18 hours. In patients with creatinine clearance ≤60 mL/min, give 25 mcg/kg over 3 minutes and then 0.075 mcg/kg/min. (2)</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
Use of thrombolytics, anticoagulants, and other antiplatelet agents.   Coadministration of antiplatelet agents, thrombolytics, heparin, and aspirin increases the risk of bleeding.        Coadministration of antiplatelet agents, thrombolytics, heparin, or aspirin increases the risk of bleeding. (7)</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
AGGRASTAT can cause serious bleeding. If bleeding cannot be controlled discontinue AGGRASTAT. (5.1) Thrombocytopenia: Discontinue AGGRASTAT and heparin. (5.2)          Bleeding is the most common complication encountered during therapy with AGGRASTAT. Most bleeding associated with AGGRASTAT occurs at the arterial access site for cardiac catheterization. Minimize the use of traumatic or potentially traumatic procedures such arterial and venous punctures, intramuscular injections, nasotracheal intubation, etc. Fatal bleeding events have been reported [see Adverse Reactions (6.2)].  Concomitant use of fibrinolytics, oral anticoagulants and antiplatelet drugs increases the risk of bleeding.           Profound thrombocytopenia has been reported with AGGRASTAT. Monitor platelet counts beginning about 6 hours after treatment initiation and daily thereafter. If the platelet count decreases to &amp;lt;90,000/mm3, monitor platelet counts to exclude pseudothrombocytopenia. If thrombocytopenia is confirmed, discontinue AGGRASTAT and heparin. Previous exposure to a glycoprotein (GP) IIb/IIIa receptor antagonist may increase the risk of developing thrombocytopenia [see Adverse Reactions (6.1)].</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
AGGRASTAT is a reversible antagonist of fibrinogen binding to the GP IIb/IIIa receptor, the major platelet surface receptor involved in platelet aggregation. When administered intravenously, AGGRASTAT inhibits ex vivo platelet aggregation in a dose- and concentration-dependent manner. When given according to the PRISM-PLUS regimen of 0.4 mcg/kg/min for 30 minutes followed by a 0.1 mcg/kg/min maintenance infusion, &amp;gt;90% inhibition of platelet aggregation is attained by the end of the 30-minute infusion. When given according to the recommended regimen of 25 mcg/kg over 3 min followed by a 0.15 mcg/kg/min maintenance infusion, &amp;gt;90% inhibition of platelet aggregation is attained within 10 minutes. Platelet aggregation inhibition is reversible following cessation of the infusion of AGGRASTAT.           AGGRASTAT inhibits platelet function, as demonstrated by its ability to inhibit ex vivo adenosine phosphate (ADP)-induced platelet aggregation and prolong bleeding time in healthy subjects and patients with coronary artery disease. The time course of inhibition parallels the plasma concentration profile of the drug. Following discontinuation of an infusion of AGGRASTAT 0.10 mcg/kg/min, ex vivo platelet aggregation returns to near baseline in 4 to 8 hours in approximately 90% of patients with coronary artery disease. The addition of heparin to this regimen does not significantly alter the percentage of subjects with &amp;gt;70% inhibition of platelet aggregation (IPA), but does increase the average bleeding time, as well as the number of patients with bleeding times prolonged to &amp;gt;30 minutes. Similar platelet aggregation recovery rates are observed following discontinuation of a 0.15 mcg/kg/min infusion.          Tirofiban has a half-life of approximately 2 hours. It is cleared from the plasma largely by renal excretion, with about 65% of an administered dose appearing in urine and about 25% in feces, both largely as unchanged tirofiban. Metabolism appears to be limited.  Tirofiban is not highly bound to plasma proteins and protein binding is concentration independent over the range of 0.01 to 25 mcg/mL. The unbound fraction in human plasma is 35%. The steady state volume of distribution of tirofiban ranges from 22 to 42 liters.  In healthy subjects, the plasma clearance of tirofiban ranges from 213 to 314 mL/min. Renal clearance accounts for 39 to 69% of plasma clearance.         There is no effect on clearance of tirofiban by sex, race, age, or hepatic impairment.  Renal Insufficiency  Plasma clearance of tirofiban is decreased about 40% in subjects with creatinine clearance &amp;lt;60 mL/min and &amp;gt;50% in patients with creatinine clearance &amp;lt;30 mL/min, including patients requiring hemodialysis [see Dosage and Administration (2)]. Tirofiban is removed by hemodialysis.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="2406" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>AGGRASTAT is contraindicated in patients with: Severe hypersensitivity reaction to AGGRASTAT (i.e., anaphylactic reactions).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2407" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>A history of thrombocytopenia following prior exposure to AGGRASTAT.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2408" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Active internal bleeding or a history of bleeding diathesis, major surgical procedure or severe physical trauma within the previous month.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2409" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Known hypersensitivity to any component of AGGRASTAT.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2410" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>History of thrombocytopenia with prior exposure to AGGRASTAT.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2411" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Active internal bleeding, or history of bleeding diathesis, major surgical procedure or severe physical trauma within the previous month.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2412" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Administer intravenously 25 mcg/kg within 5 minutes and then 0.15 mcg/kg/min for up to 18 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2413" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In patients with creatinine clearance ≤60 mL/min, give 25 mcg/kg within 5 minutes and then 0.075 mcg/kg/min.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2414" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommended dosage is 25 mcg/kg administered intravenously within 5 minutes and then 0.15 mcg/kg/min for up to 18 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2415" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Parenteral drug products should be inspected visually for particulate matter and discoloration prior to administration whenever solution and container permit.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2416" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>To open the 250 mL premixed bag, first tear off its foil overpouch.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2417" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The plastic may be somewhat opaque because of moisture absorption during sterilization; the opacity will diminish gradually.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2418" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Check for leaks by squeezing the inner bag firmly; if any leaks are found or sterility is suspect then the solution should be discarded.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2419" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not use unless the solution is clear and the seal is intact.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2420" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Administration Instructions Withdraw the bolus dose of AGGRASTAT from the 15 mL premixed bolus vial into a syringe.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2421" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Alternatively, the bolus dose of AGGRASTAT may be administered from the 100 mL premixed vial or from the 250 mL premixed bag.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2422" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Administer the bolus dose within 5 minutes via a syringe or IV pump.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2423" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Immediately following the bolus dose administration, administer the maintenance infusion from the 100 mL premixed vial or 250 mL premixed bag via an IV pump.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2424" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Discard any unused portion left in the vial or bag.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2425" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommended bolus volume using the 15 mL premixed bolus vial can be calculated using the following equation: The recommended bolus volume using the 100 mL premixed vial or 250 mL premixed bag can be calculated using the following equation: The recommended infusion rate for patients with CrCl (Creatinine Clearance) &gt;60 mL/min using the 100 mL premixed vial or 250 mL premixed bag can be calculated using the following equation: Example calculation of infusion rate for 60 kg patient with CrCl &gt;60 mL/min using the 100 mL premixed vial or 250 mL premixed bag: Drug Compatibilities AGGRASTAT can be administered in the same intravenous line as heparin, atropine sulfate, dobutamine, dopamine, epinephrine hydrochloride (HCl), famotidine injection, furosemide, lidocaine, midazolam HCl, morphine sulfate, nitroglycerin, potassium chloride, and propranolol HCl.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2426" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not administer AGGRASTAT through the same IV line as diazepam.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M1" type="Trigger" span="0 17;28 24" str="Do not administer | through the same IV line"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="56 8" str="diazepam" code="Q3JTX2Q7TU"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M1" precipitant="M2"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2427" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not add other drugs or remove solution directly from the bag with a syringe. equation-1 equation-2 equation-3 equation-4 The recommended dosage in patients with CrCl ≤60 mL/min is 25 mcg/kg intravenously within 5 minutes and then 0.075 mcg/kg/min, for up to 18 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2428" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommended infusion rate for patients with CrCl ≤60 mL/min using the 100 mL premixed vial or 250 mL premixed bag can be calculated using the following equation: equation-5</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2429" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant use of fibrinolytics, anticoagulants and antiplatelet drugs increases the risk of bleeding.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M9" type="Trigger" span="72 18" str="increases the risk"/>
<Mention id="M4" type="Precipitant" span="34 14" str="anticoagulants" code="N0000175980"/>
<Mention id="M11" type="SpecificInteraction" span="94 8" str="bleeding" code="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M7" type="Precipitant" span="53 18" str="antiplatelet drugs" code="N0000175578"/>
<Mention id="M10" type="Precipitant" span="19 13" str="fibrinolytics" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M9" precipitant="M4" effect="M11"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M9" precipitant="M7" effect="M11"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M9" precipitant="M10" effect="M11"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2430" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Coadministration of fibrinolytics, anticoagulants and antiplatelet agents, increases the risk of bleeding.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M18" type="Trigger" span="75 18" str="increases the risk"/>
<Mention id="M13" type="Precipitant" span="35 14" str="anticoagulants" code="N0000175980"/>
<Mention id="M20" type="SpecificInteraction" span="97 8" str="bleeding" code="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M16" type="Precipitant" span="54 19" str="antiplatelet agents" code="N0000175578"/>
<Mention id="M19" type="Precipitant" span="20 13" str="fibrinolytics" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M18" precipitant="M13" effect="M20"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M18" precipitant="M16" effect="M20"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M18" precipitant="M19" effect="M20"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2431" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If bleeding cannot be controlled discontinue AGGRASTAT.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2432" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Thrombocytopenia: Discontinue AGGRASTAT and heparin.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M21" type="Trigger" span="18 11" str="Discontinue"/>
<Mention id="M22" type="Precipitant" span="44 7" str="heparin" code="T2410KM04A"/>
<Mention id="M23" type="SpecificInteraction" span="-1 16" str="thrombocytopenia" code="302215000:  Thrombocytopenic disorder (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M21" precipitant="M22" effect="M23"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2433" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Bleeding is the most common complication encountered during therapy with AGGRASTAT.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2434" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Most bleeding associated with AGGRASTAT occurs at the arterial access site for cardiac catheterization.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2435" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Minimize the use of traumatic or potentially traumatic procedures such as arterial and venous punctures, intramuscular injections, nasotracheal intubation, etc.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2436" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Profound thrombocytopenia has been reported with AGGRASTAT.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2437" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor platelet counts beginning about 6 hours after treatment initiation and daily thereafter.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2438" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If the platelet count decreases to &lt;90,000/mm3, monitor platelet counts to exclude pseudothrombocytopenia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2439" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If thrombocytopenia is confirmed, discontinue AGGRASTAT and heparin.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M24" type="Trigger" span="34 11" str="discontinue"/>
<Mention id="M25" type="Precipitant" span="60 7" str="heparin" code="T2410KM04A"/>
<Mention id="M26" type="SpecificInteraction" span="3 16" str="thrombocytopenia" code="302215000:  Thrombocytopenic disorder (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M24" precipitant="M25" effect="M26"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2440" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Previous exposure to a glycoprotein (GP) IIb/IIIa receptor antagonist may increase the risk of developing thrombocytopenia.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M33" type="Trigger" span="74 17" str="increase the risk"/>
<Mention id="M28" type="Precipitant" span="23 46" str="glycoprotein (GP) IIb/IIIa receptor antagonist" code="N0000009962"/>
<Mention id="M35" type="SpecificInteraction" span="106 16" str="thrombocytopenia" code="302215000:  Thrombocytopenic disorder (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M31" type="Precipitant" span="23 12;41 28" str="glycoprotein | IIb/IIIa receptor antagonist" code="N0000009962"/>
<Mention id="M34" type="Precipitant" span="37 2;41 28" str="GP | IIb/IIIa receptor antagonist" code="N0000009962"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M33" precipitant="M28" effect="M35"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M33" precipitant="M31" effect="M35"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M33" precipitant="M34" effect="M35"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2441" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>AGGRASTAT is a reversible antagonist of fibrinogen binding to the GP IIb/IIIa receptor, the major platelet surface receptor involved in platelet aggregation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2442" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>When administered intravenously, AGGRASTAT inhibits ex vivo platelet aggregation in a dose- and concentration-dependent manner.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2443" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>When given according to the PRISM-PLUS regimen of 0.4 mcg/kg/min over 30 minutes followed by a 0.1 mcg/kg/min maintenance infusion, &gt;90% inhibition of platelet aggregation is attained by the end of the 30-minute infusion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2444" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>When given according to the recommended regimen of 25 mcg/kg followed by a 0.15 mcg/kg/min maintenance infusion, &gt;90% inhibition of platelet aggregation is attained within 10 minutes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2445" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Platelet aggregation inhibition is reversible following cessation of the infusion of AGGRASTAT.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2446" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>AGGRASTAT inhibits platelet function, as demonstrated by its ability to inhibit ex vivo adenosine phosphate (ADP)-induced platelet aggregation and prolong bleeding time in healthy subjects and patients with coronary artery disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2447" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The time course of inhibition parallels the plasma concentration profile of the drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2448" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following discontinuation of an infusion of AGGRASTAT 0.10 mcg/kg/min, ex vivo platelet aggregation returns to near baseline in 4 to 8 hours in approximately 90% of patients with coronary artery disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2449" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The addition of heparin to this regimen does not significantly alter the percentage of subjects with &gt;70% inhibition of platelet aggregation (IPA), but does increase the average bleeding time, as well as the number of patients with bleeding times prolonged to &gt;30 minutes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2450" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Similar platelet aggregation recovery rates are observed following discontinuation of a 0.15 mcg/kg/min infusion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2451" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Tirofiban has a half-life of approximately 2 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2452" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>It is cleared from the plasma largely by renal excretion, with about 65% of an administered dose appearing in urine and about 25% in feces, both largely as unchanged tirofiban.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2453" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Tirofiban is not highly bound to plasma proteins and protein binding is concentration independent over the range of 0.01 to 25 mcg/mL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2454" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The unbound fraction in human plasma is 35%.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2455" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The steady state volume of distribution of tirofiban ranges from 22 to 42 liters.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2456" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In healthy subjects, the plasma clearance of tirofiban ranges from 213 to 314 mL/min.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2457" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Renal clearance accounts for 39 to 69% of plasma clearance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2458" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There is no effect on clearance of tirofiban by sex, race, age, or hepatic impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2459" LabelDrug="AGGRASTAT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Renal Insufficiency Plasma clearance of tirofiban is decreased about 40% in subjects with creatinine clearance &lt;60 mL/min and &gt;50% in patients with creatinine clearance &lt;30 mL/min, including patients requiring hemodialysis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="diazepam" precipitantCode="Q3JTX2Q7TU"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="anticoagulants" precipitantCode="N0000175980" effect="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="antiplatelet drugs" precipitantCode="N0000175578" effect="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="fibrinolytics" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="antiplatelet agents" precipitantCode="N0000175578" effect="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="heparin" precipitantCode="T2410KM04A" effect="302215000:  Thrombocytopenic disorder (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="glycoprotein (gp) iib/iiia receptor antagonist" precipitantCode="N0000009962" effect="302215000:  Thrombocytopenic disorder (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="glycoprotein | iib/iiia receptor antagonist" precipitantCode="N0000009962" effect="302215000:  Thrombocytopenic disorder (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="gp | iib/iiia receptor antagonist" precipitantCode="N0000009962" effect="302215000:  Thrombocytopenic disorder (disorder)"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>