<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="ALTACE" setid="0fc34cd8-86e6-4034-73bd-4263a68ba046">
<Text><Section name="BOXED WARNING SECTION" id="34066-1">
When pregnancy is detected, discontinue ALTACE as soon as possible (5.6).   Drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause injury and death to the developing fetus (5.6).        WARNING: FETAL TOXICITY  See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning    When pregnancy is detected, discontinue ALTACE as soon as possible (5.6).   Drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause injury and death to the developing fetus (5.6).</Section>
<Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
ALTACE is contraindicated in patients who are hypersensitive to this product or any other ACE inhibitor (e.g., a patient who has experienced angioedema during therapy with any other ACE inhibitor).  Do not co-administer aliskiren with ALTACE in patients with diabetes.       Angioedema related to previous treatment with an ACE inhibitor, or a history of hereditary or idiopathic angioedema. (4). Do not co-administer aliskiren with ALTACE in patients with diabetes. (4)</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
Hypertension: Initial dose is 2.5 mg to 20 mg once daily. Adjust dosage according to blood pressure response after 2–4 weeks of treatment. The usual maintenance dose following titration is 2.5 mg to 20 mg daily as a single dose or equally divided doses (2.1). Reduction in the risk of myocardial infarction, stroke, or death from cardiovascular causes: 2.5 mg once daily for 1 week, 5 mg once daily for 3 weeks, and increased as tolerated to a maintenance dose of 10 mg once daily (2.2). Heart failure post-myocardial infarction: Starting dose of 2.5 mg twice daily. If patient becomes hypotensive at this dose, decrease dosage to 1.25 mg twice daily. Increase dose as tolerated toward a target dose of 5 mg twice daily, with dosage increases about 3 weeks apart (2.3). Dosage adjustment: See respective sections pertaining to dosage adjustment in special situations (2.5).         The recommended initial dose for patients not receiving a diuretic is 2.5 mg once a day. Adjust dose according to blood pressure response. The usual maintenance dosage range is 2.5 mg to 20 mg per day administered as a single dose or in two equally divided doses. In some patients treated once daily, the antihypertensive effect may diminish toward the end of the dosing interval. In such patients, consider an increase in dosage or twice daily administration. If blood pressure is not controlled with ALTACE alone, a diuretic can be added.          Initiate dosing at 2.5 mg once daily for 1 week, 5 mg once daily for the next 3 weeks, and then increase as tolerated, to a maintenance dose of 10 mg once daily. If the patient is hypertensive or recently post-myocardial infarction, ALTACE can also be given as a divided dose.          For the treatment of post-myocardial infarction patients who have shown signs of congestive heart failure, the recommended starting dose of ALTACE is 2.5 mg twice daily (5 mg per day). A patient who becomes hypotensive at this dose may be switched to 1.25 mg twice daily. After one week at the starting dose, increase dose (if tolerated) toward a target dose of 5 mg twice daily, with dosage increases being about 3 weeks apart. After the initial dose of ALTACE, observe the patient under medical supervision for at least two hours and until blood pressure has stabilized for at least an additional hour. If possible, reduce the dose of any concomitant diuretic as this may diminish the likelihood of hypotension. The appearance of hypotension after the initial dose of ALTACE does not preclude subsequent careful dose titration with the drug, following effective management of the hypotension [see Warnings and Precautions (5.5), Drug Interactions (7.1)].           Generally, swallow ALTACE capsules whole. The ALTACE capsule can also be opened and the contents sprinkled on a small amount (about 4 oz.) of applesauce or mixed in 4 oz. (120 mL) of water or apple juice. To be sure that ramipril is not lost when such a mixture is used, consume the mixture in its entirety. The described mixtures can be pre-prepared and stored for up to 24 hours at room temperature or up to 48 hours under refrigeration. Concomitant administration of ALTACE with potassium supplements, potassium salt substitutes, or potassium-sparing diuretics can lead to increases of serum potassium [see Warnings and Precautions (5.8)].                 Renal Impairment  Establish baseline renal function in patients initiating ALTACE. Usual regimens of therapy with ALTACE may be followed in patients with estimated creatinine clearance &amp;gt;40 mL/min. However, in patients with worse impairment, 25% of the usual dose of ramipril is expected to produce full therapeutic levels of ramiprilat [see Use in Specific Populations (8.6)].           Hypertension  For patients with hypertension and renal impairment, the recommended initial dose is 1.25 mg ALTACE once daily. Dosage may be titrated upward until blood pressure is controlled or to a maximum total daily dose of 5 mg.           Heart Failure Post-Myocardial Infarction  For patients with heart failure and renal impairment, the recommended initial dose is 1.25 mg ALTACE once daily. The dose may be increased to 1.25 mg twice daily, and up to a maximum dose of 2.5 mg twice daily depending on clinical response and tolerability.           Volume Depletion or Renal Artery Stenosis  Blood pressure decreases associated with any dose of ALTACE depend, in part, on the presence or absence of volume depletion (e.g., past and current diuretic use) or the presence or absence of renal artery stenosis. If such circumstances are suspected to be present, initiate dosing at 1.25 mg once daily. Adjust dosage according to blood pressure response.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
Diuretics: Possibility of excessive hypotension (7.1). Lithium: Use with caution (7.3). Gold: Nitritoid reactions have been reported (7.4). NSAIDS use may lead to increased risk of renal impairment and loss of antihypertensive effect (7.5). mTOR inhibitor use may increase angioedema risk (7.7)         Patients on diuretics, especially those in whom diuretic therapy was recently instituted, may occasionally experience an excessive reduction of blood pressure after initiation of therapy with ALTACE. The possibility of hypotensive effects with ALTACE can be minimized by either decreasing or discontinuing the diuretic or increasing the salt intake prior to initiation of treatment with ALTACE. If this is not possible, reduce the starting dose [see Dosage and Administration (2)].  ALTACE can attenuate potassium loss caused by thiazide diuretics. Potassium-sparing diuretics (spironolactone, amiloride, triamterene, and others) or potassium supplements can increase the risk of hyperkalemia. Therefore, if concomitant use of such agents is indicated, monitor the patient's serum potassium frequently.          Limited experience in controlled and uncontrolled trials combining ALTACE with a calcium channel blocker, a loop diuretic, or triple therapy (beta-blocker, vasodilator, and a diuretic) indicate no unusual drug-drug interactions. Other ACE inhibitors have had less than additive effects with beta adrenergic blockers, presumably because both drug classes lower blood pressure by inhibiting parts of the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system. The combination of ramipril and propranolol showed no adverse effects on dynamic parameters (blood pressure and heart rate). In a large-scale, long-term clinical efficacy study, the combination of telmisartan and ramipril resulted in an increased incidence of clinically important renal dysfunction (death, doubling of serum creatinine, dialysis) compared with groups receiving either drug alone. Therefore, concomitant use of telmisartan and ramipril is not recommended [see Dual Blockade of the Renin-Angiotensin-Aldosterone System (5.7)].          Increased serum lithium levels and symptoms of lithium toxicity have been reported in patients receiving ACE inhibitors during therapy with lithium; therefore, frequent monitoring of serum lithium levels is recommended. If a diuretic is also used, the risk of lithium toxicity may be increased.          Nitritoid reactions (symptoms include facial flushing, nausea, vomiting and hypotension) have been reported rarely in patients on therapy with injectable gold (sodium aurothiomalate) and concomitant ACE inhibitor therapy including ALTACE.          In patients who are elderly, volume-depleted (including those on diuretic therapy), or with compromised renal function, co-administration of NSAIDs, including selective COX-2 inhibitors, with ACE inhibitors, including ramipril, may result in deterioration of renal function, including possible acute renal failure. These effects are usually reversible. Monitor renal function periodically in patients receiving ramipril and NSAID therapy. The antihypertensive effect of ACE inhibitors, including ramipril, may be attenuated by NSAIDs.          Do not co-administer aliskiren with ALTACE in patients with diabetes. Avoid concomitant use of aliskiren with ALTACE in patients with renal impairment (GFR &amp;lt;60 mL/min/1.73 m2) [see Warnings and Precautions (5.7)].          Patients taking concomitant mTOR inhibitor (e.g. temsirolimus) therapy may be at increased risk for angioedema [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)].           Neither ramipril nor its metabolites have been found to interact with food, digoxin, antacid, furosemide, cimetidine, indomethacin, and simvastatin. The co-administration of ramipril and warfarin did not adversely affect the anticoagulation effects of the latter drug. Additionally, co-administration of ramipril with phenprocoumon did not affect minimum phenprocoumon levels or interfere with the patients' state of anticoagulation.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
ACE inhibitor use has been associated with the following: Angioedema, with increased risk in patients with a prior history or when combined with mTOR inhibitors (5.1) Hypotension and hyperkalemia (5.5, 5.8) Renal impairment: monitor renal function during therapy (5.3) Increased risk of renal impairment when combined with another blocker of the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system (5.7) Avoid concomitant use with aliskiren in patients with moderate to severe renal impairment. (5.7) Rare cholestatic jaundice and hepatic failure (5.2) Rare neutropenia and agranulocytosis (5.4)         Presumably because drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system (e.g., ACE inhibitors) affect the metabolism of eicosanoids and polypeptides, including endogenous bradykinin, patients receiving these drugs (including ALTACE) may be subject to a variety of adverse reactions, some of them serious.         Angioedema          Head and Neck Angioedema  Patients with a history of angioedema unrelated to ACE inhibitor therapy may be at increased risk of angioedema while receiving an ACE inhibitor. Angioedema of the face, extremities, lips, tongue, glottis, and larynx has been reported in patients treated with ACE inhibitors. Angioedema associated with laryngeal edema can be fatal. If laryngeal stridor or angioedema of the face, tongue, or glottis occurs, discontinue treatment with ALTACE and institute appropriate therapy immediately. Where there is involvement of the tongue, glottis, or larynx likely to cause airway obstruction, administer appropriate therapy (e.g., subcutaneous epinephrine solution 1:1000 [0.3 mL to 0.5 mL]) promptly [see Adverse Reactions (6)].  In considering the use of ALTACE, note that in controlled clinical trials ACE inhibitors cause a higher rate of angioedema in Black patients than in non-Black patients. In a large U.S. post-marketing study, angioedema (defined as reports of angio, face, larynx, tongue, or throat edema) was reported in 3/1523 (0.20%) Black patients and in 8/8680 (0.09%) non-Black patients. These rates were not different statistically.  Patients taking concomitant mTOR inhibitor (e.g. temsirolimus) therapy may be at increased risk for angioedema [see Drug Interactions (7.7)].             Intestinal Angioedema  Intestinal angioedema has been reported in patients treated with ACE inhibitors. These patients presented with abdominal pain (with or without nausea or vomiting); in some cases there was no prior history of facial angioedema and C-1 esterase levels were normal. The angioedema was diagnosed by procedures including abdominal CT scan or ultrasound, or at surgery, and symptoms resolved after stopping the ACE inhibitor. Include intestinal angioedema in the differential diagnosis of patients on ACE inhibitors presenting with abdominal pain.             Anaphylactoid Reactions During Desensitization  Two patients undergoing desensitizing treatment with hymenoptera venom while receiving ACE inhibitors sustained life-threatening anaphylactoid reactions. In the same patients, these reactions were avoided when ACE inhibitors were temporarily withheld, but they reappeared upon inadvertent rechallenge.           Anaphylactoid Reactions During Membrane Exposure  Anaphylactoid reactions have been reported in patients dialyzed with high-flux membranes and treated concomitantly with an ACE inhibitor. Anaphylactoid reactions have also been reported in patients undergoing low-density lipoprotein apheresis with dextran sulfate absorption.            Rarely, ACE inhibitors, including ALTACE, have been associated with a syndrome that starts with cholestatic jaundice and progresses to fulminant hepatic necrosis and sometimes death. The mechanism of this syndrome is not understood. Discontinue ALTACE if patient develops jaundice or marked elevations of hepatic enzymes. As ramipril is primarily metabolized by hepatic esterases to its active moiety, ramiprilat, patients with impaired liver function could develop markedly elevated plasma levels of ramipril. No formal pharmacokinetic studies have been carried out in hypertensive patients with impaired liver function.          As a consequence of inhibiting the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system, changes in renal function may be anticipated in susceptible individuals. In patients with severe congestive heart failure whose renal function may depend on the activity of the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system, treatment with ACE inhibitors, including ALTACE, may be associated with oliguria or progressive azotemia and rarely with acute renal failure or death. In hypertensive patients with unilateral or bilateral renal artery stenosis, increases in blood urea nitrogen and serum creatinine may occur. Experience with another ACE inhibitor suggests that these increases would be reversible upon discontinuation of ALTACE and/or diuretic therapy. In such patients, monitor renal function during the first few weeks of therapy. Some hypertensive patients with no apparent pre-existing renal vascular disease have developed increases in blood urea nitrogen and serum creatinine, usually minor and transient, especially when ALTACE has been given concomitantly with a diuretic. This is more likely to occur in patients with pre-existing renal impairment. Dosage reduction of ALTACE and/or discontinuation of the diuretic may be required.          In rare instances, treatment with ACE inhibitors may be associated with mild reductions in red blood cell count and hemoglobin content, blood cell or platelet counts. In isolated cases, agranulocytosis, pancytopenia, and bone marrow depression may occur. Hematological reactions to ACE inhibitors are more likely to occur in patients with collagen-vascular disease (e.g., systemic lupus erythematosus, scleroderma) and renal impairment. Consider monitoring white blood cell counts in patients with collagen-vascular disease, especially if the disease is associated with impaired renal function.                General Considerations  ALTACE can cause symptomatic hypotension, after either the initial dose or a later dose when the dosage has been increased. Like other ACE inhibitors, ALTACE, has been only rarely associated with hypotension in uncomplicated hypertensive patients. Symptomatic hypotension is most likely to occur in patients who have been volume- and/or salt-depleted as a result of prolonged diuretic therapy, dietary salt restriction, dialysis, diarrhea, or vomiting. Correct volume- and salt-depletion before initiating therapy with ALTACE. If excessive hypotension occurs, place the patient in a supine position and, if necessary, treat with intravenous infusion of physiological saline. ALTACE treatment usually can be continued following restoration of blood pressure and volume.            Heart Failure Post-Myocardial Infarction  In patients with heart failure post-myocardial infarction who are currently being treated with a diuretic, symptomatic hypotension occasionally can occur following the initial dose of ALTACE. If the initial dose of 2.5 mg ALTACE cannot be tolerated, use an initial dose of 1.25 mg ALTACE to avoid excessive hypotension. Consider reducing the dose of concomitant diuretic to decrease the incidence of hypotension.           Congestive Heart Failure  In patients with congestive heart failure, with or without associated renal insufficiency, ACE inhibitor therapy may cause excessive hypotension, which may be associated with oliguria or azotemia and rarely, with acute renal failure and death. In such patients, initiate ALTACE therapy under close medical supervision and follow patients closely for the first 2 weeks of treatment and whenever the dose of ALTACE or diuretic is increased.           Surgery and Anesthesia  In patients undergoing surgery or during anesthesia with agents that produce hypotension, ramipril may block angiotensin II formation that would otherwise occur secondary to compensatory renin release. Hypotension that occurs as a result of this mechanism can be corrected by volume expansion.                  Pregnancy Category D  Use of drugs that act on the renin-angiotensin system during the second and third trimesters of pregnancy reduces fetal renal function and increases fetal and neonatal morbidity and death. Resulting oligohydramnios can be associated with fetal lung hypoplasia and skeletal deformations. Potential neonatal adverse effects include skull hypoplasia, anuria, hypotension, renal failure, and death. When pregnancy is detected, discontinue ALTACE as soon as possible [see Use in Specific Populations (8.1)].             Dual blockade of the RAS with angiotensin receptor blockers, ACE inhibitors, or aliskiren is associated with increased risks of hypotension, hyperkalemia, and changes in renal function (including acute renal failure) compared to monotherapy. Closely monitor blood pressure, renal function and electrolytes in patients on ALTACE and other agents that affect the RAS.          Telmisartan  The ONTARGET trial enrolled 25,620 patients &amp;gt;55 years old with atherosclerotic disease or diabetes with end-organ damage, randomized them to telmisartan only, ramipril only, or the combination, and followed them for a median of 56 months. Patients receiving the combination of telmisartan and ramipril did not obtain any benefit in the composite endpoint of cardiovascular death, MI, stroke and heart failure hospitalization compared to monotherapy, but experienced an increased incidence of clinically important renal dysfunction (death, doubling of serum creatinine, or dialysis) compared with groups receiving telmisartan alone or ramipril alone. Concomitant use of telmisartan and ramipril is not recommended.            Aliskiren    Do not co-administer aliskiren with ALTACE in patients with diabetes. Avoid concomitant use of aliskiren with ALTACE in patients with renal impairment (GFR &amp;lt;60 mL/min/1.73 m2) [see Drug Interactions (7.6)].              In clinical trials with ALTACE, hyperkalemia (serum potassium &amp;gt;5.7 mEq/L) occurred in approximately 1% of hypertensive patients receiving ALTACE. In most cases, these were isolated values, which resolved despite continued therapy. None of these patients were discontinued from the trials because of hyperkalemia. Risk factors for the development of hyperkalemia include renal insufficiency, diabetes mellitus, and the concomitant use of potassium-sparing diuretics, potassium supplements, and/or potassium-containing salt substitutes, which should be used cautiously, if at all, with ALTACE [see Drug Interactions (7.1)].          Presumably caused by inhibition of the degradation of endogenous bradykinin, persistent nonproductive cough has been reported with all ACE inhibitors, always resolving after discontinuation of therapy. Consider the possibility of angiotensin converting enzyme inhibitor induced-cough in the differential diagnosis of cough.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Ramipril and ramiprilat inhibit ACE in human subjects and animals. Angiotensin converting enzyme is a peptidyl dipeptidase that catalyzes the conversion of angiotensin I to the vasoconstrictor substance, angiotensin II. Angiotensin II also stimulates aldosterone secretion by the adrenal cortex. Inhibition of ACE results in decreased plasma angiotensin II, which leads to decreased vasopressor activity and to decreased aldosterone secretion. The latter decrease may result in a small increase of serum potassium. In hypertensive patients with normal renal function treated with ALTACE alone for up to 56 weeks, approximately 4% of patients during the trial had an abnormally high serum potassium and an increase from baseline greater than 0.75 mEq/L, and none of the patients had an abnormally low potassium and a decrease from baseline greater than 0.75 mEq/L. In the same study, approximately 2% of patients treated with ALTACE and hydrochlorothiazide for up to 56 weeks had abnormally high potassium values and an increase from baseline of 0.75 mEq/L or greater; and approximately 2% had abnormally low values and decreases from baseline of 0.75 mEq/L or greater [see Warnings and Precautions (5.8)]. Removal of angiotensin II negative feedback on renin secretion leads to increased plasma renin activity. The effect of ramipril on hypertension appears to result at least in part from inhibition of both tissue and circulating ACE activity, thereby reducing angiotensin II formation in tissue and plasma. Angiotensin converting enzyme is identical to kininase, an enzyme that degrades bradykinin. Whether increased levels of bradykinin, a potent vasopressor peptide, play a role in the therapeutic effects of ALTACE remains to be elucidated. While the mechanism through which ALTACE lowers blood pressure is believed to be primarily suppression of the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system, ALTACE has an antihypertensive effect even in patients with low-renin hypertension. Although ALTACE was antihypertensive in all races studied, Black hypertensive patients (usually a low-renin hypertensive population) had a blood pressure lowering response to monotherapy, albeit a smaller average response, than non-Black patients.          Single doses of ramipril of 2.5 mg–20 mg produce approximately 60%–80% inhibition of ACE activity 4 hours after dosing with approximately 40%–60% inhibition after 24 hours. Multiple oral doses of ramipril of 2.0 mg or more cause plasma ACE activity to fall by more than 90% 4 hours after dosing, with over 80% inhibition of ACE activity remaining 24 hours after dosing. The more prolonged effect of even small multiple doses presumably reflects saturation of ACE binding sites by ramiprilat and relatively slow release from those sites.                Absorption  Following oral administration of ALTACE, peak plasma concentrations (Cmax) of ramipril are reached within 1 hour. The extent of absorption is at least 50%–60%, and is not significantly influenced by the presence of food in the gastrointestinal tract, although the rate of absorption is reduced. In a trial in which subjects received ALTACE capsules or the contents of identical capsules dissolved in water, dissolved in apple juice, or suspended in applesauce, serum ramiprilat levels were essentially unrelated to the use or non-use of the concomitant liquid or food.           Distribution  Cleavage of the ester group (primarily in the liver) converts ramipril to its active diacid metabolite, ramiprilat. Peak plasma concentrations of ramiprilat are reached 2–4 hours after drug intake. The serum protein binding of ramipril is about 73% and that of ramiprilat about 56%; in vitro, these percentages are independent of concentration over the range of 0.01 µg/mL–10 µg/mL.           Metabolism  Ramipril is almost completely metabolized to ramiprilat, which has about 6 times the ACE inhibitory activity of ramipril, and to the diketopiperazine ester, the diketopiperazine acid, and the glucuronides of ramipril and ramiprilat, all of which are inactive. Plasma concentrations of ramipril and ramiprilat increase with increased dose, but are not strictly dose-proportional. The 24-hour AUC for ramiprilat, however, is dose-proportional over the 2.5 mg–20 mg dose range. The absolute bioavailabilities of ramipril and ramiprilat were 28% and 44%, respectively, when 5 mg of oral ramipril was compared with the same dose of ramipril given intravenously. After once-daily dosing, steady-state plasma concentrations of ramiprilat are reached by the fourth dose. Steady-state concentrations of ramiprilat are somewhat higher than those seen after the first dose of ALTACE, especially at low doses (2.5 mg), but the difference is clinically insignificant. Plasma concentrations of ramiprilat decline in a triphasic manner (initial rapid decline, apparent elimination phase, terminal elimination phase). The initial rapid decline, which represents distribution of the drug into a large peripheral compartment and subsequent binding to both plasma and tissue ACE, has a half-life of 2–4 hours. Because of its potent binding to ACE and slow dissociation from the enzyme, ramiprilat shows two elimination phases. The apparent elimination phase corresponds to the clearance of free ramiprilat and has a half-life of 9–18 hours. The terminal elimination phase has a prolonged half-life (&amp;gt;50 hours) and probably represents the binding/dissociation kinetics of the ramiprilat/ACE complex. It does not contribute to the accumulation of the drug. After multiple daily doses of ALTACE 5 mg–10 mg, the half-life of ramiprilat concentrations within the therapeutic range was 13–17 hours. In patients with creatinine clearance &amp;lt;40 mL/min/1.73 m2, peak levels of ramiprilat are approximately doubled, and trough levels may be as much as quintupled. In multiple-dose regimens, the total exposure to ramiprilat (AUC) in these patients is 3–4 times as large as it is in patients with normal renal function who receive similar doses. In patients with impaired liver function, the metabolism of ramipril to ramiprilat appears to be slowed, possibly because of diminished activity of hepatic esterases, and plasma ramipril levels in these patients are increased about 3-fold. Peak concentrations of ramiprilat in these patients, however, are not different from those seen in subjects with normal hepatic function, and the effect of a given dose on plasma ACE activity does not vary with hepatic function.           Excretion  After oral administration of ramipril, about 60% of the parent drug and its metabolites are eliminated in the urine, and about 40% is found in the feces. Drug recovered in the feces may represent both biliary excretion of metabolites and/or unabsorbed drug, however the proportion of a dose eliminated by the bile has not been determined. Less than 2% of the administered dose is recovered in urine as unchanged ramipril. The urinary excretion of ramipril, ramiprilat, and their metabolites is reduced in patients with impaired renal function. Compared to normal subjects, patients with creatinine clearance &amp;lt;40 mL/min/1.73 m2 had higher peak and trough ramiprilat levels and slightly longer times to peak concentrations.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="6491" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>When pregnancy is detected, discontinue ALTACE as soon as possible (5.6).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6492" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause injury and death to the developing fetus (5.6).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6493" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>WARNING: FETAL TOXICITY See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning When pregnancy is detected, discontinue ALTACE as soon as possible (5.6).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6494" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>ALTACE is contraindicated in patients who are hypersensitive to this product or any other ACE inhibitor (e.g., a patient who has experienced angioedema during therapy with any other ACE inhibitor).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6495" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>ALTACE is contraindicated in combination with a neprilysin inhibitor (e.g., sacubitril).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M3" type="Trigger" span="10 15" str="contraindicated"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="48 20" str="neprilysin inhibitor" code="N0000191728"/>
<Mention id="M4" type="Precipitant" span="76 10" str="sacubitril" code="17ERJ0MKGI"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M3" precipitant="M2"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M3" precipitant="M4"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6496" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Do not administer ALTACE within 36 hours of switching to or from sacubitril/valsartan, a neprilysin inhibitor.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M7" type="Trigger" span="0 17" str="Do not administer"/>
<Mention id="M6" type="Precipitant" span="89 20" str="neprilysin inhibitor" code="N0000191728"/>
<Mention id="M8" type="Precipitant" span="65 20" str="sacubitril/valsartan" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M7" precipitant="M6"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M7" precipitant="M8"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6497" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Do not co-administer ALTACE with aliskiren: in patients with diabetes Angioedema related to previous treatment with an ACE inhibitor, or a history of hereditary or idiopathic angioedema (4).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M9" type="Trigger" span="0 20" str="Do not co-administer"/>
<Mention id="M10" type="Precipitant" span="33 9" str="aliskiren" code="502FWN4Q32"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M9" precipitant="M10"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6498" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Do not administer ALTACE within 36 hours of switching to or from sacubitril/valsartan, a neprilysin inhibitor (4).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M13" type="Trigger" span="0 17" str="Do not administer"/>
<Mention id="M12" type="Precipitant" span="89 20" str="neprilysin inhibitor" code="N0000191728"/>
<Mention id="M14" type="Precipitant" span="65 20" str="sacubitril/valsartan" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M13" precipitant="M12"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M13" precipitant="M14"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6499" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Do not co-administer aliskiren with ALTACE in patients with diabetes (4).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M15" type="Trigger" span="0 20" str="Do not co-administer"/>
<Mention id="M16" type="Precipitant" span="21 9" str="aliskiren" code="502FWN4Q32"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M15" precipitant="M16"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6500" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Hypertension: Initial dose is 2.5 mg to 20 mg once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6501" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Adjust dosage according to blood pressure response after 2–4 weeks of treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6502" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The usual maintenance dose following titration is 2.5 mg to 20 mg daily as a single dose or equally divided doses (2.1).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6503" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Reduction in the risk of myocardial infarction, stroke, or death from cardiovascular causes: 2.5 mg once daily for 1 week, 5 mg once daily for 3 weeks, and increased as tolerated to a maintenance dose of 10 mg once daily (2.2).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6504" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Heart failure post-myocardial infarction: Starting dose of 2.5 mg twice daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6505" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If patient becomes hypotensive at this dose, decrease dosage to 1.25 mg twice daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6506" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Increase dose as tolerated toward a target dose of 5 mg twice daily, with dosage increases about 3 weeks apart (2.3).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6507" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dosage adjustment: See respective sections pertaining to dosage adjustment in special situations (2.5).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6508" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommended initial dose for patients not receiving a diuretic is 2.5 mg once a day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6509" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Adjust dose according to blood pressure response.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6510" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The usual maintenance dosage range is 2.5 mg to 20 mg per day administered as a single dose or in two equally divided doses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6511" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In some patients treated once daily, the antihypertensive effect may diminish toward the end of the dosing interval.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6512" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In such patients, consider an increase in dosage or twice daily administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6513" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If blood pressure is not controlled with ALTACE alone, a diuretic can be added.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6514" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Initiate dosing at 2.5 mg once daily for 1 week, 5 mg once daily for the next 3 weeks, and then increase as tolerated, to a maintenance dose of 10 mg once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6515" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If the patient is hypertensive or recently post-myocardial infarction, ALTACE can also be given as a divided dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6516" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For the treatment of post-myocardial infarction patients who have shown signs of congestive heart failure, the recommended starting dose of ALTACE is 2.5 mg twice daily (5 mg per day).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6517" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>A patient who becomes hypotensive at this dose may be switched to 1.25 mg twice daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6518" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>After one week at the starting dose, increase dose (if tolerated) toward a target dose of 5 mg twice daily, with dosage increases being about 3 weeks apart.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6519" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>After the initial dose of ALTACE, observe the patient under medical supervision for at least two hours and until blood pressure has stabilized for at least an additional hour.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6520" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If possible, reduce the dose of any concomitant diuretic as this may diminish the likelihood of hypotension.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M17" type="Trigger" span="13 15;69 23" str="reduce the dose | diminish the likelihood"/>
<Mention id="M18" type="Precipitant" span="48 8" str="diuretic" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M19" type="SpecificInteraction" span="96 11" str="hypotension" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M17" precipitant="M18" effect="M19"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6521" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The appearance of hypotension after the initial dose of ALTACE does not preclude subsequent careful dose titration with the drug, following effective management of the hypotension.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6522" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Generally, swallow ALTACE capsules whole.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6523" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The ALTACE capsule can also be opened and the contents sprinkled on a small amount (about 4 oz.) of applesauce or mixed in 4 oz.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6524" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>To be sure that ramipril is not lost when such a mixture is used, consume the mixture in its entirety.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6525" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The described mixtures can be pre-prepared and stored for up to 24 hours at room temperature or up to 48 hours under refrigeration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6526" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant administration of ALTACE with potassium supplements, potassium salt substitutes, or potassium-sparing diuretics can lead to increases of serum potassium.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M26" type="Trigger" span="128 7" str="lead to"/>
<Mention id="M21" type="Precipitant" span="65 26" str="potassium salt substitutes" code="N0000175600"/>
<Mention id="M28" type="SpecificInteraction" span="136 28" str="increases of serum potassium" code="166689004: Raised serum potassium level (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M24" type="Precipitant" span="42 21" str="potassium supplements" code="RWP5GA015D"/>
<Mention id="M27" type="Precipitant" span="96 27" str="potassium-sparing diuretics" code="N0000175418"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M26" precipitant="M21" effect="M28"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M26" precipitant="M24" effect="M28"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M26" precipitant="M27" effect="M28"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6527" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Renal Impairment Establish baseline renal function in patients initiating ALTACE.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6528" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Usual regimens of therapy with ALTACE may be followed in patients with estimated creatinine clearance &gt;40 mL/min.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6529" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>However, in patients with worse impairment, 25% of the usual dose of ramipril is expected to produce full therapeutic levels of ramiprilat.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6530" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Hypertension For patients with hypertension and renal impairment, the recommended initial dose is 1.25 mg ALTACE once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6531" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dosage may be titrated upward until blood pressure is controlled or to a maximum total daily dose of 5 mg. Heart Failure Post-Myocardial Infarction For patients with heart failure and renal impairment, the recommended initial dose is 1.25 mg ALTACE once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6532" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The dose may be increased to 1.25 mg twice daily, and up to a maximum dose of 2.5 mg twice daily depending on clinical response and tolerability.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6533" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Volume Depletion or Renal Artery Stenosis Blood pressure decreases associated with any dose of ALTACE depend, in part, on the presence or absence of volume depletion (e.g., past and current diuretic use) or the presence or absence of renal artery stenosis.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M29" type="Trigger" span="67 15" str="associated with "/>
<Mention id="M30" type="Trigger" span="102 6;14 2" str=" depend | on"/>
<Mention id="M31" type="Precipitant" span="190 8" str="diuretic" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M32" type="SpecificInteraction" span="42 24" str="Blood pressure decreases" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M29;M30" precipitant="M31" effect="M32"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6534" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If such circumstances are suspected to be present, initiate dosing at 1.25 mg once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6535" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Adjust dosage according to blood pressure response.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6536" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Diuretics: Possibility of excessive hypotension (7.1).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M33" type="Trigger" span="26 9" str="excessive"/>
<Mention id="M34" type="Precipitant" span="0 9" str="Diuretics" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M35" type="SpecificInteraction" span="36 11" str="hypotension" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M33" precipitant="M34" effect="M35"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6537" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Gold: Nitritoid reactions have been reported (7.5).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M38" type="SpecificInteraction" span="6 19" str="Nitritoid reactions" code="426711003: Nitritoid reaction (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M37" type="Precipitant" span="0 4" str="Gold" code="79Y1949PYO"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M38" precipitant="M37" effect="M38"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6538" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>NSAIDS use may lead to increased risk of renal impairment and loss of antihypertensive effect (7.6). mTOR inhibitor or neprilysin inhibitor use may increase angioedema risk (7.7).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M42" type="Trigger" span="23 8;33 4" str="increase | risk"/>
<Mention id="M40" type="Precipitant" span="101 14" str="mTOR inhibitor" code="N0000175624"/>
<Mention id="M44" type="SpecificInteraction" span="157 10" str="angioedema" code="41291007: Angioedema (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M43" type="Precipitant" span="119 20" str="neprilysin inhibitor" code="N0000191728"/>
<Mention id="M49" type="Trigger" span="15 7" str="lead to "/>
<Mention id="M50" type="Trigger" span="23 14" str=" increased risk"/>
<Mention id="M51" type="Precipitant" span="0 6" str="NSAIDS" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M48" type="SpecificInteraction" span="41 16" str="renal impairment" code="236423003: Renal impairment (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M52" type="SpecificInteraction" span="62 31" str="loss of antihypertensive effect" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M42" precipitant="M40" effect="M44"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M42" precipitant="M43" effect="M44"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M49;M50" precipitant="M51" effect="M48"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M49;M50" precipitant="M51" effect="M52"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6539" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Patients on diuretics, especially those in whom diuretic therapy was recently instituted, may occasionally experience an excessive reduction of blood pressure after initiation of therapy with ALTACE.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M53" type="Trigger" span="121 9" str="excessive"/>
<Mention id="M54" type="Precipitant" span="12 9" str="diuretics" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M55" type="SpecificInteraction" span="131 27" str="reduction of blood pressure" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M53" precipitant="M54" effect="M55"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6540" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The possibility of hypotensive effects with ALTACE can be minimized by either decreasing or discontinuing the diuretic or increasing the salt intake prior to initiation of treatment with ALTACE.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M56" type="Trigger" span="31 7;58 47" str="effects | minimized by either decreasing or discontinuing"/>
<Mention id="M57" type="Precipitant" span="110 8" str="diuretic" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M58" type="SpecificInteraction" span="19 19;58 47" str="hypotensive effects | minimized by either decreasing or discontinuing" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M56" precipitant="M57" effect="M58"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6541" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>If this is not possible, reduce the starting dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6542" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Coadministration of ALTACE with other drugs that raise serum potassium levels may result in hyperkalemia.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M59" type="Trigger" span="82 9" str="result in"/>
<Mention id="M60" type="Precipitant" span="38 39" str="drugs that raise serum potassium levels" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M61" type="SpecificInteraction" span="92 12" str="hyperkalemia" code="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M59" precipitant="M60" effect="M61"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6543" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor serum potassium in such patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6544" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>In general, avoid combined use of RAS inhibitors.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M62" type="Trigger" span="12 5" str="avoid"/>
<Mention id="M63" type="Precipitant" span="34 14" str="RAS inhibitors" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M62" precipitant="M63"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6545" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Do not co-administer aliskiren with ALTACE in patients with diabetes.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M64" type="Trigger" span="0 20" str="Do not co-administer"/>
<Mention id="M65" type="Precipitant" span="21 9" str="aliskiren" code="502FWN4Q32"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M64" precipitant="M65"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6546" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Increased serum lithium levels and symptoms of lithium toxicity have been reported in patients receiving ACE inhibitors during therapy with lithium; therefore, frequent monitoring of serum lithium levels is recommended.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M66" type="Trigger" span="0 15;24 6" str="Increased serum | levels "/>
<Mention id="M67" type="Trigger" span="55 8" str=" toxicity"/>
<Mention id="M68" type="Precipitant" span="16 7" str="lithium" code="9FN79X2M3F"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M66;M67" precipitant="M68" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6547" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>If a diuretic is also used, the risk of lithium toxicity may be increased.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M69" type="Trigger" span="32 4;64 9" str="risk | increased"/>
<Mention id="M70" type="Precipitant" span="5 8" str="diuretic" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M71" type="SpecificInteraction" span="-1 16" str="Lithium toxicity" code="290802009: Lithium poisoning (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M69" precipitant="M70" effect="M71"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6548" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Nitritoid reactions (symptoms include facial flushing, nausea, vomiting and hypotension) have been reported rarely in patients on therapy with injectable gold (sodium aurothiomalate) and concomitant ACE inhibitor therapy including ALTACE.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M135" type="Trigger" span="0 19" str="Nitritoid reactions "/>
<Mention id="M136" type="Trigger" span="38 15" str=" facial flushing "/>
<Mention id="M137" type="Trigger" span="55 6" str=" nausea "/>
<Mention id="M138" type="Trigger" span="63 8" str=" vomiting "/>
<Mention id="M139" type="Trigger" span="76 11" str=" hypotension"/>
<Mention id="M105" type="Precipitant" span="143 15" str="injectable gold" code="79Y1949PYO"/>
<Mention id="M120" type="SpecificInteraction" span="38 15" str="facial flushing" code="238810007: Flushing (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M141" type="SpecificInteraction" span="63 8" str="vomiting" code="422400008: Vomiting (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M134" type="SpecificInteraction" span="76 11" str="hypotension" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M113" type="SpecificInteraction" span="55 6" str="nausea" code="422587007: Nausea (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M127" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 19" str="Nitritoid reactions" code="426711003: Nitritoid reaction (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M140" type="Precipitant" span="160 21" str="sodium aurothiomalate" code="E4768ZY6GM"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M135;M136;M137;M138;M139" precipitant="M105" effect="M120"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M135;M136;M137;M138;M139" precipitant="M105" effect="M141"/>
<Interaction id="I29" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M135;M136;M137;M138;M139" precipitant="M105" effect="M134"/>
<Interaction id="I30" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M135;M136;M137;M138;M139" precipitant="M105" effect="M113"/>
<Interaction id="I31" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M135;M136;M137;M138;M139" precipitant="M105" effect="M127"/>
<Interaction id="I32" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M135;M136;M137;M138;M139" precipitant="M140" effect="M113"/>
<Interaction id="I33" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M135;M136;M137;M138;M139" precipitant="M140" effect="M120"/>
<Interaction id="I34" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M135;M136;M137;M138;M139" precipitant="M140" effect="M127"/>
<Interaction id="I35" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M135;M136;M137;M138;M139" precipitant="M140" effect="M134"/>
<Interaction id="I36" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M135;M136;M137;M138;M139" precipitant="M140" effect="M141"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6549" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>In patients who are elderly, volume-depleted (including those on diuretic therapy), or with compromised renal function, co-administration of NSAIDs, including selective COX-2 inhibitors, with ACE inhibitors, including ramipril, may result in deterioration of renal function, including possible acute renal failure.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M157" type="Trigger" span="232 9" str="result in"/>
<Mention id="M146" type="Precipitant" span="65 8" str="diuretic" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M156" type="SpecificInteraction" span="242 31" str="deterioration of renal function" code="236423003: Renal impairment (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M159" type="SpecificInteraction" span="294 19" str="acute renal failure" code="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M152" type="Precipitant" span="141 6" str="NSAIDs" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M158" type="Precipitant" span="159 26" str="selective COX-2 inhibitors" code="N0000008288"/>
<Interaction id="I37" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M157" precipitant="M146" effect="M156"/>
<Interaction id="I38" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M157" precipitant="M146" effect="M159"/>
<Interaction id="I39" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M157" precipitant="M152" effect="M159"/>
<Interaction id="I40" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M157" precipitant="M152" effect="M156"/>
<Interaction id="I41" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M157" precipitant="M158" effect="M156"/>
<Interaction id="I42" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M157" precipitant="M158" effect="M159"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6550" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor renal function periodically in patients receiving ramipril and NSAID therapy.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M160" type="Trigger" span="0 7" str="Monitor"/>
<Mention id="M161" type="Precipitant" span="71 5" str="NSAID" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M162" type="SpecificInteraction" span="8 14" str="renal function" code="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I43" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M160" precipitant="M161" effect="M162"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6551" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The antihypertensive effect of ACE inhibitors, including ramipril, may be attenuated by NSAIDs.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M163" type="Trigger" span="21 6;74 10" str="effect | attenuated"/>
<Mention id="M164" type="Precipitant" span="88 6" str="NSAIDs" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M165" type="SpecificInteraction" span="4 23;74 10" str="antihypertensive effect | attenuated" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I44" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M163" precipitant="M164" effect="M165"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6552" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Patients taking concomitant mTOR inhibitor (e.g. temsirolimus) therapy or a neprilysin inhibitor may be at increased risk for angioedema.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M172" type="Trigger" span="107 14" str="increased risk"/>
<Mention id="M167" type="Precipitant" span="28 14" str="mTOR inhibitor" code="N0000175624"/>
<Mention id="M174" type="SpecificInteraction" span="126 10" str="angioedema" code="41291007: Angioedema (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M170" type="Precipitant" span="76 20" str="neprilysin inhibitor" code="N0000191728"/>
<Mention id="M173" type="Precipitant" span="49 12" str="temsirolimus" code="624KN6GM2T"/>
<Interaction id="I45" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M172" precipitant="M167" effect="M174"/>
<Interaction id="I46" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M172" precipitant="M170" effect="M174"/>
<Interaction id="I47" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M172" precipitant="M173" effect="M174"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6553" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Angioedema, increased risk in patients with a prior history (5.1) Hypotension and hyperkalemia (5.5, 5.8) Renal impairment: monitor renal function during therapy (5.3) Avoid concomitant use of an ACE inhibitor and angiotensin blocker (5.7) Rare cholestatic jaundice and hepatic failure (5.2) Rare neutropenia and agranulocytosis (5.4) Presumably because drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system (e.g., ACE inhibitors) affect the metabolism of eicosanoids and polypeptides, including endogenous bradykinin, patients receiving these drugs (including ALTACE) may be subject to a variety of adverse reactions, some of them serious.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M175" type="Trigger" span="168 5" str="Avoid"/>
<Mention id="M176" type="Precipitant" span="214 19" str="angiotensin blocker" code="N0000175561"/>
<Interaction id="I48" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M175" precipitant="M176"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6554" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Angioedema Head and Neck Angioedema Patients with a history of angioedema unrelated to ACE inhibitor therapy may be at increased risk of angioedema while receiving an ACE inhibitor.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6555" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Angioedema of the face, extremities, lips, tongue, glottis, and larynx has been reported in patients treated with ACE inhibitors.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6556" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Angioedema associated with laryngeal edema can be fatal.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6557" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If laryngeal stridor or angioedema of the face, tongue, or glottis occurs, discontinue treatment with ALTACE and institute appropriate therapy immediately.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6558" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Where there is involvement of the tongue, glottis, or larynx likely to cause airway obstruction, administer appropriate therapy (e.g., subcutaneous epinephrine solution 1:1000 [0.3 mL to 0.5 mL]) promptly.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6559" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In considering the use of ALTACE, note that in controlled clinical trials ACE inhibitors cause a higher rate of angioedema in Black patients than in non-Black patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6560" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In a large U.S. post-marketing study, angioedema (defined as reports of angio, face, larynx, tongue, or throat edema) was reported in 3/1523 (0.20%) Black patients and in 8/8680 (0.09%) non-Black patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6561" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>These rates were not different statistically.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6562" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients taking concomitant mammalian target of rapamycin (mTOR) inhibitor (e.g. temsirolimus) therapy or a neprilysin inhibitor may be at increased risk for angioedema.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M186" type="Trigger" span="139 14" str="increased risk"/>
<Mention id="M178" type="Precipitant" span="28 29;65 9" str="mammalian target of rapamycin | inhibitor" code="N0000175624"/>
<Mention id="M188" type="SpecificInteraction" span="158 10" str="angioedema" code="41291007: Angioedema (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M181" type="Precipitant" span="59 4;65 9" str="mTOR | inhibitor" code="N0000175624"/>
<Mention id="M184" type="Precipitant" span="108 20" str="neprilysin inhibitor" code="N0000191728"/>
<Mention id="M187" type="Precipitant" span="81 12" str="temsirolimus" code="624KN6GM2T"/>
<Interaction id="I49" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M186" precipitant="M178" effect="M188"/>
<Interaction id="I50" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M186" precipitant="M181" effect="M188"/>
<Interaction id="I51" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M186" precipitant="M184" effect="M188"/>
<Interaction id="I52" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M186" precipitant="M187" effect="M188"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6563" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Intestinal Angioedema Intestinal angioedema has been reported in patients treated with ACE inhibitors.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6564" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>These patients presented with abdominal pain (with or without nausea or vomiting); in some cases there was no prior history of facial angioedema and C-1 esterase levels were normal.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6565" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The angioedema was diagnosed by procedures including abdominal CT scan or ultrasound, or at surgery, and symptoms resolved after stopping the ACE inhibitor.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6566" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Include intestinal angioedema in the differential diagnosis of patients on ACE inhibitors presenting with abdominal pain.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6567" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Anaphylactoid Reactions During Desensitization Two patients undergoing desensitizing treatment with hymenoptera venom while receiving ACE inhibitors sustained life-threatening anaphylactoid reactions.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M189" type="Trigger" span="190 9" str="reactions"/>
<Mention id="M190" type="Precipitant" span="100 17" str="hymenoptera venom" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M191" type="SpecificInteraction" span="159 40" str="life-threatening anaphylactoid reactions" code="35001004: Anaphylactoid reaction (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I53" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M189" precipitant="M190" effect="M191"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6568" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In the same patients, these reactions were avoided when ACE inhibitors were temporarily withheld, but they reappeared upon inadvertent rechallenge.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6569" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Anaphylactoid Reactions During Membrane Exposure Anaphylactoid reactions have been reported in patients dialyzed with high-flux membranes and treated concomitantly with an ACE inhibitor.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6570" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Anaphylactoid reactions have also been reported in patients undergoing low-density lipoprotein apheresis with dextran sulfate absorption.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M192" type="Trigger" span="14 9" str="reactions"/>
<Mention id="M193" type="Precipitant" span="110 15" str="dextran sulfate" code="01W9V5H5WO"/>
<Mention id="M194" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 23" str="Anaphylactoid reactions" code="35001004: Anaphylactoid reaction (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I54" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M192" precipitant="M193" effect="M194"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6571" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Rarely, ACE inhibitors, including ALTACE, have been associated with a syndrome that starts with cholestatic jaundice and progresses to fulminant hepatic necrosis and sometimes death.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6572" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The mechanism of this syndrome is not understood.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6573" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Discontinue ALTACE if patient develops jaundice or marked elevations of hepatic enzymes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6574" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>As ramipril is primarily metabolized by hepatic esterases to its active moiety, ramiprilat, patients with impaired liver function could develop markedly elevated plasma levels of ramipril.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6575" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>No formal pharmacokinetic studies have been carried out in hypertensive patients with impaired liver function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6576" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>As a consequence of inhibiting the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system, changes in renal function may be anticipated in susceptible individuals.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6577" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In patients with severe congestive heart failure whose renal function may depend on the activity of the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system, treatment with ACE inhibitors, including ALTACE, may be associated with oliguria or progressive azotemia and rarely with acute renal failure or death.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6578" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In hypertensive patients with unilateral or bilateral renal artery stenosis, increases in blood urea nitrogen and serum creatinine may occur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6579" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Experience with another ACE inhibitor suggests that these increases would be reversible upon discontinuation of ALTACE and/or diuretic therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6580" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In such patients, monitor renal function during the first few weeks of therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6581" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Some hypertensive patients with no apparent pre-existing renal vascular disease have developed increases in blood urea nitrogen and serum creatinine, usually minor and transient, especially when ALTACE has been given concomitantly with a diuretic.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M198" type="Trigger" span="95 9" str="increases"/>
<Mention id="M199" type="Precipitant" span="238 8" str="diuretic" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M197" type="SpecificInteraction" span="95 32" str="increases in blood urea nitrogen" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M200" type="SpecificInteraction" span="95 9;132 16" str="increases | serum creatinine" code="166717003: Serum creatinine raised (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I55" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M198" precipitant="M199" effect="M197"/>
<Interaction id="I56" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M198" precipitant="M199" effect="M200"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6582" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>This is more likely to occur in patients with pre-existing renal impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6583" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Dosage reduction of ALTACE and/or discontinuation of the diuretic may be required.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M201" type="Trigger" span="34 15" str="discontinuation"/>
<Mention id="M202" type="Precipitant" span="57 8" str="diuretic" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I57" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M201" precipitant="M202"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6584" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In rare instances, treatment with ACE inhibitors may be associated with mild reductions in red blood cell count and hemoglobin content, blood cell or platelet counts.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6585" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In isolated cases, agranulocytosis, pancytopenia, and bone marrow depression may occur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6586" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hematological reactions to ACE inhibitors are more likely to occur in patients with collagen-vascular disease (e.g., systemic lupus erythematosus, scleroderma) and renal impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6587" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Consider monitoring white blood cell counts in patients with collagen-vascular disease, especially if the disease is associated with impaired renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6588" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>General Considerations ALTACE can cause symptomatic hypotension, after either the initial dose or a later dose when the dosage has been increased.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6589" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Like other ACE inhibitors, ALTACE, has been only rarely associated with hypotension in uncomplicated hypertensive patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6590" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Symptomatic hypotension is most likely to occur in patients who have been volume- and/or salt-depleted as a result of prolonged diuretic therapy, dietary salt restriction, dialysis, diarrhea, or vomiting.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M203" type="Trigger" span="0 23" str="Symptomatic hypotension"/>
<Mention id="M204" type="Precipitant" span="128 8" str="diuretic" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M205" type="SpecificInteraction" span="-1 23" str="symptomatic hypotension" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I58" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M203" precipitant="M204" effect="M205"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6591" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Correct volume- and salt-depletion before initiating therapy with ALTACE.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6592" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If excessive hypotension occurs, place the patient in a supine position and, if necessary, treat with intravenous infusion of physiological saline.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6593" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>ALTACE treatment usually can be continued following restoration of blood pressure and volume.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6594" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Heart Failure Post-Myocardial Infarction In patients with heart failure post-myocardial infarction who are currently being treated with a diuretic, symptomatic hypotension occasionally can occur following the initial dose of ALTACE.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M208" type="SpecificInteraction" span="148 23" str="symptomatic hypotension" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M207" type="Precipitant" span="138 8" str="diuretic" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I59" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M208" precipitant="M207" effect="M208"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6595" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If the initial dose of 2.5 mg ALTACE cannot be tolerated, use an initial dose of 1.25 mg ALTACE to avoid excessive hypotension.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6596" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Consider reducing the dose of concomitant diuretic to decrease the incidence of hypotension.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M209" type="Trigger" span="9 17;51 25" str="reducing the dose | to decrease the incidence"/>
<Mention id="M210" type="Precipitant" span="42 8" str="diuretic" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M211" type="SpecificInteraction" span="80 11" str="hypotension" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I60" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M209" precipitant="M210" effect="M211"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6597" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Congestive Heart Failure In patients with congestive heart failure, with or without associated renal insufficiency, ACE inhibitor therapy may cause excessive hypotension, which may be associated with oliguria or azotemia and rarely, with acute renal failure and death.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6598" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In such patients, initiate ALTACE therapy under close medical supervision and follow patients closely for the first 2 weeks of treatment and whenever the dose of ALTACE or diuretic is increased.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6599" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Surgery and Anesthesia In patients undergoing surgery or during anesthesia with agents that produce hypotension, ramipril may block angiotensin II formation that would otherwise occur secondary to compensatory renin release.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M212" type="Trigger" span="126 5" str="block"/>
<Mention id="M213" type="Precipitant" span="64 47" str="anesthesia with agents that produce hypotension" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M214" type="SpecificInteraction" span="126 30" str="block angiotensin II formation" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I61" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M212" precipitant="M213" effect="M214"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6600" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hypotension that occurs as a result of this mechanism can be corrected by volume expansion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6601" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Use of drugs that act on the renin-angiotensin system during the second and third trimesters of pregnancy reduces fetal renal function and increases fetal and neonatal morbidity and death.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6602" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Resulting oligohydramnios can be associated with fetal lung hypoplasia and skeletal deformations.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6603" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Potential neonatal adverse effects include skull hypoplasia, anuria, hypotension, renal failure, and death.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6604" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>When pregnancy is detected, discontinue ALTACE as soon as possible.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6605" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Dual blockade of the RAS with angiotensin receptor blockers, ACE inhibitors, or aliskiren is associated with increased risks of hypotension, hyperkalemia, and changes in renal function (including acute renal failure) compared to monotherapy.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M275" type="Trigger" span="93 15" str="associated with "/>
<Mention id="M276" type="Trigger" span="109 15" str=" increased risks"/>
<Mention id="M229" type="Precipitant" span="61 14" str="ACE inhibitors" code="N0000175562"/>
<Mention id="M270" type="SpecificInteraction" span="159 25" str="changes in renal function" code="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M274" type="SpecificInteraction" span="141 12" str="hyperkalemia" code="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M278" type="SpecificInteraction" span="196 19" str="acute renal failure" code="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M266" type="SpecificInteraction" span="128 11" str="hypotension" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M245" type="Precipitant" span="80 9" str="aliskiren" code="502FWN4Q32"/>
<Mention id="M261" type="Precipitant" span="30 29" str="angiotensin receptor blockers" code="N0000175561"/>
<Mention id="M277" type="Precipitant" span="0 24" str="Dual blockade of the RAS" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I62" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M275;M276" precipitant="M229" effect="M270"/>
<Interaction id="I63" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M275;M276" precipitant="M229" effect="M274"/>
<Interaction id="I64" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M275;M276" precipitant="M229" effect="M278"/>
<Interaction id="I65" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M275;M276" precipitant="M229" effect="M266"/>
<Interaction id="I66" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M275;M276" precipitant="M245" effect="M278"/>
<Interaction id="I67" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M275;M276" precipitant="M245" effect="M270"/>
<Interaction id="I68" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M275;M276" precipitant="M245" effect="M274"/>
<Interaction id="I69" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M275;M276" precipitant="M245" effect="M266"/>
<Interaction id="I70" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M275;M276" precipitant="M261" effect="M274"/>
<Interaction id="I71" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M275;M276" precipitant="M261" effect="M266"/>
<Interaction id="I72" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M275;M276" precipitant="M261" effect="M278"/>
<Interaction id="I73" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M275;M276" precipitant="M261" effect="M270"/>
<Interaction id="I74" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M275;M276" precipitant="M277" effect="M266"/>
<Interaction id="I75" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M275;M276" precipitant="M277" effect="M270"/>
<Interaction id="I76" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M275;M276" precipitant="M277" effect="M274"/>
<Interaction id="I77" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M275;M276" precipitant="M277" effect="M278"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6606" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Most patients receiving the combination of two RAS inhibitors do not obtain any additional benefit compared to monotherapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6607" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Closely monitor blood pressure, renal function and electrolytes in patients on ALTACE and other agents that affect the RAS.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M285" type="Trigger" span="0 15" str="Closely monitor"/>
<Mention id="M286" type="Precipitant" span="96 26" str="agents that affect the RAS" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M281" type="SpecificInteraction" span="51 12" str="electrolytes" code="166686006: Electrolytes abnormal (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M284" type="SpecificInteraction" span="32 14" str="renal function" code="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M287" type="SpecificInteraction" span="16 14" str="blood pressure" code="38936003: Abnormal blood pressure (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I78" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M285" precipitant="M286" effect="M281"/>
<Interaction id="I79" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M285" precipitant="M286" effect="M284"/>
<Interaction id="I80" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M285" precipitant="M286" effect="M287"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6608" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Telmisartan The ONTARGET trial enrolled 25,620 patients &gt;55 years old with atherosclerotic disease or diabetes with end-organ damage, randomized them to telmisartan only, ramipril only, or the combination, and followed them for a median of 56 months.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6609" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients receiving the combination of telmisartan and ramipril did not obtain any benefit in the composite endpoint of cardiovascular death, MI, stroke and heart failure hospitalization compared to monotherapy, but experienced an increased incidence of clinically important renal dysfunction (death, doubling of serum creatinine, or dialysis) compared with groups receiving telmisartan alone or ramipril alone.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M297" type="Trigger" span="230 19" str="increased incidence"/>
<Mention id="M298" type="Precipitant" span="38 11" str="telmisartan" code="U5SYW473RQ"/>
<Mention id="M290" type="SpecificInteraction" span="333 8" str="dialysis" code="251859005: Dialysis finding (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M293" type="SpecificInteraction" span="274 17" str="renal dysfunction" code="236423003: Renal impairment (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M296" type="SpecificInteraction" span="300 28" str="doubling of serum creatinine" code="166717003: Serum creatinine raised (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M299" type="SpecificInteraction" span="134 5" str="death" code="419620001: Death (event)"/>
<Interaction id="I81" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M297" precipitant="M298" effect="M290"/>
<Interaction id="I82" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M297" precipitant="M298" effect="M293"/>
<Interaction id="I83" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M297" precipitant="M298" effect="M296"/>
<Interaction id="I84" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M297" precipitant="M298" effect="M299"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6610" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant use of telmisartan and ramipril is not recommended.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M300" type="Trigger" span="47 15" str="not recommended"/>
<Mention id="M301" type="Precipitant" span="19 11" str="telmisartan" code="U5SYW473RQ"/>
<Interaction id="I85" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M300" precipitant="M301"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6611" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Aliskiren Do not co-administer aliskiren with ALTACE in patients with diabetes.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M302" type="Trigger" span="10 20" str="Do not co-administer"/>
<Mention id="M303" type="Precipitant" span="31 9" str="aliskiren" code="502FWN4Q32"/>
<Interaction id="I86" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M302" precipitant="M303"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6612" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Avoid concomitant use of aliskiren with ALTACE in patients with renal impairment (GFR &lt;60 mL/min/1.73 m2).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M304" type="Trigger" span="0 5" str="Avoid"/>
<Mention id="M305" type="Precipitant" span="25 9" str="aliskiren" code="502FWN4Q32"/>
<Interaction id="I87" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M304" precipitant="M305"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6613" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In clinical trials with ALTACE, hyperkalemia (serum potassium &gt;5.7 mEq/L) occurred in approximately 1% of hypertensive patients receiving ALTACE.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6614" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In most cases, these were isolated values, which resolved despite continued therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6615" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>None of these patients were discontinued from the trials because of hyperkalemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6616" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Risk factors for the development of hyperkalemia include renal insufficiency, diabetes mellitus, and the concomitant use of other drugs that raise serum potassium levels.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M306" type="Trigger" span="0 12" str="Risk factors"/>
<Mention id="M307" type="Precipitant" span="130 39" str="drugs that raise serum potassium levels" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M308" type="SpecificInteraction" span="36 12" str="hyperkalemia" code="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I88" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M306" precipitant="M307" effect="M308"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6617" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Presumably caused by inhibition of the degradation of endogenous bradykinin, persistent nonproductive cough has been reported with all ACE inhibitors, always resolving after discontinuation of therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6618" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Consider the possibility of angiotensin converting enzyme inhibitor induced-cough in the differential diagnosis of cough.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6619" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Ramipril and ramiprilat inhibit ACE in human subjects and animals.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6620" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Angiotensin converting enzyme is a peptidyl dipeptidase that catalyzes the conversion of angiotensin I to the vasoconstrictor substance, angiotensin II.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6621" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Angiotensin II also stimulates aldosterone secretion by the adrenal cortex.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6622" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Inhibition of ACE results in decreased plasma angiotensin II, which leads to decreased vasopressor activity and to decreased aldosterone secretion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6623" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The latter decrease may result in a small increase of serum potassium.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6624" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In hypertensive patients with normal renal function treated with ALTACE alone for up to 56 weeks, approximately 4% of patients during the trial had an abnormally high serum potassium and an increase from baseline greater than 0.75 mEq/L, and none of the patients had an abnormally low potassium and a decrease from baseline greater than 0.75 mEq/L.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6625" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In the same study, approximately 2% of patients treated with ALTACE and hydrochlorothiazide for up to 56 weeks had abnormally high potassium values and an increase from baseline of 0.75 mEq/L or greater; and approximately 2% had abnormally low values and decreases from baseline of 0.75 mEq/L or greater.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6626" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Removal of angiotensin II negative feedback on renin secretion leads to increased plasma renin activity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6627" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The effect of ramipril on hypertension appears to result at least in part from inhibition of both tissue and circulating ACE activity, thereby reducing angiotensin II formation in tissue and plasma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6628" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Angiotensin converting enzyme is identical to kininase, an enzyme that degrades bradykinin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6629" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Whether increased levels of bradykinin, a potent vasopressor peptide, play a role in the therapeutic effects of ALTACE remains to be elucidated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6630" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>While the mechanism through which ALTACE lowers blood pressure is believed to be primarily suppression of the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system, ALTACE has an antihypertensive effect even in patients with low-renin hypertension.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6631" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Although ALTACE was antihypertensive in all races studied, Black hypertensive patients (usually a low-renin hypertensive population) had a blood pressure lowering response to monotherapy, albeit a smaller average response, than non-Black patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6632" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Single doses of ramipril of 2.5 mg–20 mg produce approximately 60%–80% inhibition of ACE activity 4 hours after dosing with approximately 40%–60% inhibition after 24 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6633" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Multiple oral doses of ramipril of 2.0 mg or more cause plasma ACE activity to fall by more than 90% 4 hours after dosing, with over 80% inhibition of ACE activity remaining 24 hours after dosing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6634" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The more prolonged effect of even small multiple doses presumably reflects saturation of ACE binding sites by ramiprilat and relatively slow release from those sites.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6635" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Absorption Following oral administration of ALTACE, peak plasma concentrations (Cmax) of ramipril are reached within 1 hour.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6636" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The extent of absorption is at least 50%–60%, and is not significantly influenced by the presence of food in the gastrointestinal tract, although the rate of absorption is reduced.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6637" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In a trial in which subjects received ALTACE capsules or the contents of identical capsules dissolved in water, dissolved in apple juice, or suspended in applesauce, serum ramiprilat levels were essentially unrelated to the use or non-use of the concomitant liquid or food.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6638" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Distribution Cleavage of the ester group (primarily in the liver) converts ramipril to its active diacid metabolite, ramiprilat.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6639" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Peak plasma concentrations of ramiprilat are reached 2–4 hours after drug intake.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6640" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The serum protein binding of ramipril is about 73% and that of ramiprilat about 56%; in vitro, these percentages are independent of concentration over the range of 0.01 µg/mL–10 µg/mL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6641" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Metabolism Ramipril is almost completely metabolized to ramiprilat, which has about 6 times the ACE inhibitory activity of ramipril, and to the diketopiperazine ester, the diketopiperazine acid, and the glucuronides of ramipril and ramiprilat, all of which are inactive.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6642" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Plasma concentrations of ramipril and ramiprilat increase with increased dose, but are not strictly dose-proportional.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6643" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The 24-hour AUC for ramiprilat, however, is dose-proportional over the 2.5 mg–20 mg dose range.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6644" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The absolute bioavailabilities of ramipril and ramiprilat were 28% and 44%, respectively, when 5 mg of oral ramipril was compared with the same dose of ramipril given intravenously.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6645" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>After once-daily dosing, steady-state plasma concentrations of ramiprilat are reached by the fourth dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6646" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Steady-state concentrations of ramiprilat are somewhat higher than those seen after the first dose of ALTACE, especially at low doses (2.5 mg), but the difference is clinically insignificant.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6647" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Plasma concentrations of ramiprilat decline in a triphasic manner (initial rapid decline, apparent elimination phase, terminal elimination phase).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6648" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The initial rapid decline, which represents distribution of the drug into a large peripheral compartment and subsequent binding to both plasma and tissue ACE, has a half-life of 2–4 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6649" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Because of its potent binding to ACE and slow dissociation from the enzyme, ramiprilat shows two elimination phases.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6650" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The apparent elimination phase corresponds to the clearance of free ramiprilat and has a half-life of 9–18 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6651" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The terminal elimination phase has a prolonged half-life (&gt;50 hours) and probably represents the binding/dissociation kinetics of the ramiprilat/ACE complex.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6652" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>It does not contribute to the accumulation of the drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6653" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>After multiple daily doses of ALTACE 5 mg–10 mg, the half-life of ramiprilat concentrations within the therapeutic range was 13–17 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6654" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In patients with creatinine clearance &lt;40 mL/min/1.73 m2, peak levels of ramiprilat are approximately doubled, and trough levels may be as much as quintupled.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6655" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In multiple-dose regimens, the total exposure to ramiprilat (AUC) in these patients is 3–4 times as large as it is in patients with normal renal function who receive similar doses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6656" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In patients with impaired liver function, the metabolism of ramipril to ramiprilat appears to be slowed, possibly because of diminished activity of hepatic esterases, and plasma ramipril levels in these patients are increased about 3-fold.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6657" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Peak concentrations of ramiprilat in these patients, however, are not different from those seen in subjects with normal hepatic function, and the effect of a given dose on plasma ACE activity does not vary with hepatic function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6658" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Excretion After oral administration of ramipril, about 60% of the parent drug and its metabolites are eliminated in the urine, and about 40% is found in the feces.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6659" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Drug recovered in the feces may represent both biliary excretion of metabolites and/or unabsorbed drug, however the proportion of a dose eliminated by the bile has not been determined.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6660" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Less than 2% of the administered dose is recovered in urine as unchanged ramipril.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6661" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The urinary excretion of ramipril, ramiprilat, and their metabolites is reduced in patients with impaired renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6662" LabelDrug="ALTACE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Compared to normal subjects, patients with creatinine clearance &lt;40 mL/min/1.73 m2 had higher peak and trough ramiprilat levels and slightly longer times to peak concentrations.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="neprilysin inhibitor" precipitantCode="N0000191728" effect="41291007: Angioedema (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="neprilysin inhibitor" precipitantCode="N0000191728"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="sacubitril" precipitantCode="17ERJ0MKGI"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="sacubitril/valsartan" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="aliskiren" precipitantCode="502FWN4Q32" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="aliskiren" precipitantCode="502FWN4Q32" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="aliskiren" precipitantCode="502FWN4Q32" effect="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="aliskiren" precipitantCode="502FWN4Q32" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="aliskiren" precipitantCode="502FWN4Q32"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="diuretic" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect=" 39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="diuretic" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="diuretic" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="166717003: Serum creatinine raised (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="diuretic" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="236423003: Renal impairment (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="diuretic" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="290802009: Lithium poisoning (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="diuretic" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="diuretic" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="diuretic" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="potassium salt substitutes" precipitantCode="N0000175600" effect="166689004: Raised serum potassium level (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="potassium supplements" precipitantCode="RWP5GA015D" effect="166689004: Raised serum potassium level (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="potassium-sparing diuretics" precipitantCode="N0000175418" effect="166689004: Raised serum potassium level (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="diuretics" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="gold" precipitantCode="79Y1949PYO" effect="426711003: Nitritoid reaction (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="mtor inhibitor" precipitantCode="N0000175624" effect="41291007: Angioedema (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nsaids" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect=" 39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nsaids" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nsaids" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="236423003: Renal impairment (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nsaids" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="drugs that raise serum potassium levels" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="ras inhibitors" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="lithium" precipitantCode="9FN79X2M3F" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="injectable gold" precipitantCode="79Y1949PYO" effect="238810007: Flushing (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="injectable gold" precipitantCode="79Y1949PYO" effect="422400008: Vomiting (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="injectable gold" precipitantCode="79Y1949PYO" effect="422587007: Nausea (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="injectable gold" precipitantCode="79Y1949PYO" effect="426711003: Nitritoid reaction (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="injectable gold" precipitantCode="79Y1949PYO" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sodium aurothiomalate" precipitantCode="E4768ZY6GM" effect="238810007: Flushing (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sodium aurothiomalate" precipitantCode="E4768ZY6GM" effect="422400008: Vomiting (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sodium aurothiomalate" precipitantCode="E4768ZY6GM" effect="422587007: Nausea (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sodium aurothiomalate" precipitantCode="E4768ZY6GM" effect="426711003: Nitritoid reaction (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sodium aurothiomalate" precipitantCode="E4768ZY6GM" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="selective cox-2 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000008288" effect=" 39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="selective cox-2 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000008288" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="selective cox-2 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000008288" effect="236423003: Renal impairment (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nsaid" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="temsirolimus" precipitantCode="624KN6GM2T" effect="41291007: Angioedema (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="angiotensin blocker" precipitantCode="N0000175561"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="mammalian target of rapamycin | inhibitor" precipitantCode="N0000175624" effect="41291007: Angioedema (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="mtor | inhibitor" precipitantCode="N0000175624" effect="41291007: Angioedema (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="hymenoptera venom" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="35001004: Anaphylactoid reaction (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="dextran sulfate" precipitantCode="01W9V5H5WO" effect="35001004: Anaphylactoid reaction (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="anesthesia with agents that produce hypotension" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ace inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175562" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ace inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175562" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ace inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175562" effect="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ace inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175562" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="angiotensin receptor blockers" precipitantCode="N0000175561" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="angiotensin receptor blockers" precipitantCode="N0000175561" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="angiotensin receptor blockers" precipitantCode="N0000175561" effect="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="angiotensin receptor blockers" precipitantCode="N0000175561" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="dual blockade of the ras" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="dual blockade of the ras" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="dual blockade of the ras" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="dual blockade of the ras" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="agents that affect the ras" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="166686006: Electrolytes abnormal (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="agents that affect the ras" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="38936003: Abnormal blood pressure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="agents that affect the ras" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="telmisartan" precipitantCode="U5SYW473RQ" effect="166717003: Serum creatinine raised (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="telmisartan" precipitantCode="U5SYW473RQ" effect="236423003: Renal impairment (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="telmisartan" precipitantCode="U5SYW473RQ" effect="251859005: Dialysis finding (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="telmisartan" precipitantCode="U5SYW473RQ" effect="419620001: Death (event)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="telmisartan" precipitantCode="U5SYW473RQ"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>