<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="amiloride hydrocloride" setid="2b70cf0c-45be-428f-b396-5001ed4e30fc">
<Text><Section name="Boxed Warning section" id="34066-1">
Like other potassium-conserving agents, amiloride may cause hyperkalemia (serum potassium levels greater than 5.5 mEq per liter) which, if uncorrected, is potentially fatal. Hyperkalemia occurs commonly (about 10%) when amiloride is used without a kaliuretic diuretic. This incidence is greater in patients with renal impairment, diabetes mellitus (with or without recognized renal insufficiency), and in the elderly. When amiloride HCl is used concomitantly with a thiazide diuretic in patients without these complications, the risk of hyperkalemia is reduced to about 1-2 percent. It is thus essential to monitor serum potassium levels carefully in any patient receiving amiloride, particularly when it is first introduced, at the time of diuretic dosage adjustments, and during any illness that could affect renal function.</Section>
<Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
Amiloride HCl should not be used in the presence of elevated serum potassium levels (greater than 5.5 mEq per liter).          Amiloride HCl should not be given to patients receiving other potassium-conserving agents, such as spironolactone or triamterene. Potassium supplementation in the form of medication, potassium-containing salt substitutes or a potassium-rich diet should not be used with amiloride HCl except in severe and/or refractory cases of hypokalemia. Such concomitant therapy can be associated with rapid increases in serum potassium levels. If potassium supplementation is used, careful monitoring of the serum potassium level is necessary.          Anuria, acute or chronic renal insufficiency, and evidence of diabetic nephropathy are contraindications to the use of amiloride HCl. Patients with evidence of renal functional impairment (blood urea nitrogen [BUN] levels over 30 mg per 100 mL or serum creatinine levels over 1.5 mg per 100 mL) or diabetes mellitus should not receive the drug without careful, frequent and continuing monitoring of serum electrolytes, creatinine, and BUN levels. Potassium retention associated with the use of an antikaliuretic agent is accentuated in the presence of renal impairment and may result in the rapid development of hyperkalemia.          Amiloride HCl is contraindicated in patients who are hypersensitive to this product.</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
Amiloride HCl should be administered with food. Amiloride HCl, one 5 mg tablet daily, should be added to the usual antihypertensive or diuretic dosage of a kaliuretic diuretic. The dosage may be increased to 10 mg per day, if necessary. More than two 5 mg tablets of amiloride HCl daily usually are not needed, and there is little controlled experience with such doses. If persistent hypokalemia is documented with 10 mg, the dose can be increased to 15 mg, then 20 mg, with careful monitoring of electrolytes. In treating patients with congestive heart failure after an initial diuresis has been achieved, potassium loss may also decrease and the need for amiloride HCl should be re-evaluated. Dosage adjustment may be necessary. Maintenance therapy may be on an intermittent basis. If it is necessary to use amiloride HCl alone (See  INDICATIONS ), the starting dosage should be one 5 mg tablet daily. This dosage may be increased to 10 mg per day, if necessary. More than two 5 mg tablets usually are not needed, and there is little controlled experience with such doses. If persistent hypokalemia is documented with 10 mg, the dose can be increased to 15 mg, then 20 mg, with careful monitoring of electrolytes.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
When amiloride HCl is administered concomitantly with an angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitor, an angiotensin II receptor antagonist, cyclosporine or tacrolimus, the risk of hyperkalemia may be increased. Therefore, if concomitant use of these agents is indicated because of demonstrated hypokalemia, they should be used with caution and with frequent monitoring of serum potassium. (See  WARNINGS.) Lithium generally should not be given with diuretics because they reduce its renal clearance and add a high risk of lithium toxicity. Read circulars for lithium preparations before use of such concomitant therapy. In some patients, the administration of a non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agent can reduce the diuretic, natriuretic, and antihypertensive effects of loop, potassium-sparing and thiazide diuretics. Therefore, when amiloride HCl and non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agents are used concomitantly, the patient should be observed closely to determine if the desired effect of the diuretic is obtained. Since indomethacin and potassium-sparing diuretics, including amiloride HCl, may each be associated with increased serum potassium levels, the potential effects on potassium kinetics and renal function should be considered when these agents are administered concurrently.</Section>
<Section name="PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="42232-9">
Hyponatremia and hypochloremia may occur when amiloride HCl is used with other diuretics and increases in BUN levels have been reported. These increases usually have accompanied vigorous fluid elimination, especially when diuretic therapy was used in seriously ill patients, such as those who had hepatic cirrhosis with ascites and metabolic alkalosis, or those with resistant edema. Therefore, when amiloride HCl is given with other diuretics to such patients, careful monitoring of serum electrolytes and BUN levels is important. In patients with pre-existing severe liver disease, hepatic encephalopathy, manifested by tremors, confusion, and coma, and increased jaundice, have been reported in association with diuretics, including amiloride HCl.            When amiloride HCl is administered concomitantly with an angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitor, an angiotensin II receptor antagonist, cyclosporine or tacrolimus, the risk of hyperkalemia may be increased. Therefore, if concomitant use of these agents is indicated because of demonstrated hypokalemia, they should be used with caution and with frequent monitoring of serum potassium. (See  WARNINGS.) Lithium generally should not be given with diuretics because they reduce its renal clearance and add a high risk of lithium toxicity. Read circulars for lithium preparations before use of such concomitant therapy. In some patients, the administration of a non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agent can reduce the diuretic, natriuretic, and antihypertensive effects of loop, potassium-sparing and thiazide diuretics. Therefore, when amiloride HCl and non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agents are used concomitantly, the patient should be observed closely to determine if the desired effect of the diuretic is obtained. Since indomethacin and potassium-sparing diuretics, including amiloride HCl, may each be associated with increased serum potassium levels, the potential effects on potassium kinetics and renal function should be considered when these agents are administered concurrently.          There was no evidence of a tumorigenic effect when amiloride HCl was administered for 92 weeks to mice at doses up to 10 mg/kg/day (25 times the maximum daily human dose). Amiloride HCl has also been administered for 104 weeks to male and female rats at doses up to 6 and 8 mg/kg/day (15 and 20 times the maximum daily dose for humans, respectively) and showed no evidence of carcinogenicity. Amiloride HCl was devoid of mutagenic activity in various strains of Salmonella  typhimurium with or without a mammalian liver microsomal activation system (Ames test).               Teratogenicity studies with amiloride HCl in rabbits and mice given 20 and 25 times the maximum human dose, respectively, revealed no evidence of harm to the fetus, although studies showed that the drug crossed the placenta in modest amounts. Reproduction studies in rats at 20 times the expected maximum daily dose for humans showed no evidence of impaired fertility. At approximately 5 or more times the expected maximum daily dose for humans, some toxicity was seen in adult rats and rabbits and a decrease in rat pup growth and survival occurred. There are, however, no adequate and well-controlled studies in pregnant women. Because animal reproduction studies are not always predictive of human response, this drug should be used during pregnancy only if clearly needed.            Studies in rats have shown that amiloride is excreted in milk in concentrations higher than those found in blood, but it is not known whether amiloride HCl is excreted in human milk. Because many drugs are excreted in human milk and because of the potential for serious adverse reactions in nursing infants from amiloride HCl, a decision should be made whether to discontinue nursing or to discontinue the drug, taking into account the importance of the drug to the mother.          Safety and effectiveness in pediatric patients have not been established.          Clinical studies of amiloride HCl did not include sufficient numbers of subjects aged 65 and over to determine whether they respond differently from younger subjects. Other reported clinical experience has not identified differences in responses between the elderly and younger patients. In general, dose selection for an elderly patient should be cautious, usually starting at the low end of the dosing range, reflecting the greater frequency of decreased hepatic, renal or cardiac function, and of concomitant disease or other drug therapy. This drug is known to be substantially excreted by the kidney, and the risk of toxic reactions to this drug may be greater in patients with impaired renal function. Because elderly patients are more likely to have decreased renal function, care should be taken in dose selection, and it may be useful to monitor renal function. (See   CONTRAINDICATIONS, Impaired Renal Function  .)</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS SECTION" id="34071-1">
Like other potassium-conserving agents, amiloride may cause hyperkalemia (serum potassium levels greater than 5.5 mEq per liter) which, if uncorrected, is potentially fatal. Hyperkalemia occurs commonly (about 10%) when amiloride is used without a kaliuretic diuretic. This incidence is greater in patients with renal impairment, diabetes mellitus (with or without recognized renal insufficiency), and in the elderly. When amiloride HCl is used concomitantly with a thiazide diuretic in patients without these complications, the risk of hyperkalemia is reduced to about 1-2 percent. It is thus essential to monitor serum potassium levels carefully in any patient receiving amiloride, particularly when it is first introduced, at the time of diuretic dosage adjustments, and during any illness that could affect renal function.          The risk of hyperkalemia may be increased when potassium-conserving agents, including amiloride HCl, are administered concomitantly with an angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitor, an angiotensin II receptor antagonist, cyclosporine or tacrolimus. (See   PRECAUTIONS, Drug Interactions  .) Warning signs or symptoms of hyperkalemia include paresthesias, muscular weakness, fatigue, flaccid paralysis of the extremities, bradycardia, shock, and ECG abnormalities. Monitoring of the serum potassium level is essential because mild hyperkalemia is not usually associated with an abnormal ECG. When abnormal, the ECG in hyperkalemia is characterized primarily by tall, peaked T waves or elevations from previous tracings. There may also be lowering of the R wave and increased depth of the S wave, widening and even disappearance of the P wave, progressive widening of the QRS complex, prolongation of the PR interval, and ST depression.          If hyperkalemia occurs in patients taking amiloride HCl, the drug should be discontinued immediately. If the serum potassium level exceeds 6.5 mEq per liter, active measures should be taken to reduce it. Such measures include the intravenous administration of sodium bicarbonate solution or oral or parenteral glucose with a rapid-acting insulin preparation. If needed, a cation exchange resin such as sodium polystyrene sulfonate may be given orally or by enema. Patients with persistent hyperkalemia may require dialysis.            In diabetic patients, hyperkalemia has been reported with the use of all potassium-conserving diuretics, including amiloride HCl, even in patients without evidence of diabetic nephropathy. Therefore, amiloride HCl should be avoided, if possible, in diabetic patients and, if it is used, serum electrolytes and renal function must be monitored frequently. Amiloride HCl should be discontinued at least three days before glucose tolerance testing.          Antikaliuretic therapy should be instituted only with caution in severely ill patients in whom respiratory or metabolic acidosis may occur, such as patients with cardiopulmonary disease or poorly controlled diabetes. If amiloride HCl is given to these patients, frequent monitoring of acid-base balance is necessary. Shifts in acid-base balance alter the ratio of extracellular/intracellular potassium, and the development of acidosis may be associated with rapid increases in serum potassium levels.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Amiloride HCl is a potassium-conserving (antikaliuretic) drug that possesses weak (compared with thiazide diuretics) natriuretic, diuretic, and antihypertensive activity. These effects have been partially additive to the effects of thiazide diuretics in some clinical studies. When administered with a thiazide or loop diuretic, amiloride HCl has been shown to decrease the enhanced urinary excretion of magnesium which occurs when a thiazide or loop diuretic is used alone. Amiloride HCl has potassium-conserving activity in patients receiving kaliuretic-diuretic agents. Amiloride HCl is not an aldosterone antagonist and its effects are seen even in the absence of aldosterone. Amiloride HCl exerts its potassium sparing effect through the inhibition of sodium reabsorption at the distal convoluted tubule, cortical collecting tubule and collecting duct; this decreases the net negative potential of the tubular lumen and reduces both potassium and hydrogen secretion and their subsequent excretion. This mechanism accounts in large part for the potassium sparing action of amiloride. Amiloride HCl usually begins to act within 2 hours after an oral dose. Its effect on electrolyte excretion reaches a peak between 6 and 10 hours and lasts about 24 hours. Peak plasma levels are obtained in 3 to 4 hours and the plasma half-life varies from 6 to 9 hours. Effects on electrolytes increase with single doses of amiloride HCl up to approximately 15 mg. Amiloride HCl is not metabolized by the liver but is excreted unchanged by the kidneys. About 50 percent of a 20 mg dose of amiloride HCl is excreted in the urine and 40 percent in the stool within 72 hours. Amiloride HCl has little effect on glomerular filtration rate or renal blood flow. Because amiloride HCl is not metabolized by the liver, drug accumulation is not anticipated in patients with hepatic dysfunction, but accumulation can occur if the hepatorenal syndrome develops.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="7056" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Like other potassium-conserving agents, amiloride may cause hyperkalemia (serum potassium levels greater than 5.5 mEq per liter) which, if uncorrected, is potentially fatal.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7057" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Hyperkalemia occurs commonly (about 10%) when amiloride is used without a kaliuretic diuretic.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7058" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>This incidence is greater in patients with renal impairment, diabetes mellitus (with or without recognized renal insufficiency), and in the elderly.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7059" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>When amiloride HCl is used concomitantly with a thiazide diuretic in patients without these complications, the risk of hyperkalemia is reduced to about 1-2 percent.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M1" type="Trigger" span="111 4;135 7" str="risk | reduced"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="48 17" str="thiazide diuretic" code="N0000175419"/>
<Mention id="M3" type="SpecificInteraction" span="119 12" str="hyperkalemia" code="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M1" precipitant="M2" effect="M3"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7060" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>It is thus essential to monitor serum potassium levels carefully in any patient receiving amiloride, particularly when it is first introduced, at the time of diuretic dosage adjustments, and during any illness that could affect renal function.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M4" type="Trigger" span="24 7" str="monitor"/>
<Mention id="M5" type="Precipitant" span="158 8" str="diuretic" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M6" type="SpecificInteraction" span="32 22" str="serum potassium levels" code="24529006: Potassium disorder (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M4" precipitant="M5" effect="M6"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7061" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Amiloride HCl should not be used in the presence of elevated serum potassium levels (greater than 5.5 mEq per liter).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7062" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Amiloride HCl should not be given to patients receiving other potassium-conserving agents, such as spironolactone or triamterene.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M11" type="Trigger" span="14 19" str="should not be given"/>
<Mention id="M8" type="Precipitant" span="62 27" str="potassium-conserving agents" code="N0000175418"/>
<Mention id="M10" type="Precipitant" span="99 14" str="spironolactone" code="27O7W4T232"/>
<Mention id="M12" type="Precipitant" span="117 11" str="triamterene" code="WS821Z52LQ"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M11" precipitant="M8"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M11" precipitant="M10"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M11" precipitant="M12"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7063" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Potassium supplementation in the form of medication, potassium-containing salt substitutes or a potassium-rich diet should not be used with amiloride HCl except in severe and/or refractory cases of hypokalemia.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M17" type="Trigger" span="116 18" str="should not be used"/>
<Mention id="M14" type="Precipitant" span="0 25" str="Potassium supplementation" code="RWP5GA015D"/>
<Mention id="M16" type="Precipitant" span="53 37" str="potassium-containing salt substitutes" code="N0000175600"/>
<Mention id="M18" type="Precipitant" span="96 19" str="potassium-rich diet" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M17" precipitant="M14"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M17" precipitant="M16"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M17" precipitant="M18"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7064" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Such concomitant therapy can be associated with rapid increases in serum potassium levels.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7065" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>If potassium supplementation is used, careful monitoring of the serum potassium level is necessary.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M19" type="Trigger" span="38 18" str="careful monitoring"/>
<Mention id="M20" type="Precipitant" span="3 25" str="potassium supplementation" code="RWP5GA015D"/>
<Mention id="M21" type="SpecificInteraction" span="64 21" str="serum potassium level" code="24529006: Potassium disorder (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M19" precipitant="M20" effect="M21"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7066" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Anuria, acute or chronic renal insufficiency, and evidence of diabetic nephropathy are contraindications to the use of amiloride HCl.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7067" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Patients with evidence of renal functional impairment (blood urea nitrogen [BUN] levels over 30 mg per 100 mL or serum creatinine levels over 1.5 mg per 100 mL) or diabetes mellitus should not receive the drug without careful, frequent and continuing monitoring of serum electrolytes, creatinine, and BUN levels.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7068" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Potassium retention associated with the use of an antikaliuretic agent is accentuated in the presence of renal impairment and may result in the rapid development of hyperkalemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7069" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Amiloride HCl is contraindicated in patients who are hypersensitive to this product.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7070" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Amiloride HCl should be administered with food.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M22" type="Trigger" span="14 27" str="should be administered with"/>
<Mention id="M23" type="Precipitant" span="42 4" str="food" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M22" precipitant="M23"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7071" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Amiloride HCl, one 5 mg tablet daily, should be added to the usual antihypertensive or diuretic dosage of a kaliuretic diuretic.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M24" type="Trigger" span="38 18" str="should be added to"/>
<Mention id="M25" type="Precipitant" span="108 19" str="kaliuretic diuretic" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M24" precipitant="M25"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7072" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The dosage may be increased to 10 mg per day, if necessary.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7073" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>More than two 5 mg tablets of amiloride HCl daily usually are not needed, and there is little controlled experience with such doses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7074" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If persistent hypokalemia is documented with 10 mg, the dose can be increased to 15 mg, then 20 mg, with careful monitoring of electrolytes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7075" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In treating patients with congestive heart failure after an initial diuresis has been achieved, potassium loss may also decrease and the need for amiloride HCl should be re-evaluated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7076" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Maintenance therapy may be on an intermittent basis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7077" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If it is necessary to use amiloride HCl alone, the starting dosage should be one 5 mg tablet daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7078" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>This dosage may be increased to 10 mg per day, if necessary.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7079" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>More than two 5 mg tablets usually are not needed, and there is little controlled experience with such doses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7080" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>When amiloride HCl is administered concomitantly with an angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitor, an angiotensin II receptor antagonist, cyclosporine or tacrolimus, the risk of hyperkalemia may be increased.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M35" type="Trigger" span="169 4;197 9" str="risk | increased"/>
<Mention id="M27" type="Precipitant" span="101 34" str="angiotensin II receptor antagonist" code="N0000000070"/>
<Mention id="M37" type="SpecificInteraction" span="177 12" str="hyperkalemia" code="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M30" type="Precipitant" span="57 39" str="angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitor" code="N0000175562"/>
<Mention id="M33" type="Precipitant" span="137 12" str="cyclosporine" code="83HN0GTJ6D"/>
<Mention id="M36" type="Precipitant" span="153 10" str="tacrolimus" code="WM0HAQ4WNM"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M27" effect="M37"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M30" effect="M37"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M33" effect="M37"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M36" effect="M37"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7081" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Therefore, if concomitant use of these agents is indicated because of demonstrated hypokalemia, they should be used with caution and with frequent monitoring of serum potassium.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7082" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Lithium generally should not be given with diuretics because they reduce its renal clearance and add a high risk of lithium toxicity.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M38" type="Trigger" span="66 26" str="reduce its renal clearance "/>
<Mention id="M39" type="Trigger" span="124 8" str=" toxicity"/>
<Mention id="M40" type="Precipitant" span="116 7" str="lithium" code="9FN79X2M3F"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M38;M39" precipitant="M40" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7083" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Read circulars for lithium preparations before use of such concomitant therapy.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M41" type="Trigger" span="0 14;40 10" str="Read circulars | before use"/>
<Mention id="M42" type="Precipitant" span="19 20" str="lithium preparations" code="9FN79X2M3F"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M41" precipitant="M42"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7084" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>In some patients, the administration of a non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agent can reduce the diuretic, natriuretic, and antihypertensive effects of loop, potassium-sparing and thiazide diuretics.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M49" type="Trigger" span="84 6;139 7" str="reduce | effects"/>
<Mention id="M50" type="Precipitant" span="42 37" str="non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agent" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M45" type="SpecificInteraction" span="84 6;122 24" str="reduce | antihypertensive effects" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M48" type="SpecificInteraction" span="84 6;105 11;139 7" str="reduce | natriuretic | effects" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M51" type="SpecificInteraction" span="84 19;139 7" str="reduce the diuretic | effects" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M49" precipitant="M50" effect="M45"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M49" precipitant="M50" effect="M48"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M49" precipitant="M50" effect="M51"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7085" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Therefore, when amiloride HCl and non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agents are used concomitantly, the patient should be observed closely to determine if the desired effect of the diuretic is obtained.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M52" type="Trigger" span="109 26" str="should be observed closely"/>
<Mention id="M53" type="Precipitant" span="34 38" str="non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agents" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M54" type="SpecificInteraction" span="164 22" str="effect of the diuretic" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M52" precipitant="M53" effect="M54"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7086" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Since indomethacin and potassium-sparing diuretics, including amiloride HCl, may each be associated with increased serum potassium levels, the potential effects on potassium kinetics and renal function should be considered when these agents are administered concurrently.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M61" type="Trigger" span="143 17" str="potential effects"/>
<Mention id="M62" type="Precipitant" span="6 12" str="indomethacin" code="XXE1CET956"/>
<Mention id="M57" type="SpecificInteraction" span="164 18" str="potassium kinetics" code="24529006: Potassium disorder (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M58" type="Trigger" span="89 15" str="associated with"/>
<Mention id="M60" type="SpecificInteraction" span="105 32" str="increased serum potassium levels" code="166689004: Raised serum potassium level (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M63" type="SpecificInteraction" span="187 14" str="renal function" code="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M61" precipitant="M62" effect="M57"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M58" precipitant="M62" effect="M60"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M61" precipitant="M62" effect="M63"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7087" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Hyponatremia and hypochloremia may occur when amiloride HCl is used with other diuretics and increases in BUN levels have been reported.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M74" type="Trigger" span="0 12" str="Hyponatremia "/>
<Mention id="M75" type="Trigger" span="17 13" str=" hypochloremia "/>
<Mention id="M76" type="Trigger" span="93 23" str=" increases in BUN levels"/>
<Mention id="M77" type="Precipitant" span="79 9" str="diuretics" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M68" type="SpecificInteraction" span="93 23" str="increases in BUN levels" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M73" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 12" str="Hyponatremia" code="89627008: Hyponatremia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M78" type="SpecificInteraction" span="17 13" str="hypochloremia" code="10399008: Hypochloremia (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M74;M75;M76" precipitant="M77" effect="M68"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M74;M75;M76" precipitant="M77" effect="M73"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M74;M75;M76" precipitant="M77" effect="M78"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7088" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>These increases usually have accompanied vigorous fluid elimination, especially when diuretic therapy was used in seriously ill patients, such as those who had hepatic cirrhosis with ascites and metabolic alkalosis, or those with resistant edema.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M79" type="Trigger" span="29 11" str="accompanied"/>
<Mention id="M80" type="Precipitant" span="85 8" str="diuretic" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M81" type="SpecificInteraction" span="41 26" str="vigorous fluid elimination" code="28560003: Hypovolemia (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M79" precipitant="M80" effect="M81"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7089" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Therefore, when amiloride HCl is given with other diuretics to such patients, careful monitoring of serum electrolytes and BUN levels is important.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M85" type="Trigger" span="78 18" str="careful monitoring"/>
<Mention id="M86" type="Precipitant" span="50 9" str="diuretics" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M84" type="SpecificInteraction" span="123 10" str="BUN levels" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M87" type="SpecificInteraction" span="100 18" str="serum electrolytes" code="166686006: Electrolytes abnormal (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I29" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M85" precipitant="M86" effect="M84"/>
<Interaction id="I30" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M85" precipitant="M86" effect="M87"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7090" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In patients with pre-existing severe liver disease, hepatic encephalopathy, manifested by tremors, confusion, and coma, and increased jaundice, have been reported in association with diuretics, including amiloride HCl.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7091" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>There was no evidence of a tumorigenic effect when amiloride HCl was administered for 92 weeks to mice at doses up to 10 mg/kg/day (25 times the maximum daily human dose).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7092" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Amiloride HCl has also been administered for 104 weeks to male and female rats at doses up to 6 and 8 mg/kg/day (15 and 20 times the maximum daily dose for humans, respectively) and showed no evidence of carcinogenicity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7093" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Amiloride HCl was devoid of mutagenic activity in various strains of Salmonella typhimurium with or without a mammalian liver microsomal activation system (Ames test).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7094" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Teratogenicity studies with amiloride HCl in rabbits and mice given 20 and 25 times the maximum human dose, respectively, revealed no evidence of harm to the fetus, although studies showed that the drug crossed the placenta in modest amounts.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7095" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Reproduction studies in rats at 20 times the expected maximum daily dose for humans showed no evidence of impaired fertility.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7096" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>At approximately 5 or more times the expected maximum daily dose for humans, some toxicity was seen in adult rats and rabbits and a decrease in rat pup growth and survival occurred.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7097" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>There are, however, no adequate and well-controlled studies in pregnant women.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7098" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because animal reproduction studies are not always predictive of human response, this drug should be used during pregnancy only if clearly needed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7099" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Studies in rats have shown that amiloride is excreted in milk in concentrations higher than those found in blood, but it is not known whether amiloride HCl is excreted in human milk.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7100" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because many drugs are excreted in human milk and because of the potential for serious adverse reactions in nursing infants from amiloride HCl, a decision should be made whether to discontinue nursing or to discontinue the drug, taking into account the importance of the drug to the mother.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7101" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Safety and effectiveness in pediatric patients have not been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7102" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Clinical studies of amiloride HCl did not include sufficient numbers of subjects aged 65 and over to determine whether they respond differently from younger subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7103" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Other reported clinical experience has not identified differences in responses between the elderly and younger patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7104" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In general, dose selection for an elderly patient should be cautious, usually starting at the low end of the dosing range, reflecting the greater frequency of decreased hepatic, renal or cardiac function, and of concomitant disease or other drug therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7105" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>This drug is known to be substantially excreted by the kidney, and the risk of toxic reactions to this drug may be greater in patients with impaired renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7106" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because elderly patients are more likely to have decreased renal function, care should be taken in dose selection, and it may be useful to monitor renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7107" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The risk of hyperkalemia may be increased when potassium-conserving agents, including amiloride HCl, are administered concomitantly with an angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitor, an angiotensin II receptor antagonist, cyclosporine or tacrolimus.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M97" type="Trigger" span="4 4;32 9" str="risk | increased"/>
<Mention id="M89" type="Precipitant" span="184 34" str="angiotensin II receptor antagonist" code="N0000000070"/>
<Mention id="M99" type="SpecificInteraction" span="12 12" str="hyperkalemia" code="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M92" type="Precipitant" span="140 39" str="angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitor" code="N0000175562"/>
<Mention id="M95" type="Precipitant" span="220 12" str="cyclosporine" code="83HN0GTJ6D"/>
<Mention id="M98" type="Precipitant" span="236 10" str="tacrolimus" code="WM0HAQ4WNM"/>
<Interaction id="I31" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M97" precipitant="M89" effect="M99"/>
<Interaction id="I32" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M97" precipitant="M92" effect="M99"/>
<Interaction id="I33" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M97" precipitant="M95" effect="M99"/>
<Interaction id="I34" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M97" precipitant="M98" effect="M99"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7108" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Warning signs or symptoms of hyperkalemia include paresthesias, muscular weakness, fatigue, flaccid paralysis of the extremities, bradycardia, shock, and ECG abnormalities.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7109" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Monitoring of the serum potassium level is essential because mild hyperkalemia is not usually associated with an abnormal ECG.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7110" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>When abnormal, the ECG in hyperkalemia is characterized primarily by tall, peaked T waves or elevations from previous tracings.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7111" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>There may also be lowering of the R wave and increased depth of the S wave, widening and even disappearance of the P wave, progressive widening of the QRS complex, prolongation of the PR interval, and ST depression.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7112" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>If hyperkalemia occurs in patients taking amiloride HCl, the drug should be discontinued immediately.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7113" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>If the serum potassium level exceeds 6.5 mEq per liter, active measures should be taken to reduce it.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7114" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Such measures include the intravenous administration of sodium bicarbonate solution or oral or parenteral glucose with a rapid-acting insulin preparation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7115" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>If needed, a cation exchange resin such as sodium polystyrene sulfonate may be given orally or by enema.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7116" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Patients with persistent hyperkalemia may require dialysis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7117" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>In diabetic patients, hyperkalemia has been reported with the use of all potassium-conserving diuretics, including amiloride HCl, even in patients without evidence of diabetic nephropathy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7118" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Therefore, amiloride HCl should be avoided, if possible, in diabetic patients and, if it is used, serum electrolytes and renal function must be monitored frequently.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7119" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Amiloride HCl should be discontinued at least three days before glucose tolerance testing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7120" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Antikaliuretic therapy should be instituted only with caution in severely ill patients in whom respiratory or metabolic acidosis may occur, such as patients with cardiopulmonary disease or poorly controlled diabetes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7121" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>If amiloride HCl is given to these patients, frequent monitoring of acid-base balance is necessary.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7122" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Shifts in acid-base balance alter the ratio of extracellular/intracellular potassium, and the development of acidosis may be associated with rapid increases in serum potassium levels.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7123" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Amiloride HCl is a potassium-conserving (antikaliuretic) drug that possesses weak (compared with thiazide diuretics) natriuretic, diuretic, and antihypertensive activity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7124" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>These effects have been partially additive to the effects of thiazide diuretics in some clinical studies.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M100" type="Trigger" span="6 7;34 8" str="effects | additive"/>
<Mention id="M101" type="Precipitant" span="61 18" str="thiazide diuretics" code="N0000175419"/>
<Mention id="M102" type="SpecificInteraction" span="50 29" str="effects of thiazide diuretics" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I35" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M100" precipitant="M101" effect="M102"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7125" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>When administered with a thiazide or loop diuretic, amiloride HCl has been shown to decrease the enhanced urinary excretion of magnesium which occurs when a thiazide or loop diuretic is used alone.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M108" type="SpecificInteraction" span="84 52" str="decrease the enhanced urinary excretion of magnesium" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M104" type="Precipitant" span="37 13" str="loop diuretic" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M107" type="Precipitant" span="25 8;42 8" str="thiazide | diuretic" code="N0000175419"/>
<Interaction id="I36" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M108" precipitant="M104" effect="M108"/>
<Interaction id="I37" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M108" precipitant="M107" effect="M108"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7126" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Amiloride HCl has potassium-conserving activity in patients receiving kaliuretic-diuretic agents.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M111" type="SpecificInteraction" span="18 29" str="potassium-conserving activity" code="24529006: Potassium disorder (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M110" type="Precipitant" span="70 26" str="kaliuretic-diuretic agents" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I38" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M111" precipitant="M110" effect="M111"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7127" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Amiloride HCl is not an aldosterone antagonist and its effects are seen even in the absence of aldosterone.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7128" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Amiloride HCl exerts its potassium sparing effect through the inhibition of sodium reabsorption at the distal convoluted tubule, cortical collecting tubule and collecting duct; this decreases the net negative potential of the tubular lumen and reduces both potassium and hydrogen secretion and their subsequent excretion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7129" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This mechanism accounts in large part for the potassium sparing action of amiloride.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7130" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Amiloride HCl usually begins to act within 2 hours after an oral dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7131" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Its effect on electrolyte excretion reaches a peak between 6 and 10 hours and lasts about 24 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7132" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Peak plasma levels are obtained in 3 to 4 hours and the plasma half-life varies from 6 to 9 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7133" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Effects on electrolytes increase with single doses of amiloride HCl up to approximately 15 mg. Amiloride HCl is not metabolized by the liver but is excreted unchanged by the kidneys.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7134" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>About 50 percent of a 20 mg dose of amiloride HCl is excreted in the urine and 40 percent in the stool within 72 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7135" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Amiloride HCl has little effect on glomerular filtration rate or renal blood flow.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7136" LabelDrug="amiloride hydrocloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Because amiloride HCl is not metabolized by the liver, drug accumulation is not anticipated in patients with hepatic dysfunction, but accumulation can occur if the hepatorenal syndrome develops.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="thiazide diuretic" precipitantCode="N0000175419" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="diuretic" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="24529006: Potassium disorder (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="diuretic" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="28560003: Hypovolemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="potassium-conserving agents" precipitantCode="N0000175418"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="spironolactone" precipitantCode="27O7W4T232"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="triamterene" precipitantCode="WS821Z52LQ"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="potassium supplementation" precipitantCode="RWP5GA015D" effect="24529006: Potassium disorder (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="potassium supplementation" precipitantCode="RWP5GA015D"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="potassium-containing salt substitutes" precipitantCode="N0000175600"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="potassium-rich diet" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="food" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="kaliuretic diuretic" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="angiotensin ii receptor antagonist" precipitantCode="N0000000070" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitor" precipitantCode="N0000175562" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cyclosporine" precipitantCode="83HN0GTJ6D" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="tacrolimus" precipitantCode="WM0HAQ4WNM" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="lithium" precipitantCode="9FN79X2M3F" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="lithium preparations" precipitantCode="9FN79X2M3F"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agent" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agents" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="indomethacin" precipitantCode="XXE1CET956" effect="166689004: Raised serum potassium level (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="indomethacin" precipitantCode="XXE1CET956" effect="24529006: Potassium disorder (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="indomethacin" precipitantCode="XXE1CET956" effect="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="diuretics" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="10399008: Hypochloremia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="diuretics" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="166686006: Electrolytes abnormal (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="diuretics" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="89627008: Hyponatremia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="diuretics" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="thiazide diuretics" precipitantCode="N0000175419" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="loop diuretic" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="thiazide | diuretic" precipitantCode="N0000175419" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="kaliuretic-diuretic agents" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="24529006: Potassium disorder (disorder)"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>