<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="ATACAND" setid="a73e1339-9643-4eea-2cbe-e879c88fb50e">
<Text><Section name="Boxed Warning section" id="34066-1">
•When pregnancy is detected, discontinue ATACAND as soon as possible.  (5.1)    •Drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause injury and death to the developing fetus.  (5.1)          WARNING: FETAL TOXICITY    See Full Prescribing Information for complete boxed warning.    •When pregnancy is detected, discontinue ATACAND as soon as possible.  (5.1)    •Drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause injury and death to the developing fetus.  (5.1)</Section>
<Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
ATACAND is contraindicated in patients who are hypersensitive to candesartan.  Do not co-administer aliskiren with ATACAND in patients with diabetes [see DRUG INTERACTIONS (7)].        Known hypersensitivity to product components (4). Do not co-administer aliskiren with ATACAND in patients with diabetes. (4).</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
Starting Dose     Dose Range     Target Maintenance Dose      Adult Hypertension (2.1)    16 mg tablet once daily   8 - 32 mg tablet total daily dose   –     Pediatric Hypertension (1 to &amp;lt; 6 years) (2.2)    0.20 mg/kg oral suspension once daily   0.05 - 0.4 mg/kg oral suspension once daily or consider divided dose   -     Pediatric Hypertension (6 to &amp;lt; 17 years) (2.2)    &amp;lt; 50 kg 4 – 8 mg tablet once daily &amp;gt; 50 kg 8 – 16 mg tablet once daily   &amp;lt; 50 kg 4 – 16 mg tablet once daily or consider divided dose &amp;gt; 50 kg 4 – 32 mg tablet once daily or consider divided dose   –     Adult Heart Failure (2.3)    4 mg tablet once daily    32 mg tablet once daily1              Dosage must be individualized. Blood pressure response is dose related over the range of 2 to 32 mg. The usual recommended starting dose of ATACAND is 16 mg once daily when it is used as monotherapy in patients who are not volume depleted. ATACAND can be administered once or twice daily with total daily doses ranging from 8 mg to 32 mg. Larger doses do not appear to have a greater effect, and there is relatively little experience with such doses. Most of the antihypertensive effect is present within 2 weeks, and maximal blood pressure reduction is generally obtained within 4 to 6 weeks of treatment with ATACAND. Use in Hepatic Impairment: Initiate with 8 mg ATACAND in patients with moderate hepatic insufficiency. Dosing recommendations cannot be provided for patients with severe hepatic insufficiency [see CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY (12.3) ]. ATACAND may be administered with or without food. If blood pressure is not controlled by ATACAND alone, a diuretic may be added. ATACAND may be administered with other antihypertensive agents.          ATACAND may be administered once daily or divided into two equal doses. Adjust the dosage according to blood pressure response. For patients with possible depletion of intravascular volume (e.g., patients treated with diuretics, particularly those with impaired renal function), initiate ATACAND under close medical supervision and consider administration of a lower dose [see WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS (5.3)]. Children 1 to &amp;lt; 6 years of age: The dose range is 0.05 to 0.4 mg/kg per day. The recommended starting dose is 0.20 mg/kg (oral suspension). Children 6 to &amp;lt; 17 years of age:  For those less than 50 kg, the dose range is 2 to 16 mg per day. The recommended starting dose is 4 to 8 mg. For those greater than 50 kg, the dose range is 4 to 32 mg per day. The recommended starting dose is 8 to 16 mg. Doses above 0.4 mg/kg (1 to &amp;lt; 6 year olds) or 32 mg (6 to &amp;lt; 17 year olds) have not been studied in pediatric patients [see CLINICAL STUDIES (14.1)].   An antihypertensive effect is usually present within 2 weeks, with full effect generally obtained within 4 weeks of treatment with ATACAND. Children &amp;lt; 1 year of age must not receive ATACAND for hypertension.  All pediatric patients with a glomerular filtration rate less than 30 ml/min/1.73m2 should not receive ATACAND since ATACAND has not been studied in this population [see  SPECIAL POPULATIONS (8)].  For children who cannot swallow tablets, an oral suspension may be substituted as described below:  Preparation of Oral Suspension:  ATACAND oral suspension can be prepared in concentrations within the range of 0.1 to 2.0 mg/mL. Typically, a concentration of 1 mg/mL will be suitable for the prescribed dose. Any strength of ATACAND tablets can be used in the preparation of the suspension. Follow the steps below for preparation of the suspension. The number of tablets and volume of vehicle specified below will yield 160 mL of a 1 mg/mL suspension.   •Prepare the vehicle by adding equal volumes of Ora-Plus®, Ora-Sweet SF®, and Ora-Blend SF® are registered trademarks of Paddock Laboratories, Inc.2 Supplied as a 50/50% pre-mix of Ora-Plus® and Ora-Sweet®Ora-Plus® (80 mL) and 1Ora-Sweet SF® (80 mL) or, alternatively, use, 1,2Ora-Blend SF® (160 mL).  •Add a small amount of vehicle to the required number of ATACAND tablets (five 32 mg tablets) and grind into a smooth paste using a mortar and pestle.  •Add the paste to a preparation vessel of suitable size.  •Rinse the mortar and pestle clean using the vehicle and add this to the vessel. Repeat, if necessary.  •Prepare the final volume by adding the remaining vehicle.  •Mix thoroughly.  •Dispense into suitably sized amber PET bottles.  •Label with an expiry date of 100 days and include the following instructions:  Store at room temperature (below 30°C/86°F). Use within 30 days after first opening. Do not use after the expiry date stated on the bottle. Do not freeze.  Shake well before each use.          The recommended initial dose for treating heart failure is 4 mg once daily. The target dose is 32 mg once daily, which is achieved by doubling the dose at approximately 2-week intervals, as tolerated by the patient.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
Because candesartan is not significantly metabolized by the cytochrome P450 system and at therapeutic concentrations has no effects on P450 enzymes, interactions with drugs that inhibit or are metabolized by those enzymes would not be expected.  Non-Steroidal Anti-Inflammatory Agents including Selective Cyclooxygenase-2 Inhibitors (COX-2 Inhibitors). In patients who are elderly, volume-depleted (including those on diuretic therapy), or with compromised renal function, co-administration of NSAIDs, including selective COX-2 inhibitors, with angiotensin II receptor antagonists, including candesartan, may result in deterioration of renal function, including possible acute renal failure. These effects are usually reversible. Monitor renal function periodically in patients receiving candesartan and NSAID therapy. The antihypertensive effect of angiotensin II receptor antagonists, including candesartan may be attenuated by NSAIDs including selective COX-2 inhibitors.  Lithium  Reversible increases in serum lithium concentrations and toxicity have been reported during concomitant administration of lithium with ACE inhibitors, and with some angiotensin II receptor antagonists. An increase in serum lithium concentration has been reported during concomitant administration of lithium with ATACAND. Monitor serum lithium levels.  Dual Blockade of the Renin-Angiotensin System (RAS)  Dual blockade of the RAS with angiotensin receptor blockers, ACE inhibitors, or aliskiren is associated with increased risks of hypotension, hyperkalemia, and changes in renal function (including acute renal failure) compared to monotherapy. Closely monitor blood pressure, renal function and electrolytes in patients on ATACAND and other agents that affect the RAS. Do not co-administer aliskiren with ATACAND in patients with diabetes. Avoid use of aliskiren with ATACAND in patients with renal impairment (GFR &amp;lt;60 ml/min) [see CONTRAINDICATIONS (4) ].        •Lithium: Reversible increases in serum lithium concentrations and toxicity (7).  •NSAIDS use may lead to increased risk of renal impairment and loss of antihypertensive effect (7).  •Dual inhibition of the renin-angiotensin system: Increased risk of renal impairment, hypotension, and hyperkalemia (7)</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
•Observe for signs and symptoms of hypotension (5.3).  •Monitor renal function (5.4) and potassium levels (5.5).           Pregnancy Category D   Use of drugs that act on the renin-angiotensin system during the second and third trimesters of pregnancy reduces fetal renal function and increases fetal and neonatal morbidity and death. Resulting oligohydramnios can be associated with fetal lung hypoplasia and skeletal deformations. Potential neonatal adverse effects include skull hypoplasia, anuria, hypotension, renal failure and death. When pregnancy is detected, discontinue ATACAND as soon as possible [see    USE IN SPECIFIC POPULATIONS (8.1) ]  .  Oral doses ≥10 mg of candesartan cilexetil/kg/day administered to pregnant rats during late gestation and continued through lactation were associated with reduced survival and an increased incidence of hydronephrosis in the offspring. The 10-mg/kg/day dose in rats is approximately 2.8 times the maximum recommended daily human dose (MRHD) of 32 mg on a mg/m2 basis (comparison assumes human body weight of 50 kg). Candesartan cilexetil given to pregnant rabbits at an oral dose of 3 mg/kg/day (approximately 1.7 times the MRHD on a mg/m2 basis) caused maternal toxicity (decreased body weight and death) but, in surviving dams, had no adverse effects on fetal survival, fetal weight, or external, visceral, or skeletal development. No maternal toxicity or adverse effects on fetal development were observed when oral doses up to 1000 mg of candesartan cilexetil/kg/day (approximately 138 times the MRHD on a mg/m2 basis) were administered to pregnant mice.          Children &amp;lt; 1 year of age must not receive ATACAND for hypertension. Drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system (RAS) can have effects on the development of immature kidneys.          ATACAND can cause symptomatic hypotension. Symptomatic hypotension is most likely to occur in patients who have been volume and/or salt depleted as a result of prolonged diuretic therapy, dietary salt restriction, dialysis, diarrhea, or vomiting. Patients with symptomatic hypotension may require temporarily reducing the dose of ATACAND, diuretic or both, and volume repletion. Volume and/or salt depletion should be corrected before initiating therapy with ATACAND. In the CHARM program (heart failure patients), hypotension was reported in 18.8% of patients on ATACAND versus 9.8% of patients on placebo. The incidence of hypotension leading to drug discontinuation in ATACAND-treated patients was 4.1% compared with 2.0% in placebo-treated patients. In the CHARM-Added program, where candesartan or placebo was given in addition to ACE inhibitors, hypotension was reported in 22.6% of patients treated with ATACAND versus 13.8% treated with placebo [see DRUG INTERACTIONS (7) ]. Monitoring of blood pressure is recommended during dose escalation and periodically thereafter.  Major Surgery/Anesthesia   Hypotension may occur during major surgery and anesthesia in patients treated with angiotensin II receptor antagonists, including ATACAND, due to blockade of the renin-angiotensin system. Very rarely, hypotension may be severe such that it may warrant the use of intravenous fluids and/or vasopressors.          Monitor renal function periodically in patients treated with ATACAND. Changes in renal function including acute renal failure can be caused by drugs that inhibit the renin-angiotensin system. Patients whose renal function may depend, in part, on the activity of the renin-angiotensin system (e.g., patient with renal artery stenosis, chronic kidney disease, severe heart failure, or volume depletion) may be at particular risk of developing oliguria, progressive azotemia or acute renal failure when treated with ATACAND. Consider withholding or discontinuing therapy in patients who develop a clinically significant decrease in renal function on ATACAND.  In the CHARM program (heart failure patients), the incidence of abnormal renal function (e.g., creatinine increase) was 12.5% in patients treated with ATACAND versus 6.3% in patients treated with placebo. The incidence of abnormal renal function (e.g., creatinine increase) leading to drug discontinuation in ATACAND-treated patients was 6.3% compared with 2.9% in placebo-treated patients. In the CHARM-Added program, where candesartan or placebo was given in addition to ACE inhibitors, the incidence of abnormal renal function (e.g., creatinine increase) was 15% in patients treated with ATACAND versus 9% in patients treated with placebo [see DRUG INTERACTIONS (7) ].           Drugs that inhibit the renin-angiotensin system can cause hyperkalemia. Monitor serum potassium periodically. In the CHARM program (heart failure patients), the incidence of hyperkalemia was 6.3% in patients treated with ATACAND versus 2.1% in patients treated with placebo. The incidence of hyperkalemia leading to drug discontinuation in ATACAND-treated patients was 2.4% compared with 0.6% in placebo-treated patients. In the CHARM-Added program where candesartan or placebo was given in addition to ACE inhibitors, the incidence of hyperkalemia was 9.5% in patients treated with ATACAND versus 3.5% in patients treated with placebo [see DRUG INTERACTIONS (7) ].</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Angiotensin II is formed from angiotensin I in a reaction catalyzed by angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE, kininase II). Angiotensin II is the principal pressor agent of the renin-angiotensin system, with effects that include vasoconstriction, stimulation of synthesis and release of aldosterone, cardiac stimulation, and renal reabsorption of sodium. Candesartan blocks the vasoconstrictor and aldosterone-secreting effects of angiotensin II by selectively blocking the binding of angiotensin II to the AT1 receptor in many tissues, such as vascular smooth muscle and the adrenal gland. Its action is, therefore, independent of the pathways for angiotensin II synthesis. There is also an AT2 receptor found in many tissues, but AT2 is not known to be associated with cardiovascular homeostasis. Candesartan has much greater affinity (&amp;gt;10,000-fold) for the AT1 receptor than for the AT2 receptor. Blockade of the renin-angiotensin system with ACE inhibitors, which inhibit the biosynthesis of angiotensin II from angiotensin I, is widely used in the treatment of hypertension. ACE inhibitors also inhibit the degradation of bradykinin, a reaction also catalyzed by ACE. Because candesartan does not inhibit ACE (kininase II), it does not affect the response to bradykinin. Whether this difference has clinical relevance is not yet known. Candesartan does not bind to or block other hormone receptors or ion channels known to be important in cardiovascular regulation. Blockade of the angiotensin II receptor inhibits the negative regulatory feedback of angiotensin II on renin secretion, but the resulting increased plasma renin activity and angiotensin II circulating levels do not overcome the effect of candesartan on blood pressure.          Candesartan inhibits the pressor effects of angiotensin II infusion in a dose-dependent manner. After 1 week of once daily dosing with 8 mg of candesartan cilexetil, the pressor effect was inhibited by approximately 90% at peak with approximately 50% inhibition persisting for 24 hours.  Plasma concentrations of angiotensin I and angiotensin II, and plasma renin activity (PRA), increased in a dose-dependent manner after single and repeated administration of candesartan cilexetil to healthy subjects, hypertensive, and heart failure patients. ACE activity was not altered in healthy subjects after repeated candesartan cilexetil administration. The once-daily administration of up to 16 mg of candesartan cilexetil to healthy subjects did not influence plasma aldosterone concentrations, but a decrease in the plasma concentration of aldosterone was observed when 32 mg of candesartan cilexetil was administered to hypertensive patients. In spite of the effect of candesartan cilexetil on aldosterone secretion, very little effect on serum potassium was observed.  Hypertension  Adults In multiple-dose studies with hypertensive patients, there were no clinically significant changes in metabolic function, including serum levels of total cholesterol, triglycerides, glucose, or uric acid. In a 12-week study of 161 patients with non-insulin-dependent (type 2) diabetes mellitus and hypertension, there was no change in the level of HbA1c.  Heart Failure  In heart failure patients, candesartan ≥ 8 mg resulted in decreases in systemic vascular resistance and pulmonary capillary wedge pressure.           Distribution  The volume of distribution of candesartan is 0.13 L/kg. Candesartan is highly bound to plasma proteins (&amp;gt;99%) and does not penetrate red blood cells. The protein binding is constant at candesartan plasma concentrations well above the range achieved with recommended doses. In rats, it has been demonstrated that candesartan crosses the blood-brain barrier poorly, if at all. It has also been demonstrated in rats that candesartan passes across the placental barrier and is distributed in the fetus.  Metabolism and Excretion  Total plasma clearance of candesartan is 0.37 mL/min/kg, with a renal clearance of 0.19 mL/min/kg. When candesartan is administered orally, about 26% of the dose is excreted unchanged in urine. Following an oral dose of 14C-labeled candesartan cilexetil, approximately 33% of radioactivity is recovered in urine and approximately 67% in feces. Following an intravenous dose of 14C-labeled candesartan, approximately 59% of radioactivity is recovered in urine and approximately 36% in feces. Biliary excretion contributes to the elimination of candesartan.  Adults  Candesartan cilexetil is rapidly and completely bioactivated by ester hydrolysis during absorption from the gastrointestinal tract to candesartan, a selective AT1 subtype angiotensin II receptor antagonist. Candesartan is mainly excreted unchanged in urine and feces (via bile). It undergoes minor hepatic metabolism by O-deethylation to an inactive metabolite. The elimination half-life of candesartan is approximately 9 hours. After single and repeated administration, the pharmacokinetics of candesartan are linear for oral doses up to 32 mg of candesartan cilexetil. Candesartan and its inactive metabolite do not accumulate in serum upon repeated once-daily dosing. Following administration of candesartan cilexetil, the absolute bioavailability of candesartan was estimated to be 15%. After tablet ingestion, the peak serum concentration (Cmax) is reached after 3 to 4 hours. Food with a high fat content does not affect the bioavailability of candesartan after candesartan cilexetil administration.  Pediatrics  In children 1 to 17 years of age, plasma levels are greater than 10–fold higher at peak (approximately 4 hours) than 24 hours after a single dose. Children 1 to &amp;lt; 6 years of age, given 0.2 mg/kg had exposure similar to adults given 8 mg. Children &amp;gt; 6 years of age had exposure similar to adults given the same dose.  The pharmacokinetics (Cmax and AUC) were not modified by age, sex or body weight. Candesartan cilexetil pharmacokinetics have not been investigated in pediatric patients less than 1 year of age. From the dose-ranging studies of candesartan cilexetil, there was a dose related increase in plasma candesartan concentrations. The renin-angiotensin system (RAS) plays a critical role in kidney development. RAS blockade has been shown to lead to abnormal kidney development in very young mice. Children &amp;lt; 1 year of age must not receive ATACAND. Administering drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system (RAS) can alter normal renal development.  Geriatric and Sex  The pharmacokinetics of candesartan have been studied in the elderly (≥ 65 years) and in both sexes. The plasma concentration of candesartan was higher in the elderly (Cmax was approximately 50% higher, and AUC was approximately 80% higher) compared to younger subjects administered the same dose. The pharmacokinetics of candesartan were linear in the elderly, and candesartan and its inactive metabolite did not accumulate in the serum of these subjects upon repeated, once-daily administration. No initial dosage adjustment is necessary [see DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION (2)]. There is no difference in the pharmacokinetics of candesartan between male and female subjects.  Renal Insufficiency  In hypertensive patients with renal insufficiency, serum concentrations of candesartan were elevated. After repeated dosing, the AUC and Cmax were approximately doubled in patients with severe renal impairment (creatinine clearance &amp;lt;30 mL/min/1.73m2) compared to patients with normal kidney function. The pharmacokinetics of candesartan in hypertensive patients undergoing hemodialysis are similar to those in hypertensive patients with severe renal impairment. Candesartan cannot be removed by hemodialysis. No initial dosage adjustment is necessary in patients with renal insufficiency [see DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION (2.1)].  In heart failure patients with renal impairment, AUC0-72h was 36% and 65% higher in mild and moderate renal impairment, respectively. Cmax was 15% and 55% higher in mild and moderate renal impairment, respectively.  Pediatrics:  ATACAND pharmacokinetics have not been determined in children with renal insufficiency.  Hepatic Insufficiency  The pharmacokinetics of candesartan were compared in patients with mild and moderate hepatic impairment to matched healthy volunteers following a single oral dose of 16 mg candesartan cilexetil. The increase in AUC for candesartan was 30% in patients with mild hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh A) and 145% in patients with moderate hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh B). The increase in Cmax for candesartan was 56% in patients with mild hepatic impairment and 73% in patients with moderate hepatic impairment. The pharmacokinetics after candesartan cilexetil administration have not been investigated in patients with severe hepatic impairment. No initial dosage adjustment is necessary in patients with mild hepatic impairment. In hypertensive patients with moderate hepatic impairment, consideration should be given to initiation of ATACAND at a lower dose [see DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION (2.1)].   Heart Failure  The pharmacokinetics of candesartan were linear in patients with heart failure (NYHA class II and III) after candesartan cilexetil doses of 4, 8, and 16 mg. After repeated dosing, the AUC was approximately doubled in these patients compared with healthy, younger patients. The pharmacokinetics in heart failure patients is similar to that in healthy elderly volunteers [see DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION (2.3)].</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="5069" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>• When pregnancy is detected, discontinue ATACAND as soon as possible.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5070" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>• Drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause injury and death to the developing fetus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5071" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>WARNING: FETAL TOXICITY See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5072" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>•When pregnancy is detected, discontinue ATACAND as soon as possible.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5073" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>•Drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause injury and death to the developing fetus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5074" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>ATACAND is contraindicated in patients who are hypersensitive to candesartan.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5075" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Do not co-administer aliskiren with ATACAND in patients with diabetes.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M1" type="Trigger" span="0 20" str="Do not co-administer"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="21 9" str="aliskiren" code="502FWN4Q32"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M1" precipitant="M2"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5076" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Known hypersensitivity to product components (4).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5077" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Do not co-administer aliskiren with ATACAND in patients with diabetes (4).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M3" type="Trigger" span="0 20" str="Do not co-administer"/>
<Mention id="M4" type="Precipitant" span="21 9" str="aliskiren" code="502FWN4Q32"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M3" precipitant="M4"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5078" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Starting Dose Target Dose Adult Hypertension (2.1) 16 mg tablet once daily 8 – 32 mg tablet total daily dose Pediatric Hypertension (1 to &lt; 6 years) (2.2) 0.20 mg/kg oral suspension once daily 0.05 – 0.4 mg/kg oral suspension once daily or consider divided dose Pediatric Hypertension (6 to &lt; 17 years) (2.2) &lt; 50 kg 4 – 8 mg tablet once daily &gt;50 kg 8 – 16 mg tablet once daily &lt; 50 kg 4 – 16 mg tablet once daily or consider divided dose &gt; 50 kg 4 – 32 mg tablet once daily or consider divided dose Adult Heart Failure (2.3) 4 mg tablet once daily 32 mg tablet once dailyThe target dose is 32 mg once daily, which is achieved by doubling the dose at approximately 2-week intervals, as tolerated by patient Dosage must be individualized.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5079" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Blood pressure response is dose related over the range of 2 to 32 mg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5080" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The usual recommended starting dose of ATACAND is 16 mg once daily when it is used as monotherapy in patients who are not volume depleted.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5081" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>ATACAND can be administered once or twice daily with total daily doses ranging from 8 mg to 32 mg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5082" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Larger doses do not appear to have a greater effect, and there is relatively little experience with such doses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5083" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Most of the antihypertensive effect is present within 2 weeks, and maximal blood pressure reduction is generally obtained within 4 to 6 weeks of treatment with ATACAND.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5084" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Use in Hepatic Impairment: Initiate with 8 mg ATACAND in patients with moderate hepatic insufficiency.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5085" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dosing recommendations cannot be provided for patients with severe hepatic insufficiency.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5086" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>ATACAND may be administered with or without food.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5087" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If blood pressure is not controlled by ATACAND alone, a diuretic may be added.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5088" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>ATACAND may be administered with other antihypertensive agents.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5089" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>ATACAND may be administered once daily or divided into two equal doses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5090" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Adjust the dosage according to blood pressure response.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5091" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For patients with possible depletion of intravascular volume (e.g., patients treated with diuretics, particularly those with impaired renal function), initiate ATACAND under close medical supervision and consider administration of a lower dose.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M5" type="Trigger" span="174 25" str="close medical supervision "/>
<Mention id="M6" type="Trigger" span="233 10" str=" lower dose"/>
<Mention id="M7" type="Precipitant" span="90 9" str="diuretics" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M5;M6" precipitant="M7"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5092" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Children 1 to &lt; 6 years of age: The dose range is 0.05 to 0.4 mg/kg per day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5093" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommended starting dose is 0.20 mg/kg (oral suspension).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5094" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Children 6 to &lt; 17 years of age: For those less than 50 kg, the dose range is 2 to 16 mg per day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5095" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommended starting dose is 4 to 8 mg. For those greater than 50 kg, the dose range is 4 to 32 mg per day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5096" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommended starting dose is 8 to 16 mg. Doses above 0.4 mg/kg (1 to &lt; 6 year olds) or 32 mg (6 to &lt; 17 year olds) have not been studied in pediatric patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5097" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>An antihypertensive effect is usually present within 2 weeks, with full effect generally obtained within 4 weeks of treatment with ATACAND.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5098" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Children &lt; 1 year of age must not receive ATACAND for hypertension.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5099" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>All pediatric patients with a glomerular filtration rate less than 30 ml/min/1.73m2 should not receive ATACAND since ATACAND has not been studied in this population.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5100" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For children who cannot swallow tablets, an oral suspension may be substituted as described below: Preparation of Oral Suspension: ATACAND oral suspension can be prepared in concentrations within the range of 0.1 to 2.0 mg/mL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5101" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Typically, a concentration of 1 mg/mL will be suitable for the prescribed dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5102" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Any strength of ATACAND tablets can be used in the preparation of the suspension.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5103" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Follow the steps below for preparation of the suspension.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5104" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The number of tablets and volume of vehicle specified below will yield 160 mL of a 1 mg/mL suspension.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5105" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>•Prepare the vehicle by adding equal volumes of Ora-Plus® (80 mL) and Ora-Sweet SF® (80 mL) or, alternatively, use Ora-Blend SF® (160 mL).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5106" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>•Add a small amount of vehicle to the required number of ATACAND tablets (five 32 mg tablets) and grind into a smooth paste using a mortar and pestle.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5107" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>•Add the paste to a preparation vessel of suitable size.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5108" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>•Rinse the mortar and pestle clean using the vehicle and add this to the vessel.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5109" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>•Prepare the final volume by adding the remaining vehicle.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5110" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>•Dispense into suitably sized amber PET bottles.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5111" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>•Label with an expiry date of 100 days and include the following instructions: Store at room temperature (below 30°C/86°F).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5112" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not use after the expiry date stated on the bottle.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5113" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommended initial dose for treating heart failure is 4 mg once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5114" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The target dose is 32 mg once daily, which is achieved by doubling the dose at approximately 2-week intervals, as tolerated by the patient.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5115" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>•Lithium: Increases in serum lithium concentrations and toxicity (7).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M8" type="Trigger" span="10 18;37 14" str="Increases in serum | concentrations "/>
<Mention id="M9" type="Trigger" span="56 8" str=" toxicity"/>
<Mention id="M10" type="Precipitant" span="29 7" str="lithium" code="9FN79X2M3F"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M8;M9" precipitant="M10" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5116" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>•NSAIDS use may lead to increased risk of renal impairment and loss of antihypertensive effect (7).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M11" type="Trigger" span="63 7;88 6" str="loss of | effect"/>
<Mention id="M15" type="Precipitant" span="1 6" str="NSAIDS" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M13" type="SpecificInteraction" span="63 31" str="loss of antihypertensive effect" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M14" type="Trigger" span="24 14" str="increased risk"/>
<Mention id="M16" type="SpecificInteraction" span="42 16" str="renal impairment" code="236423003: Renal impairment (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M11" precipitant="M15" effect="M13"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M14" precipitant="M15" effect="M16"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5117" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>•Combined inhibition of the renin-angiotensin system: Increased risk of renal impairment, hypotension, and hyperkalemia (7).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M23" type="Trigger" span="54 14" str="Increased risk"/>
<Mention id="M24" type="Precipitant" span="1 51" str="Combined inhibition of the renin-angiotensin system" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M19" type="SpecificInteraction" span="72 16" str="renal impairment" code="236423003: Renal impairment (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M22" type="SpecificInteraction" span="107 12" str="hyperkalemia" code="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M25" type="SpecificInteraction" span="90 11" str="hypotension" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M23" precipitant="M24" effect="M19"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M23" precipitant="M24" effect="M22"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M23" precipitant="M24" effect="M25"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5118" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Co-administration of ATACAND with potassium sparing diuretics, potassium supplements, potassium-containing salt substitutes or other drugs that raise serum potassium levels may result in hyperkalemia.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M35" type="Trigger" span="177 9" str="result in"/>
<Mention id="M27" type="Precipitant" span="133 39" str="drugs that raise serum potassium levels" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M37" type="SpecificInteraction" span="187 12" str="hyperkalemia" code="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M30" type="Precipitant" span="34 27" str="potassium sparing diuretics" code="N0000175418"/>
<Mention id="M33" type="Precipitant" span="63 21" str="potassium supplements" code="RWP5GA015D"/>
<Mention id="M36" type="Precipitant" span="86 37" str="potassium-containing salt substitutes" code="N0000175600"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M27" effect="M37"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M30" effect="M37"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M33" effect="M37"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M36" effect="M37"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5119" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor serum potassium in such patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5120" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Increases in serum lithium concentrations and toxicity have been reported during concomitant administration of lithium with angiotensin II receptor antagonists, including ATACAND.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M38" type="Trigger" span="0 18;27 14" str="Increases in serum | concentrations "/>
<Mention id="M39" type="Trigger" span="46 8" str=" toxicity"/>
<Mention id="M40" type="Precipitant" span="19 7" str="lithium" code="9FN79X2M3F"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M38;M39" precipitant="M40" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5121" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>In patients who are elderly, volume-depleted (including those on diuretic therapy), or with compromised renal function, co-administration of NSAIDs, including selective COX-2 inhibitors, with angiotensin II receptor antagonists, including candesartan, may result in deterioration of renal function, including possible acute renal failure.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M50" type="Trigger" span="256 9" str="result in"/>
<Mention id="M45" type="Precipitant" span="141 6" str="NSAIDs" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M52" type="SpecificInteraction" span="266 31" str="deterioration of renal function" code="236423003: Renal impairment (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M49" type="SpecificInteraction" span="318 19" str="acute renal failure" code="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M51" type="Precipitant" span="159 26" str="selective COX-2 inhibitors" code="N0000008288"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M50" precipitant="M45" effect="M52"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M50" precipitant="M45" effect="M49"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M50" precipitant="M51" effect="M49"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M50" precipitant="M51" effect="M52"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5122" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor renal function periodically in patients receiving candesartan and NSAID therapy.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M53" type="Trigger" span="0 7" str="Monitor"/>
<Mention id="M54" type="Precipitant" span="74 5" str="NSAID" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M55" type="SpecificInteraction" span="8 14" str="renal function" code="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M53" precipitant="M54" effect="M55"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5123" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The antihypertensive effect of angiotensin II receptor antagonists, including candesartan may be attenuated by NSAIDs including selective COX-2 inhibitors.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M59" type="Trigger" span="21 6;97 10" str="effect | attenuated"/>
<Mention id="M57" type="Precipitant" span="111 6" str="NSAIDs" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M61" type="SpecificInteraction" span="4 23;97 10" str="antihypertensive effect | attenuated" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M60" type="Precipitant" span="128 26" str="selective COX-2 inhibitors" code="N0000008288"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M59" precipitant="M57" effect="M61"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M59" precipitant="M60" effect="M61"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5124" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Dual blockade of the RAS with angiotensin receptor blockers, ACE inhibitors, or aliskiren is associated with increased risks of hypotension, hyperkalemia, and changes in renal function (including acute renal failure) compared to monotherapy.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M122" type="Trigger" span="93 15" str="associated with "/>
<Mention id="M123" type="Trigger" span="109 15" str=" increased risks"/>
<Mention id="M76" type="Precipitant" span="61 14" str="ACE inhibitors" code="N0000175562"/>
<Mention id="M121" type="SpecificInteraction" span="196 19" str="acute renal failure" code="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M125" type="SpecificInteraction" span="159 25" str="changes in renal function" code="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M117" type="SpecificInteraction" span="141 12" str="hyperkalemia" code="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M113" type="SpecificInteraction" span="128 11" str="hypotension" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M92" type="Precipitant" span="80 9" str="aliskiren" code="502FWN4Q32"/>
<Mention id="M108" type="Precipitant" span="30 29" str="angiotensin receptor blockers" code="N0000175561"/>
<Mention id="M124" type="Precipitant" span="0 24" str="Dual blockade of the RAS" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M122;M123" precipitant="M76" effect="M121"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M122;M123" precipitant="M76" effect="M125"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M122;M123" precipitant="M76" effect="M117"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M122;M123" precipitant="M76" effect="M113"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M122;M123" precipitant="M92" effect="M113"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M122;M123" precipitant="M92" effect="M117"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M122;M123" precipitant="M92" effect="M125"/>
<Interaction id="I29" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M122;M123" precipitant="M92" effect="M121"/>
<Interaction id="I30" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M122;M123" precipitant="M108" effect="M125"/>
<Interaction id="I31" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M122;M123" precipitant="M108" effect="M121"/>
<Interaction id="I32" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M122;M123" precipitant="M108" effect="M113"/>
<Interaction id="I33" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M122;M123" precipitant="M108" effect="M117"/>
<Interaction id="I34" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M122;M123" precipitant="M124" effect="M113"/>
<Interaction id="I35" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M122;M123" precipitant="M124" effect="M117"/>
<Interaction id="I36" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M122;M123" precipitant="M124" effect="M121"/>
<Interaction id="I37" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M122;M123" precipitant="M124" effect="M125"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5125" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Triple combination of ATACAND with an ACE-inhibitor and a mineralocorticoid receptor antagonist is generally not recommended.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M128" type="Trigger" span="109 15" str="not recommended"/>
<Mention id="M127" type="Precipitant" span="38 13" str="ACE-inhibitor" code="N0000175562"/>
<Mention id="M129" type="Precipitant" span="58 37" str="mineralocorticoid receptor antagonist" code="N0000000139"/>
<Interaction id="I38" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M128" precipitant="M127"/>
<Interaction id="I39" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M128" precipitant="M129"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5126" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Closely monitor blood pressure, renal function and electrolytes in patients on ATACAND and other agents that affect the RAS.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M136" type="Trigger" span="0 15" str="Closely monitor"/>
<Mention id="M137" type="Precipitant" span="97 26" str="agents that affect the RAS" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M132" type="SpecificInteraction" span="16 14" str="blood pressure" code="38936003: Abnormal blood pressure (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M135" type="SpecificInteraction" span="51 12" str="electrolytes" code="166686006: Electrolytes abnormal (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M138" type="SpecificInteraction" span="32 14" str="renal function" code="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I40" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M136" precipitant="M137" effect="M132"/>
<Interaction id="I41" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M136" precipitant="M137" effect="M135"/>
<Interaction id="I42" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M136" precipitant="M137" effect="M138"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5127" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Avoid use of aliskiren with ATACAND in patients with renal impairment (GFR &lt;60 ml/min).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M139" type="Trigger" span="0 5" str="Avoid"/>
<Mention id="M140" type="Precipitant" span="13 9" str="aliskiren" code="502FWN4Q32"/>
<Interaction id="I43" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M139" precipitant="M140"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5128" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>•Observe for signs and symptoms of hypotension (5.3).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5129" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>• Monitor renal function (5.4) and potassium levels (5.5).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5130" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Pregnancy Category D Use of drugs that act on the renin-angiotensin system during the second and third trimesters of pregnancy reduces fetal renal function and increases fetal and neonatal morbidity and death.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5131" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Resulting oligohydramnios can be associated with fetal lung hypoplasia and skeletal deformations.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5132" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Potential neonatal adverse effects include skull hypoplasia, anuria, hypotension, renal failure and death.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5133" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>When pregnancy is detected, discontinue ATACAND as soon as possible.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5134" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Oral doses ≥10 mg of candesartan cilexetil/kg/day administered to pregnant rats during late gestation and continued through lactation were associated with reduced survival and an increased incidence of hydronephrosis in the offspring.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5135" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The 10-mg/kg/day dose in rats is approximately 2.8 times the maximum recommended daily human dose (MRHD) of 32 mg on a mg/m2 basis (comparison assumes human body weight of 50 kg).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5136" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Candesartan cilexetil given to pregnant rabbits at an oral dose of 3 mg/kg/day (approximately 1.7 times the MRHD on a mg/m2 basis) caused maternal toxicity (decreased body weight and death) but, in surviving dams, had no adverse effects on fetal survival, fetal weight, or external, visceral, or skeletal development.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5137" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>No maternal toxicity or adverse effects on fetal development were observed when oral doses up to 1000 mg of candesartan cilexetil/kg/day (approximately 138 times the MRHD on a mg/m2 basis) were administered to pregnant mice.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5138" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system (RAS) can have effects on the development of immature kidneys.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5139" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>ATACAND can cause symptomatic hypotension.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5140" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Symptomatic hypotension is most likely to occur in patients who have been volume and/or salt depleted as a result of prolonged diuretic therapy, dietary salt restriction, dialysis, diarrhea, or vomiting.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M141" type="Trigger" span="32 15" str="likely to occur"/>
<Mention id="M142" type="Precipitant" span="117 26" str="prolonged diuretic therapy" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M143" type="SpecificInteraction" span="-1 23" str="symptomatic hypotension" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I44" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M141" precipitant="M142" effect="M143"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5141" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients with symptomatic hypotension may require temporarily reducing the dose of ATACAND, diuretic or both, and volume repletion.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M144" type="Trigger" span="62 17" str="reducing the dose"/>
<Mention id="M145" type="Precipitant" span="92 8" str="diuretic" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I45" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M144" precipitant="M145" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5142" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Volume and/or salt depletion should be corrected before initiating therapy with ATACAND.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5143" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In the CHARM program (heart failure patients), hypotension was reported in 18.8% of patients on ATACAND versus 9.8% of patients on placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5144" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The incidence of hypotension leading to drug discontinuation in ATACAND-treated patients was 4.1% compared with 2.0% in placebo-treated patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5145" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In the CHARM-Added program, where candesartan or placebo was given in addition to ACE inhibitors, hypotension was reported in 22.6% of patients treated with ATACAND versus 13.8% treated with placebo.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M148" type="SpecificInteraction" span="98 11" str="hypotension" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M147" type="Precipitant" span="82 14" str="ACE inhibitors" code="N0000175562"/>
<Interaction id="I46" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M148" precipitant="M147" effect="M148"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5146" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Monitoring of blood pressure is recommended during dose escalation and periodically thereafter.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5147" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Major Surgery/Anesthesia Hypotension may occur during major surgery and anesthesia in patients treated with angiotensin II receptor antagonists, including ATACAND, due to blockade of the renin-angiotensin system.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M149" type="Trigger" span="171 8" str="blockade"/>
<Mention id="M153" type="Precipitant" span="72 10" str="anesthesia" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M151" type="SpecificInteraction" span="171 40" str="blockade of the renin-angiotensin system" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M152" type="Trigger" span="25 11" str="Hypotension"/>
<Mention id="M154" type="SpecificInteraction" span="-1 11" str="hypotension" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I47" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M149" precipitant="M153" effect="M151"/>
<Interaction id="I48" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M152" precipitant="M153" effect="M154"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5148" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Very rarely, hypotension may be severe such that it may warrant the use of intravenous fluids and/or vasopressors.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5149" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor renal function periodically in patients treated with ATACAND.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5150" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Changes in renal function including acute renal failure can be caused by drugs that inhibit the renin-angiotensin system.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5151" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients whose renal function may depend, in part, on the activity of the renin-angiotensin system (e.g., patient with renal artery stenosis, chronic kidney disease, severe heart failure, or volume depletion) may be at particular risk of developing oliguria, progressive azotemia or acute renal failure when treated with ATACAND.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5152" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Consider withholding or discontinuing therapy in patients who develop a clinically significant decrease in renal function on ATACAND.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5153" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In the CHARM program (heart failure patients), the incidence of abnormal renal function (e.g., creatinine increase) was 12.5% in patients treated with ATACAND versus 6.3% in patients treated with placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5154" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The incidence of abnormal renal function (e.g., creatinine increase) leading to drug discontinuation in ATACAND-treated patients was 6.3% compared with 2.9% in placebo-treated patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5155" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In the CHARM-Added program, where candesartan or placebo was given in addition to ACE inhibitors, the incidence of abnormal renal function (e.g., creatinine increase) was 15% in patients treated with ATACAND versus 9% in patients treated with placebo.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M158" type="Trigger" span="102 9" str="incidence"/>
<Mention id="M159" type="Precipitant" span="82 14" str="ACE inhibitors" code="N0000175562"/>
<Mention id="M157" type="SpecificInteraction" span="146 19" str="creatinine increase" code="166717003: Serum creatinine raised (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M160" type="SpecificInteraction" span="115 23" str="abnormal renal function" code="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I49" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M158" precipitant="M159" effect="M157"/>
<Interaction id="I50" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M158" precipitant="M159" effect="M160"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5156" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Drugs that inhibit the renin-angiotensin system can cause hyperkalemia.Concomitant use of ATACAND with drugs that increase potassium levels may increase the risk of hyperkalemia.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M161" type="Trigger" span="144 17" str="increase the risk"/>
<Mention id="M162" type="Precipitant" span="103 36" str="drugs that increase potassium levels" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M163" type="SpecificInteraction" span="58 12" str="hyperkalemia" code="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I51" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M161" precipitant="M162" effect="M163"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5157" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In the CHARM program (heart failure patients), the incidence of hyperkalemia was 6.3% in patients treated with ATACAND versus 2.1% in patients treated with placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5158" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The incidence of hyperkalemia leading to drug discontinuation in ATACAND-treated patients was 2.4% compared with 0.6% in placebo-treated patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5159" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In the CHARM-Added program where candesartan or placebo was given in addition to ACE inhibitors, the incidence of hyperkalemia was 9.5% in patients treated with ATACAND versus 3.5% in patients treated with placebo.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M164" type="Trigger" span="101 9" str="incidence"/>
<Mention id="M165" type="Precipitant" span="81 14" str="ACE inhibitors" code="N0000175562"/>
<Mention id="M166" type="SpecificInteraction" span="114 12" str="hyperkalemia" code="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I52" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M164" precipitant="M165" effect="M166"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5160" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Angiotensin II is formed from angiotensin I in a reaction catalyzed by angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE, kininase II).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5161" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Angiotensin II is the principal pressor agent of the renin-angiotensin system, with effects that include vasoconstriction, stimulation of synthesis and release of aldosterone, cardiac stimulation, and renal reabsorption of sodium.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5162" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Candesartan blocks the vasoconstrictor and aldosterone-secreting effects of angiotensin II by selectively blocking the binding of angiotensin II to the AT1 receptor in many tissues, such as vascular smooth muscle and the adrenal gland.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5163" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Its action is, therefore, independent of the pathways for angiotensin II synthesis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5164" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There is also an AT2 receptor found in many tissues, but AT2 is not known to be associated with cardiovascular homeostasis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5165" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Candesartan has much greater affinity (&gt;10,000-fold) for the AT1 receptor than for the AT2 receptor.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5166" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Blockade of the renin-angiotensin system with ACE inhibitors, which inhibit the biosynthesis of angiotensin II from angiotensin I, is widely used in the treatment of hypertension.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5167" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>ACE inhibitors also inhibit the degradation of bradykinin, a reaction also catalyzed by ACE.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5168" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Because candesartan does not inhibit ACE (kininase II), it does not affect the response to bradykinin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5169" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Whether this difference has clinical relevance is not yet known.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5170" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Candesartan does not bind to or block other hormone receptors or ion channels known to be important in cardiovascular regulation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5171" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Blockade of the angiotensin II receptor inhibits the negative regulatory feedback of angiotensin II on renin secretion, but the resulting increased plasma renin activity and angiotensin II circulating levels do not overcome the effect of candesartan on blood pressure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5172" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Candesartan inhibits the pressor effects of angiotensin II infusion in a dose-dependent manner.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M167" type="Trigger" span="12 8;33 7" str="inhibits | effects"/>
<Mention id="M168" type="Precipitant" span="44 23" str="angiotensin II infusion" code="M089EFU921"/>
<Mention id="M169" type="SpecificInteraction" span="12 28" str="inhibits the pressor effects" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I53" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M167" precipitant="M168" effect="M169"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5173" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>After 1 week of once daily dosing with 8 mg of candesartan cilexetil, the pressor effect was inhibited by approximately 90% at peak with approximately 50% inhibition persisting for 24 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5174" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Plasma concentrations of angiotensin I and angiotensin II, and plasma renin activity (PRA), increased in a dose-dependent manner after single and repeated administration of candesartan cilexetil to healthy subjects, hypertensive, and heart failure patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5175" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>ACE activity was not altered in healthy subjects after repeated candesartan cilexetil administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5176" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The once-daily administration of up to 16 mg of candesartan cilexetil to healthy subjects did not influence plasma aldosterone concentrations, but a decrease in the plasma concentration of aldosterone was observed when 32 mg of candesartan cilexetil was administered to hypertensive patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5177" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In spite of the effect of candesartan cilexetil on aldosterone secretion, very little effect on serum potassium was observed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5178" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Hypertension Adults In multiple-dose studies with hypertensive patients, there were no clinically significant changes in metabolic function, including serum levels of total cholesterol, triglycerides, glucose, or uric acid.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5179" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In a 12-week study of 161 patients with non-insulin-dependent (type 2) diabetes mellitus and hypertension, there was no change in the level of HbA1c.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5180" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Heart Failure In heart failure patients, candesartan ≥ 8 mg resulted in decreases in systemic vascular resistance and pulmonary capillary wedge pressure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5181" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Distribution The volume of distribution of candesartan is 0.13 L/kg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5182" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Candesartan is highly bound to plasma proteins (&gt;99%) and does not penetrate red blood cells.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5183" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The protein binding is constant at candesartan plasma concentrations well above the range achieved with recommended doses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5184" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In rats, it has been demonstrated that candesartan crosses the blood-brain barrier poorly, if at all.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5185" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>It has also been demonstrated in rats that candesartan passes across the placental barrier and is distributed in the fetus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5186" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Metabolism and Excretion Because candesartan is not significantly metabolized by the cytochrome P450 system and at therapeutic concentrations has no effects on P450 enzymes, interactions with drugs that inhibit or are metabolized by those enzymes would not be expected.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5187" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Total plasma clearance of candesartan is 0.37 mL/min/kg, with a renal clearance of 0.19 mL/min/kg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5188" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>When candesartan is administered orally, about 26% of the dose is excreted unchanged in urine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5189" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following an oral dose of 14C-labeled candesartan cilexetil, approximately 33% of radioactivity is recovered in urine and approximately 67% in feces.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5190" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following an intravenous dose of 14C-labeled candesartan, approximately 59% of radioactivity is recovered in urine and approximately 36% in feces.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5191" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Biliary excretion contributes to the elimination of candesartan.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5192" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Adults Candesartan cilexetil is rapidly and completely bioactivated by ester hydrolysis during absorption from the gastrointestinal tract to candesartan, a selective AT1 subtype angiotensin II receptor antagonist.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5193" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Candesartan is mainly excreted unchanged in urine and feces (via bile).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5194" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>It undergoes minor hepatic metabolism by O-deethylation to an inactive metabolite.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5195" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The elimination half-life of candesartan is approximately 9 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5196" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>After single and repeated administration, the pharmacokinetics of candesartan are linear for oral doses up to 32 mg of candesartan cilexetil.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5197" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Candesartan and its inactive metabolite do not accumulate in serum upon repeated once-daily dosing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5198" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following administration of candesartan cilexetil, the absolute bioavailability of candesartan was estimated to be 15%.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5199" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>After tablet ingestion, the peak serum concentration (Cmax) is reached after 3 to 4 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5200" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Food with a high fat content does not affect the bioavailability of candesartan after candesartan cilexetil administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5201" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Pediatrics In children 1 to 17 years of age, plasma levels are greater than 10–fold higher at peak (approximately 4 hours) than 24 hours after a single dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5202" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Children 1 to &lt; 6 years of age, given 0.2 mg/kg had exposure similar to adults given 8 mg. Children &gt; 6 years of age had exposure similar to adults given the same dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5203" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacokinetics (Cmax and AUC) were not modified by age, sex or body weight.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5204" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Candesartan cilexetil pharmacokinetics have not been investigated in pediatric patients less than 1 year of age.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5205" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>From the dose-ranging studies of candesartan cilexetil, there was a dose related increase in plasma candesartan concentrations.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5206" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The renin-angiotensin system (RAS) plays a critical role in kidney development.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5207" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>RAS blockade has been shown to lead to abnormal kidney development in very young mice.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5208" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Children &lt; 1 year of age must not receive ATACAND.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5209" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Administering drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system (RAS) can alter normal renal development.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5210" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Geriatric and Sex The pharmacokinetics of candesartan have been studied in the elderly (≥ 65 years) and in both sexes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5211" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The plasma concentration of candesartan was higher in the elderly (Cmax was approximately 50% higher, and AUC was approximately 80% higher) compared to younger subjects administered the same dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5212" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacokinetics of candesartan were linear in the elderly, and candesartan and its inactive metabolite did not accumulate in the serum of these subjects upon repeated, once-daily administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5213" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No initial dosage adjustment is necessary.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5214" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There is no difference in the pharmacokinetics of candesartan between male and female subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5215" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Renal Insufficiency In hypertensive patients with renal insufficiency, serum concentrations of candesartan were elevated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5216" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>After repeated dosing, the AUC and Cmax were approximately doubled in patients with severe renal impairment (creatinine clearance &lt;30 mL/min/1.73m2) compared to patients with normal kidney function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5217" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacokinetics of candesartan in hypertensive patients undergoing hemodialysis are similar to those in hypertensive patients with severe renal impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5218" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Candesartan cannot be removed by hemodialysis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5219" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No initial dosage adjustment is necessary in patients with renal insufficiency.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5220" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In heart failure patients with renal impairment, AUC0-72h was 36% and 65% higher in mild and moderate renal impairment, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5221" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Cmax was 15% and 55% higher in mild and moderate renal impairment, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5222" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Pediatrics ATACAND pharmacokinetics have not been determined in children with renal insufficiency.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5223" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Hepatic Insufficiency The pharmacokinetics of candesartan were compared in patients with mild and moderate hepatic impairment to matched healthy volunteers following a single oral dose of 16 mg candesartan cilexetil.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5224" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The increase in AUC for candesartan was 30% in patients with mild hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh A) and 145% in patients with moderate hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh B).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5225" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The increase in Cmax for candesartan was 56% in patients with mild hepatic impairment and 73% in patients with moderate hepatic impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5226" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacokinetics after candesartan cilexetil administration have not been investigated in patients with severe hepatic impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5227" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No initial dosage adjustment is necessary in patients with mild hepatic impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5228" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In hypertensive patients with moderate hepatic impairment, consideration should be given to initiation of ATACAND at a lower dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5229" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Heart Failure The pharmacokinetics of candesartan were linear in patients with heart failure (NYHA class II and III) after candesartan cilexetil doses of 4, 8, and 16 mg. After repeated dosing, the AUC was approximately doubled in these patients compared with healthy, younger patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5230" LabelDrug="ATACAND" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacokinetics in heart failure patients is similar to that in healthy elderly volunteers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="aliskiren" precipitantCode="502FWN4Q32" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="aliskiren" precipitantCode="502FWN4Q32" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="aliskiren" precipitantCode="502FWN4Q32" effect="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="aliskiren" precipitantCode="502FWN4Q32" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="aliskiren" precipitantCode="502FWN4Q32"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="diuretics" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="lithium" precipitantCode="9FN79X2M3F" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nsaids" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect=" 39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nsaids" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nsaids" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="236423003: Renal impairment (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nsaids" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="combined inhibition of the renin-angiotensin system" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="combined inhibition of the renin-angiotensin system" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="236423003: Renal impairment (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="combined inhibition of the renin-angiotensin system" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="drugs that raise serum potassium levels" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="potassium sparing diuretics" precipitantCode="N0000175418" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="potassium supplements" precipitantCode="RWP5GA015D" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="potassium-containing salt substitutes" precipitantCode="N0000175600" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="selective cox-2 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000008288" effect=" 39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="selective cox-2 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000008288" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="selective cox-2 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000008288" effect="236423003: Renal impairment (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="selective cox-2 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000008288" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nsaid" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ace inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175562" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ace inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175562" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ace inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175562" effect="166717003: Serum creatinine raised (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ace inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175562" effect="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ace inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175562" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="angiotensin receptor blockers" precipitantCode="N0000175561" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="angiotensin receptor blockers" precipitantCode="N0000175561" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="angiotensin receptor blockers" precipitantCode="N0000175561" effect="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="angiotensin receptor blockers" precipitantCode="N0000175561" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="dual blockade of the ras" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="dual blockade of the ras" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="dual blockade of the ras" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="dual blockade of the ras" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="ace-inhibitor" precipitantCode="N0000175562"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="mineralocorticoid receptor antagonist" precipitantCode="N0000000139"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="agents that affect the ras" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="166686006: Electrolytes abnormal (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="agents that affect the ras" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="38936003: Abnormal blood pressure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="agents that affect the ras" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="prolonged diuretic therapy" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="diuretic" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="anesthesia" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="anesthesia" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="drugs that increase potassium levels" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="angiotensin ii infusion" precipitantCode="M089EFU921" effect="NO MAP"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>