<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Atropine Sulfate" setid="ad8916e7-206e-409e-2582-30d072845dd4">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
Atropine generally is contraindicated in patients with glaucoma, pyloric stenosis or prostatic hypertrophy, except in doses ordinarily used for preanesthetic medication.</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
Atropine Sulfate Injection, USP in the Ansyr Syringe is intended for intravenous use, but may be administered subcutaneously or intramuscularly. Its use usually requires titration, using heart rate, PR interval, blood pressure and/or patient’s symptoms as a guide for having reached an appropriate dose.    Adults     Initial single doses in adults vary from around 0.5 mg to 1 mg (5-10 mL of the 0.1 mg/mL solution for antisialagogue and other antivagal effects, to 2 to 3 mg (20-30 mL) of the 0.1 mg/mL solution) as an antidote for organophosporous or muscarinic mushroom poisoning. When used as an antidote, the 2 to 3 mg dose should be repeated no less often than every 20 to 30 minutes until the signs of poisoning are sufficiently lessened or signs of atropine poisoning (see ADVERSE REACTIONS and OVERDOSAGE) occur. When the recurrent use of atropine is essential in patients with coronary artery disease, the total dose should be restricted to 2 to 3 mg (maximum 0.03 to 0.04 mg/kg) to avoid the detrimental effects of atropine-induced tachycardia on myocardial oxygen demand. For patients with bradyasystolic cardiac arrest, a 1 mg dose of atropine is administered intravenously and is repeated every 3-5 minutes if asystole persists. Three milligrams (0.04 mg/kg) given I.V. is a fully vagolytic dose in most patients. The administration of this dose of atropine should be reserved for patients with bradyasystolic cardiac arrest. Administration of less than 0.5 mg can produce a paradoxical bradycardia because of the central or peripheral parasympathomimetic effects of low doses in adults. Endotracheal administration of atropine can be used in patients without I.V. access. The recommended adult dose of atropine for endotracheal administration is 1 to 2 mg diluted to a total not to exceed 10 mL of sterile water or normal saline. Titration intervals of one or two hours are recommended in circumstances that are not life-threatening.   Pediatrics   Dosing information in pediatric populations has not been well studied. Usage history of initial dose has been in the range of 0.01 to 0.03 mg/kg body weight. Parenteral drug products should be inspected visually for particulate matter and/or discoloration prior to administration (see PRECAUTIONS).</Section>
<Section name="PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="42232-9">
Do not administer unless solution is clear and seal is intact. Discard unused portion. Atropine Sulfate Injection, USP should be used with caution in all individuals over 40 years of age. Conventional systemic doses may precipitate acute glaucoma in susceptible patients, convert partial organic pyloric stenosis into complete obstruction, lead to complete urinary retention in patients with prostatic hypertrophy or cause inspissation of bronchial secretions and formation of dangerous viscid plugs in patients with chronic lung disease.        Studies have not been performed to evaluate the carcinogenic or mutagenic potential of atropine or its potential to adversely affect fertility.          Animal reproduction studies have not been conducted with atropine. It also is not known whether atropine can cause fetal harm when given to a pregnant woman or can affect reproduction capacity. Atropine should be given to a pregnant woman only if clearly needed.          Safety and effectiveness in pediatric populations have not been established.          An evaluation of current literature revealed no clinical experience identifying differences in response between elderly and younger patients. In general, dose selection for an elderly patient should be cautious, usually starting at the low end of the dosing range, reflecting the greater frequency of decreased hepatic, renal, or cardiac function, and of concomitant disease or other drug therapy.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS SECTION" id="34071-1">
Atropine is a highly potent drug and due care is essential to avoid overdosage, especially with intravenous administration. Pediatric populations are more susceptible than adults to the toxic effects of anticholinergic agents. Atropine I.V. decreased the rate of mexiletine absorption without altering the relative oral bioavailability; this delay in mexiletine absorption was reversed by the combination of atropine and intravenous metoclopramide during pretreatment for anesthesia. Atropine is not removed by dialysis.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Atropine is commonly classified as an anticholinergic or antiparasympathetic (parasympatholytic) drug. More precisely, however, it is termed an antimuscarinic agent since it antagonizes the muscarine-like actions of acetyl-choline and other choline esters. Atropine inhibits the muscarinic actions of acetylcholine on structures innervated by postganglionic cholinergic nerves, and on smooth muscles which respond to endogenous acetylcholine but are not so innervated. As with other antimuscarinic agents, the major action of atropine is a competitive or surmountable antagonism which can be overcome by increasing the concentration of acetylcholine at receptor sites of the effector organ (e.g., by using anticholinesterase agents which inhibit the enzymatic destruction of acetylcholine). The receptors antagonized by atropine are the peripheral structures that are stimulated or inhibited by muscarine (i.e., exocrine glands and smooth and cardiac muscle). Responses to postganglionic cholinergic nerve stimulation also may be inhibited by atropine but this occurs less readily than with responses to injected (exogenous) choline esters. Atropine-induced parasympathetic inhibition may be preceded by a transient phase of stimulation, especially on the heart where small doses first slow the rate before characteristic tachycardia develops due to paralysis of vagal control. Atropine exerts a more potent and prolonged effect on heart, intestine and bronchial muscle than scopolamine, but its action on the iris, ciliary body and certain secretory glands is weaker than that of scopolamine. Unlike the latter, atropine in clinical doses does not depress the central nervous system but may stimulate the medulla and higher cerebral centers. Although mild vagal excitation occurs, the increased respiratory rate and (sometimes) increased depth of respiration produced by atropine are more probably the result of bronchiolar dilatation. Accordingly, atropine is an unreliable respiratory stimulant and large or repeated doses may depress respiration. Adequate doses of atropine abolish various types of reflex vagal cardiac slowing or asystole. The drug also prevents or abolishes bradycardia or asystole produced by injection of choline esters, anticholinesterase agents or other parasympathomimetic drugs, and cardiac arrest produced by stimulation of the vagus. Atropine also may lessen the degree of partial heart block when vagal activity is an etiologic factor. In some patients with complete heart block, the idioventricular rate may be accelerated by atropine; in others, the rate is stabilized. Occasionally a large dose may cause atrioventricular (A-V) block and nodal rhythm. Atropine Sulfate Injection, USP in clinical doses counteracts the peripheral dilatation and abrupt decrease in blood pressure produced by choline esters. However, when given by itself, atropine does not exert a striking or uniform effect on blood vessels or blood pressure. Systemic doses slightly raise systolic and lower diastolic pressures and can produce significant postural hypotension. Such doses also slightly increase cardiac output and decrease central venous pressure. Occasionally, therapeutic doses dilate cutaneous blood vessels, particularly in the “blush” area (atropine flush), and may cause atropine “fever” due to suppression of sweat gland activity in infants and small children. Atropine disappears rapidly from the blood following injection and is distributed throughout the body. Much of the drug is destroyed by enzymatic hydrolysis, particularly in the liver; from 13 to 50% is excreted unchanged in the urine. Traces are found in various secretions, including milk. The major metabolites of atropine are noratropine, atropin-n-oxide, tropine, and tropic acid. The metabolism of atropine is inhibited by organophosphate pesticides (e.g., diazon). Atropine readily crosses the placental barrier and enters the fetal circulation, but is not found in amniotic fluid. Exercise, both prior to and immediately following intramuscular administration of atropine, significantly increases the absorption of atropine due to increased perfusion in the muscle and significantly decreases the clearance of atropine. The pharmacokinetics of atropine is nonlinear after intravenous administration of 0.5 to 4 mg. Atropine binds poorly (about 44%) to plasma protein, mainly to alpha-1 acid glycoprotein; age has no effect on the serum protein binding of atropine. Atropine binding to α-1 acid glycoprotein was concentration-dependent (2-20 μg/mL) and nonlinear  in vitro and  in vivo . The elimination half-life of atropine is more than doubled in children under two years and the elderly (&amp;gt;65 years old) compared to other age groups (2-64 years old). There is no gender effect on the pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics (heart rate changes) of atropine. The effects of intravenous atropine on heart rate (maximum heart rate) and saliva flow (minimum flow) after I.V. administration (rapid, constant infusion over 3 min.) are delayed by 7 to 8 minutes after drug administration and both effects are non-linearly related to the amount of drug in the peripheral compartment. Changes in plasma atropine levels following intramuscular administration (0.5 to 4 mg doses) and heart rate are closely overlapped but the time course of the changes in atropine levels and behavioral impairment indicates that pharmacokinetics is not the primary rate-limiting mechanism for the central nervous system effect of atropine. Sodium chloride added to render the solution isotonic for injection of the active ingredient is present in amounts insufficient to affect serum electrolyte balance of sodium (Na+) and chloride (Cl¯) ions.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="3219" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For intravenous administration, but may also be administered via subcutaneous, intramuscular or via an endotracheal tube (2.1, 2.3).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3220" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Titrate according to heart rate, PR interval, blood pressure and symptoms.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3221" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Adult dosage -Antisialagogue or for antivagal effects: Initial single dose of 0.5 mg to 1mg. (2.2) -Antidote for organophosphorus or muscarinic mushroom poisoning: Initial single dose of 2 mg to 3 mg, repeated every 20-30 minutes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3222" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>-Bradyasystolic cardiac arrest: 1 mg dose, repeated every 3-5 minutes if asystole persists.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3223" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Patients with Coronary Artery Disease: Limit the total dose to 0.03mg/kg to 0.04 mg/kg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3224" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Parenteral drug products should be inspected visually for particulate matter and discoloration prior to administration, whenever solution and container permit.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3225" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not administer unless solution is clear and seal is intact.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3226" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Each syringe is intended for single dose only.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3227" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Intravenous administration is usually preferred, but subcutaneous, intramuscular, and endotracheal administration are possible.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3228" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For administration via an endotracheal tube, dilute 1-2 mg in no more than 10mL of sterile water or normal saline.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3229" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Titrate based on heart rate, PR interval, blood pressure and symptoms.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3230" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Table 1: Recommended Dosage Use Dose (adults) Repeat Antisialagogue or other antivagal 0.5 to 1 mg 1-2 hours Organophosphorus or muscarinic mushroom poisoning 2 to 3 mg 20-30 minutes Bradyasystolic cardiac arrest 1 mg 3-5 minutes; 3 mg maximum total dose Dosing in pediatric populations has not been well studied.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3231" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Usual initial dose is 0.01 to 0.03 mg/kg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3232" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Limit the total dose of atropine sulfate to 0.03 mg/kg to 0.04 mg/kg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3233" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Mexiletine: Decreases rate of mexiletine absorption.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M1" type="Trigger" span="12 17;41 10" str="Decreases rate of | absorption"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="30 10" str="mexiletine" code="1U511HHV4Z"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M1" precipitant="M2" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3234" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Atropine Sulfate Injection decreased the rate of mexiletine absorption without altering the relative oral bioavailability; this delay in mexiletine absorption was reversed by the combination of atropine and intravenous metoclopramide during pretreatment for anesthesia.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M3" type="Trigger" span="27 21;60 10" str="decreased the rate of | absorption "/>
<Mention id="M4" type="Trigger" span="128 5;60 10" str=" delay | absorption"/>
<Mention id="M5" type="Precipitant" span="49 10" str="mexiletine" code="1U511HHV4Z"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M3;M4" precipitant="M5" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3235" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Tachycardia (5.1)Glaucoma (5.2)Pyloric obstruction (5.3)Worsening urinary retention (5.4)Viscid bronchial plugs (5.5) When the recurrent use of atropine is essential in patients with coronary artery disease, the total dose should be restricted to 2 to 3 mg (maximum 0.03 to 0.04 mg/kg) to avoid the detrimental effects of atropine-induced tachycardia on myocardial oxygen demand.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3236" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Atropine may convert partial organic pyloric stenosis into complete obstruction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3237" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Atropine may lead to complete urinary retention in patients with prostatic hypertrophy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3238" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Atropine may cause inspissation of bronchial secretions and formation of viscid plugs in patients with chronic lung disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3239" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Atropine is an antimuscarinic agent since it antagonizes the muscarine-like actions of acetylcholine and other choline esters.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M11" type="SpecificInteraction" span="45 38" str="antagonizes the muscarine-like actions" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M7" type="Precipitant" span="87 13" str="acetylcholine" code="N9YNS0M02X"/>
<Mention id="M10" type="Precipitant" span="111 14" str="choline esters" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M11" precipitant="M7" effect="M11"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M11" precipitant="M10" effect="M11"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3240" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Atropine inhibits the muscarinic actions of acetylcholine on structures innervated by postganglionic cholinergic nerves, and on smooth muscles which respond to endogenous acetylcholine but are not so innervated.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M14" type="SpecificInteraction" span="9 31" str="inhibits the muscarinic actions" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M13" type="Precipitant" span="44 13" str="acetylcholine" code="N9YNS0M02X"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M14" precipitant="M13" effect="M14"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3241" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>As with other antimuscarinic agents, the major action of atropine is a competitive or surmountable antagonism which can be overcome by increasing the concentration of acetylcholine at receptor sites of the effector organ (e.g., by using anticholinesterase agents which inhibit the enzymatic destruction of acetylcholine).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M15" type="Trigger" span="99 10" str="antagonism"/>
<Mention id="M16" type="Precipitant" span="167 13" str="acetylcholine" code="N9YNS0M02X"/>
<Mention id="M17" type="SpecificInteraction" span="99 10;164 16" str="antagonism | of acetylcholine" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M15" precipitant="M16" effect="M17"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3242" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The receptors antagonized by atropine are the peripheral structures that are stimulated or inhibited by muscarine (i.e., exocrine glands and smooth and cardiac muscle).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M18" type="Trigger" span="14 11" str="antagonized"/>
<Mention id="M19" type="Precipitant" span="104 9" str="muscarine" code="7T101UWZ5W"/>
<Mention id="M20" type="SpecificInteraction" span="14 11;104 9" str="antagonized | muscarine" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M18" precipitant="M19" effect="M20"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3243" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Responses to postganglionic cholinergic nerve stimulation also may be inhibited by atropine but this occurs less readily than with responses to injected (exogenous) choline esters.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3244" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Atropine-induced parasympathetic inhibition may be preceded by a transient phase of stimulation, especially on the heart where small doses first slow the rate before characteristic tachycardia develops due to paralysis of vagal control.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3245" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Atropine exerts a more potent and prolonged effect on heart, intestine and bronchial muscle than scopolamine, but its action on the iris, ciliary body and certain secretory glands is weaker than that of scopolamine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3246" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Unlike the latter, atropine in clinical doses does not depress the central nervous system but may stimulate the medulla and higher cerebral centers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3247" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Although mild vagal excitation occurs, the increased respiratory rate and (sometimes) increased depth of respiration produced by atropine are more probably the result of bronchiolar dilatation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3248" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Accordingly, atropine is an unreliable respiratory stimulant and large or repeated doses may depress respiration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3249" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Adequate doses of atropine abolish various types of reflex vagal cardiac slowing or asystole.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3250" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The drug also prevents or abolishes bradycardia or asystole produced by injection of choline esters, anticholinesterase agents or other parasympathomimetic drugs, and cardiac arrest produced by stimulation of the vagus.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M27" type="Trigger" span="14 57" str="prevents or abolishes bradycardia or asystole produced by"/>
<Mention id="M22" type="Precipitant" span="101 25" str="anticholinesterase agents" code="N0000175723"/>
<Mention id="M23" type="SpecificInteraction" span="14 57;101 25" str="prevents or abolishes bradycardia or asystole produced by | anticholinesterase agents" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M25" type="Precipitant" span="85 14" str="choline esters" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M26" type="SpecificInteraction" span="14 85" str="prevents or abolishes bradycardia or asystole produced by injection of choline esters" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M28" type="Precipitant" span="136 25" str="parasympathomimetic drugs" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M29" type="SpecificInteraction" span="14 57;136 25" str="prevents or abolishes bradycardia or asystole produced by | parasympathomimetic drugs" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M27" precipitant="M22" effect="M23"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M27" precipitant="M25" effect="M26"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M27" precipitant="M28" effect="M29"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3251" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Atropine also may lessen the degree of partial heart block when vagal activity is an etiologic factor.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3252" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In some patients with complete heart block, the idioventricular rate may be accelerated by atropine; in others, the rate is stabilized.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3253" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Occasionally a large dose may cause atrioventricular (A-V) block and nodal rhythm.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3254" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Atropine Sulfate Injection, USP in clinical doses counteracts the peripheral dilatation and abrupt decrease in blood pressure produced by choline esters.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M30" type="Trigger" span="50 75" str="counteracts the peripheral dilatation and abrupt decrease in blood pressure"/>
<Mention id="M31" type="Precipitant" span="138 14" str="choline esters" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M32" type="SpecificInteraction" span="50 102" str="counteracts the peripheral dilatation and abrupt decrease in blood pressure produced by choline esters" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M30" precipitant="M31" effect="M32"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3255" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>However, when given by itself, atropine does not exert a striking or uniform effect on blood vessels or blood pressure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3256" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Systemic doses slightly raise systolic and lower diastolic pressures and can produce significant postural hypotension.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3257" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Such doses also slightly increase cardiac output and decrease central venous pressure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3258" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Occasionally, therapeutic doses dilate cutaneous blood vessels, particularly in the blush area (atropine flush), and may cause atropine fever due to suppression of sweat gland activity in infants and small children.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3259" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The effects of intravenous atropine on heart rate (maximum heart rate) and saliva flow (minimum flow) after intravenous administration (rapid, constant infusion over 3 min.) are delayed by 7 to 8 minutes after drug administration and both effects are non-linearly related to the amount of drug in the peripheral compartment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3260" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Changes in plasma atropine levels following intramuscular administration (0.5 to 4mgdoses) and heart rate are closely overlapped but the time course of the changes in atropine levels and behavioral impairment indicates that pharmacokinetics is not the primary rate-limiting mechanism for the central nervous system effect of atropine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3261" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Atropine disappears rapidly from the blood following injection and is distributed throughout the body.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3262" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Exercise, both prior to and immediately following intramuscular administration of atropine, significantly increases the absorption of atropine due to increased perfusion in the muscle and significantly decreases the clearance of atropine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3263" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacokinetics of atropine is nonlinear after intravenous administration of 0.5 to 4 mg. Atropine's plasma protein binding is about 44% and saturable in the 2-20 μg/mL concentration range.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3264" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Atropine readily crosses the placental barrier and enters the fetal circulation, but is not found in amniotic fluid.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3265" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Much of the drug is destroyed by enzymatic hydrolysis, particularly in the liver; from 13 to 50% is excreted unchanged in the urine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3266" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Traces are found in various secretions, including milk.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3267" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The major metabolites of atropine are noratropine, atropin-n-oxide, tropine, and tropic acid.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3268" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The metabolism of atropine is inhibited by organophosphate pesticides.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M33" type="Trigger" span="4 10;30 9" str="metabolism | inhibited"/>
<Mention id="M34" type="Precipitant" span="43 26" str="organophosphate pesticides" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M33" precipitant="M34" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3269" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Specific Populations The elimination half-life of atropine is more than doubled in children under two years and the elderly (&gt;65 years old) compared to other age groups.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3270" LabelDrug="Atropine Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There is no gender effect on the pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics (heart rate changes) of atropine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="mexiletine" precipitantCode="1U511HHV4Z" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="acetylcholine" precipitantCode="N9YNS0M02X" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="choline esters" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="muscarine" precipitantCode="7T101UWZ5W" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="anticholinesterase agents" precipitantCode="N0000175723" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="parasympathomimetic drugs" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="organophosphate pesticides" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54355"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>