<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Avalide" setid="0d91895e-c869-4b33-9b83-d55c1ad6317e">
<Text><Section name="BOXED WARNING SECTION" id="34066-1">
When pregnancy is detected, discontinue AVALIDE as soon as possible. [See  Warnings and Precautions (5.1) .]   Drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause injury and death to the developing fetus. [See Warnings and Precautions (5.1) .]        WARNING: FETAL TOXICITY  See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.    When pregnancy is detected, discontinue AVALIDE as soon as possible. (5.1)   Drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause injury and death to the developing fetus. (5.1)</Section>
<Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
AVALIDE is contraindicated in patients who are hypersensitive to any component of this product. Because of the hydrochlorothiazide component, this product is contraindicated in patients with anuria or hypersensitivity to other sulfonamide-derived drugs. Do not coadminister aliskiren with AVALIDE in patients with diabetes [see  Drug Interactions (7) ].        Hypersensitivity to any component of this product (4) Anuria (4) Hypersensitivity to sulfonamide-derived drugs (4) Do not coadminister aliskiren with AVALIDE in patients with diabetes (4)</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
General Considerations    Maximum effects within 2 to 4 weeks after dose change. (2.1) Renal impairment: Not recommended for patients with severe renal impairment (creatinine clearance &amp;lt;30 mL/min). (2.1, 5.8)   Hypertension   Initiate with 150/12.5 mg. Titrate to 300/12.5 mg then 300/25 mg if needed. (2.2) Replacement therapy: May be substituted for titrated components. (2.3)          The side effects of irbesartan are generally rare and apparently independent of dose; those of hydrochlorothiazide are a mixture of dose-dependent (primarily hypokalemia) and dose-independent phenomena (e.g., pancreatitis), the former much more common than the latter. [See  Adverse Reactions (6) .] Maximum antihypertensive effects are attained within 2 to 4 weeks after a change in dose. AVALIDE may be administered with or without food. AVALIDE may be administered with other antihypertensive agents.  Renal impairment. The usual regimens of therapy with AVALIDE may be followed as long as the patient's creatinine clearance is &amp;gt;30 mL/min. In patients with more severe renal impairment, loop diuretics are preferred to thiazides, so AVALIDE is not recommended.  Hepatic impairment. No dosage adjustment is necessary in patients with hepatic impairment.          In patients not controlled on monotherapy with irbesartan or hydrochlorothiazide, the recommended doses of AVALIDE, in order of increasing mean effect, are (irbesartan-hydrochlorothiazide) 150/12.5 mg, 300/12.5 mg, and 300/25 mg. The largest incremental effect will likely be in the transition from monotherapy to 150/12.5 mg. [See  Clinical Studies (14.2) .]          AVALIDE may be substituted for the titrated components.          The usual starting dose is AVALIDE 150/12.5 mg once daily. The dosage can be increased after 1 to 2 weeks of therapy to a maximum of 300/25 mg once daily as needed to control blood pressure [see  Clinical Studies (14.2) ]. AVALIDE is not recommended as initial therapy in patients with intravascular volume depletion [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2) ].</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
Irbesartan (7):   NSAIDs and selective COX-2 inhibitors: May lead to increased risk of renal impairment and loss of antihypertensive effect. Monitor renal function periodically. Dual blockade of the renin-angiotensin system: Increased risk of renal impairment, hypotension, and hyperkalemia.   Hydrochlorothiazide (7):   Antidiabetic drugs: Dosage adjustment of antidiabetic may be required Cholestyramine and colestipol: Reduced absorption of thiazides Lithium: Reduced renal clearance and high risk of lithium toxicity when used with diuretics. Should not be given with diuretics. NSAIDs: Can reduce diuretic, natriuretic, and antihypertensive effects of diuretics and increase risk for renal impairment. Carbamazepine: Increased risk of hyponatremia.           Irbesartan  No significant drug-drug interactions have been found in interaction studies with hydrochlorothiazide, digoxin, warfarin, and nifedipine. [See  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3) .]           Non-Steroidal Anti-Inflammatory Agents Including Selective Cyclooxygenase-2 Inhibitors (COX-2 Inhibitors)  In patients who are elderly, volume-depleted (including those on diuretic therapy), or with compromised renal function, coadministration of NSAIDs, including selective COX-2 inhibitors, with angiotensin II receptor antagonists, including irbesartan, may result in deterioration of renal function, including possible acute renal failure. These effects are usually reversible. Monitor renal function periodically in patients receiving irbesartan and NSAID therapy. The antihypertensive effect of angiotensin II receptor antagonists, including irbesartan, may be attenuated by NSAIDs including selective COX-2 inhibitors.           Dual Blockade of the Renin-Angiotensin System (RAS)  Dual blockade of the RAS with angiotensin-receptor blockers, ACE inhibitors, or aliskiren is associated with increased risks of hypotension, hyperkalemia, and changes in renal function (including acute renal failure) compared to monotherapy. Closely monitor blood pressure, renal function, and electrolytes in patients on AVALIDE and other agents that affect the RAS. Do not coadminister aliskiren with AVALIDE in patients with diabetes. Avoid use of aliskiren with AVALIDE in patients with renal impairment (GFR &amp;lt;60 mL/min).           Hydrochlorothiazide  When administered concurrently the following drugs may interact with thiazide diuretics:  Alcohol, Barbiturates, or Narcotics: potentiation of orthostatic hypotension may occur.  Antidiabetic Drugs (oral agents and insulin): dosage adjustment of the antidiabetic drug may be required.  Other Antihypertensive Drugs: additive effect or potentiation.  Cholestyramine and Colestipol Resins: absorption of hydrochlorothiazide is impaired in the presence of anionic exchange resins. Single doses of either cholestyramine or colestipol resins bind the hydrochlorothiazide and reduce its absorption from the gastrointestinal tract by up to 85% and 43%, respectively. AVALIDE should be taken at least one hour before or four hours after these medications.  Corticosteroids, ACTH: intensified electrolyte depletion, particularly hypokalemia.  Pressor Amines ( e.g., Norepinephrine): possible decreased response to pressor amines but not sufficient to preclude their use.  Skeletal Muscle Relaxants, Nondepolarizing ( e.g., Tubocurarine): possible increased responsiveness to the muscle relaxant.  Lithium: should not generally be given with diuretics. Diuretic agents reduce the renal clearance of lithium and add a high risk of lithium toxicity. Refer to the package insert for lithium preparations before use of such preparations with AVALIDE. [See  Warnings and Precautions (5.5) .]  Non-steroidal Anti-inflammatory Drugs: in some patients, the administration of a non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agent can reduce the diuretic, natriuretic, and antihypertensive effects of loop, potassium-sparing, and thiazide diuretics. Therefore, when AVALIDE (irbesartan-hydrochlorothiazide) Tablets and non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agents are used concomitantly, the patient should be observed closely to determine if the desired effect of the diuretic is obtained.  Carbamazepine: concomitant use of carbamazepine and hydrochlorothiazide has been associated with the risk of symptomatic hyponatremia. Electrolytes should be monitored during concomitant use.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
Hypotension: Correct volume-depletion prior to administration. (5.2) Impaired renal function. (5.8) Thiazide diuretics may cause an exacerbation or activation of systemic lupus erythematosus. (5.4) Acute myopia and secondary angle-closure glaucoma. (5.9)                Pregnancy Category D   Use of drugs that act on the renin-angiotensin system during the second and third trimesters of pregnancy reduces fetal renal function and increases fetal and neonatal morbidity and death. Resulting oligohydramnios can be associated with fetal lung hypoplasia and skeletal deformations. Potential neonatal adverse effects include skull hypoplasia, anuria, hypotension, renal failure, and death. When pregnancy is detected, discontinue AVALIDE as soon as possible [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.1) ].   Thiazides cross the placenta, and use of thiazides during pregnancy is associated with a risk of fetal or neonatal jaundice, thrombocytopenia, and possibly other adverse reactions that have occurred in adults.             Excessive reduction of blood pressure was rarely seen in patients with uncomplicated hypertension treated with irbesartan alone (&amp;lt;0.1%) or with irbesartan-hydrochlorothiazide (approximately 1%). Initiation of antihypertensive therapy may cause symptomatic hypotension in patients with intravascular volume- or sodium-depletion, e.g., in patients treated vigorously with diuretics or in patients on dialysis. Such volume depletion should be corrected prior to administration of antihypertensive therapy. If hypotension occurs, the patient should be placed in the supine position and, if necessary, given an intravenous infusion of normal saline. A transient hypotensive response is not a contraindication to further treatment, which usually can be continued without difficulty once the blood pressure has stabilized.                Hydrochlorothiazide  Hypersensitivity reactions to hydrochlorothiazide may occur in patients with or without a history of allergy or bronchial asthma, but are more likely in patients with such a history.                  Hydrochlorothiazide  Thiazide diuretics have been reported to cause exacerbation or activation of systemic lupus erythematosus.                  Hydrochlorothiazide  Lithium generally should not be given with thiazides. [See  Drug Interactions (7) .]                  Irbesartan-Hydrochlorothiazide  In double-blind clinical trials of various doses of irbesartan and hydrochlorothiazide, the incidence of hypertensive patients who developed hypokalemia (serum potassium &amp;lt;3.5 mEq/L) was 7.5% versus 6.0% for placebo; the incidence of hyperkalemia (serum potassium &amp;gt;5.7 mEq/L) was &amp;lt;1.0% versus 1.7% for placebo. No patient discontinued due to increases or decreases in serum potassium. On average, the combination of irbesartan and hydrochlorothiazide had no effect on serum potassium. Higher doses of irbesartan ameliorated the hypokalemic response to hydrochlorothiazide.  Based on experience with the use of other drugs that affect the renin-angiotensin system, concomitant use of potassium-sparing diuretics, potassium supplements, or salt substitutes containing potassium may lead to increases in serum potassium. Concurrent therapy with hydrochlorothiazide may reduce the frequency of this effect.            Hydrochlorothiazide   Hydrochlorothiazide can cause hypokalemia and hyponatremia. Hypomagnesemia can result in hypokalemia which appears difficult to treat despite potassium repletion. Drugs that inhibit the renin-angiotensin system can cause hyperkalemia. Monitor serum electrolytes periodically.  Hyperuricemia may occur or frank gout may be precipitated in certain patients receiving thiazide therapy.  Hydrochlorothiazide may alter glucose tolerance and raise serum levels of cholesterol and triglycerides.  The antihypertensive effects of the drug may be enhanced in the post-sympathectomy patient. Thiazides may decrease urinary calcium excretion. Thiazides may cause intermittent and slight elevation of serum calcium in the absence of known disorders of calcium metabolism. Marked hypercalcemia may be evidence of hidden hyperparathyroidism. Thiazides should be discontinued before carrying out tests for parathyroid function.                  Hydrochlorothiazide  Thiazides should be used with caution in patients with impaired hepatic function or progressive liver disease, since minor alterations of fluid and electrolyte balance may precipitate hepatic coma.            As a consequence of inhibiting the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system, changes in renal function may be anticipated in susceptible individuals [see  Drug Interactions (7) ]. In patients whose renal function may depend on the activity of the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system (e.g., patients with severe congestive heart failure), treatment with ACE inhibitors has been associated with oliguria and/or progressive azotemia and (rarely) with acute renal failure and/or death. Irbesartan would be expected to behave similarly. In studies of ACE inhibitors in patients with unilateral or bilateral renal artery stenosis, increases in serum creatinine or BUN have been reported. There has been no known use of irbesartan in patients with unilateral or bilateral renal artery stenosis, but a similar effect should be anticipated. Thiazides should be used with caution in severe renal disease. In patients with renal disease, thiazides may precipitate azotemia. Cumulative effects of the drug may develop in patients with impaired renal function.          Sulfonamide or sulfonamide derivative drugs, such as hydrochlorothiazide, can cause an idiosyncratic reaction, resulting in transient myopia and acute angle-closure glaucoma. Cases of acute angle-closure glaucoma have been reported with hydrochlorothiazide. Symptoms include acute onset of decreased visual acuity or ocular pain and typically occur within hours to weeks of drug initiation. Untreated acute angle-closure glaucoma can lead to permanent vision loss. The primary treatment is to discontinue drug intake as rapidly as possible. Prompt medical or surgical treatments may need to be considered if the intraocular pressure remains uncontrolled. Risk factors for developing acute angle-closure glaucoma may include a history of sulfonamide or penicillin allergy.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Irbesartan  Angiotensin II is a potent vasoconstrictor formed from angiotensin I in a reaction catalyzed by angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE, kininase II). Angiotensin II is the principal pressor agent of the RAS and also stimulates aldosterone synthesis and secretion by adrenal cortex, cardiac contraction, renal resorption of sodium, activity of the sympathetic nervous system, and smooth muscle cell growth. Irbesartan blocks the vasoconstrictor and aldosterone-secreting effects of angiotensin II by selectively binding to the AT1 angiotensin II receptor. There is also an AT2 receptor in many tissues, but it is not involved in cardiovascular homeostasis. Irbesartan is a specific competitive antagonist of AT1 receptors with a much greater affinity (more than 8500-fold) for the AT1 receptor than for the AT2 receptor, and no agonist activity. Blockade of the AT1 receptor removes the negative feedback of angiotensin II on renin secretion, but the resulting increased plasma renin activity and circulating angiotensin II do not overcome the effects of irbesartan on blood pressure. Irbesartan does not inhibit ACE or renin or affect other hormone receptors or ion channels known to be involved in the cardiovascular regulation of blood pressure and sodium homeostasis. Because irbesartan does not inhibit ACE, it does not affect the response to bradykinin; whether this has clinical relevance is not known.           Hydrochlorothiazide  Hydrochlorothiazide is a thiazide diuretic. Thiazides affect the renal tubular mechanisms of electrolyte reabsorption, directly increasing excretion of sodium and chloride in approximately equivalent amounts. Indirectly, the diuretic action of hydrochlorothiazide reduces plasma volume, with consequent increases in plasma renin activity, increases in aldosterone secretion, increases in urinary potassium loss, and decreases in serum potassium. The renin-aldosterone link is mediated by angiotensin II, so coadministration of an angiotensin II receptor antagonist tends to reverse the potassium loss associated with these diuretics. The mechanism of the antihypertensive effect of thiazides is not fully understood.                  Irbesartan  In healthy subjects, single oral irbesartan doses of up to 300 mg produced dose-dependent inhibition of the pressor effect of angiotensin II infusions. Inhibition was complete (100%) 4 hours following oral doses of 150 mg or 300 mg and partial inhibition was sustained for 24 hours (60% and 40% at 300 mg and 150 mg, respectively). In hypertensive patients, angiotensin II receptor inhibition following chronic administration of irbesartan causes a 1.5- to 2-fold rise in angiotensin II plasma concentration and a 2- to 3-fold increase in plasma renin levels. Aldosterone plasma concentrations generally decline following irbesartan administration, but serum potassium levels are not significantly affected at recommended doses. In hypertensive patients, chronic oral doses of irbesartan (up to 300 mg) had no effect on glomerular filtration rate, renal plasma flow or filtration fraction. In multiple dose studies in hypertensive patients, there were no clinically important effects on fasting triglycerides, total cholesterol, HDL-cholesterol, or fasting glucose concentrations. There was no effect on serum uric acid during chronic oral administration and no uricosuric effect.           Hydrochlorothiazide  After oral administration of hydrochlorothiazide, diuresis begins within 2 hours, peaks in about 4 hours and lasts about 6 to 12 hours.                  Irbesartan  Irbesartan is an orally active agent that does not require biotransformation into an active form. The oral absorption of irbesartan is rapid and complete with an average absolute bioavailability of 60% to 80%. Following oral administration of irbesartan, peak plasma concentrations of irbesartan are attained at 1.5 to 2 hours after dosing. Food does not affect the bioavailability of irbesartan. Irbesartan exhibits linear pharmacokinetics over the therapeutic dose range. The terminal elimination half-life of irbesartan averaged 11 to 15 hours. Steady-state concentrations are achieved within 3 days. Limited accumulation of irbesartan (&amp;lt;20%) is observed in plasma upon repeated once-daily dosing.           Hydrochlorothiazide  When plasma levels have been followed for at least 24 hours, the plasma half-life has been observed to vary between 5.6 and 14.8 hours.           Metabolism and Elimination          Irbesartan  Irbesartan is metabolized via glucuronide conjugation and oxidation. Following oral or intravenous administration of 14C-labeled irbesartan, more than 80% of the circulating plasma radioactivity is attributable to unchanged irbesartan. The primary circulating metabolite is the inactive irbesartan glucuronide conjugate (approximately 6%). The remaining oxidative metabolites do not add appreciably to irbesartan's pharmacologic activity. Irbesartan and its metabolites are excreted by both biliary and renal routes. Following either oral or intravenous administration of 14C-labeled irbesartan, about 20% of radioactivity is recovered in the urine and the remainder in the feces, as irbesartan or irbesartan glucuronide.  In vitro studies of irbesartan oxidation by cytochrome P450 isoenzymes indicated irbesartan was oxidized primarily by 2C9; metabolism by 3A4 was negligible. Irbesartan was neither metabolized by, nor did it substantially induce or inhibit, isoenzymes commonly associated with drug metabolism (1A1, 1A2, 2A6, 2B6, 2D6, 2E1). There was no induction or inhibition of 3A4.           Hydrochlorothiazide  Hydrochlorothiazide is not metabolized but is eliminated rapidly by the kidney. At least 61% of the oral dose is eliminated unchanged within 24 hours.             Distribution          Irbesartan  Irbesartan is 90% bound to serum proteins (primarily albumin and α1-acid glycoprotein) with negligible binding to cellular components of blood. The average volume of distribution is 53 to 93 liters. Total plasma and renal clearances are in the range of 157 to 176 mL/min and 3.0 to 3.5 mL/min, respectively. With repetitive dosing, irbesartan accumulates to no clinically relevant extent. Studies in animals indicate that radiolabeled irbesartan weakly crosses the blood-brain barrier and placenta. Irbesartan is excreted in the milk of lactating rats.           Hydrochlorothiazide  Hydrochlorothiazide crosses the placental but not the blood-brain barrier and is excreted in breast milk.             Pediatric  Irbesartan-hydrochlorothiazide pharmacokinetics have not been investigated in patients &amp;lt;18 years of age.           Gender  No gender-related differences in pharmacokinetics were observed in healthy elderly (age 65 to 80 years) or in healthy young (age 18 to 40 years) subjects. In studies of hypertensive patients, there was no gender difference in half-life or accumulation, but somewhat higher plasma concentrations of irbesartan were observed in females (11% to 44%). No gender-related dosage adjustment is necessary.           Geriatric  In elderly subjects (age 65 to 80 years), irbesartan elimination half-life was not significantly altered, but AUC and Cmax values were about 20% to 50% greater than those of young subjects (age 18 to 40 years). No dosage adjustment is necessary in the elderly.           Race  In healthy black subjects, irbesartan AUC values were approximately 25% greater than whites; there were no differences in Cmax values.           Renal Insufficiency  The pharmacokinetics of irbesartan were not altered in patients with renal impairment or in patients on hemodialysis. Irbesartan is not removed by hemodialysis. No dosage adjustment is necessary in patients with mild to severe renal impairment unless a patient with renal impairment is also volume depleted. [See  Warnings and Precautions (5.2) .]           Hepatic Insufficiency  The pharmacokinetics of irbesartan following repeated oral administration were not significantly affected in patients with mild to moderate cirrhosis of the liver. No dosage adjustment is necessary in patients with hepatic insufficiency.           Drug-Drug Interactions  No significant drug-drug pharmacokinetic (or pharmacodynamic) interactions have been found in interaction studies with hydrochlorothiazide, digoxin, warfarin, and nifedipine.  In vitro studies show significant inhibition of the formation of oxidized irbesartan metabolites with the known cytochrome CYP 2C9 substrates/inhibitors sulphenazole, tolbutamide, and nifedipine. However, in clinical studies the consequences of concomitant irbesartan on the pharmacodynamics of warfarin were negligible. Concomitant nifedipine or hydrochlorothiazide had no effect on irbesartan pharmacokinetics. Based on in vitro data, no interaction would be expected with drugs whose metabolism is dependent upon cytochrome P450 isoenzymes 1A1, 1A2, 2A6, 2B6, 2D6, 2E1, or 3A4. In separate studies of patients receiving maintenance doses of warfarin, hydrochlorothiazide, or digoxin, irbesartan administration for 7 days had no effect on the pharmacodynamics of warfarin (prothrombin time) or the pharmacokinetics of digoxin. The pharmacokinetics of irbesartan were not affected by coadministration of nifedipine or hydrochlorothiazide.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="5985" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>When pregnancy is detected, discontinue AVALIDE as soon as possible.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5986" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause injury and death to the developing fetus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5987" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>WARNING: FETAL TOXICITY See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5988" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>AVALIDE is contraindicated in patients who are hypersensitive to any component of this product.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5989" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Because of the hydrochlorothiazide component, this product is contraindicated in patients with anuria or hypersensitivity to other sulfonamide-derived drugs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5990" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Do not coadminister aliskiren with AVALIDE in patients with diabetes.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M1" type="Trigger" span="0 19" str="Do not coadminister"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="20 9" str="aliskiren" code="502FWN4Q32"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M1" precipitant="M2"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5991" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Hypersensitivity to any component of this product.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5992" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Hypersensitivity to sulfonamide-derived drugs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5993" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>General Considerations Maximum effects within 2 to 4 weeks after dose change.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5994" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Renal impairment: Not recommended for patients with severe renal impairment (creatinine clearance &lt;30 mL/min).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5995" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Hypertension Initiate with 150/12.5 mg. Titrate to 300/12.5 mg then 300/25 mg if needed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5996" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Replacement therapy: May be substituted for titrated components.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5997" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The side effects of irbesartan are generally rare and apparently independent of dose; those of hydrochlorothiazide are a mixture of dose-dependent (primarily hypokalemia) and dose-independent phenomena (e.g., pancreatitis), the former much more common than the latter.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5998" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Maximum antihypertensive effects are attained within 2 to 4 weeks after a change in dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5999" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>AVALIDE may be administered with or without food.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6000" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>AVALIDE may be administered with other antihypertensive agents.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6001" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Renal Impairment The usual regimens of therapy with AVALIDE may be followed as long as the patient's creatinine clearance is &gt;30 mL/min.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6002" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In patients with more severe renal impairment, loop diuretics are preferred to thiazides, so AVALIDE is not recommended.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6003" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Hepatic Impairment No dosage adjustment is necessary in patients with hepatic impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6004" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In patients not controlled on monotherapy with irbesartan or hydrochlorothiazide, the recommended doses of AVALIDE, in order of increasing mean effect, are (irbesartan-hydrochlorothiazide) 150/12.5 mg, 300/12.5 mg, and 300/25 mg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6005" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The largest incremental effect will likely be in the transition from monotherapy to 150/12.5 mg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6006" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>AVALIDE may be substituted for the titrated components.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6007" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The usual starting dose is AVALIDE 150/12.5 mg once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6008" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The dosage can be increased after 1 to 2 weeks of therapy to a maximum of 300/25 mg once daily as needed to control blood pressure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6009" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>AVALIDE is not recommended as initial therapy in patients with intravascular volume depletion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6010" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>NSAIDs and selective COX-2 inhibitors: Can reduce diuretic, natriuretic of diuretic, may lead to increased risk of renal impairment and reduced antihypertensive effect.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M16" type="Trigger" span="89 7" str="lead to "/>
<Mention id="M17" type="Trigger" span="97 14" str=" increased risk"/>
<Mention id="M5" type="Precipitant" span="0 6" str="NSAIDs" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M19" type="SpecificInteraction" span="115 16" str="renal impairment" code="236423003: Renal impairment (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M26" type="Trigger" span="43 6;161 6" str="reduce | effect"/>
<Mention id="M14" type="Precipitant" span="0 37" str="NSAIDs and selective COX-2 inhibitors" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M22" type="SpecificInteraction" span="43 6;60 11;161 6" str="reduce | natriuretic | effect" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M25" type="SpecificInteraction" span="136 31" str="reduced antihypertensive effect" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M28" type="SpecificInteraction" span="43 15;161 6" str="reduce diuretic | effect" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M27" type="Precipitant" span="11 26" str="selective COX-2 inhibitors" code="N0000008288"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M16;M17" precipitant="M5" effect="M19"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M26" precipitant="M14" effect="M22"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M26" precipitant="M14" effect="M25"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M26" precipitant="M14" effect="M28"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M16;M17" precipitant="M27" effect="M19"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M26" precipitant="M27" effect="M22"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M26" precipitant="M27" effect="M25"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M26" precipitant="M27" effect="M28"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6011" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Dual blockade of the renin-angiotensin system: Increased risk of renal impairment, hypotension, and hyperkalemia.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M35" type="Trigger" span="47 14" str="Increased risk"/>
<Mention id="M36" type="Precipitant" span="0 45" str="Dual blockade of the renin-angiotensin system" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M31" type="SpecificInteraction" span="100 12" str="hyperkalemia" code="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M34" type="SpecificInteraction" span="83 11" str="hypotension" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M37" type="SpecificInteraction" span="65 16" str="renal impairment" code="236423003: Renal impairment (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M36" effect="M31"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M36" effect="M34"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M36" effect="M37"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6012" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Antidiabetic drugs: Dosage adjustment of antidiabetic may be required.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M38" type="Trigger" span="20 17" str="Dosage adjustment"/>
<Mention id="M39" type="Precipitant" span="0 18" str="Antidiabetic drugs" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M38" precipitant="M39"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6013" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Cholestyramine and colestipol: Reduced absorption of thiazides.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M42" type="Trigger" span="31 18" str="Reduced absorption"/>
<Mention id="M41" type="Precipitant" span="0 14" str="Cholestyramine" code="4B33BGI082"/>
<Mention id="M43" type="Precipitant" span="19 10" str="colestipol" code="K50N755924"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M42" precipitant="M41" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M42" precipitant="M43" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6014" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Lithium: Increases in serum lithium concentrations and lithium toxicity.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M44" type="Trigger" span="9 18;36 14" str="Increases in serum | concentrations "/>
<Mention id="M45" type="Trigger" span="63 8" str=" toxicity"/>
<Mention id="M46" type="Precipitant" span="28 7" str="lithium" code="9FN79X2M3F"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M44;M45" precipitant="M46" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6015" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Carbamazepine: Increased risk of hyponatremia.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M47" type="Trigger" span="15 14" str="Increased risk"/>
<Mention id="M48" type="Precipitant" span="0 13" str="Carbamazepine" code="33CM23913M"/>
<Mention id="M49" type="SpecificInteraction" span="33 12" str="hyponatremia" code="89627008: Hyponatremia (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M47" precipitant="M48" effect="M49"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6016" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Irbesartan In patients who are elderly, volume depleted (including those on diuretic therapy), or with compromised renal function, coadministration of NSAIDs, including selective COX-2 inhibitors, with angiotensin II receptor antagonists, including irbesartan, may result in deterioration of renal function, including possible acute renal failure.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M65" type="Trigger" span="265 9" str="result in"/>
<Mention id="M54" type="Precipitant" span="76 16" str="diuretic therapy" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M64" type="SpecificInteraction" span="327 19" str="acute renal failure" code="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M67" type="SpecificInteraction" span="275 31" str="deterioration of renal function" code="236423003: Renal impairment (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M60" type="Precipitant" span="151 6" str="NSAIDs" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M66" type="Precipitant" span="169 26" str="selective COX-2 inhibitors" code="N0000008288"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M65" precipitant="M54" effect="M64"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M65" precipitant="M54" effect="M67"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M65" precipitant="M60" effect="M67"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M65" precipitant="M60" effect="M64"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M65" precipitant="M66" effect="M64"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M65" precipitant="M66" effect="M67"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6017" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Therefore, monitor renal function and blood pressure periodically in patients receiving irbesartan and NSAID therapy.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M71" type="Trigger" span="11 7" str="monitor"/>
<Mention id="M72" type="Precipitant" span="103 5" str="NSAID" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M70" type="SpecificInteraction" span="38 14" str="blood pressure" code="38936003: Abnormal blood pressure (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M73" type="SpecificInteraction" span="19 14" str="renal function" code="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M71" precipitant="M72" effect="M70"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M71" precipitant="M72" effect="M73"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6018" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Hydrochlorothiazide Administration of a non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agent, including a selective COX-2 inhibitor can reduce the diuretic, natriuretic, and antihypertensive effects of loop, potassium-sparing, and thiazide diuretics.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M89" type="Trigger" span="121 6;176 7" str="reduce | effects"/>
<Mention id="M81" type="Precipitant" span="40 37" str="non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agent" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M88" type="SpecificInteraction" span="121 19;176 7" str="reduce the diuretic | effects" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M91" type="SpecificInteraction" span="121 6;142 11;176 7" str="reduce | natriuretic | effects" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M85" type="SpecificInteraction" span="121 6;159 24" str="reduce | antihypertensive effects" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M90" type="Precipitant" span="91 25" str="selective COX-2 inhibitor" code="N0000008288"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M89" precipitant="M81" effect="M88"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M89" precipitant="M81" effect="M91"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M89" precipitant="M81" effect="M85"/>
<Interaction id="I29" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M89" precipitant="M90" effect="M85"/>
<Interaction id="I30" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M89" precipitant="M90" effect="M88"/>
<Interaction id="I31" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M89" precipitant="M90" effect="M91"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6019" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Therefore, when AVALIDE (irbesartan-hydrochlorothiazide) tablets and non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agents are used concomitantly, the patient should be observed closely to determine if the desired effect of the diuretic is obtained.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M92" type="Trigger" span="144 26" str="should be observed closely"/>
<Mention id="M93" type="Precipitant" span="69 38" str="non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agents" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M94" type="SpecificInteraction" span="199 22" str="effect of the diuretic" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I32" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M92" precipitant="M93" effect="M94"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6020" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Dual blockade of the RAS with angiotensin-receptor blockers, ACE inhibitors, or aliskiren is associated with increased risks of hypotension, hyperkalemia, and changes in renal function (including acute renal failure) compared to monotherapy.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M155" type="Trigger" span="93 15" str="associated with "/>
<Mention id="M156" type="Trigger" span="109 15" str=" increased risks"/>
<Mention id="M109" type="Precipitant" span="61 14" str="ACE inhibitors" code="N0000175562"/>
<Mention id="M154" type="SpecificInteraction" span="128 11" str="hypotension" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M146" type="SpecificInteraction" span="196 19" str="acute renal failure" code="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M158" type="SpecificInteraction" span="159 25" str="changes in renal function" code="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M150" type="SpecificInteraction" span="141 12" str="hyperkalemia" code="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M125" type="Precipitant" span="80 9" str="aliskiren" code="502FWN4Q32"/>
<Mention id="M141" type="Precipitant" span="30 29" str="angiotensin-receptor blockers" code="N0000175561"/>
<Mention id="M157" type="Precipitant" span="0 24" str="Dual blockade of the RAS" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I33" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M155;M156" precipitant="M109" effect="M154"/>
<Interaction id="I34" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M155;M156" precipitant="M109" effect="M146"/>
<Interaction id="I35" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M155;M156" precipitant="M109" effect="M158"/>
<Interaction id="I36" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M155;M156" precipitant="M109" effect="M150"/>
<Interaction id="I37" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M155;M156" precipitant="M125" effect="M150"/>
<Interaction id="I38" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M155;M156" precipitant="M125" effect="M158"/>
<Interaction id="I39" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M155;M156" precipitant="M125" effect="M154"/>
<Interaction id="I40" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M155;M156" precipitant="M125" effect="M146"/>
<Interaction id="I41" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M155;M156" precipitant="M141" effect="M154"/>
<Interaction id="I42" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M155;M156" precipitant="M141" effect="M158"/>
<Interaction id="I43" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M155;M156" precipitant="M141" effect="M146"/>
<Interaction id="I44" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M155;M156" precipitant="M141" effect="M150"/>
<Interaction id="I45" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M155;M156" precipitant="M157" effect="M146"/>
<Interaction id="I46" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M155;M156" precipitant="M157" effect="M150"/>
<Interaction id="I47" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M155;M156" precipitant="M157" effect="M154"/>
<Interaction id="I48" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M155;M156" precipitant="M157" effect="M158"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6021" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Closely monitor blood pressure, renal function, and electrolytes in patients on AVALIDE and other agents that affect the RAS.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M165" type="Trigger" span="0 15" str="Closely monitor"/>
<Mention id="M166" type="Precipitant" span="98 26" str="agents that affect the RAS" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M161" type="SpecificInteraction" span="52 12" str="electrolytes" code="166686006: Electrolytes abnormal (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M164" type="SpecificInteraction" span="32 14" str="renal function" code="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M167" type="SpecificInteraction" span="16 14" str="blood pressure" code="38936003: Abnormal blood pressure (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I49" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M165" precipitant="M166" effect="M161"/>
<Interaction id="I50" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M165" precipitant="M166" effect="M164"/>
<Interaction id="I51" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M165" precipitant="M166" effect="M167"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6022" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>In most patients no benefit has been associated with using two RAS inhibitors concomitantly.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6023" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>In general, avoid combined use of RAS inhibitors.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M168" type="Trigger" span="12 5" str="avoid"/>
<Mention id="M169" type="Precipitant" span="34 14" str="RAS inhibitors" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I52" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M168" precipitant="M169"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6024" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Avoid use of aliskiren with AVALIDE in patients with renal impairment (GFR &lt;60 mL/min).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M170" type="Trigger" span="0 5" str="Avoid"/>
<Mention id="M171" type="Precipitant" span="13 9" str="aliskiren" code="502FWN4Q32"/>
<Interaction id="I53" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M170" precipitant="M171"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6025" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Coadministration of AVALIDE with other drugs that raise serum potassium levels may result in hyperkalemia, sometimes severe.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M172" type="Trigger" span="83 9" str="result in"/>
<Mention id="M173" type="Precipitant" span="39 39" str="drugs that raise serum potassium levels" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M174" type="SpecificInteraction" span="93 12" str="hyperkalemia" code="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I54" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M172" precipitant="M173" effect="M174"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6026" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor serum potassium in such patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6027" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Dosage adjustment of the antidiabetic drug may be required when coadministered with hydrochlorothiazide.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M175" type="Trigger" span="0 17" str="Dosage adjustment"/>
<Mention id="M176" type="Precipitant" span="25 17" str="antidiabetic drug" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I55" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M175" precipitant="M176"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6028" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Absorption of hydrochlorothiazide is impaired in the presence of anionic exchange resins.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M177" type="Trigger" span="0 10;37 8" str="Absorption | impaired"/>
<Mention id="M178" type="Precipitant" span="65 23" str="anionic exchange resins" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I56" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M177" precipitant="M178" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6029" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Stagger the dosage of hydrochlorothiazide and the resin such that AVALIDE is administered at least 4 hours before or 4 to 6 hours after the administration of the resin.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M179" type="Trigger" span="0 18" str="Stagger the dosage"/>
<Mention id="M180" type="Precipitant" span="50 5" str="resin" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I57" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M179" precipitant="M180"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6030" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Increases in serum lithium concentrations and lithium toxicity have been reported with concomitant use of irbesartan or thiazide diuretics.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M181" type="Trigger" span="0 18;27 14" str="Increases in serum | concentrations "/>
<Mention id="M182" type="Trigger" span="54 8" str=" toxicity"/>
<Mention id="M183" type="Precipitant" span="19 7" str="lithium" code="9FN79X2M3F"/>
<Interaction id="I58" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M181;M182" precipitant="M183" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6031" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor lithium levels in patients receiving Avalide and lithium.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M184" type="Trigger" span="0 7" str="Monitor"/>
<Mention id="M185" type="Precipitant" span="8 7" str="lithium" code="9FN79X2M3F"/>
<Interaction id="I59" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M184" precipitant="M185"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6032" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant use of carbamazepine and hydrochlorothiazide has been associated with the risk of symptomatic hyponatremia.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M186" type="Trigger" span="66 15" str="associated with "/>
<Mention id="M187" type="Trigger" span="86 7" str=" risk of"/>
<Mention id="M188" type="Precipitant" span="19 13" str="carbamazepine" code="33CM23913M"/>
<Mention id="M189" type="SpecificInteraction" span="94 24" str="symptomatic hyponatremia" code="89627008: Hyponatremia (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I60" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M186;M187" precipitant="M188" effect="M189"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6033" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor electrolytes during concomitant use.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6034" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hypotension: Correct volume depletion prior to administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6035" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Thiazide diuretics may cause an exacerbation or activation of systemic lupus erythematosus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6036" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Secondary acute angle-closure glaucoma and/or acute myopia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6037" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Pregnancy Category D Use of drugs that act on the renin-angiotensin system during the second and third trimesters of pregnancy reduces fetal renal function and increases fetal and neonatal morbidity and death.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6038" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Resulting oligohydramnios can be associated with fetal lung hypoplasia and skeletal deformations.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6039" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Potential neonatal adverse effects include skull hypoplasia, anuria, hypotension, renal failure, and death.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6040" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Thiazides cross the placenta, and use of thiazides during pregnancy is associated with a risk of fetal or neonatal jaundice, thrombocytopenia, and possibly other adverse reactions that have occurred in adults.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6041" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Excessive reduction of blood pressure was rarely seen in patients with uncomplicated hypertension treated with irbesartan alone (&lt;0.1%) or with irbesartan-hydrochlorothiazide (approximately 1%).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6042" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Initiation of antihypertensive therapy may cause symptomatic hypotension in patients with intravascular volume or sodium-depletion, e.g., in patients treated vigorously with diuretics or in patients on dialysis.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M190" type="Trigger" span="43 5" str="cause"/>
<Mention id="M191" type="Precipitant" span="174 9" str="diuretics" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M192" type="SpecificInteraction" span="49 23" str="symptomatic hypotension" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I61" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M190" precipitant="M191" effect="M192"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6043" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Such volume depletion should be corrected prior to administration of antihypertensive therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6044" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If hypotension occurs, the patient should be placed in the supine position and, if necessary, given an intravenous infusion of normal saline.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6045" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>A transient hypotensive response is not a contraindication to further treatment, which usually can be continued without difficulty once the blood pressure has stabilized.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6046" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hydrochlorothiazide Hypersensitivity reactions to hydrochlorothiazide may occur in patients with or without a history of allergy or bronchial asthma, but are more likely in patients with such a history.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6047" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hydrochlorothiazide Thiazide diuretics have been reported to cause exacerbation or activation of systemic lupus erythematosus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6048" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Irbesartan-Hydrochlorothiazide In double-blind clinical trials of various doses of irbesartan and hydrochlorothiazide, the incidence of hypertensive patients who developed hypokalemia (serum potassium &lt;3.5 mEq/L) was 7.5% versus 6.0% for placebo; the incidence of hyperkalemia (serum potassium &gt;5.7 mEq/L) was &lt;1.0% versus 1.7% for placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6049" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>No patient discontinued due to increases or decreases in serum potassium.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6050" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>On average, the combination of irbesartan and hydrochlorothiazide had no effect on serum potassium.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6051" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Higher doses of irbesartan ameliorated the hypokalemic response to hydrochlorothiazide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6052" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Coadministration of AVALIDE with potassium sparing diuretics, potassium supplements, potassium-containing salt substitutes or other drugs that raise serum potassium levels may result in hyperkalemia, sometimes severe.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M202" type="Trigger" span="176 9" str="result in"/>
<Mention id="M194" type="Precipitant" span="132 39" str="drugs that raise serum potassium levels" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M204" type="SpecificInteraction" span="186 12" str="hyperkalemia" code="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M197" type="Precipitant" span="33 27" str="potassium sparing diuretics" code="N0000175418"/>
<Mention id="M200" type="Precipitant" span="62 21" str="potassium supplements" code="RWP5GA015D"/>
<Mention id="M203" type="Precipitant" span="85 37" str="potassium-containing salt substitutes" code="N0000175600"/>
<Interaction id="I62" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M202" precipitant="M194" effect="M204"/>
<Interaction id="I63" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M202" precipitant="M197" effect="M204"/>
<Interaction id="I64" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M202" precipitant="M200" effect="M204"/>
<Interaction id="I65" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M202" precipitant="M203" effect="M204"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6053" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hydrochlorothiazide Hydrochlorothiazide can cause hypokalemia and hyponatremia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6054" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hypomagnesemia can result in hypokalemia which appears difficult to treat despite potassium repletion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6055" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Drugs that inhibit the renin-angiotensin system can cause hyperkalemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6056" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hyperuricemia may occur or frank gout may be precipitated in certain patients receiving thiazide therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6057" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hydrochlorothiazide may alter glucose tolerance and raise serum levels of cholesterol and triglycerides.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6058" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The antihypertensive effects of the drug may be enhanced in the post-sympathectomy patient.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6059" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Thiazides may decrease urinary calcium excretion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6060" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Thiazides may cause intermittent and slight elevation of serum calcium in the absence of known disorders of calcium metabolism.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6061" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Marked hypercalcemia may be evidence of hidden hyperparathyroidism.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6062" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Thiazides should be discontinued before carrying out tests for parathyroid function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6063" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hydrochlorothiazide Thiazides should be used with caution in patients with impaired hepatic function or progressive liver disease, since minor alterations of fluid and electrolyte balance may precipitate hepatic coma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6064" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>As a consequence of inhibiting the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system, changes in renal function may be anticipated in susceptible individuals.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6065" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In patients whose renal function may depend on the activity of the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system (e.g., patients with severe congestive heart failure), treatment with ACE inhibitors has been associated with oliguria and/or progressive azotemia and (rarely) with acute renal failure and/or death.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M214" type="Trigger" span="198 15" str="associated with"/>
<Mention id="M215" type="Precipitant" span="174 14" str="ACE inhibitors" code="N0000175562"/>
<Mention id="M207" type="SpecificInteraction" span="269 19" str="acute renal failure" code="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M210" type="SpecificInteraction" span="230 20" str="progressive azotemia" code="445009001: Azotemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M213" type="SpecificInteraction" span="296 5" str="death" code="419620001: Death (event)"/>
<Mention id="M216" type="SpecificInteraction" span="214 8" str="oliguria" code="83128009: Oliguria (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I66" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M214" precipitant="M215" effect="M207"/>
<Interaction id="I67" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M214" precipitant="M215" effect="M210"/>
<Interaction id="I68" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M214" precipitant="M215" effect="M213"/>
<Interaction id="I69" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M214" precipitant="M215" effect="M216"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6066" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Irbesartan would be expected to behave similarly.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6067" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In studies of ACE inhibitors in patients with unilateral or bilateral renal artery stenosis, increases in serum creatinine or BUN have been reported.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6068" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There has been no known use of irbesartan in patients with unilateral or bilateral renal artery stenosis, but a similar effect should be anticipated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6069" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Thiazides should be used with caution in severe renal disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6070" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In patients with renal disease, thiazides may precipitate azotemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6071" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Cumulative effects of the drug may develop in patients with impaired renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6072" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hydrochlorothiazide Sulfonamide or sulfonamide derivative drugs, such as hydrochlorothiazide, can cause an idiosyncratic reaction, resulting in transient myopia and/or acute angle-closure glaucoma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6073" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Cases of acute angle-closure glaucoma have been reported with hydrochlorothiazide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6074" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Symptoms include acute onset of decreased visual acuity or ocular pain and typically occur within hours to weeks of drug initiation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6075" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Untreated acute angle-closure glaucoma can lead to permanent vision loss.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6076" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The primary treatment is to discontinue drug intake as rapidly as possible.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6077" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Prompt medical or surgical treatments may need to be considered if the intraocular pressure remains uncontrolled.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6078" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Risk factors for developing acute angle-closure glaucoma may include a history of sulfonamide or penicillin allergy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6079" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Irbesartan Angiotensin II is a potent vasoconstrictor formed from angiotensin I in a reaction catalyzed by angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE, kininase II).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6080" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Angiotensin II is the principal pressor agent of the RAS and also stimulates aldosterone synthesis and secretion by adrenal cortex, cardiac contraction, renal resorption of sodium, activity of the sympathetic nervous system, and smooth muscle cell growth.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6081" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Irbesartan blocks the vasoconstrictor and aldosterone-secreting effects of angiotensin II by selectively binding to the AT1 angiotensin II receptor.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6082" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There is also an AT2 receptor in many tissues, but it is not involved in cardiovascular homeostasis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6083" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Irbesartan is a specific competitive antagonist of AT1 receptors with a much greater affinity (more than 8500-fold) for the AT1 receptor than for the AT2 receptor, and no agonist activity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6084" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Blockade of the AT1 receptor removes the negative feedback of angiotensin II on renin secretion, but the resulting increased plasma renin activity and circulating angiotensin II do not overcome the effects of irbesartan on blood pressure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6085" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Irbesartan does not inhibit ACE or renin or affect other hormone receptors or ion channels known to be involved in the cardiovascular regulation of blood pressure and sodium homeostasis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6086" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Because irbesartan does not inhibit ACE, it does not affect the response to bradykinin; whether this has clinical relevance is not known.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6087" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Hydrochlorothiazide Hydrochlorothiazide is a thiazide diuretic.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6088" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Thiazides affect the renal tubular mechanisms of electrolyte reabsorption, directly increasing excretion of sodium and chloride in approximately equivalent amounts.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6089" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Indirectly, the diuretic action of hydrochlorothiazide reduces plasma volume, with consequent increases in plasma renin activity, increases in aldosterone secretion, increases in urinary potassium loss, and decreases in serum potassium.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6090" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The renin-aldosterone link is mediated by angiotensin II, so coadministration of an angiotensin II receptor antagonist tends to reverse the potassium loss associated with these diuretics.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6091" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mechanism of the antihypertensive effect of thiazides is not fully understood.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6092" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Irbesartan In healthy subjects, single oral irbesartan doses of up to 300 mg produced dose-dependent inhibition of the pressor effect of angiotensin II infusions.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M217" type="Trigger" span="101 10" str="inhibition"/>
<Mention id="M218" type="Precipitant" span="137 24" str="angiotensin II infusions" code="M089EFU921"/>
<Mention id="M219" type="SpecificInteraction" span="101 32" str="inhibition of the pressor effect" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I70" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M217" precipitant="M218" effect="M219"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6093" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Inhibition was complete (100%) 4 hours following oral doses of 150 mg or 300 mg and partial inhibition was sustained for 24 hours (60% and 40% at 300 mg and 150 mg, respectively).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6094" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In hypertensive patients, angiotensin II receptor inhibition following chronic administration of irbesartan causes a 1.5-fold to 2-fold rise in angiotensin II plasma concentration and a 2-fold to 3-fold increase in plasma renin levels.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6095" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Aldosterone plasma concentrations generally decline following irbesartan administration, but serum potassium levels are not significantly affected at recommended doses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6096" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In hypertensive patients, chronic oral doses of irbesartan (up to 300 mg) had no effect on glomerular filtration rate, renal plasma flow or filtration fraction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6097" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In multiple dose studies in hypertensive patients, there were no clinically important effects on fasting triglycerides, total cholesterol, HDL-cholesterol, or fasting glucose concentrations.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6098" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There was no effect on serum uric acid during chronic oral administration and no uricosuric effect.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6099" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Hydrochlorothiazide After oral administration of hydrochlorothiazide, diuresis begins within 2 hours, peaks in about 4 hours and lasts about 6 to 12 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6100" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Drug Interactions Hydrochlorothiazide Alcohol, barbiturates, or narcotics: Potentiation of orthostatic hypotension may occur.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M226" type="Trigger" span="75 12" str="Potentiation"/>
<Mention id="M221" type="Precipitant" span="38 7" str="Alcohol" code="3K9958V90M"/>
<Mention id="M228" type="SpecificInteraction" span="91 23" str="orthostatic hypotension" code="28651003: Orthostatic hypotension (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M224" type="Precipitant" span="47 12" str="barbiturates" code="N0000175693"/>
<Mention id="M227" type="Precipitant" span="64 9" str="narcotics" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I71" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M226" precipitant="M221" effect="M228"/>
<Interaction id="I72" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M226" precipitant="M224" effect="M228"/>
<Interaction id="I73" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M226" precipitant="M227" effect="M228"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6101" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Skeletal muscle relaxants: Possible increased responsiveness to muscle relaxants such as curare derivatives.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M235" type="Trigger" span="36 24" str="increased responsiveness"/>
<Mention id="M230" type="Precipitant" span="89 18" str="curare derivatives" code="900961Z8VR"/>
<Mention id="M237" type="SpecificInteraction" span="36 44" str="increased responsiveness to muscle relaxants" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M233" type="Precipitant" span="9 16" str="muscle relaxants" code="N0000175737"/>
<Mention id="M236" type="Precipitant" span="0 25" str="Skeletal muscle relaxants" code="N0000175738"/>
<Interaction id="I74" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M235" precipitant="M230" effect="M237"/>
<Interaction id="I75" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M235" precipitant="M233" effect="M237"/>
<Interaction id="I76" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M235" precipitant="M236" effect="M237"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6102" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Corticosteroids, ACTH–intensified electrolyte depletion, particularly hypokalemia.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M247" type="Trigger" span="22 11" str="intensified"/>
<Mention id="M242" type="Precipitant" span="17 4" str="ACTH" code="K0U68Q2TXA"/>
<Mention id="M246" type="SpecificInteraction" span="70 11" str="hypokalemia" code="43339004: Hypokalemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M249" type="SpecificInteraction" span="34 21" str="electrolyte depletion" code="166686006: Electrolytes abnormal (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M248" type="Precipitant" span="0 15" str="Corticosteroids" code="N0000175576"/>
<Interaction id="I77" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M247" precipitant="M242" effect="M246"/>
<Interaction id="I78" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M247" precipitant="M242" effect="M249"/>
<Interaction id="I79" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M247" precipitant="M248" effect="M246"/>
<Interaction id="I80" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M247" precipitant="M248" effect="M249"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6103" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Pressor amines (e.g., norepinephrine)–possible decreased response to pressor amines but not sufficient to preclude their use.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M253" type="Trigger" span="47 18" str="decreased response"/>
<Mention id="M251" type="Precipitant" span="22 14" str="norepinephrine" code="X4W3ENH1CV"/>
<Mention id="M255" type="SpecificInteraction" span="47 36" str="decreased response to pressor amines" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M254" type="Precipitant" span="69 14" str="pressor amines" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I81" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M253" precipitant="M251" effect="M255"/>
<Interaction id="I82" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M253" precipitant="M254" effect="M255"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6104" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Irbesartan Irbesartan is an orally active agent that does not require biotransformation into an active form.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6105" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The oral absorption of irbesartan is rapid and complete with an average absolute bioavailability of 60% to 80%.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6106" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following oral administration of irbesartan, peak plasma concentrations of irbesartan are attained at 1.5 to 2 hours after dosing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6107" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Food does not affect the bioavailability of irbesartan.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6108" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Irbesartan exhibits linear pharmacokinetics over the therapeutic dose range.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6109" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The terminal elimination half-life of irbesartan averaged 11 to 15 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6110" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Steady-state concentrations are achieved within 3 days.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6111" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Limited accumulation of irbesartan (&lt;20%) is observed in plasma upon repeated once-daily dosing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6112" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Hydrochlorothiazide When plasma levels have been followed for at least 24 hours, the plasma half-life has been observed to vary between 5.6 and 14.8 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6113" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Metabolism and Elimination Irbesartan Irbesartan is metabolized via glucuronide conjugation and oxidation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6114" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following oral or intravenous administration of 14C-labeled irbesartan, more than 80% of the circulating plasma radioactivity is attributable to unchanged irbesartan.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6115" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The primary circulating metabolite is the inactive irbesartan glucuronide conjugate (approximately 6%).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6116" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The remaining oxidative metabolites do not add appreciably to irbesartan's pharmacologic activity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6117" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Irbesartan and its metabolites are excreted by both biliary and renal routes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6118" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following either oral or intravenous administration of 14C-labeled irbesartan, about 20% of radioactivity is recovered in the urine and the remainder in the feces, as irbesartan or irbesartan glucuronide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6119" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In vitro studies of irbesartan oxidation by cytochrome P450 isoenzymes indicated irbesartan was oxidized primarily by 2C9; metabolism by 3A4 was negligible.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6120" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Irbesartan was neither metabolized by, nor did it substantially induce or inhibit, isoenzymes commonly associated with drug metabolism (1A1, 1A2, 2A6, 2B6, 2D6, 2E1).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6121" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There was no induction or inhibition of 3A4.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6122" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Hydrochlorothiazide Hydrochlorothiazide is not metabolized but is eliminated rapidly by the kidney.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6123" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>At least 61% of the oral dose is eliminated unchanged within 24 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6124" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Distribution Irbesartan Irbesartan is 90% bound to serum proteins (primarily albumin and α1-acid glycoprotein) with negligible binding to cellular components of blood.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6125" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The average volume of distribution is 53 to 93 liters.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6126" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Total plasma and renal clearances are in the range of 157 to 176 mL/min and 3.0 to 3.5 mL/min, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6127" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>With repetitive dosing, irbesartan accumulates to no clinically relevant extent.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6128" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Studies in animals indicate that radiolabeled irbesartan weakly crosses the blood-brain barrier and placenta.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6129" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Irbesartan is excreted in the milk of lactating rats.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6130" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Hydrochlorothiazide Hydrochlorothiazide crosses the placental but not the blood-brain barrier and is excreted in breast milk.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6131" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Specific Populations Pediatric Irbesartan-hydrochlorothiazide pharmacokinetics have not been investigated in patients &lt;18 years of age.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6132" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Gender No gender-related differences in pharmacokinetics were observed in healthy elderly (age 65 to 80 years) or in healthy young (age 18 to 40 years) subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6133" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In studies of hypertensive patients, there was no gender difference in half-life or accumulation, but somewhat higher plasma concentrations of irbesartan were observed in females (11% to 44%).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6134" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No gender-related dosage adjustment is necessary.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6135" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Geriatric In elderly subjects (age 65 to 80 years), irbesartan elimination half-life was not significantly altered, but AUC and Cmax values were about 20% to 50% greater than those of young subjects (age 18 to 40 years).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6136" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No dosage adjustment is necessary in the elderly.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6137" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Race In healthy black subjects, irbesartan AUC values were approximately 25% greater than whites; there were no differences in Cmax values.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6138" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Renal insufficiency The pharmacokinetics of irbesartan were not altered in patients with renal impairment or in patients on hemodialysis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6139" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Irbesartan is not removed by hemodialysis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6140" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No dosage adjustment is necessary in patients with mild to severe renal impairment unless a patient with renal impairment is also volume depleted.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6141" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Hepatic insufficiency The pharmacokinetics of irbesartan following repeated oral administration were not significantly affected in patients with mild to moderate cirrhosis of the liver.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6142" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No dosage adjustment is necessary in patients with hepatic insufficiency.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6143" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Drug-Drug Interactions No significant drug-drug pharmacokinetic (or pharmacodynamic) interactions have been found in interaction studies with hydrochlorothiazide, digoxin, warfarin, and nifedipine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6144" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In vitro studies show significant inhibition of the formation of oxidized irbesartan metabolites with the known cytochrome CYP2C9 substrates/inhibitors sulphenazole, tolbutamide, and nifedipine.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M264" type="Trigger" span="34 10;85 11" str="inhibition | metabolites"/>
<Mention id="M257" type="Precipitant" span="112 17;141 10" str="cytochrome CYP2C9 | inhibitors" code="N0000185504"/>
<Mention id="M259" type="Precipitant" span="112 28" str="cytochrome CYP2C9 substrates" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M261" type="Precipitant" span="183 10" str="nifedipine" code="I9ZF7L6G2L"/>
<Mention id="M263" type="Precipitant" span="152 12" str="sulphenazole" code="0J8L4V3F81"/>
<Mention id="M265" type="Precipitant" span="166 11" str="tolbutamide" code="982XCM1FOI"/>
<Interaction id="I83" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M264" precipitant="M257" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I84" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M264" precipitant="M259" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I85" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M264" precipitant="M261" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I86" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M264" precipitant="M263" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I87" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M264" precipitant="M265" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6145" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>However, in clinical studies the consequences of concomitant irbesartan on the pharmacodynamics of warfarin were negligible.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6146" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Concomitant nifedipine or hydrochlorothiazide had no effect on irbesartan pharmacokinetics.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6147" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Based on in vitro data, no interaction would be expected with drugs whose metabolism is dependent upon cytochrome P450 isoenzymes 1A1, 1A2, 2A6, 2B6, 2D6, 2E1, or 3A4.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6148" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In separate studies of patients receiving maintenance doses of warfarin, hydrochlorothiazide, or digoxin, irbesartan administration for 7 days had no effect on the pharmacodynamics of warfarin (prothrombin time) or the pharmacokinetics of digoxin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6149" LabelDrug="Avalide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacokinetics of irbesartan were not affected by coadministration of nifedipine or hydrochlorothiazide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="aliskiren" precipitantCode="502FWN4Q32" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="aliskiren" precipitantCode="502FWN4Q32" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="aliskiren" precipitantCode="502FWN4Q32" effect="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="aliskiren" precipitantCode="502FWN4Q32" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="aliskiren" precipitantCode="502FWN4Q32"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nsaids" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect=" 39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nsaids" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nsaids" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="236423003: Renal impairment (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nsaids and selective cox-2 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="selective cox-2 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000008288" effect=" 39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="selective cox-2 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000008288" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="selective cox-2 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000008288" effect="236423003: Renal impairment (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="selective cox-2 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000008288" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="dual blockade of the renin-angiotensin system" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="dual blockade of the renin-angiotensin system" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="236423003: Renal impairment (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="dual blockade of the renin-angiotensin system" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="antidiabetic drugs" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cholestyramine" precipitantCode="4B33BGI082" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="colestipol" precipitantCode="K50N755924" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="lithium" precipitantCode="9FN79X2M3F" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="lithium" precipitantCode="9FN79X2M3F"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="carbamazepine" precipitantCode="33CM23913M" effect="89627008: Hyponatremia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="diuretic therapy" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect=" 39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="diuretic therapy" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="diuretic therapy" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="236423003: Renal impairment (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nsaid" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="38936003: Abnormal blood pressure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nsaid" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agent" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="selective cox-2 inhibitor" precipitantCode="N0000008288" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agents" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ace inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175562" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ace inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175562" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ace inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175562" effect="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ace inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175562" effect="419620001: Death (event)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ace inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175562" effect="445009001: Azotemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ace inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175562" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ace inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175562" effect="83128009: Oliguria (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="angiotensin-receptor blockers" precipitantCode="N0000175561" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="angiotensin-receptor blockers" precipitantCode="N0000175561" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="angiotensin-receptor blockers" precipitantCode="N0000175561" effect="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="angiotensin-receptor blockers" precipitantCode="N0000175561" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="dual blockade of the ras" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="dual blockade of the ras" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="dual blockade of the ras" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="dual blockade of the ras" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="agents that affect the ras" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="166686006: Electrolytes abnormal (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="agents that affect the ras" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="38936003: Abnormal blood pressure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="agents that affect the ras" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="ras inhibitors" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="drugs that raise serum potassium levels" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="antidiabetic drug" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="anionic exchange resins" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="resin" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="diuretics" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="potassium sparing diuretics" precipitantCode="N0000175418" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="potassium supplements" precipitantCode="RWP5GA015D" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="potassium-containing salt substitutes" precipitantCode="N0000175600" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="angiotensin ii infusions" precipitantCode="M089EFU921" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="alcohol" precipitantCode="3K9958V90M" effect="28651003: Orthostatic hypotension (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="barbiturates" precipitantCode="N0000175693" effect="28651003: Orthostatic hypotension (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="narcotics" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="28651003: Orthostatic hypotension (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="curare derivatives" precipitantCode="900961Z8VR" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="muscle relaxants" precipitantCode="N0000175737" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="skeletal muscle relaxants" precipitantCode="N0000175738" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="acth" precipitantCode="K0U68Q2TXA" effect="166686006: Electrolytes abnormal (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="acth" precipitantCode="K0U68Q2TXA" effect="43339004: Hypokalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="corticosteroids" precipitantCode="N0000175576" effect="166686006: Electrolytes abnormal (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="corticosteroids" precipitantCode="N0000175576" effect="43339004: Hypokalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="norepinephrine" precipitantCode="X4W3ENH1CV" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="pressor amines" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cytochrome cyp2c9 | inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000185504" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cytochrome cyp2c9 substrates" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="nifedipine" precipitantCode="I9ZF7L6G2L" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="sulphenazole" precipitantCode="0J8L4V3F81" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="tolbutamide" precipitantCode="982XCM1FOI" effect="C54355"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>