<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Catapres" setid="d7f569dc-6bed-42dc-9bec-940a9e6b090d">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
Catapres® (clonidine hydrochloride, USP) tablets should not be used in patients with known hypersensitivity to clonidine (see  PRECAUTIONS ).</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
The dose of Catapres® (clonidine hydrochloride, USP) tablets must be adjusted according to the patient's individual blood pressure response. The following is a general guide to its administration.          0.1 mg tablet twice daily (morning and bedtime). Elderly patients may benefit from a lower initial dose.          Further increments of 0.1 mg per day may be made at weekly intervals if necessary until the desired response is achieved. Taking the larger portion of the oral daily dose at bedtime may minimize transient adjustment effects of dry mouth and drowsiness. The therapeutic doses most commonly employed have ranged from 0.2 mg to 0.6 mg per day given in divided doses. Studies have indicated that 2.4 mg is the maximum effective daily dose, but doses as high as this have rarely been employed.          Patients with renal impairment may benefit from a lower initial dose. Patients should be carefully monitored. Since only a minimal amount of clonidine is removed during routine hemodialysis, there is no need to give supplemental clonidine following dialysis.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
Clonidine may potentiate the CNS-depressive effects of alcohol, barbiturates or other sedating drugs. If a patient receiving clonidine hydrochloride is also taking tricyclic antidepressants, the hypotensive effect of clonidine may be reduced, necessitating an increase in the clonidine dose. If a patient receiving clonidine is also taking neuroleptics, orthostatic regulation disturbances (e.g., orthostatic hypotension, dizziness, fatigue) may be induced or exacerbated. Monitor heart rate in patients receiving clonidine concomitantly with agents known to affect sinus node function or AV nodal conduction, e.g., digitalis, calcium channel blockers and beta-blockers. Sinus bradycardia resulting in hospitalization and pacemaker insertion has been reported in association with the use of clonidine concomitantly with diltiazem or verapamil. Amitriptyline in combination with clonidine enhances the manifestation of corneal lesions in rats (see  Toxicology ). Based on observations in patients in a state of alcoholic delirium it has been suggested that high intravenous doses of clonidine may increase the arrhythmogenic potential (QT-prolongation, ventricular fibrillation) of high intravenous doses of haloperidol. Causal relationship and relevance for clonidine oral tablets have not been established.</Section>
<Section name="PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="42232-9">
In patients who have developed localized contact sensitization to Catapres-TTS® (clonidine), continuation of Catapres-TTS or substitution of oral clonidine hydrochloride therapy may be associated with the development of a generalized skin rash. In patients who develop an allergic reaction to Catapres-TTS, substitution of oral clonidine hydrochloride may also elicit an allergic reaction (including generalized rash, urticaria, or angioedema). The sympatholytic action of clonidine may worsen sinus node dysfunction and atrioventricular (AV) block, especially in patients taking other sympatholytic drugs. There are post-marketing reports of patients with conduction abnormalities and/or taking other sympatholytic drugs who developed severe bradycardia requiring IV atropine, IV isoproterenol and temporary cardiac pacing while taking clonidine. In hypertension caused by pheochromocytoma, no therapeutic effect of CATAPRES tablets can be expected.          Administration of Catapres® (clonidine hydrochloride, USP) tablets should be continued to within 4 hours of surgery and resumed as soon as possible thereafter. Blood pressure should be carefully monitored during surgery and additional measures to control blood pressure should be available if required.          Patients should be cautioned against interruption of CATAPRES tablets therapy without their physician's advice. Since patients may experience a possible sedative effect, dizziness, or accommodation disorder with use of clonidine, caution patients about engaging in activities such as driving a vehicle or operating appliances or machinery. Also, inform patients that this sedative effect may be increased by concomitant use of alcohol, barbiturates, or other sedating drugs. Patients who wear contact lenses should be cautioned that treatment with CATAPRES tablets may cause dryness of eyes.          Clonidine may potentiate the CNS-depressive effects of alcohol, barbiturates or other sedating drugs. If a patient receiving clonidine hydrochloride is also taking tricyclic antidepressants, the hypotensive effect of clonidine may be reduced, necessitating an increase in the clonidine dose. If a patient receiving clonidine is also taking neuroleptics, orthostatic regulation disturbances (e.g., orthostatic hypotension, dizziness, fatigue) may be induced or exacerbated. Monitor heart rate in patients receiving clonidine concomitantly with agents known to affect sinus node function or AV nodal conduction, e.g., digitalis, calcium channel blockers and beta-blockers. Sinus bradycardia resulting in hospitalization and pacemaker insertion has been reported in association with the use of clonidine concomitantly with diltiazem or verapamil. Amitriptyline in combination with clonidine enhances the manifestation of corneal lesions in rats (see  Toxicology ). Based on observations in patients in a state of alcoholic delirium it has been suggested that high intravenous doses of clonidine may increase the arrhythmogenic potential (QT-prolongation, ventricular fibrillation) of high intravenous doses of haloperidol. Causal relationship and relevance for clonidine oral tablets have not been established.          In several studies with oral clonidine hydrochloride, a dose-dependent increase in the incidence and severity of spontaneous retinal degeneration was seen in albino rats treated for six months or longer. Tissue distribution studies in dogs and monkeys showed a concentration of clonidine in the choroid. In view of the retinal degeneration seen in rats, eye examinations were performed during clinical trials in 908 patients before, and periodically after, the start of clonidine therapy. In 353 of these 908 patients, the eye examinations were carried out over periods of 24 months or longer. Except for some dryness of the eyes, no drug-related abnormal ophthalmological findings were recorded and, according to specialized tests such as electroretinography and macular dazzle, retinal function was unchanged. In combination with amitriptyline, clonidine hydrochloride administration led to the development of corneal lesions in rats within 5 days.          Chronic dietary administration of clonidine was not carcinogenic to rats (132 weeks) or mice (78 weeks) dosed, respectively, at up to 46 or 70 times the maximum recommended daily human dose as mg/kg (9 or 6 times the MRDHD on a mg/m2 basis). There was no evidence of genotoxicity in the Ames test for mutagenicity or mouse micronucleus test for clastogenicity. Fertility of male or female rats was unaffected by clonidine doses as high as 150 µg/kg (approximately 3 times MRDHD). In a separate experiment, fertility of female rats appeared to be affected at dose levels of 500 to 2000 µg/kg (10 to 40 times the oral MRDHD on a mg/kg basis; 2 to 8 times the MRDHD on a mg/m2 basis).               Reproduction studies performed in rabbits at doses up to approximately 3 times the oral maximum recommended daily human dose (MRDHD) of Catapres® (clonidine hydrochloride, USP) tablets produced no evidence of a teratogenic or embryotoxic potential in rabbits. In rats, however, doses as low as 1/3 the oral MRDHD (1/15 the MRDHD on a mg/m2 basis) of clonidine were associated with increased resorptions in a study in which dams were treated continuously from 2 months prior to mating. Increased resorptions were not associated with treatment at the same time or at higher dose levels (up to 3 times the oral MRDHD) when the dams were treated on gestation days 6 to 15. Increases in resorption were observed at much higher dose levels (40 times the oral MRDHD on a mg/kg basis; 4 to 8 times the MRDHD on a mg/m2 basis) in mice and rats treated on gestation days 1 to 14 (lowest dose employed in the study was 500 µg/kg). No adequate, well-controlled studies have been conducted in pregnant women. Clonidine crosses the placental barrier (see   CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY, Pharmacokinetics  ). Because animal reproduction studies are not always predictive of human response, this drug should be used during pregnancy only if clearly needed.            As clonidine hydrochloride is excreted in human milk, caution should be exercised when CATAPRES tablets are administered to a nursing woman.          Safety and effectiveness in pediatric patients have not been established in adequate and well-controlled trials (see  WARNINGS, Withdrawal ).</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS SECTION" id="34071-1">
Patients should be instructed not to discontinue therapy without consulting their physician. Sudden cessation of clonidine treatment has, in some cases, resulted in symptoms such as nervousness, agitation, headache, and tremor accompanied or followed by a rapid rise in blood pressure and elevated catecholamine concentrations in the plasma. The likelihood of such reactions to discontinuation of clonidine therapy appears to be greater after administration of higher doses or continuation of concomitant beta-blocker treatment and special caution is therefore advised in these situations. Rare instances of hypertensive encephalopathy, cerebrovascular accidents and death have been reported after clonidine withdrawal. When discontinuing therapy with CATAPRES tablets, the physician should reduce the dose gradually over 2 to 4 days to avoid withdrawal symptomatology. An excessive rise in blood pressure following discontinuation of CATAPRES tablets therapy can be reversed by administration of oral clonidine hydrochloride or by intravenous phentolamine. If therapy is to be discontinued in patients receiving a beta-blocker and clonidine concurrently, the beta-blocker should be withdrawn several days before the gradual discontinuation of CATAPRES tablets.  Because children commonly have gastrointestinal illnesses that lead to vomiting, they may be particularly susceptible to hypertensive episodes resulting from abrupt inability to take medication.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Clonidine stimulates alpha-adrenoreceptors in the brain stem. This action results in reduced sympathetic outflow from the central nervous system and in decreases in peripheral resistance, renal vascular resistance, heart rate, and blood pressure. CATAPRES tablets act relatively rapidly. The patient’s blood pressure declines within 30 to 60 minutes after an oral dose, the maximum decrease occurring within 2 to 4 hours. Renal blood flow and glomerular filtration rate remain essentially unchanged. Normal postural reflexes are intact; therefore, orthostatic symptoms are mild and infrequent. Acute studies with clonidine hydrochloride in humans have demonstrated a moderate reduction (15% to 20%) of cardiac output in the supine position with no change in the peripheral resistance: at a 45° tilt there is a smaller reduction in cardiac output and a decrease of peripheral resistance. During long term therapy, cardiac output tends to return to control values, while peripheral resistance remains decreased. Slowing of the pulse rate has been observed in most patients given clonidine, but the drug does not alter normal hemodynamic response to exercise. Tolerance to the antihypertensive effect may develop in some patients, necessitating a reevaluation of therapy. Other studies in patients have provided evidence of a reduction in plasma renin activity and in the excretion of aldosterone and catecholamines. The exact relationship of these pharmacologic actions to the antihypertensive effect of clonidine has not been fully elucidated. Clonidine acutely stimulates growth hormone release in both children and adults, but does not produce a chronic elevation of growth hormone with long-term use.        The pharmacokinetics of clonidine is dose-proportional in the range of 100 to 600 µg. The absolute bioavailability of clonidine on oral administration is 70% to 80%. Peak plasma clonidine levels are attained in approximately 1 to 3 hours. Following intravenous administration, clonidine displays biphasic disposition with a distribution half-life of about 20 minutes and an elimination half-life ranging from 12 to 16 hours. The half-life increases up to 41 hours in patients with severe impairment of renal function. Clonidine crosses the placental barrier. It has been shown to cross the blood-brain barrier in rats. Following oral administration about 40% to 60% of the absorbed dose is recovered in the urine as unchanged drug in 24 hours. About 50% of the absorbed dose is metabolized in the liver. Neither food nor the race of the patient influences the pharmacokinetics of clonidine. The antihypertensive effect is reached at plasma concentrations between about 0.2 and 2.0 ng/mL in patients with normal excretory function. A further rise in the plasma levels will not enhance the antihypertensive effect.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="1006" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Catapres® (clonidine hydrochloride, USP) tablets should not be used in patients with known hypersensitivity to clonidine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1007" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The dose of Catapres® (clonidine hydrochloride, USP) tablets must be adjusted according to the patient's individual blood pressure response.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1008" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The following is a general guide to its administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1009" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>0.1 mg tablet twice daily (morning and bedtime).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1010" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Elderly patients may benefit from a lower initial dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1011" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Further increments of 0.1 mg per day may be made at weekly intervals if necessary until the desired response is achieved.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1012" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Taking the larger portion of the oral daily dose at bedtime may minimize transient adjustment effects of dry mouth and drowsiness.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1013" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The therapeutic doses most commonly employed have ranged from 0.2 mg to 0.6 mg per day given in divided doses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1014" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Studies have indicated that 2.4 mg is the maximum effective daily dose, but doses as high as this have rarely been employed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1015" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Patients with renal impairment may benefit from a lower initial dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1016" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Since only a minimal amount of clonidine is removed during routine hemodialysis, there is no need to give supplemental clonidine following dialysis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1017" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Clonidine may potentiate the CNS-depressive effects of alcohol, barbiturates or other sedating drugs.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M7" type="Trigger" span="14 10" str="potentiate"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="55 7" str="alcohol" code="3K9958V90M"/>
<Mention id="M9" type="SpecificInteraction" span="29 22" str="CNS-depressive effects" code="418072004: Central nervous system depression (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M5" type="Precipitant" span="64 12" str="barbiturates" code="N0000175693"/>
<Mention id="M8" type="Precipitant" span="86 14" str="sedating drugs" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M7" precipitant="M2" effect="M9"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M7" precipitant="M5" effect="M9"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M7" precipitant="M8" effect="M9"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1018" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>If a patient receiving clonidine hydrochloride is also taking tricyclic antidepressants, the hypotensive effect of clonidine may be reduced, necessitating an increase in the clonidine dose.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M10" type="Trigger" span="105 6;132 7" str="effect | reduced"/>
<Mention id="M14" type="Precipitant" span="62 25" str="tricyclic antidepressants" code="N0000175752"/>
<Mention id="M12" type="SpecificInteraction" span="93 18;132 7" str="hypotensive effect | reduced" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M13" type="Trigger" span="158 8;184 4" str="increase | dose"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M10" precipitant="M14" effect="M12"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M13" precipitant="M14" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1019" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>If a patient receiving clonidine is also taking neuroleptics, orthostatic regulation disturbances (e.g., orthostatic hypotension, dizziness, fatigue) may be induced or exacerbated.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M27" type="Trigger" span="157 7" str="induced "/>
<Mention id="M28" type="Trigger" span="168 11" str=" exacerbated"/>
<Mention id="M29" type="Precipitant" span="48 12" str="neuroleptics" code="N0000178316"/>
<Mention id="M18" type="SpecificInteraction" span="130 9" str="dizziness" code="404640003: Dizziness (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M22" type="SpecificInteraction" span="62 35" str="orthostatic regulation disturbances" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M26" type="SpecificInteraction" span="105 23" str="orthostatic hypotension" code="28651003: Orthostatic hypotension (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M30" type="SpecificInteraction" span="141 7" str="fatigue" code="84229001: Fatigue (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M27;M28" precipitant="M29" effect="M18"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M27;M28" precipitant="M29" effect="M22"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M27;M28" precipitant="M29" effect="M26"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M27;M28" precipitant="M29" effect="M30"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1020" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor heart rate in patients receiving clonidine concomitantly with agents known to affect sinus node function or AV nodal conduction, e.g., digitalis, calcium channel blockers and beta-blockers.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M43" type="Trigger" span="0 7" str="Monitor"/>
<Mention id="M32" type="Precipitant" span="70 22;116 19" str="agents known to affect | AV nodal conduction" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M45" type="SpecificInteraction" span="8 10" str="heart rate" code="361135004: Abnormal cardiac rate (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M35" type="Precipitant" span="70 42" str="agents known to affect sinus node function" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M38" type="Precipitant" span="183 13" str="beta-blockers" code="N0000175556"/>
<Mention id="M41" type="Precipitant" span="154 24" str="calcium channel blockers" code="N0000175566"/>
<Mention id="M44" type="Precipitant" span="143 9" str="digitalis" code="F1T8QT9U8B"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M43" precipitant="M32" effect="M45"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M43" precipitant="M35" effect="M45"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M43" precipitant="M38" effect="M45"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M43" precipitant="M41" effect="M45"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M43" precipitant="M44" effect="M45"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1021" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Sinus bradycardia resulting in hospitalization and pacemaker insertion has been reported in association with the use of clonidine concomitantly with diltiazem or verapamil.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M49" type="Trigger" span="92 16" str="association with"/>
<Mention id="M47" type="Precipitant" span="149 9" str="diltiazem" code="EE92BBP03H"/>
<Mention id="M51" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 70" str="Sinus bradycardia resulting in hospitalization and pacemaker insertion" code="49710005: Sinus bradycardia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M50" type="Precipitant" span="162 9" str="verapamil" code="CJ0O37KU29"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M49" precipitant="M47" effect="M51"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M49" precipitant="M50" effect="M51"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1022" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Amitriptyline in combination with clonidine enhances the manifestation of corneal lesions in rats.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M52" type="Trigger" span="44 26" str="enhances the manifestation"/>
<Mention id="M53" type="Precipitant" span="0 13" str="Amitriptyline" code="1806D8D52K"/>
<Mention id="M54" type="SpecificInteraction" span="74 15" str="corneal lesions" code="63725005:  Corneal lesion (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M52" precipitant="M53" effect="M54"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1023" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Based on observations in patients in a state of alcoholic delirium it has been suggested that high intravenous doses of clonidine may increase the arrhythmogenic potential (QT-prolongation, ventricular fibrillation) of high intravenous doses of haloperidol.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M61" type="Trigger" span="134 8" str="increase"/>
<Mention id="M62" type="Precipitant" span="245 11" str="haloperidol" code="J6292F8L3D"/>
<Mention id="M57" type="SpecificInteraction" span="190 24" str="ventricular fibrillation" code="71908006: Ventricular fibrillation (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M60" type="SpecificInteraction" span="173 15" str="QT-prolongation" code="111975006: Prolonged QT interval (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M63" type="SpecificInteraction" span="147 24" str="arrhythmogenic potential" code="698247007: Cardiac arrhythmia (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M61" precipitant="M62" effect="M57"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M61" precipitant="M62" effect="M60"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M61" precipitant="M62" effect="M63"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1024" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Causal relationship and relevance for clonidine oral tablets have not been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1025" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In patients who have developed localized contact sensitization to Catapres-TTS® (clonidine), continuation of Catapres-TTS or substitution of oral clonidine hydrochloride therapy may be associated with the development of a generalized skin rash.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1026" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In patients who develop an allergic reaction to Catapres-TTS, substitution of oral clonidine hydrochloride may also elicit an allergic reaction (including generalized rash, urticaria, or angioedema).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1027" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The sympatholytic action of clonidine may worsen sinus node dysfunction and atrioventricular (AV) block, especially in patients taking other sympatholytic drugs.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M73" type="Trigger" span="42 6" str="worsen"/>
<Mention id="M74" type="Precipitant" span="141 19" str="sympatholytic drugs" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M66" type="SpecificInteraction" span="76 16;98 5" str="atrioventricular | block" code="233917008: Atrioventricular block (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M69" type="SpecificInteraction" span="94 2;98 5" str="AV | block" code="233917008: Atrioventricular block (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M72" type="SpecificInteraction" span="76 27" str="atrioventricular (AV) block" code="233917008: Atrioventricular block (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M75" type="SpecificInteraction" span="49 22" str="sinus node dysfunction" code="60423000: Sinus node dysfunction (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M73" precipitant="M74" effect="M66"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M73" precipitant="M74" effect="M69"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M73" precipitant="M74" effect="M72"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M73" precipitant="M74" effect="M75"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1028" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>There are post-marketing reports of patients with conduction abnormalities and/or taking other sympatholytic drugs who developed severe bradycardia requiring IV atropine, IV isoproterenol and temporary cardiac pacing while taking clonidine.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M76" type="Trigger" span="119 9" str="developed"/>
<Mention id="M77" type="Precipitant" span="95 19" str="sympatholytic drugs" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M78" type="SpecificInteraction" span="129 87" str="severe bradycardia requiring IV atropine, IV isoproterenol and temporary cardiac pacing" code="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M76" precipitant="M77" effect="M78"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1029" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In hypertension caused by pheochromocytoma, no therapeutic effect of CATAPRES tablets can be expected.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1030" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Administration of Catapres® (clonidine hydrochloride, USP) tablets should be continued to within 4 hours of surgery and resumed as soon as possible thereafter.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1031" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Blood pressure should be carefully monitored during surgery and additional measures to control blood pressure should be available if required.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1032" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Patients should be cautioned against interruption of CATAPRES tablets therapy without their physician's advice.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1033" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Since patients may experience a possible sedative effect, dizziness, or accommodation disorder with use of clonidine, caution patients about engaging in activities such as driving a vehicle or operating appliances or machinery.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1034" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Also, inform patients that this sedative effect may be increased by concomitant use of alcohol, barbiturates, or other sedating drugs.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M85" type="Trigger" span="41 23" str="effect may be increased"/>
<Mention id="M80" type="Precipitant" span="87 7" str="alcohol" code="3K9958V90M"/>
<Mention id="M87" type="SpecificInteraction" span="32 32" str="sedative effect may be increased" code="17971005: Sedated (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M83" type="Precipitant" span="96 12" str="barbiturates" code="N0000175693"/>
<Mention id="M86" type="Precipitant" span="119 14" str="sedating drugs" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M85" precipitant="M80" effect="M87"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M85" precipitant="M83" effect="M87"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M85" precipitant="M86" effect="M87"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1035" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Patients who wear contact lenses should be cautioned that treatment with CATAPRES tablets may cause dryness of eyes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1036" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In several studies with oral clonidine hydrochloride, a dose-dependent increase in the incidence and severity of spontaneous retinal degeneration was seen in albino rats treated for six months or longer.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1037" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Tissue distribution studies in dogs and monkeys showed a concentration of clonidine in the choroid.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1038" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In view of the retinal degeneration seen in rats, eye examinations were performed during clinical trials in 908 patients before, and periodically after, the start of clonidine therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1039" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In 353 of these 908 patients, the eye examinations were carried out over periods of 24 months or longer.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1040" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Except for some dryness of the eyes, no drug-related abnormal ophthalmological findings were recorded and, according to specialized tests such as electroretinography and macular dazzle, retinal function was unchanged.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1041" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In combination with amitriptyline, clonidine hydrochloride administration led to the development of corneal lesions in rats within 5 days.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M88" type="Trigger" span="85 11" str="development"/>
<Mention id="M89" type="Precipitant" span="20 13" str="amitriptyline" code="1806D8D52K"/>
<Mention id="M90" type="SpecificInteraction" span="100 15" str="corneal lesions" code="63725005:  Corneal lesion (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I29" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M88" precipitant="M89" effect="M90"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1042" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Chronic dietary administration of clonidine was not carcinogenic to rats (132 weeks) or mice (78 weeks) dosed, respectively, at up to 46 or 70 times the maximum recommended daily human dose as mg/kg (9 or 6 times the MRDHD on a mg/m2 basis).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1043" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>There was no evidence of genotoxicity in the Ames test for mutagenicity or mouse micronucleus test for clastogenicity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1044" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Fertility of male or female rats was unaffected by clonidine doses as high as 150 µg/kg (approximately 3 times MRDHD).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1045" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In a separate experiment, fertility of female rats appeared to be affected at dose levels of 500 to 2000 µg/kg (10 to 40 times the oral MRDHD on a mg/kg basis; 2 to 8 times the MRDHD on a mg/m2 basis).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1046" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Reproduction studies performed in rabbits at doses up to approximately 3 times the oral maximum recommended daily human dose (MRDHD) of Catapres® (clonidine hydrochloride, USP) tablets produced no evidence of a teratogenic or embryotoxic potential in rabbits.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1047" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In rats, however, doses as low as 1/3 the oral MRDHD (1/15 the MRDHD on a mg/m2 basis) of clonidine were associated with increased resorptions in a study in which dams were treated continuously from 2 months prior to mating.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1048" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Increased resorptions were not associated with treatment at the same time or at higher dose levels (up to 3 times the oral MRDHD) when the dams were treated on gestation days 6 to 15.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1049" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Increases in resorption were observed at much higher dose levels (40 times the oral MRDHD on a mg/kg basis; 4 to 8 times the MRDHD on a mg/m2 basis) in mice and rats treated on gestation days 1 to 14 (lowest dose employed in the study was 500 µg/kg).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1050" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>No adequate, well-controlled studies have been conducted in pregnant women.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1051" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Clonidine crosses the placental barrier.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1052" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because animal reproduction studies are not always predictive of human response, this drug should be used during pregnancy only if clearly needed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1053" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>As clonidine hydrochloride is excreted in human milk, caution should be exercised when CATAPRES tablets are administered to a nursing woman.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1054" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Safety and effectiveness in pediatric patients have not been established in adequate and well-controlled trials.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1055" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Patients should be instructed not to discontinue therapy without consulting their physician.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1056" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Sudden cessation of clonidine treatment has, in some cases, resulted in symptoms such as nervousness, agitation, headache, and tremor accompanied or followed by a rapid rise in blood pressure and elevated catecholamine concentrations in the plasma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1057" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The likelihood of such reactions to discontinuation of clonidine therapy appears to be greater after administration of higher doses or continuation of concomitant beta-blocker treatment and special caution is therefore advised in these situations.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M91" type="Trigger" span="190 15" str="special caution"/>
<Mention id="M92" type="Precipitant" span="163 12" str="beta-blocker" code="N0000175556"/>
<Interaction id="I30" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M91" precipitant="M92"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1058" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Rare instances of hypertensive encephalopathy, cerebrovascular accidents and death have been reported after clonidine withdrawal.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1059" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>When discontinuing therapy with CATAPRES tablets, the physician should reduce the dose gradually over 2 to 4 days to avoid withdrawal symptomatology.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1060" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>An excessive rise in blood pressure following discontinuation of CATAPRES tablets therapy can be reversed by administration of oral clonidine hydrochloride or by intravenous phentolamine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1061" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>If therapy is to be discontinued in patients receiving a beta-blocker and clonidine concurrently, the beta-blocker should be withdrawn several days before the gradual discontinuation of CATAPRES tablets.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M93" type="Trigger" span="115 19" str="should be withdrawn"/>
<Mention id="M94" type="Precipitant" span="57 12" str="beta-blocker" code="N0000175556"/>
<Interaction id="I31" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M93" precipitant="M94"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1062" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Because children commonly have gastrointestinal illnesses that lead to vomiting, they may be particularly susceptible to hypertensive episodes resulting from abrupt inability to take medication.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1063" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Clonidine stimulates alpha-adrenoreceptors in the brain stem.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1064" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This action results in reduced sympathetic outflow from the central nervous system and in decreases in peripheral resistance, renal vascular resistance, heart rate, and blood pressure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1065" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The patient’s blood pressure declines within 30 to 60 minutes after an oral dose, the maximum decrease occurring within 2 to 4 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1066" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Renal blood flow and glomerular filtration rate remain essentially unchanged.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1067" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Normal postural reflexes are intact; therefore, orthostatic symptoms are mild and infrequent.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1068" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Acute studies with clonidine hydrochloride in humans have demonstrated a moderate reduction (15% to 20%) of cardiac output in the supine position with no change in the peripheral resistance: at a 45° tilt there is a smaller reduction in cardiac output and a decrease of peripheral resistance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1069" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>During long term therapy, cardiac output tends to return to control values, while peripheral resistance remains decreased.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1070" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Slowing of the pulse rate has been observed in most patients given clonidine, but the drug does not alter normal hemodynamic response to exercise.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1071" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Tolerance to the antihypertensive effect may develop in some patients, necessitating a reevaluation of therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1072" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Other studies in patients have provided evidence of a reduction in plasma renin activity and in the excretion of aldosterone and catecholamines.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1073" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The exact relationship of these pharmacologic actions to the antihypertensive effect of clonidine has not been fully elucidated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1074" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Clonidine acutely stimulates growth hormone release in both children and adults, but does not produce a chronic elevation of growth hormone with long-term use.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1075" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacokinetics of clonidine is dose-proportional in the range of 100 to 600 µg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1076" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The absolute bioavailability of clonidine on oral administration is 70% to 80%.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1077" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Peak plasma clonidine levels are attained in approximately 1 to 3 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1078" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following intravenous administration, clonidine displays biphasic disposition with a distribution half-life of about 20 minutes and an elimination half-life ranging from 12 to 16 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1079" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The half-life increases up to 41 hours in patients with severe impairment of renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1080" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>It has been shown to cross the blood-brain barrier in rats.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1081" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following oral administration about 40% to 60% of the absorbed dose is recovered in the urine as unchanged drug in 24 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1082" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>About 50% of the absorbed dose is metabolized in the liver.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1083" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Neither food nor the race of the patient influences the pharmacokinetics of clonidine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1084" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The antihypertensive effect is reached at plasma concentrations between about 0.2 and 2.0 ng/mL in patients with normal excretory function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1085" LabelDrug="Catapres" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A further rise in the plasma levels will not enhance the antihypertensive effect.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="alcohol" precipitantCode="3K9958V90M" effect="17971005: Sedated (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="alcohol" precipitantCode="3K9958V90M" effect="418072004: Central nervous system depression (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="barbiturates" precipitantCode="N0000175693" effect="17971005: Sedated (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="barbiturates" precipitantCode="N0000175693" effect="418072004: Central nervous system depression (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sedating drugs" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="17971005: Sedated (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sedating drugs" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="418072004: Central nervous system depression (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="tricyclic antidepressants" precipitantCode="N0000175752" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="tricyclic antidepressants" precipitantCode="N0000175752" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="neuroleptics" precipitantCode="N0000178316" effect="28651003: Orthostatic hypotension (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="neuroleptics" precipitantCode="N0000178316" effect="404640003: Dizziness (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="neuroleptics" precipitantCode="N0000178316" effect="84229001: Fatigue (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="neuroleptics" precipitantCode="N0000178316" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="agents known to affect | av nodal conduction" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="361135004: Abnormal cardiac rate (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="agents known to affect sinus node function" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="361135004: Abnormal cardiac rate (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="beta-blockers" precipitantCode="N0000175556" effect="361135004: Abnormal cardiac rate (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="calcium channel blockers" precipitantCode="N0000175566" effect="361135004: Abnormal cardiac rate (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="digitalis" precipitantCode="F1T8QT9U8B" effect="361135004: Abnormal cardiac rate (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="diltiazem" precipitantCode="EE92BBP03H" effect="49710005: Sinus bradycardia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="verapamil" precipitantCode="CJ0O37KU29" effect="49710005: Sinus bradycardia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="amitriptyline" precipitantCode="1806D8D52K" effect="63725005:  Corneal lesion (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="haloperidol" precipitantCode="J6292F8L3D" effect="111975006: Prolonged QT interval (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="haloperidol" precipitantCode="J6292F8L3D" effect="698247007: Cardiac arrhythmia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="haloperidol" precipitantCode="J6292F8L3D" effect="71908006: Ventricular fibrillation (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sympatholytic drugs" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="233917008: Atrioventricular block (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sympatholytic drugs" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sympatholytic drugs" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="60423000: Sinus node dysfunction (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="beta-blocker" precipitantCode="N0000175556"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>