<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Cleviprex" setid="095081a0-1398-11dc-82e1-0002a5d5c51b">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
Cleviprex is contraindicated in patients with:  Allergy to soy or eggs (4.1)  Defective lipid metabolism (4.2)  Severe aortic stenosis (4.3)           Cleviprex is contraindicated in patients with allergies to soybeans, soy products, eggs, or egg products.           Cleviprex is contraindicated in patients with defective lipid metabolism such as pathologic hyperlipemia, lipoid nephrosis, or acute pancreatitis if it is accompanied by hyperlipidemia.          Cleviprex is contraindicated in patients with severe aortic stenosis because afterload reduction can be expected to reduce myocardial oxygen delivery.</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
For intravenous use: Cleviprex is intended for intravenous use. Titrate Cleviprex to achieve the desired blood pressure reduction. Individualize dosage depending on the blood pressure response of the patient and the goal blood pressure. (2.2)  Monitoring: Monitor blood pressure and heart rate during infusion, and until vital signs stabilize. (2.1)  Initial dose: Initiate intravenous infusion of Cleviprex at 1- 2 mg/hour. (2.2)  Dose titration: Double the dose at short (90 second) intervals initially. As the blood pressure approaches goal, increase the dose by less than doubling and lengthen the time between dose adjustments to every 5-10 minutes. An approximately 1-2 mg/hour increase will generally produce an additional 2-4 mmHg decrease in systolic pressure. (2.2)  Maintenance dose: Most patients will achieve the desired therapeutic response at approximately 4-6 mg/hour. Severe hypertension is likely to require higher doses. (2.2)  Maximum dose: Most patients have received maximum doses of 16 mg/hour or less. There is limited experience with short-term dosing as high as 32 mg/hour. Because of lipid load restrictions, no more than 1000 mL or an average of 21 mg/hour of Cleviprex infusion is recommended per 24 hour period. There is little experience beyond 72 hours at any dose. (2.2)           Monitor blood pressure and heart rate continually during infusion, and then until vital signs are stable. Patients who receive prolonged Cleviprex infusions and are not transitioned to other antihypertensive therapies should be monitored for the possibility of rebound hypertension for at least 8 hours after the infusion is stopped. These patients may need follow-up adjustments in blood pressure control.           Cleviprex is intended for intravenous use. Titrate drug to achieve the desired blood pressure reduction. Individualize dosage depending on the blood pressure to be obtained and the response of the patient.  Initial dose: Initiate the intravenous infusion of Cleviprex at 1-2 mg/hour.  Dose titration: The dose may be doubled at short (90 second) intervals initially. As the blood pressure approaches goal, the increase in doses should be less than doubling and the time between dose adjustments should be lengthened to every 5-10 minutes. An approximately 1-2 mg/hour increase will generally produce an additional 2-4 mmHg decrease in systolic pressure.  Maintenance dose: The desired therapeutic response for most patients occurs at doses of 4-6 mg/hour. Patients with severe hypertension may require doses up to 32 mg/hour, but there is limited experience at this dose rate.  Maximum dose: Most patients were treated with maximum doses of 16 mg/hour or less. There is limited short-term experience with doses up to 32 mg/hour. Because of lipid load restrictions, no more than 1000 mL or an average of 21 mg/hour of Cleviprex infusion is recommended per 24 hour period. In clinical trials, 55 hypertensive patients were treated with &amp;gt; 500mL of Cleviprex infusion per 24 hour period. There is little experience with infusion durations beyond 72 hours at any dose.  Transition to an oral antihypertensive agent: Discontinue Cleviprex or titrate downward while appropriate oral therapy is established. When an oral antihypertensive agent is being instituted, consider the lag time of onset of the oral agent’s effect. Continue blood pressure monitoring until desired effect is achieved.  Special populations: Special populations were not specifically studied. In clinical trials, 78 patients with abnormal hepatic function (one or more of the following: elevated serum bilirubin, AST/SGOT, ALT/SGPT) and 121 patients with moderate to severe renal impairment were treated with Cleviprex. An initial Cleviprex infusion rate of 1-2 mg/hour is appropriate in these patients. Table 1 is a guideline for dosing conversion from mg/hour to mL/hour.  Table 1. Dose conversion    Dose (mg/hour)   Dose (mL/hour)    1 2   2 4   4 8   6 12   8 16   10 20   12 24   14 28   16 32   18 36   20 40   22 44   24 48   26 52   28 56   30 60   32 64              Maintain aseptic technique while handling Cleviprex. Cleviprex is a single-use parenteral product. Do not use if contamination is suspected. Once the stopper is punctured, use within 12 hours and discard any unused portion. Cleviprex is supplied in sterile, pre-mixed, ready-to-use 50 mL or 100 mL vials. Invert vial gently several times before use to ensure uniformity of the emulsion prior to administration. Inspect parenteral drug products for particulate matter and discoloration prior to administration whenever solution and container permit. Administer Cleviprex using an infusion device allowing calibrated infusion rates. Commercially available standard plastic cannulae may be used to administer the infusion.Administer Cleviprex by a central line or a peripheral line.  Cleviprex should not be administered in the same line as other medications.  Cleviprex should not be diluted, but it can be administered with the following:   Water for Injection, USP Sodium Chloride (0.9%) Injection, USP Dextrose (5%) Injection, USP Dextrose (5%) in Sodium Chloride (0.9%) Injection, USP Dextrose (5%) in Ringers Lactate Injection, USP Lactated Ringers Injection, USP 10% amino acid</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
No clinical drug interaction studies were conducted. Clevidipine and its major dihydropyridine metabolite do not have the potential for blocking or inducing any CYP enzyme.       At clinically relevant concentrations, clevidipine and its metabolites do not inhibit or induce any CYP450 enzymes. The potential of clevidipine to interact with other drugs is low.(7)</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
Maintain aseptic technique. Discard unused portion 12 hours after stopper puncture. (5.1)  Hypotension and reflex tachycardia are potential consequences of rapid upward titration of Cleviprex. (5.2)  Dihydropyridine calcium channel blockers can produce negative inotropic effects and exacerbate heart failure. Monitor heart failure patients carefully (5.4)  Cleviprex gives no protection against the effects of abrupt beta-blocker withdrawal. (5.5)  Patients who receive prolonged Cleviprex infusions and are not transitioned to other antihypertensive therapies should be monitored for the possibility of rebound hypertension for at least 8 hours after the infusion is stopped. (5.6)            Use aseptic technique and discard any unused product within 12 hours of stopper puncture  [see Dosage and Administration (2.3)] .           Cleviprex may produce systemic hypotension and reflex tachycardia. If either occurs, decrease the dose of Cleviprex. There is limited experience with short-duration therapy with beta-blockers as a treatment for Cleviprex-induced tachycardia. Beta-blocker use for this purpose is not recommended.           Cleviprex contains approximately 0.2 g of lipid per mL (2.0 kcal). Lipid intake restrictions may be necessary for patients with significant disorders of lipid metabolism. For these patients, a reduction in the quantity of concurrently administered lipids may be necessary to compensate for the amount of lipid infused as part of the Cleviprex formulation.           Dihydropyridine calcium channel blockers can produce negative inotropic effects and exacerbate heart failure. Monitor heart failure patients carefully.          Cleviprex is not a beta-blocker, does not reduce heart rate, and gives no protection against the effects of abrupt beta-blocker withdrawal. Beta-blockers should be withdrawn only after a gradual reduction in dose.          Patients who receive prolonged Cleviprex infusions and are not transitioned to other antihypertensive therapies should be monitored for the possibility of rebound hypertension for at least 8 hours after the infusion is stopped.          There is no information to guide use of Cleviprex in treating hypertension associated with pheochromocytoma.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Clevidipine is a dihydropyridine L-type calcium channel blocker. L-type calcium channels mediate the influx of calcium during depolarization in arterial smooth muscle. Experiments in anesthetized rats and dogs show that clevidipine reduces mean arterial blood pressure by decreasing systemic vascular resistance. Clevidipine does not reduce cardiac filling pressure (pre-load), confirming lack of effects on the venous capacitance vessels.          Cleviprex is titrated to the desired reduction in blood pressure. The effect of Cleviprex appears to plateau at approximately 25% of baseline systolic pressure. The infusion rate for which half the maximal effect is observed is approximately 10 mg/hour.  Onset of Effect: In the perioperative patient population, Cleviprex produces a 4-5% reduction in systolic blood pressure within 2-4 minutes after starting a 0.4 mcg/kg/min infusion (approximately 1-2 mg/hr).  Maintenance of Effect: In studies up to 72 hours of continuous infusion, there was no evidence of tolerance or hysteresis.  Offset of Effect: In most patients, full recovery of blood pressure is achieved in 5-15 minutes after the infusion is stopped. In studies up to 72 hours of continuous infusion, in patients that were not transitioned to other antihypertensive therapies, there was some evidence of rebound hypertension following Cleviprex discontinuation.  Hemodynamics: Cleviprex causes a dose-dependent decrease in systemic vascular resistance.  Heart Rate: An increase in heart rate is a normal response to vasodilation and decrease in blood pressure; in some patients these increases in heart rate may be pronounced  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)] .  Electrophysiologic Effects: In healthy volunteers, clevidipine or its major carboxylic acid metabolite, at therapeutic and supratherapeutic concentrations (approximately 2.8 times steady-state), did not prolong cardiac repolarization.          Clevidipine is rapidly distributed and metabolized resulting in a very short half life. The arterial blood concentration of clevidipine declines in a multi-phasic pattern following termination of the infusion. The initial phase half-life is approximately 1 minute, and accounts for 85-90% of clevidipine elimination. The terminal half-life is approximately 15 minutes.  Distribution: Clevidipine is &amp;gt;99.5% bound to proteins in plasma at 37°C. The steady-state volume of distribution was determined to be 0.17 L/kg in arterial blood.  Metabolism and Elimination: Clevidipine is rapidly metabolized by hydrolysis of the ester linkage, primarily by esterases in the blood and extravascular tissues, making its elimination unlikely to be affected by hepatic or renal dysfunction. The primary metabolites are the carboxylic acid metabolite and formaldehyde formed by hydrolysis of the ester group. The carboxylic acid metabolite is inactive as an antihypertensive. This metabolite is further metabolized by glucuronidation or oxidation to the corresponding pyridine derivative. The clearance of the primary dihydropyridine metabolite is 0.03 L/h/kg and the terminal half life is approximately 9 hours.  In vitro studies show that clevidipine and its metabolite at the concentrations achieved in clinical practice will not inhibit or induce any CYP enzyme. In a clinical study with radiolabeled clevidipine, 83% of the drug was excreted in urine and feces. The major fraction, 63-74% is excreted in the urine, 7-22% in the feces. More than 90% of the recovered radioactivity is excreted within the first 72 hours of collection.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="6392" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Cleviprex is contraindicated in patients with: Allergy to soy or eggs (4.1) Defective lipid metabolism (4.2) Severe aortic stenosis (4.3) Cleviprex is contraindicated in patients with allergies to soybeans, soy products, eggs, or egg products.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6393" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Cleviprex is contraindicated in patients with defective lipid metabolism such as pathologic hyperlipemia, lipoid nephrosis, or acute pancreatitis if it is accompanied by hyperlipidemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6394" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Cleviprex is contraindicated in patients with severe aortic stenosis because afterload reduction can be expected to reduce myocardial oxygen delivery.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6395" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For intravenous use: Cleviprex is intended for intravenous use.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6396" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Titrate Cleviprex to achieve the desired blood pressure reduction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6397" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Individualize dosage depending on the blood pressure response of the patient and the goal blood pressure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6398" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Monitoring: Monitor blood pressure and heart rate during infusion, and until vital signs stabilize.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6399" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Initial dose: Initiate intravenous infusion of Cleviprex at 1- 2 mg/hour.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6400" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dose titration: Double the dose at short (90 second) intervals initially.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6401" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>As the blood pressure approaches goal, increase the dose by less than doubling and lengthen the time between dose adjustments to every 5-10 minutes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6402" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>An approximately 1-2 mg/hour increase will generally produce an additional 2-4 mmHg decrease in systolic pressure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6403" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Maintenance dose: Most patients will achieve the desired therapeutic response at approximately 4-6 mg/hour.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6404" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Severe hypertension is likely to require higher doses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6405" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Maximum dose: Most patients have received maximum doses of 16 mg/hour or less.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6406" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>There is limited experience with short-term dosing as high as 32 mg/hour.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6407" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Because of lipid load restrictions, no more than 1000 mL or an average of 21 mg/hour of Cleviprex infusion is recommended per 24 hour period.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6408" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>There is little experience beyond 72 hours at any dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6409" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor blood pressure and heart rate continually during infusion, and then until vital signs are stable.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6410" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Patients who receive prolonged Cleviprex infusions and are not transitioned to other antihypertensive therapies should be monitored for the possibility of rebound hypertension for at least 8 hours after the infusion is stopped.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6411" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>These patients may need follow-up adjustments in blood pressure control.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6412" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Cleviprex is intended for intravenous use.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6413" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Titrate drug to achieve the desired blood pressure reduction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6414" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Individualize dosage depending on the blood pressure to be obtained and the response of the patient.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6415" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Initial dose: Initiate the intravenous infusion of Cleviprex at 1-2 mg/hour.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6416" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dose titration: The dose may be doubled at short (90 second) intervals initially.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6417" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>As the blood pressure approaches goal, the increase in doses should be less than doubling and the time between dose adjustments should be lengthened to every 5-10 minutes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6418" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Maintenance dose: The desired therapeutic response for most patients occurs at doses of 4-6 mg/hour.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6419" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Patients with severe hypertension may require doses up to 32 mg/hour, but there is limited experience at this dose rate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6420" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Maximum dose: Most patients were treated with maximum doses of 16 mg/hour or less.There is limited short-term experience with doses up to 32 mg/hour.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6421" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In clinical trials, 55 hypertensive patients were treated with &gt;500mL of Cleviprex infusion per 24 hour period.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6422" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>There is little experience with infusion durations beyond 72 hours at any dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6423" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Transition to an oral antihypertensive agent: Discontinue Cleviprex or titrate downward while appropriate oral therapy is established.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M1" type="Trigger" span="46 11" str="Discontinue "/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Trigger" span="71 16" str=" titrate downward"/>
<Mention id="M3" type="Precipitant" span="17 27" str="oral antihypertensive agent" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M1;M2" precipitant="M3"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6424" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>When an oral antihypertensive agent is being instituted, consider the lag time of onset of the oral agent’s effect.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M4" type="Trigger" span="57 21" str="consider the lag time"/>
<Mention id="M5" type="Precipitant" span="8 27" str="oral antihypertensive agent" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M4" precipitant="M5"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6425" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Continue blood pressure monitoring until desired effect is achieved.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6426" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Special populations: Special populations were not specifically studied.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6427" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In clinical trials, 78 patients with abnormal hepatic function (one or more of the following: elevated serum bilirubin, AST/SGOT, ALT/SGPT) and 121 patients with moderate to severe renal impairment were treated with Cleviprex.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6428" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>An initial Cleviprex infusion rate of 1-2 mg/hour is appropriate in these patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6429" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Table 1 is a guideline for dosing conversion from mg/hour to mL/hour.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6430" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dose conversion Dose (mg/hour) Dose (mL/hour) 1 2 2 4 4 8 6 12 8 16 10 20 12 24 14 28 16 32 18 36 20 40 22 44 24 48 26 52 28 56 30 60 32 64 Maintain aseptic technique while handling Cleviprex.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6431" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Cleviprex is a single-use parenteral product.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6432" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not use if contamination is suspected.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6433" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Once the stopper is punctured, use within 12 hours and discard any unused portion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6434" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Cleviprex is supplied in sterile, pre-mixed, ready-to-use 50 mL, or 100 mL, or 250 mL vials.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6435" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Invert vial gently several times before use to ensure uniformity of the emulsion prior to administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6436" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Inspect parenteral drug products for particulate matter and discoloration prior to administration whenever solution and container permit.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6437" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Administer Cleviprex using an infusion device allowing calibrated infusion rates.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6438" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Commercially available standard plastic cannulae may be used to administer the infusion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6439" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Administer Cleviprex by a central line or a peripheral line.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6440" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Cleviprex should not be administered in the same line as other medications.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6441" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Cleviprex should not be diluted, but it can be administered with the following: Water for Injection, USP Sodium Chloride (0.9%) Injection, USP Dextrose (5%) Injection, USP Dextrose (5%) in Sodium Chloride (0.9%) Injection, USP Dextrose (5%) in Ringers Lactate Injection, USP Lactated Ringers Injection, USP 10% amino acid</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6442" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>No clinical drug interaction studies were conducted.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6443" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Clevidipine and its major dihydropyridine metabolite do not have the potential for blocking or inducing any CYP enzyme.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6444" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>At clinically relevant concentrations, clevidipine and its metabolites do not inhibit or induce any CYP450 enzymes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6445" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The potential of clevidipine to interact with other drugs is low.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6446" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Discard unused portion 12 hours after stopper puncture.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6447" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hypotension and reflex tachycardia are potential consequences of rapid upward titration of Cleviprex.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6448" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Dihydropyridine calcium channel blockers can produce negative inotropic effects and exacerbate heart failure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6449" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor heart failure patients carefully.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6450" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Cleviprex gives no protection against the effects of abrupt beta-blocker withdrawal.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6451" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Use aseptic technique and discard any unused product within 12 hours of stopper puncture.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6452" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Cleviprex may produce systemic hypotension and reflex tachycardia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6453" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If either occurs, decrease the dose of Cleviprex.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6454" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There is limited experience with short-duration therapy with beta-blockers as a treatment for Cleviprex-induced tachycardia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6455" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Beta-blocker use for this purpose is not recommended.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6456" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Cleviprex contains approximately 0.2 g of lipid per mL (2.0 kcal).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6457" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Lipid intake restrictions may be necessary for patients with significant disorders of lipid metabolism.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6458" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>For these patients, a reduction in the quantity of concurrently administered lipids may be necessary to compensate for the amount of lipid infused as part of the Cleviprex formulation.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M6" type="Trigger" span="22 25" str="reduction in the quantity"/>
<Mention id="M7" type="Precipitant" span="77 6" str="lipids" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M6" precipitant="M7"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6459" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Cleviprex is not a beta-blocker, does not reduce heart rate, and gives no protection against the effects of abrupt beta-blocker withdrawal.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6460" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Beta-blockers should be withdrawn only after a gradual reduction in dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6461" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There is no information to guide use of Cleviprex in treating hypertension associated with pheochromocytoma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6462" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Clevidipine is a dihydropyridine L-type calcium channel blocker.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6463" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>L-type calcium channels mediate the influx of calcium during depolarization in arterial smooth muscle.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6464" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Experiments in anesthetized rats and dogs show that clevidipine reduces mean arterial blood pressure by decreasing systemic vascular resistance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6465" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Clevidipine does not reduce cardiac filling pressure (pre-load), confirming lack of effects on the venous capacitance vessels.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6466" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Cleviprex is titrated to the desired reduction in blood pressure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6467" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The effect of Cleviprex appears to plateau at approximately 25% of baseline systolic pressure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6468" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The infusion rate for which half the maximal effect is observed is approximately 10 mg/hour.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6469" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Onset of Effect: In the perioperative patient population, Cleviprex produces a 4-5% reduction in systolic blood pressure within 2-4 minutes after starting a 0.4 mcg/kg/min infusion (approximately 1-2 mg/hr).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6470" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Maintenance of Effect: In studies up to 72 hours of continuous infusion, there was no evidence of tolerance or hysteresis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6471" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Offset of Effect: In most patients, full recovery of blood pressure is achieved in 5-15 minutes after the infusion is stopped.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6472" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In studies up to 72 hours of continuous infusion, in patients that were not transitioned to other antihypertensive therapies, there was some evidence of rebound hypertension following Cleviprex discontinuation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6473" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Hemodynamics: Cleviprex causes a dose-dependent decrease in systemic vascular resistance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6474" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Heart Rate:An increase in heart rate is a normal response to vasodilation and decrease in blood pressure; in some patients these increases in heart rate may be pronounced.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6475" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Electrophysiologic Effects:In healthy volunteers, clevidipine or its major carboxylic acid metabolite, at therapeutic and supratherapeutic concentrations (approximately 2.8 times steady-state), did not prolong cardiac repolarization.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6476" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Clevidipine is rapidly distributed and metabolized resulting in a very short half life.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6477" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The arterial blood concentration of clevidipine declines in a multi-phasic pattern following termination of the infusion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6478" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The initial phase half-life is approximately 1 minute, and accounts for 85-90% of clevidipine elimination.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6479" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The terminal half-life is approximately 15 minutes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6480" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Distribution: Clevidipine is &gt;99.5% bound to proteins in plasma at 37°C.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6481" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The steady-state volume of distribution was determined to be 0.17 L/kg in arterial blood.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6482" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Metabolism and Elimination: Clevidipine is rapidly metabolized by hydrolysis of the ester linkage, primarily by esterases in the blood and extravascular tissues, making its elimination unlikely to be affected by hepatic or renal dysfunction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6483" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The primary metabolites are the carboxylic acid metabolite and formaldehyde formed by hydrolysis of the ester group.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6484" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The carboxylic acid metabolite is inactive as an antihypertensive.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6485" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This metabolite is further metabolized by glucuronidation or oxidation to the corresponding pyridine derivative.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6486" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The clearance of the primary dihydropyridine metabolite is 0.03 L/h/kg and the terminal half-life is approximately 9 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6487" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In vitro studies show that clevidipine and its metabolite at the concentrations achieved in clinical practice will not inhibit or induce any CYP enzyme.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6488" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In a clinical study with radiolabeled clevidipine, 83% of the drug was excreted in urine and feces.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6489" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The major fraction, 63-74% is excreted in the urine, 7-22% in the feces.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6490" LabelDrug="Cleviprex" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>More than 90% of the recovered radioactivity is excreted within the first 72 hours of collection.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="oral antihypertensive agent" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="lipids" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>