<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="COREG" setid="c57982f2-c7da-488a-7ea9-b9609439ac68">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
COREG is contraindicated in the following conditions:   •Bronchial asthma or related bronchospastic conditions. Deaths from status asthmaticus have been reported following single doses of COREG.  •Second- or third-degree AV block.  •Sick sinus syndrome.  •Severe bradycardia (unless a permanent pacemaker is in place).  •Patients with cardiogenic shock or who have decompensated heart failure requiring the use of intravenous inotropic therapy. Such patients should first be weaned from intravenous therapy before initiating COREG.  •Patients with severe hepatic impairment.  •Patients with a history of a serious hypersensitivity reaction (e.g., Stevens-Johnson syndrome, anaphylactic reaction, angioedema) to any component of this medication or other medications containing carvedilol.         •Bronchial asthma or related bronchospastic conditions. (4)  •Second- or third-degree AV block. (4)  •Sick sinus syndrome. (4)  •Severe bradycardia (unless permanent pacemaker in place). (4)  •Patients in cardiogenic shock or decompensated heart failure requiring the use of IV inotropic therapy. (4)  •Severe hepatic impairment (2.4, 4).  •History of serious hypersensitivity reaction (e.g., Stevens-Johnson syndrome, anaphylactic reaction, angioedema) to any component of this medication or other medications containing carvedilol. (4)</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
COREG should be taken with food to slow the rate of absorption and reduce the incidence of orthostatic effects.      Take with food. Individualize dosage and monitor during up-titration. (2)   •Heart failure: Start at 3.125 mg twice daily and increase to 6.25, 12.5, and then 25 mg twice daily over intervals of at least 2 weeks. Maintain lower doses if higher doses are not tolerated. (2.1)  •Left ventricular dysfunction following myocardial infarction: Start at 6.25 mg twice daily and increase to 12.5 mg then 25 mg twice daily after intervals of 3 to 10 days. A lower starting dose or slower titration may be used. (2.2)  •Hypertension: Start at 6.25 mg twice daily and increase if needed for blood pressure control to 12.5 mg then 25 mg twice daily over intervals of 1 to 2 weeks. (2.3)          DOSAGE MUST BE INDIVIDUALIZED AND CLOSELY MONITORED BY A PHYSICIAN DURING UP-TITRATION. Prior to initiation of COREG, it is recommended that fluid retention be minimized. The recommended starting dose of COREG is 3.125 mg twice daily for 2 weeks. If tolerated, patients may have their dose increased to 6.25, 12.5, and 25 mg twice daily over successive intervals of at least 2 weeks. Patients should be maintained on lower doses if higher doses are not tolerated. A maximum dose of 50 mg twice daily has been administered to patients with mild-to-moderate heart failure weighing over 85 kg (187 lbs). Patients should be advised that initiation of treatment and (to a lesser extent) dosage increases may be associated with transient symptoms of dizziness or lightheadedness (and rarely syncope) within the first hour after dosing. During these periods, patients should avoid situations such as driving or hazardous tasks, where symptoms could result in injury. Vasodilatory symptoms often do not require treatment, but it may be useful to separate the time of dosing of COREG from that of the ACE inhibitor or to reduce temporarily the dose of the ACE inhibitor. The dose of COREG should not be increased until symptoms of worsening heart failure or vasodilation have been stabilized. Fluid retention (with or without transient worsening heart failure symptoms) should be treated by an increase in the dose of diuretics. The dose of COREG should be reduced if patients experience bradycardia (heart rate &amp;lt;55 beats/minute). Episodes of dizziness or fluid retention during initiation of COREG can generally be managed without discontinuation of treatment and do not preclude subsequent successful titration of, or a favorable response to, carvedilol.          DOSAGE MUST BE INDIVIDUALIZED AND MONITORED DURING UP-TITRATION. Treatment with COREG may be started as an inpatient or outpatient and should be started after the patient is hemodynamically stable and fluid retention has been minimized. It is recommended that COREG be started at 6.25 mg twice daily and increased after 3 to 10 days, based on tolerability, to 12.5 mg twice daily, then again to the target dose of 25 mg twice daily. A lower starting dose may be used (3.125 mg twice daily) and/or the rate of up-titration may be slowed if clinically indicated (e.g., due to low blood pressure or heart rate, or fluid retention). Patients should be maintained on lower doses if higher doses are not tolerated. The recommended dosing regimen need not be altered in patients who received treatment with an IV or oral β-blocker during the acute phase of the myocardial infarction.          DOSAGE MUST BE INDIVIDUALIZED. The recommended starting dose of COREG is 6.25 mg twice daily. If this dose is tolerated, using standing systolic pressure measured about 1 hour after dosing as a guide, the dose should be maintained for 7 to 14 days, and then increased to 12.5 mg twice daily if needed, based on trough blood pressure, again using standing systolic pressure one hour after dosing as a guide for tolerance. This dose should also be maintained for 7 to 14 days and can then be adjusted upward to 25 mg twice daily if tolerated and needed. The full antihypertensive effect of COREG is seen within 7 to 14 days. Total daily dose should not exceed 50 mg. Concomitant administration with a diuretic can be expected to produce additive effects and exaggerate the orthostatic component of carvedilol action.          COREG should not be given to patients with severe hepatic impairment [see Contraindications (4)].</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
•CYP P450 2D6 enzyme inhibitors may increase and rifampin may decrease carvedilol levels. (7.1, 7.5)  •Hypotensive agents (e.g., reserpine, MAO inhibitors, clonidine) may increase the risk of hypotension and/or severe bradycardia. (7.2)  •Cyclosporine or digoxin levels may increase. (7.3, 7.4)  •Both digitalis glycosides and β-blockers slow atrioventricular conduction and decrease heart rate. Concomitant use can increase the risk of bradycardia. (7.4)  •Amiodarone may increase carvedilol levels resulting in further slowing of the heart rate or cardiac conduction. (7.6)  •Verapamil- or diltiazem-type calcium channel blockers may affect ECG and/or blood pressure. (7.7)  •Insulin and oral hypoglycemics action may be enhanced. (7.8)          Interactions of carvedilol with potent inhibitors of CYP2D6 isoenzyme (such as quinidine, fluoxetine, paroxetine, and propafenone) have not been studied, but these drugs would be expected to increase blood levels of the R(+) enantiomer of carvedilol [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)]. Retrospective analysis of side effects in clinical trials showed that poor 2D6 metabolizers had a higher rate of dizziness during up-titration, presumably resulting from vasodilating effects of the higher concentrations of the α-blocking R(+) enantiomer.          Patients taking both agents with β-blocking properties and a drug that can deplete catecholamines (e.g., reserpine and monoamine oxidase inhibitors) should be observed closely for signs of hypotension and/or severe bradycardia. Concomitant administration of clonidine with agents with β-blocking properties may potentiate blood-pressure- and heart-rate-lowering effects. When concomitant treatment with agents with β-blocking properties and clonidine is to be terminated, the β-blocking agent should be discontinued first. Clonidine therapy can then be discontinued several days later by gradually decreasing the dosage.          Modest increases in mean trough cyclosporine concentrations were observed following initiation of carvedilol treatment in 21 renal transplant subjects suffering from chronic vascular rejection. In about 30% of subjects, the dose of cyclosporine had to be reduced in order to maintain cyclosporine concentrations within the therapeutic range, while in the remainder no adjustment was needed. On the average for the group, the dose of cyclosporine was reduced about 20% in these subjects. Due to wide interindividual variability in the dose adjustment required, it is recommended that cyclosporine concentrations be monitored closely after initiation of carvedilol therapy and that the dose of cyclosporine be adjusted as appropriate.          Both digitalis glycosides and β-blockers slow atrioventricular conduction and decrease heart rate. Concomitant use can increase the risk of bradycardia. Digoxin concentrations are increased by about 15% when digoxin and carvedilol are administered concomitantly. Therefore, increased monitoring of digoxin is recommended when initiating, adjusting, or discontinuing COREG [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.5)].          Rifampin reduced plasma concentrations of carvedilol by about 70% [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.5)]. Cimetidine increased AUC by about 30% but caused no change in Cmax [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.5)].          Amiodarone, and its metabolite desethyl amiodarone, inhibitors of CYP2C9 and P-glycoprotein, increased concentrations of the S(-)-enantiomer of carvedilol by at least 2-fold [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.5)]. The concomitant administration of amiodarone or other CYP2C9 inhibitors such as fluconazole with COREG may enhance the β-blocking properties of carvedilol resulting in further slowing of the heart rate or cardiac conduction. Patients should be observed for signs of bradycardia or heart block, particularly when one agent is added to pre-existing treatment with the other.          Conduction disturbance (rarely with hemodynamic compromise) has been observed when COREG is co-administered with diltiazem. As with other agents with β-blocking properties, if COREG is to be administered with calcium channel blockers of the verapamil or diltiazem type, it is recommended that ECG and blood pressure be monitored.          Agents with β-blocking properties may enhance the blood-sugar-reducing effect of insulin and oral hypoglycemics. Therefore, in patients taking insulin or oral hypoglycemics, regular monitoring of blood glucose is recommended [see Warnings and Precautions (5.6)].          If treatment with COREG is to be continued perioperatively, particular care should be taken when anesthetic agents which depress myocardial function, such as ether, cyclopropane, and trichloroethylene, are used [see Overdosage (10)].</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
•Acute exacerbation of coronary artery disease upon cessation of therapy: Do not abruptly discontinue. (5.1)  •Bradycardia, hypotension, worsening heart failure/fluid retention may occur. Reduce the dose as needed. (5.2, 5.3, 5.4)  •Non-allergic bronchospasm (e.g., chronic bronchitis and emphysema): Avoid β-blockers. (4) However, if deemed necessary, use with caution and at lowest effective dose. (5.5)  •Diabetes: Monitor glucose as β-blockers may mask symptoms of hypoglycemia or worsen hyperglycemia. (5.6)           Patients with coronary artery disease, who are being treated with COREG, should be advised against abrupt discontinuation of therapy. Severe exacerbation of angina and the occurrence of myocardial infarction and ventricular arrhythmias have been reported in angina patients following the abrupt discontinuation of therapy with β-blockers. The last 2 complications may occur with or without preceding exacerbation of the angina pectoris. As with other β-blockers, when discontinuation of COREG is planned, the patients should be carefully observed and advised to limit physical activity to a minimum. COREG should be discontinued over 1 to 2 weeks whenever possible. If the angina worsens or acute coronary insufficiency develops, it is recommended that COREG be promptly reinstituted, at least temporarily. Because coronary artery disease is common and may be unrecognized, it may be prudent not to discontinue therapy with COREG abruptly even in patients treated only for hypertension or heart failure.           In clinical trials, COREG caused bradycardia in about 2% of hypertensive subjects, 9% of heart failure subjects, and 6.5% of myocardial infarction subjects with left ventricular dysfunction. If pulse rate drops below 55 beats/minute, the dosage should be reduced.          In clinical trials of primarily mild‑to‑moderate heart failure, hypotension and postural hypotension occurred in 9.7% and syncope in 3.4% of subjects receiving COREG compared with 3.6% and 2.5% of placebo subjects, respectively. The risk for these events was highest during the first 30 days of dosing, corresponding to the up‑titration period and was a cause for discontinuation of therapy in 0.7% of subjects receiving COREG, compared with 0.4% of placebo subjects. In a long‑term, placebo‑controlled trial in severe heart failure (COPERNICUS), hypotension and postural hypotension occurred in 15.1% and syncope in 2.9% of heart failure subjects receiving COREG compared with 8.7% and 2.3% of placebo subjects, respectively. These events were a cause for discontinuation of therapy in 1.1% of subjects receiving COREG, compared with 0.8% of placebo subjects. Postural hypotension occurred in 1.8% and syncope in 0.1% of hypertensive subjects, primarily following the initial dose or at the time of dose increase and was a cause for discontinuation of therapy in 1% of subjects. In the CAPRICORN trial of survivors of an acute myocardial infarction, hypotension or postural hypotension occurred in 20.2% of subjects receiving COREG compared with 12.6% of placebo subjects. Syncope was reported in 3.9% and 1.9% of subjects, respectively. These events were a cause for discontinuation of therapy in 2.5% of subjects receiving COREG, compared with 0.2% of placebo subjects. Starting with a low dose, administration with food, and gradual up-titration should decrease the likelihood of syncope or excessive hypotension [see Dosage and Administration (2.1, 2.2, 2.3)]. During initiation of therapy, the patient should be cautioned to avoid situations such as driving or hazardous tasks, where injury could result should syncope occur.          Worsening heart failure or fluid retention may occur during up-titration of carvedilol. If such symptoms occur, diuretics should be increased and the carvedilol dose should not be advanced until clinical stability resumes [see Dosage and Administration (2)]. Occasionally it is necessary to lower the carvedilol dose or temporarily discontinue it. Such episodes do not preclude subsequent successful titration of, or a favorable response to, carvedilol. In a placebo-controlled trial of subjects with severe heart failure, worsening heart failure during the first 3 months was reported to a similar degree with carvedilol and with placebo. When treatment was maintained beyond 3 months, worsening heart failure was reported less frequently in subjects treated with carvedilol than with placebo. Worsening heart failure observed during long-term therapy is more likely to be related to the patients’ underlying disease than to treatment with carvedilol.          Patients with bronchospastic disease (e.g., chronic bronchitis and emphysema) should, in general, not receive β-blockers. COREG may be used with caution, however, in patients who do not respond to, or cannot tolerate, other antihypertensive agents. It is prudent, if COREG is used, to use the smallest effective dose, so that inhibition of endogenous or exogenous β-agonists is minimized. In clinical trials of subjects with heart failure, subjects with bronchospastic disease were enrolled if they did not require oral or inhaled medication to treat their bronchospastic disease. In such patients, it is recommended that carvedilol be used with caution. The dosing recommendations should be followed closely and the dose should be lowered if any evidence of bronchospasm is observed during up-titration.          In general, β-blockers may mask some of the manifestations of hypoglycemia, particularly tachycardia. Nonselective β-blockers may potentiate insulin-induced hypoglycemia and delay recovery of serum glucose levels. Patients subject to spontaneous hypoglycemia, or diabetic patients receiving insulin or oral hypoglycemic agents, should be cautioned about these possibilities. In heart failure patients with diabetes, carvedilol therapy may lead to worsening hyperglycemia, which responds to intensification of hypoglycemic therapy. It is recommended that blood glucose be monitored when carvedilol dosing is initiated, adjusted, or discontinued. Trials designed to examine the effects of carvedilol on glycemic control in patients with diabetes and heart failure have not been conducted. In a trial designed to examine the effects of carvedilol on glycemic control in a population with mild-to-moderate hypertension and well-controlled type 2 diabetes mellitus, carvedilol had no adverse effect on glycemic control, based on HbA1c measurements [see Clinical Studies (14.4)].           β-blockers can precipitate or aggravate symptoms of arterial insufficiency in patients with peripheral vascular disease. Caution should be exercised in such individuals.          Rarely, use of carvedilol in patients with heart failure has resulted in deterioration of renal function. Patients at risk appear to be those with low blood pressure (systolic blood pressure &amp;lt;100 mm Hg), ischemic heart disease and diffuse vascular disease, and/or underlying renal insufficiency. Renal function has returned to baseline when carvedilol was stopped. In patients with these risk factors it is recommended that renal function be monitored during up-titration of carvedilol and the drug discontinued or dosage reduced if worsening of renal function occurs.          Chronically administered beta-blocking therapy should not be routinely withdrawn prior to major surgery; however, the impaired ability of the heart to respond to reflex adrenergic stimuli may augment the risks of general anesthesia and surgical procedures.          β-adrenergic blockade may mask clinical signs of hyperthyroidism, such as tachycardia. Abrupt withdrawal of β-blockade may be followed by an exacerbation of the symptoms of hyperthyroidism or may precipitate thyroid storm.          In patients with pheochromocytoma, an α-blocking agent should be initiated prior to the use of any β-blocking agent. Although carvedilol has both α- and β-blocking pharmacologic activities, there has been no experience with its use in this condition. Therefore, caution should be taken in the administration of carvedilol to patients suspected of having pheochromocytoma.          Agents with non-selective β-blocking activity may provoke chest pain in patients with Prinzmetal’s variant angina. There has been no clinical experience with carvedilol in these patients although the α-blocking activity may prevent such symptoms. However, caution should be taken in the administration of carvedilol to patients suspected of having Prinzmetal’s variant angina.          While taking β-blockers, patients with a history of severe anaphylactic reaction to a variety of allergens may be more reactive to repeated challenge, either accidental, diagnostic, or therapeutic. Such patients may be unresponsive to the usual doses of epinephrine used to treat allergic reaction.          Intraoperative Floppy Iris Syndrome (IFIS) has been observed during cataract surgery in some patients treated with alpha-1 blockers (COREG is an alpha/beta blocker). This variant of small pupil syndrome is characterized by the combination of a flaccid iris that billows in response to intraoperative irrigation currents, progressive intraoperative miosis despite preoperative dilation with standard mydriatic drugs, and potential prolapse of the iris toward the phacoemulsification incisions. The patient’s ophthalmologist should be prepared for possible modifications to the surgical technique, such as utilization of iris hooks, iris dilator rings, or viscoelastic substances. There does not appear to be a benefit of stopping alpha-1 blocker therapy prior to cataract surgery.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
COREG is a racemic mixture in which nonselective β-adrenoreceptor blocking activity is present in the S(-) enantiomer and α1-adrenergic blocking activity is present in both R(+) and S(-) enantiomers at equal potency. COREG has no intrinsic sympathomimetic activity.               The basis for the beneficial effects of COREG in heart failure is not established. Two placebo‑controlled trials compared the acute hemodynamic effects of COREG with baseline measurements in 59 and 49 subjects with NYHA class II‑IV heart failure receiving diuretics, ACE inhibitors, and digitalis. There were significant reductions in systemic blood pressure, pulmonary artery pressure, pulmonary capillary wedge pressure, and heart rate. Initial effects on cardiac output, stroke volume index, and systemic vascular resistance were small and variable. These trials measured hemodynamic effects again at 12 to 14 weeks. COREG significantly reduced systemic blood pressure, pulmonary artery pressure, right atrial pressure, systemic vascular resistance, and heart rate, while stroke volume index was increased. Among 839 subjects with NYHA class II‑III heart failure treated for 26 to 52 weeks in 4 US placebo‑controlled trials, average left ventricular ejection fraction (EF) measured by radionuclide ventriculography increased by 9 EF units (%) in subjects receiving COREG and by 2 EF units in placebo subjects at a target dose of 25 to 50 mg twice daily. The effects of carvedilol on ejection fraction were related to dose. Doses of 6.25 mg twice daily, 12.5 mg twice daily, and 25 mg twice daily were associated with placebo‑corrected increases in EF of 5 EF units, 6 EF units, and 8 EF units, respectively; each of these effects were nominally statistically significant.          The basis for the beneficial effects of COREG in patients with left ventricular dysfunction following an acute myocardial infarction is not established.          The mechanism by which β-blockade produces an antihypertensive effect has not been established. β-adrenoreceptor blocking activity has been demonstrated in animal and human studies showing that carvedilol (1) reduces cardiac output in normal subjects; (2) reduces exercise- and/or isoproterenol-induced tachycardia; and (3) reduces reflex orthostatic tachycardia. Significant β-adrenoreceptor blocking effect is usually seen within 1 hour of drug administration. α1-adrenoreceptor blocking activity has been demonstrated in human and animal studies, showing that carvedilol (1) attenuates the pressor effects of phenylephrine; (2) causes vasodilation; and (3) reduces peripheral vascular resistance. These effects contribute to the reduction of blood pressure and usually are seen within 30 minutes of drug administration. Due to the α1-receptor blocking activity of carvedilol, blood pressure is lowered more in the standing than in the supine position, and symptoms of postural hypotension (1.8%), including rare instances of syncope, can occur. Following oral administration, when postural hypotension has occurred, it has been transient and is uncommon when COREG is administered with food at the recommended starting dose and titration increments are closely followed [see Dosage and Administration (2)]. In hypertensive patients with normal renal function, therapeutic doses of COREG decreased renal vascular resistance with no change in glomerular filtration rate or renal plasma flow. Changes in excretion of sodium, potassium, uric acid, and phosphorus in hypertensive patients with normal renal function were similar after COREG and placebo. COREG has little effect on plasma catecholamines, plasma aldosterone, or electrolyte levels, but it does significantly reduce plasma renin activity when given for at least 4 weeks. It also increases levels of atrial natriuretic peptide.            COREG is rapidly and extensively absorbed following oral administration, with absolute bioavailability of approximately 25% to 35% due to a significant degree of first-pass metabolism. Following oral administration, the apparent mean terminal elimination half-life of carvedilol generally ranges from 7 to 10 hours. Plasma concentrations achieved are proportional to the oral dose administered. When administered with food, the rate of absorption is slowed, as evidenced by a delay in the time to reach peak plasma levels, with no significant difference in extent of bioavailability. Taking COREG with food should minimize the risk of orthostatic hypotension. Carvedilol is extensively metabolized. Following oral administration of radiolabelled carvedilol to healthy volunteers, carvedilol accounted for only about 7% of the total radioactivity in plasma as measured by area under the curve (AUC). Less than 2% of the dose was excreted unchanged in the urine. Carvedilol is metabolized primarily by aromatic ring oxidation and glucuronidation. The oxidative metabolites are further metabolized by conjugation via glucuronidation and sulfation. The metabolites of carvedilol are excreted primarily via the bile into the feces. Demethylation and hydroxylation at the phenol ring produce 3 active metabolites with β-receptor blocking activity. Based on preclinical studies, the 4'-hydroxyphenyl metabolite is approximately 13 times more potent than carvedilol for β-blockade. Compared with carvedilol, the 3 active metabolites exhibit weak vasodilating activity. Plasma concentrations of the active metabolites are about one-tenth of those observed for carvedilol and have pharmacokinetics similar to the parent. Carvedilol undergoes stereoselective first-pass metabolism with plasma levels of R(+)-carvedilol approximately 2 to 3 times higher than S(-)-carvedilol following oral administration in healthy subjects. The mean apparent terminal elimination half-lives for R(+)-carvedilol range from 5 to 9 hours compared with 7 to 11 hours for the S(-)-enantiomer. The primary P450 enzymes responsible for the metabolism of both R(+) and S(-)-carvedilol in human liver microsomes were CYP2D6 and CYP2C9 and to a lesser extent CYP3A4, 2C19, 1A2, and 2E1. CYP2D6 is thought to be the major enzyme in the 4’- and 5’-hydroxylation of carvedilol, with a potential contribution from 3A4. CYP2C9 is thought to be of primary importance in the O-methylation pathway of S(-)-carvedilol. Carvedilol is subject to the effects of genetic polymorphism with poor metabolizers of debrisoquin (a marker for cytochrome P450 2D6) exhibiting 2- to 3-fold higher plasma concentrations of R(+)-carvedilol compared with extensive metabolizers. In contrast, plasma levels of S(-)-carvedilol are increased only about 20% to 25% in poor metabolizers, indicating this enantiomer is metabolized to a lesser extent by cytochrome P450 2D6 than R(+)-carvedilol. The pharmacokinetics of carvedilol do not appear to be different in poor metabolizers of S-mephenytoin (patients deficient in cytochrome P450 2C19). Carvedilol is more than 98% bound to plasma proteins, primarily with albumin. The plasma-protein binding is independent of concentration over the therapeutic range. Carvedilol is a basic, lipophilic compound with a steady-state volume of distribution of approximately 115 L, indicating substantial distribution into extravascular tissues. Plasma clearance ranges from 500 to 700 mL/min.               Steady‑state plasma concentrations of carvedilol and its enantiomers increased proportionally over the 6.25 to 50 mg dose range in subjects with heart failure. Compared with healthy subjects, heart failure subjects had increased mean AUC and Cmax values for carvedilol and its enantiomers, with up to 50% to 100% higher values observed in 6 subjects with NYHA class IV heart failure. The mean apparent terminal elimination half‑life for carvedilol was similar to that observed in healthy subjects.          Plasma levels of carvedilol average about 50% higher in the elderly compared with young subjects.          Compared with healthy subjects, patients with severe liver impairment (cirrhosis) exhibit a 4- to 7-fold increase in carvedilol levels. Carvedilol is contraindicated in patients with severe liver impairment.           Although carvedilol is metabolized primarily by the liver, plasma concentrations of carvedilol have been reported to be increased in patients with renal impairment. Based on mean AUC data, approximately 40% to 50% higher plasma concentrations of carvedilol were observed in hypertensive subjects with moderate to severe renal impairment compared to a control group of hypertensive subjects with normal renal function. However, the ranges of AUC values were similar for both groups. Changes in mean peak plasma levels were less pronounced, approximately 12% to 26% higher in subjects with impaired renal function. Consistent with its high degree of plasma protein‑binding, carvedilol does not appear to be cleared significantly by hemodialysis.            Since carvedilol undergoes substantial oxidative metabolism, the metabolism and pharmacokinetics of carvedilol may be affected by induction or inhibition of cytochrome P450 enzymes.        In a pharmacokinetic trial conducted in 106 Japanese subjects with heart failure, coadministration of small loading and maintenance doses of amiodarone with carvedilol resulted in at least a 2-fold increase in the steady-state trough concentrations of S(-)-carvedilol [see Drug Interactions (7.6)].          In a pharmacokinetic trial conducted in 10 healthy male subjects, cimetidine (1,000 mg/day) increased the steady-state AUC of carvedilol by 30% with no change in Cmax [see Drug Interactions (7.5)].          Following concomitant administration of carvedilol (25 mg once daily) and digoxin (0.25 mg once daily) for 14 days, steady-state AUC and trough concentrations of digoxin were increased by 14% and 16%, respectively, in 12 hypertensive subjects [see Drug Interactions (7.4)].          In 12 healthy subjects, combined administration of carvedilol (25 mg once daily) and a single dose of glyburide did not result in a clinically relevant pharmacokinetic interaction for either compound.          A single oral dose of carvedilol 25 mg did not alter the pharmacokinetics of a single oral dose of hydrochlorothiazide 25 mg in 12 subjects with hypertension. Likewise, hydrochlorothiazide had no effect on the pharmacokinetics of carvedilol.          In a pharmacokinetic trial conducted in 8 healthy male subjects, rifampin (600 mg daily for 12 days) decreased the AUC and Cmax of carvedilol by about 70% [see Drug Interactions (7.5)].          In a trial of 12 healthy subjects, combined oral administration of carvedilol 25 mg once daily and torsemide 5 mg once daily for 5 days did not result in any significant differences in their pharmacokinetics compared with administration of the drugs alone.          Carvedilol (12.5 mg twice daily) did not have an effect on the steady-state prothrombin time ratios and did not alter the pharmacokinetics of R(+)- and S(-)-warfarin following concomitant administration with warfarin in 9 healthy volunteers.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="5699" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>COREG is contraindicated in the following conditions: •Bronchial asthma or related bronchospastic conditions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5700" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Deaths from status asthmaticus have been reported following single doses of COREG.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5701" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>•Severe bradycardia (unless a permanent pacemaker is in place).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5702" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>•Patients with cardiogenic shock or who have decompensated heart failure requiring the use of intravenous inotropic therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5703" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Such patients should first be weaned from intravenous therapy before initiating COREG.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5704" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>•Patients with severe hepatic impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5705" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>•Patients with a history of a serious hypersensitivity reaction (e.g., Stevens-Johnson syndrome, anaphylactic reaction, angioedema) to any component of this medication or other medications containing carvedilol.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5706" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>•Bronchial asthma or related bronchospastic conditions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5707" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>•Second-orthird-degree AV block.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5708" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>•Severe bradycardia (unless permanent pacemaker in place).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5709" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>•Patients in cardiogenic shock or decompensated heart failure requiring the use of IV inotropic therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5710" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>•History of serious hypersensitivity reaction (e.g., Stevens-Johnson syndrome, anaphylactic reaction, angioedema) to any component of this medication or other medications containing carvedilol.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5711" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>COREG should be taken with food to slow the rate of absorption and reduce the incidence of orthostatic effects.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M1" type="Trigger" span="67 20" str="reduce the incidence"/>
<Mention id="M5" type="Precipitant" span="27 4" str="food" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M3" type="SpecificInteraction" span="91 19" str="orthostatic effects" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M4" type="Trigger" span="35 27" str="slow the rate of absorption"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M1" precipitant="M5" effect="M3"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M4" precipitant="M5" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5712" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Individualize dosage and monitor during up-titration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5713" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>•Heart failure: Start at 3.125mg twice daily and increase to 6.25, 12.5, and then 25mg twice daily over intervals of at least 2 weeks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5714" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Maintain lower doses if higher doses are not tolerated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5715" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>•Left ventricular dysfunction following myocardial infarction: Start at 6.25mg twice daily and increase to 12.5 mg then 25 mg twice daily after intervals of 3 to 10days.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5716" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>A lower starting dose or slower titration may be used.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5717" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>•Hypertension: Start at 6.25mg twice daily and increase if needed for blood pressure control to 12.5mg then 25mg twice daily over intervals of 1to2 weeks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5718" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>DOSAGE MUST BE INDIVIDUALIZED AND CLOSELY MONITORED BY A PHYSICIAN DURING UP-TITRATION.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5719" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Prior to initiation of COREG, it is recommended that fluid retention be minimized.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5720" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommended starting dose of COREG is 3.125mg twice daily for 2 weeks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5721" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If tolerated, patients may have their dose increased to 6.25, 12.5, and 25mg twice daily over successive intervals of at least 2 weeks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5722" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Patients should be maintained on lower doses if higher doses are not tolerated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5723" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>A maximum dose of 50mg twice daily has been administered to patients with mild-to-moderate heart failure weighing over 85kg (187lbs).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5724" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Patients should be advised that initiation of treatment and (to a lesser extent) dosage increases may be associated with transient symptoms of dizziness or lightheadedness (and rarely syncope) within the first hour after dosing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5725" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>During these periods, patients should avoid situations such as driving or hazardous tasks, where symptoms could result in injury.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5726" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Vasodilatory symptoms often do not require treatment, but it may be useful to separate the time of dosing of COREG from that of the ACE inhibitor or to reduce temporarily the dose of the ACE inhibitor.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M6" type="Trigger" span="78 27" str="separate the time of dosing"/>
<Mention id="M7" type="Precipitant" span="132 13" str="ACE inhibitor" code="N0000175562"/>
<Mention id="M8" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 21" str="Vasodilatory symptoms" code="91081006: Vasodilatation (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M6" precipitant="M7" effect="M8"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5727" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The dose of COREG should not be increased until symptoms of worsening heart failure or vasodilation have been stabilized.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5728" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Fluid retention (with or without transient worsening heart failure symptoms) should be treated by an increase in the dose of diuretics.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M12" type="Trigger" span="77 44" str="should be treated by an increase in the dose"/>
<Mention id="M13" type="Precipitant" span="125 9" str="diuretics" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M11" type="SpecificInteraction" span="33 42" str="transient worsening heart failure symptoms" code="42343007: Congestive heart failure (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M14" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 15" str="Fluid retention" code="43498006: Body fluid retention (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M12" precipitant="M13" effect="M11"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M12" precipitant="M13" effect="M14"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5729" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The dose of COREG should be reduced if patients experience bradycardia (heart rate less than 55beats per minute).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5730" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Episodes of dizziness or fluid retention during initiation of COREG can generally be managed without discontinuation of treatment and do not preclude subsequent successful titration of, or a favorable response to, carvedilol.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5731" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>DOSAGE MUST BE INDIVIDUALIZED AND MONITORED DURING UP-TITRATION.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5732" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Treatment with COREG may be started as an inpatient or outpatient and should be started after the patient is hemodynamically stable and fluid retention has been minimized.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5733" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>It is recommended that COREG be started at 6.25mg twice daily and increased after 3 to 10days, based on tolerability, to 12.5mg twice daily, then again to the target dose of 25mg twice daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5734" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>A lower starting dose may be used (3.125mg twice daily) and/or the rate of up-titration may be slowed if clinically indicated (e.g., due to low blood pressure or heart rate, or fluid retention).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5735" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommended dosing regimen need not be altered in patients who received treatment with an IV or oral β-blocker during the acute phase of the myocardial infarction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5736" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommended starting dose of COREG is 6.25mg twice daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5737" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If this dose is tolerated, using standing systolic pressure measured about 1hour after dosing as a guide, the dose should be maintained for 7 to 14days, and then increased to 12.5mg twice daily if needed, based on trough blood pressure, again using standing systolic pressure 1 hour after dosing as a guide for tolerance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5738" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>This dose should also be maintained for 7 to 14days and can then be adjusted upward to 25mg twice daily if tolerated and needed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5739" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The full antihypertensive effect of COREG is seen within 7 to 14days.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5740" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Total daily dose should not exceed 50mg. Concomitant administration with a diuretic can be expected to produce additive effects and exaggerate the orthostatic component of carvedilol action.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M15" type="Trigger" span="103 24" str="produce additive effects"/>
<Mention id="M19" type="Precipitant" span="75 8" str="diuretic" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M17" type="SpecificInteraction" span="111 16" str="additive effects" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M18" type="Trigger" span="132 10" str="exaggerate"/>
<Mention id="M20" type="SpecificInteraction" span="147 21" str="orthostatic component" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M15" precipitant="M19" effect="M17"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M18" precipitant="M19" effect="M20"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5741" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>COREG should not be given to patients with severe hepatic impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5742" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>•CYP P450 2D6 enzyme inhibitors may increase and rifampin may decrease carvedilol levels.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M21" type="Trigger" span="36 8;82 6" str="increase | levels"/>
<Mention id="M22" type="Precipitant" span="1 30" str="CYP P450 2D6 enzyme inhibitors" code="N0000182135"/>
<Mention id="M23" type="Trigger" span="62 8;82 6" str="decrease | levels"/>
<Mention id="M24" type="Precipitant" span="49 8" str="rifampin" code="VJT6J7R4TR"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M21" precipitant="M22" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M23" precipitant="M24" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5743" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>•Hypotensive agents (e.g., reserpine, MAO inhibitors, clonidine) may increase the risk of hypotension and/or severe bradycardia.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M46" type="Trigger" span="69 17" str="increase the risk"/>
<Mention id="M29" type="Precipitant" span="54 9" str="clonidine" code="MN3L5RMN02"/>
<Mention id="M48" type="SpecificInteraction" span="109 18" str="severe bradycardia" code="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M45" type="SpecificInteraction" span="90 11" str="hypotension" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M35" type="Precipitant" span="1 18" str="Hypotensive agents" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M41" type="Precipitant" span="38 14" str="MAO inhibitors" code="N0000175744"/>
<Mention id="M47" type="Precipitant" span="27 9" str="reserpine" code="8B1QWR724A"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M46" precipitant="M29" effect="M48"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M46" precipitant="M29" effect="M45"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M46" precipitant="M35" effect="M48"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M46" precipitant="M35" effect="M45"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M46" precipitant="M41" effect="M45"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M46" precipitant="M41" effect="M48"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M46" precipitant="M47" effect="M45"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M46" precipitant="M47" effect="M48"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5744" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>•Cyclosporine or digoxin levels may increase.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M51" type="Trigger" span="25 19" str="levels may increase"/>
<Mention id="M50" type="Precipitant" span="1 12" str="Cyclosporine" code="83HN0GTJ6D"/>
<Mention id="M52" type="Precipitant" span="17 7" str="digoxin" code="73K4184T59"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M51" precipitant="M50" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M51" precipitant="M52" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5745" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>•Both digitalis glycosides and β-blockers slow atrioventricular conduction and decrease heart rate.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M56" type="Trigger" span="1 4" str="Both"/>
<Mention id="M57" type="Precipitant" span="6 20" str="digitalis glycosides" code="F1T8QT9U8B"/>
<Mention id="M55" type="SpecificInteraction" span="42 32" str="slow atrioventricular conduction" code="233917008: Atrioventricular block (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M58" type="SpecificInteraction" span="79 19" str="decrease heart rate" code="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M56" precipitant="M57" effect="M55"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M56" precipitant="M57" effect="M58"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5746" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant use can increase the risk of bradycardia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5747" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>•Amiodarone may increase carvedilol levels resulting in further slowing of the heart rate or cardiac conduction.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M62" type="Trigger" span="43 28" str="resulting in further slowing"/>
<Mention id="M66" type="Precipitant" span="1 10" str="Amiodarone" code="N3RQ532IUT"/>
<Mention id="M61" type="SpecificInteraction" span="64 7;93 18" str="slowing | cardiac conduction" code="36358004: Abnormal cardiac conduction (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M64" type="SpecificInteraction" span="64 25" str="slowing of the heart rate" code="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M65" type="Trigger" span="16 8;36 6" str="increase | levels"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M62" precipitant="M66" effect="M61"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M62" precipitant="M66" effect="M64"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M65" precipitant="M66" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5748" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>•Verapamil- or diltiazem-type calcium channel blockers may affect ECG and/or blood pressure.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M82" type="Trigger" span="59 6" str="affect"/>
<Mention id="M71" type="Precipitant" span="15 9" str="diltiazem" code="EE92BBP03H"/>
<Mention id="M84" type="SpecificInteraction" span="77 14" str="blood pressure" code="38936003: Abnormal blood pressure (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M81" type="SpecificInteraction" span="66 3" str="ECG" code="102594003: Electrocardiogram abnormal (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M77" type="Precipitant" span="1 9" str="Verapamil" code="CJ0O37KU29"/>
<Mention id="M83" type="Precipitant" span="1 53" str="Verapamil- or diltiazem-type calcium channel blockers" code="N0000175566"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M82" precipitant="M71" effect="M84"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M82" precipitant="M71" effect="M81"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M82" precipitant="M77" effect="M84"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M82" precipitant="M77" effect="M81"/>
<Interaction id="I29" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M82" precipitant="M83" effect="M81"/>
<Interaction id="I30" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M82" precipitant="M83" effect="M84"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5749" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>•Insulin and oral hypoglycemics action may be enhanced.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M90" type="SpecificInteraction" span="32 22" str="action may be enhanced" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M86" type="Precipitant" span="1 7" str="Insulin" code="N0000175944"/>
<Mention id="M89" type="Precipitant" span="13 18" str="oral hypoglycemics" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I31" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M90" precipitant="M86" effect="M90"/>
<Interaction id="I32" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M90" precipitant="M89" effect="M90"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5750" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Interactions of carvedilol with potent inhibitors of CYP2D6 isoenzyme (such as quinidine, fluoxetine, paroxetine, and propafenone) have not been studied, but these drugs would be expected to increase blood levels of the R(+) enantiomer of carvedilol.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M99" type="Trigger" span="191 21" str="increase blood levels"/>
<Mention id="M92" type="Precipitant" span="90 10" str="fluoxetine" code="01K63SUP8D"/>
<Mention id="M94" type="Precipitant" span="102 10" str="paroxetine" code="41VRH5220H"/>
<Mention id="M96" type="Precipitant" span="32 27" str="potent inhibitors of CYP2D6" code="N0000182135"/>
<Mention id="M98" type="Precipitant" span="118 11" str="propafenone" code="68IQX3T69U"/>
<Mention id="M100" type="Precipitant" span="79 9" str="quinidine" code="ITX08688JL"/>
<Interaction id="I33" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M99" precipitant="M92" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I34" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M99" precipitant="M94" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I35" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M99" precipitant="M96" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I36" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M99" precipitant="M98" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I37" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M99" precipitant="M100" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5751" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Retrospective analysis of side effects in clinical trials showed that poor 2D6 metabolizers had a higher rate of dizziness during up-titration, presumably resulting from vasodilating effects of the higher concentrations of the α-blocking R(+) enantiomer.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5752" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Patients taking a β-blocker and a drug that can deplete catecholamines (e.g., reserpine and monoamine oxidase inhibitors) should be observed closely for signs of hypotension and/or severe bradycardia.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M116" type="Trigger" span="122 26" str="should be observed closely"/>
<Mention id="M105" type="Precipitant" span="34 36" str="drug that can deplete catecholamines" code="N0000175640"/>
<Mention id="M118" type="SpecificInteraction" span="181 18" str="severe bradycardia" code="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M115" type="SpecificInteraction" span="162 11" str="hypotension" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M111" type="Precipitant" span="92 28" str="monoamine oxidase inhibitors" code="N0000175744"/>
<Mention id="M117" type="Precipitant" span="78 9" str="reserpine" code="8B1QWR724A"/>
<Interaction id="I38" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M116" precipitant="M105" effect="M118"/>
<Interaction id="I39" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M116" precipitant="M105" effect="M115"/>
<Interaction id="I40" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M116" precipitant="M111" effect="M118"/>
<Interaction id="I41" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M116" precipitant="M111" effect="M115"/>
<Interaction id="I42" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M116" precipitant="M117" effect="M115"/>
<Interaction id="I43" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M116" precipitant="M117" effect="M118"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5753" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant administration of clonidine with a β-blocker may cause hypotension and bradycardia.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M122" type="Trigger" span="61 5" str="cause"/>
<Mention id="M123" type="Precipitant" span="30 9" str="clonidine" code="MN3L5RMN02"/>
<Mention id="M121" type="SpecificInteraction" span="67 11" str="hypotension" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M124" type="SpecificInteraction" span="83 11" str="bradycardia" code="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I44" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M122" precipitant="M123" effect="M121"/>
<Interaction id="I45" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M122" precipitant="M123" effect="M124"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5754" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>When concomitant treatment with a β-blocker and clonidine is to be terminated, the β-blocker should be discontinued first.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M125" type="Trigger" span="93 22" str="should be discontinued"/>
<Mention id="M126" type="Precipitant" span="48 9" str="clonidine" code="MN3L5RMN02"/>
<Interaction id="I46" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M125" precipitant="M126"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5755" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Clonidine therapy can then be discontinued several days later by gradually decreasing the dosage.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M127" type="Trigger" span="30 12" str="discontinued"/>
<Mention id="M128" type="Precipitant" span="0 9" str="Clonidine" code="MN3L5RMN02"/>
<Interaction id="I47" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M127" precipitant="M128"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5756" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Modest increases in mean trough cyclosporine concentrations were observed following initiation of carvedilol treatment in 21renal transplant subjects suffering from chronic vascular rejection.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M129" type="Trigger" span="7 9;45 13" str="increases | concentration"/>
<Mention id="M130" type="Precipitant" span="32 12" str="cyclosporine" code="83HN0GTJ6D"/>
<Interaction id="I48" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M129" precipitant="M130" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5757" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>In about 30% of subjects, the dose of cyclosporine had to be reduced in order to maintain cyclosporine concentrations within the therapeutic range, while in the remainder no adjustment was needed.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M131" type="Trigger" span="30 4;61 7" str="dose | reduced"/>
<Mention id="M132" type="Precipitant" span="38 12" str="cyclosporine" code="83HN0GTJ6D"/>
<Interaction id="I49" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M131" precipitant="M132" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5758" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>On the average for the group, the dose of cyclosporine was reduced about 20% in these subjects.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M133" type="Trigger" span="34 4;59 7" str="dose | reduced"/>
<Mention id="M134" type="Precipitant" span="42 12" str="cyclosporine" code="83HN0GTJ6D"/>
<Interaction id="I50" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M133" precipitant="M134" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5759" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Due to wide interindividual variability in the dose adjustment required, it is recommended that cyclosporine concentrations be monitored closely after initiation of carvedilol therapy and that the dose of cyclosporine be adjusted as appropriate.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M135" type="Trigger" span="47 15" str="dose adjustment "/>
<Mention id="M136" type="Trigger" span="109 35" str=" concentrations be monitored closely "/>
<Mention id="M137" type="Trigger" span="47 4;221 8" str=" dose | adjusted"/>
<Mention id="M138" type="Precipitant" span="96 12" str="cyclosporine" code="83HN0GTJ6D"/>
<Interaction id="I51" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M135;M136;M137" precipitant="M138"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5760" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Both digitalis glycosides and β-blockers slow atrioventricular conduction and decrease heart rate.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M142" type="Trigger" span="0 4" str="Both"/>
<Mention id="M143" type="Precipitant" span="5 20" str="digitalis glycosides" code="F1T8QT9U8B"/>
<Mention id="M141" type="SpecificInteraction" span="41 32" str="slow atrioventricular conduction" code="233917008: Atrioventricular block (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M144" type="SpecificInteraction" span="78 19" str="decrease heart rate" code="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I52" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M142" precipitant="M143" effect="M141"/>
<Interaction id="I53" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M142" precipitant="M143" effect="M144"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5761" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Digoxin concentrations are increased by about 15% when digoxin and carvedilol are administered concomitantly.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M145" type="Trigger" span="8 28" str="concentrations are increased"/>
<Mention id="M146" type="Precipitant" span="0 7" str="Digoxin" code="73K4184T59"/>
<Interaction id="I54" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M145" precipitant="M146" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5762" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Therefore, increased monitoring of digoxin is recommended when initiating, adjusting, or discontinuing COREG.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M147" type="Trigger" span="11 20" str="increased monitoring"/>
<Mention id="M148" type="Precipitant" span="35 7" str="digoxin" code="73K4184T59"/>
<Interaction id="I55" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M147" precipitant="M148"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5763" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Rifampin reduced plasma concentrations of carvedilol by about 70%.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M149" type="Trigger" span="9 29" str="reduced plasma concentrations"/>
<Mention id="M150" type="Precipitant" span="0 8" str="Rifampin" code="VJT6J7R4TR"/>
<Interaction id="I56" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M149" precipitant="M150" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5764" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Cimetidine increased AUC by about 30% but caused no change in Cmax.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M151" type="Trigger" span="11 13" str="increased AUC"/>
<Mention id="M152" type="Precipitant" span="0 10" str="Cimetidine" code="80061L1WGD"/>
<Interaction id="I57" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M151" precipitant="M152" effect="C54605"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5765" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Amiodarone and its metabolite desethyl amiodarone, inhibitors of CYP2C9, and P-glycoprotein increased concentrations of the S(-)-enantiomer of carvedilol by at least 2 fold.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M159" type="Trigger" span="92 24" str="increased concentrations"/>
<Mention id="M154" type="Precipitant" span="0 10" str="Amiodarone" code="N3RQ532IUT"/>
<Mention id="M156" type="Precipitant" span="30 19" str="desethyl amiodarone" code="M31FU99E3Y"/>
<Mention id="M158" type="Precipitant" span="51 13;77 14" str="inhibitors of | P-glycoprotein" code="N0000185503"/>
<Mention id="M160" type="Precipitant" span="51 20" str="inhibitors of CYP2C9" code="N0000185504"/>
<Interaction id="I58" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M159" precipitant="M154" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I59" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M159" precipitant="M156" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I60" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M159" precipitant="M158" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I61" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M159" precipitant="M160" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5766" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The concomitant administration of amiodarone or other CYP2C9 inhibitors such as fluconazole with COREG may enhance the β-blocking activity resulting in further slowing of the heart rate or cardiac conduction.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M185" type="Trigger" span="139 28" str="resulting in further slowing"/>
<Mention id="M168" type="Precipitant" span="34 10" str="amiodarone" code="N3RQ532IUT"/>
<Mention id="M184" type="SpecificInteraction" span="160 7;189 18" str="slowing | cardiac conduction" code="36358004: Abnormal cardiac conduction (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M187" type="SpecificInteraction" span="160 25" str="slowing of the heart rate" code="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M179" type="Trigger" span="107 7;130 8" str="enhance | activity"/>
<Mention id="M181" type="SpecificInteraction" span="107 31" str="enhance the β-blocking activity" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M177" type="Precipitant" span="54 17" str="CYP2C9 inhibitors" code="N0000185504"/>
<Mention id="M186" type="Precipitant" span="80 11" str="fluconazole" code="8VZV102JFY"/>
<Interaction id="I62" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M185" precipitant="M168" effect="M184"/>
<Interaction id="I63" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M185" precipitant="M168" effect="M187"/>
<Interaction id="I64" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M179" precipitant="M168" effect="M181"/>
<Interaction id="I65" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M185" precipitant="M177" effect="M187"/>
<Interaction id="I66" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M179" precipitant="M177" effect="M181"/>
<Interaction id="I67" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M185" precipitant="M177" effect="M184"/>
<Interaction id="I68" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M179" precipitant="M186" effect="M181"/>
<Interaction id="I69" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M185" precipitant="M186" effect="M184"/>
<Interaction id="I70" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M185" precipitant="M186" effect="M187"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5767" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Patients should be observed for signs of bradycardia or heart block, particularly when one agent is added to pre-existing treatment with the other.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5768" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Conduction disturbance (rarely with hemodynamic compromise) has been observed when COREG is coadministered with diltiazem.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M192" type="Trigger" span="0 22" str="Conduction disturbance "/>
<Mention id="M193" type="Trigger" span="36 22" str=" hemodynamic compromise"/>
<Mention id="M194" type="Precipitant" span="112 9" str="diltiazem" code="EE92BBP03H"/>
<Mention id="M191" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 22" str="Conduction disturbance" code="44808001: Conduction disorder of the heart (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M195" type="SpecificInteraction" span="36 22" str="hemodynamic compromise" code="422773005: Hemodynamic instability (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I71" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M192;M193" precipitant="M194" effect="M191"/>
<Interaction id="I72" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M192;M193" precipitant="M194" effect="M195"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5769" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>As with other β-blockers, if COREG is administered with calcium channel blockers of the verapamil or diltiazem type, it is recommended that ECG and blood pressure be monitored.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M211" type="Trigger" span="166 9" str="monitored"/>
<Mention id="M200" type="Precipitant" span="56 59" str="calcium channel blockers of the verapamil or diltiazem type" code="N0000175566"/>
<Mention id="M210" type="SpecificInteraction" span="140 3" str="ECG" code="102594003: Electrocardiogram abnormal (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M213" type="SpecificInteraction" span="148 14" str="blood pressure" code="38936003: Abnormal blood pressure (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M206" type="Precipitant" span="101 9" str="diltiazem" code="EE92BBP03H"/>
<Mention id="M212" type="Precipitant" span="88 9" str="verapamil" code="CJ0O37KU29"/>
<Interaction id="I73" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M211" precipitant="M200" effect="M210"/>
<Interaction id="I74" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M211" precipitant="M200" effect="M213"/>
<Interaction id="I75" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M211" precipitant="M206" effect="M213"/>
<Interaction id="I76" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M211" precipitant="M206" effect="M210"/>
<Interaction id="I77" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M211" precipitant="M212" effect="M210"/>
<Interaction id="I78" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M211" precipitant="M212" effect="M213"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5770" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>β-blockers may enhance the blood-sugar-reducing effect of insulin and oral hypoglycemics.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M217" type="Trigger" span="15 7;48 6" str="enhance | effect"/>
<Mention id="M215" type="Precipitant" span="58 7" str="insulin" code="N0000175944"/>
<Mention id="M219" type="SpecificInteraction" span="15 39" str="enhance the blood-sugar-reducing effect" code="51798006: Decreased glucose level (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M218" type="Precipitant" span="70 18" str="oral hypoglycemics" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I79" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M217" precipitant="M215" effect="M219"/>
<Interaction id="I80" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M217" precipitant="M218" effect="M219"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5771" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Therefore, in patients taking insulin or oral hypoglycemics, regular monitoring of blood glucose is recommended.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M223" type="Trigger" span="69 10" str="monitoring"/>
<Mention id="M221" type="Precipitant" span="30 7" str="insulin" code="N0000175944"/>
<Mention id="M225" type="SpecificInteraction" span="83 13" str="blood glucose" code="166922008: Blood glucose abnormal (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M224" type="Precipitant" span="41 18" str="oral hypoglycemics" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I81" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M223" precipitant="M221" effect="M225"/>
<Interaction id="I82" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M223" precipitant="M224" effect="M225"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5772" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>If treatment with COREGis to be continued perioperatively, particular care should be taken when anesthetic agents that depress myocardial function, such as ether, cyclopropane, and trichloroethylene, are used.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M232" type="Trigger" span="59 31" str="particular care should be taken"/>
<Mention id="M227" type="Precipitant" span="96 50" str="anesthetic agents that depress myocardial function" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M229" type="Precipitant" span="163 12" str="cyclopropane" code="99TB643425"/>
<Mention id="M231" type="Precipitant" span="156 5" str="ether" code="0F5N573A2Y"/>
<Mention id="M233" type="Precipitant" span="181 17" str="trichloroethylene" code="290YE8AR51"/>
<Interaction id="I83" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M232" precipitant="M227"/>
<Interaction id="I84" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M232" precipitant="M229"/>
<Interaction id="I85" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M232" precipitant="M231"/>
<Interaction id="I86" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M232" precipitant="M233"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5773" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>•Acute exacerbation of coronary artery disease upon cessation of therapy: Do not abruptly discontinue.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5774" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>•Bradycardia, hypotension, worsening heart failure/fluid retention may occur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5775" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>•Non-allergic bronchospasm (e.g., chronic bronchitis and emphysema): Avoid β-blockers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5776" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>However, if deemed necessary, use with caution and at lowest effective dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5777" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>•Diabetes: Monitor glucose as β-blockers may mask symptoms of hypoglycemia or worsen hyperglycemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5778" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients with coronary artery disease, who are being treated with COREG, should be advised against abrupt discontinuation of therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5779" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Severe exacerbation of angina and the occurrence of myocardial infarction and ventricular arrhythmias have been reported in patients with angina following the abrupt discontinuation of therapy with β-blockers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5780" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The last 2 complications may occur with or without preceding exacerbation of the angina pectoris.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5781" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>As with other β-blockers, when discontinuation of COREG is planned, the patients should be carefully observed and advised to limit physical activity to a minimum.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5782" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>COREG should be discontinued over 1 to 2 weeks whenever possible.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5783" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If the angina worsens or acute coronary insufficiency develops, it is recommended that COREG be promptly reinstituted, at least temporarily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5784" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Because coronary artery disease is common and may be unrecognized, it may be prudent not to discontinue therapy with COREG abruptly even in patients treated only for hypertension or heart failure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5785" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In clinical trials, COREG caused bradycardia in about 2% of hypertensive subjects, 9% of subjects with heart failure, and 6.5% of subjects with myocardial infarction and left ventricular dysfunction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5786" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If pulse rate drops below 55beats per minute, the dosage should be reduced.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5787" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In clinical trials of primarily mild‑to‑moderate heart failure, hypotension and postural hypotension occurred in 9.7% and syncope in 3.4% of subjects receiving COREG compared with 3.6% and 2.5% of placebo subjects, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5788" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The risk for these events was highest during the first 30days of dosing, corresponding to the up‑titration period and was a cause for discontinuation of therapy in 0.7% of subjects receiving COREG, compared with 0.4% of placebo subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5789" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In a long‑term, placebo‑controlled trial in severe heart failure (COPERNICUS), hypotension and postural hypotension occurred in 15.1% and syncope in 2.9% of heart failure subjects receiving COREG compared with 8.7% and 2.3% of placebo subjects, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5790" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>These events were a cause for discontinuation of therapy in 1.1% of subjects receiving COREG, compared with 0.8% of placebo subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5791" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Postural hypotension occurred in 1.8% and syncope in 0.1% of hypertensive subjects, primarily following the initial dose or at the time of dose increase and was a cause for discontinuation of therapy in 1% of subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5792" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In the CAPRICORN trial of survivors of an acute myocardial infarction, hypotension or postural hypotension occurred in 20.2% of subjects receiving COREG compared with 12.6% of placebo subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5793" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Syncope was reported in 3.9% and 1.9% of subjects, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5794" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>These events were a cause for discontinuation of therapy in 2.5% of subjects receiving COREG, compared with 0.2% of placebo subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5795" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Starting with a low dose, administration with food, and gradual up-titration should decrease the likelihood of syncope or excessive hypotension.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5796" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>During initiation of therapy, the patient should be cautioned to avoid situations such as driving or hazardous tasks, where injury could result should syncope occur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5797" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Worsening heart failure or fluid retention may occur during up-titration of carvedilol.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5798" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If such symptoms occur, diuretics should be increased and the carvedilol dose should not be advanced until clinical stability resumes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5799" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Occasionally it is necessary to lower the carvedilol dose or temporarily discontinue it.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5800" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Such episodes do not preclude subsequent successful titration of, or a favorable response to, carvedilol.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5801" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In a placebo-controlled trial of subjects with severe heart failure, worsening heart failure during the first 3months was reported to a similar degree with carvedilol and with placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5802" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>When treatment was maintained beyond 3months, worsening heart failure was reported less frequently in subjects treated with carvedilol than with placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5803" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Worsening heart failure observed during long-term therapy is more likely to be related to the patients’ underlying disease than to treatment with carvedilol.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5804" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients with bronchospastic disease (e.g., chronic bronchitis, emphysema) should, in general, not receive β-blockers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5805" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>COREG may be used with caution, however, in patients who do not respond to, or cannot tolerate, other antihypertensive agents.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5806" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>It is prudent, if COREG is used, to use the smallest effective dose, so that inhibition of endogenous or exogenous β-agonists is minimized.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5807" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In clinical trials of subjects with heart failure, subjects with bronchospastic disease were enrolled if they did not require oral or inhaled medication to treat their bronchospastic disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5808" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In such patients, it is recommended that carvedilol be used with caution.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5809" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The dosing recommendations should be followed closely and the dose should be lowered if any evidence of bronchospasm is observed during up-titration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5810" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In general, β-blockers may mask some of the manifestations of hypoglycemia, particularly tachycardia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5811" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Nonselective β-blockers may potentiate insulin-induced hypoglycemia and delay recovery of serum glucose levels.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M234" type="Trigger" span="28 10" str="potentiate"/>
<Mention id="M238" type="Precipitant" span="39 7" str="insulin" code="N0000175944"/>
<Mention id="M236" type="SpecificInteraction" span="39 28" str="insulin-induced hypoglycemia" code="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M237" type="Trigger" span="72 14" str="delay recovery"/>
<Mention id="M239" type="SpecificInteraction" span="78 32" str="recovery of serum glucose levels" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I87" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M234" precipitant="M238" effect="M236"/>
<Interaction id="I88" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M237" precipitant="M238" effect="M239"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5812" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients subject to spontaneous hypoglycemia or diabetic patients receiving insulin or oral hypoglycemic agents should be cautioned about these possibilities.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M242" type="Trigger" span="112 19" str="should be cautioned"/>
<Mention id="M241" type="Precipitant" span="76 7" str="insulin" code="N0000175944"/>
<Mention id="M243" type="Precipitant" span="87 24" str="oral hypoglycemic agents" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I89" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M242" precipitant="M241"/>
<Interaction id="I90" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M242" precipitant="M243"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5813" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In patients with heart failure and diabetes, carvedilol therapy may lead to worsening hyperglycemia, which responds to intensification of hypoglycemic therapy.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M244" type="Trigger" span="68 7" str="lead to"/>
<Mention id="M245" type="Precipitant" span="138 20" str="hypoglycemic therapy" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M246" type="SpecificInteraction" span="76 23" str="worsening hyperglycemia" code="80394007: Hyperglycemia (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I91" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M244" precipitant="M245" effect="M246"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5814" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>It is recommended that blood glucose be monitored when carvedilol dosing is initiated, adjusted, or discontinued.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5815" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Trials designed to examine the effects of carvedilol on glycemic control in patients with diabetes and heart failure have not been conducted.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5816" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In a trial designed to examine the effects of carvedilol on glycemic control in a population with mild-to-moderate hypertension and well-controlled type 2 diabetes mellitus, carvedilol had no adverse effect on glycemic control, based on HbA1c measurements.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5817" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>β-blockers can precipitate or aggravate symptoms of arterial insufficiency in patients with peripheral vascular disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5818" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Caution should be exercised in such individuals.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5819" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Rarely, use of carvedilol in patients with heart failure has resulted in deterioration of renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5820" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients at risk appear to be those with low blood pressure (systolic blood pressure less than 100mm Hg), ischemic heart disease and diffuse vascular disease, and/or underlying renal insufficiency.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5821" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Renal function has returned to baseline when carvedilol was stopped.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5822" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In patients with these risk factors it is recommended that renal function be monitored during up-titration of carvedilol and the drug discontinued or dosage reduced if worsening of renal function occurs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5823" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Chronically administered β-blocking therapy should not be routinely withdrawn prior to major surgery; however, the impaired ability of the heart to respond to reflex adrenergic stimuli may augment the risks of general anesthesia and surgical procedures.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M247" type="Trigger" span="189 17" str="augment the risks"/>
<Mention id="M248" type="Precipitant" span="210 18" str="general anesthesia" code="N0000175681"/>
<Mention id="M249" type="SpecificInteraction" span="189 39" str="augment the risks of general anesthesia" code="736523005: At risk of complication of anesthesia (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I92" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M247" precipitant="M248" effect="M249"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5824" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>β-adrenergic blockade may mask clinical signs of hyperthyroidism, such as tachycardia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5825" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Abrupt withdrawal of β-blockade may be followed by an exacerbation of the symptoms of hyperthyroidism or may precipitate thyroid storm.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5826" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In patients with pheochromocytoma, an α-blocking agent should be initiated prior to the use of any β-blocking agent.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5827" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Although carvedilol has both α- and β-blocking pharmacologic activities, there has been no experience with its use in this condition.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5828" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Therefore, caution should be taken in the administration of carvedilol to patients suspected of having pheochromocytoma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5829" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Agents with non-selective β-blocking activity may provoke chest pain in patients with Prinzmetal’s variant angina.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5830" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There has been no clinical experience with carvedilol in these patients although the α-blocking activity may prevent such symptoms.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5831" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>However, caution should be taken in the administration of carvedilol to patients suspected of having Prinzmetal’s variant angina.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5832" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>While taking β-blockers, patients with a history of severe anaphylactic reaction to a variety of allergens may be more reactive to repeated challenge, either accidental, diagnostic, or therapeutic.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5833" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Such patients may be unresponsive to the usual doses of epinephrine used to treat allergic reaction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5834" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Intraoperative Floppy Iris Syndrome (IFIS) has been observed during cataract surgery in some patients treated with alpha-1 blockers (COREG is an alpha/beta blocker).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5835" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>This variant of small pupil syndrome is characterized by the combination of a flaccid iris that billows in response to intraoperative irrigation currents, progressive intraoperative miosis despite preoperative dilation with standard mydriatic drugs, and potential prolapse of the iris toward the phacoemulsification incisions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5836" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The patient’s ophthalmologist should be prepared for possible modifications to the surgical technique, such as utilization of iris hooks, iris dilator rings, or viscoelastic substances.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5837" LabelDrug="COREG" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There does not appear to be a benefit of stopping alpha-1 blocker therapy prior to cataract surgery.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5838" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>COREG is a racemic mixture in which nonselective β-adrenoreceptor blocking activity is present in the S(-) enantiomer and α1-adrenergic blocking activity is present in both R(+) and S(-) enantiomers at equal potency.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5839" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>COREG has no intrinsic sympathomimetic activity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5840" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The basis for the beneficial effects of COREG in heart failure is not established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5841" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Two placebo‑controlled trials compared the acute hemodynamic effects of COREG with baseline measurements in 59 and 49subjects with NYHA class II‑IV heart failure receiving diuretics, ACE inhibitors, and digitalis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5842" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There were significant reductions in systemic blood pressure, pulmonary artery pressure, pulmonary capillary wedge pressure, and heart rate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5843" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Initial effects on cardiac output, stroke volume index, and systemic vascular resistance were small and variable.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5844" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>These trials measured hemodynamic effects again at 12 to 14weeks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5845" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>COREG significantly reduced systemic blood pressure, pulmonary artery pressure, right atrial pressure, systemic vascular resistance, and heart rate, while stroke volume index was increased.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5846" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Among 839subjects with NYHA class II‑III heart failure treated for 26 to 52weeks in 4U.S. placebo‑controlled trials, average left ventricular ejection fraction (EF) measured by radionuclide ventriculography increased by 9EF units (%) in subjects receiving COREG and by 2EF units in placebo subjects at a target dose of 25 to 50mg twice daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5847" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The effects of carvedilol on ejection fraction were related to dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5848" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Doses of 6.25mg twice daily, 12.5mg twice daily, and 25mg twice daily were associated with placebo‑corrected increases in EF of 5EF units, 6EF units, and 8EF units, respectively; each of these effects were nominally statistically significant.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5849" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The basis for the beneficial effects of COREG in patients with left ventricular dysfunction following an acute myocardial infarction is not established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5850" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mechanism by which β-blockade produces an antihypertensive effect has not been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5851" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>β-adrenoreceptor blocking activity has been demonstrated in animal and human studies showing that carvedilol (1) reduces cardiac output in normal subjects, (2) reduces exercise- and/or isoproterenol-induced tachycardia, and (3) reduces reflex orthostatic tachycardia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5852" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Significant β-adrenoreceptor blocking effect is usually seen within 1hour of drug administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5853" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>α1-adrenoreceptor blocking activity has been demonstrated in human and animal studies, showing that carvedilol (1)attenuates the pressor effects of phenylephrine, (2)causes vasodilation, and (3)reduces peripheral vascular resistance.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M250" type="Trigger" span="114 10" str="attenuates"/>
<Mention id="M251" type="Precipitant" span="148 13" str="phenylephrine" code="1WS297W6MV"/>
<Mention id="M252" type="SpecificInteraction" span="129 15" str="pressor effects" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I93" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M250" precipitant="M251" effect="M252"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5854" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>These effects contribute to the reduction of blood pressure and usually are seen within 30minutes of drug administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5855" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Due to the α1-receptor blocking activity of carvedilol, blood pressure is lowered more in the standing than in the supine position, and symptoms of postural hypotension (1.8%), including rare instances of syncope, can occur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5856" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following oral administration, when postural hypotension has occurred, it has been transient and is uncommon when COREG is administered with food at the recommended starting dose and titration increments are closely followed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5857" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In hypertensive patients with normal renal function, therapeutic doses of COREG decreased renal vascular resistance with no change in glomerular filtration rate or renal plasma flow.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5858" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Changes in excretion of sodium, potassium, uric acid, and phosphorus in hypertensive patients with normal renal function were similar after COREG and placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5859" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>COREG has little effect on plasma catecholamines, plasma aldosterone, or electrolyte levels, but it does significantly reduce plasma renin activity when given for at least 4weeks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5860" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>It also increases levels of atrial natriuretic peptide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5861" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>COREG is rapidly and extensively absorbed following oral administration, with absolute bioavailability of approximately 25% to 35% due to a significant degree of first-pass metabolism.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5862" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following oral administration, the apparent mean terminal elimination half-life of carvedilol generally ranges from 7 to 10hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5863" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Plasma concentrations achieved are proportional to the oral dose administered.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5864" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>When administered with food, the rate of absorption is slowed, as evidenced by a delay in the time to reach peak plasma levels, with no significant difference in extent of bioavailability.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M253" type="Trigger" span="41 20" str="absorption is slowed"/>
<Mention id="M256" type="Precipitant" span="23 4" str="food" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M255" type="Trigger" span="81 45" str="delay in the time to reach peak plasma levels"/>
<Interaction id="I94" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M253" precipitant="M256" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I95" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M255" precipitant="M256" effect="C54604"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5865" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Taking COREG with food should minimize the risk of orthostatic hypotension.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M257" type="Trigger" span="30 17" str="minimize the risk"/>
<Mention id="M258" type="Precipitant" span="18 4" str="food" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M259" type="SpecificInteraction" span="51 23" str="orthostatic hypotension" code="28651003: Orthostatic hypotension (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I96" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M257" precipitant="M258" effect="M259"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5866" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following oral administration of radiolabelled carvedilol to healthy volunteers, carvedilol accounted for only about 7% of the total radioactivity in plasma as measured by area under the curve (AUC).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5867" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Less than 2% of the dose was excreted unchanged in the urine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5868" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Carvedilol is metabolized primarily by aromatic ring oxidation and glucuronidation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5869" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The oxidative metabolites are further metabolized by conjugation via glucuronidation and sulfation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5870" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The metabolites of carvedilol are excreted primarily via the bile into the feces.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5871" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Demethylation and hydroxylation at the phenol ring produce 3 active metabolites with β-receptor blocking activity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5872" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Based on preclinical studies, the 4'-hydroxyphenyl metabolite is approximately 13times more potent than carvedilol for β-blockade.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5873" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Compared with carvedilol, the 3 active metabolites exhibit weak vasodilating activity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5874" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Plasma concentrations of the active metabolites are about one-tenth of those observed for carvedilol and have pharmacokinetics similar to the parent.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5875" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Carvedilol undergoes stereoselective first-pass metabolism with plasma levels of R(+)-carvedilol approximately 2 to 3times higher than S(-)-carvedilol following oral administration in healthy subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5876" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mean apparent terminal elimination half-lives for R(+)-carvedilol range from 5 to 9hours compared with 7 to 11hours for the S(-)-enantiomer.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5877" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The primary P450 enzymes responsible for the metabolism of both R(+) and S(-)-carvedilol in human liver microsomes were CYP2D6 and CYP2C9 and to a lesser extent CYP3A4, 2C19, 1A2, and 2E1.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5878" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>CYP2D6 is thought to be the major enzyme in the 4’- and 5’-hydroxylation of carvedilol, with a potential contribution from 3A4.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5879" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>CYP2C9 is thought to be of primary importance in the O-methylation pathway of S(-)-carvedilol.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5880" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Carvedilol is subject to the effects of genetic polymorphism with poor metabolizers of debrisoquin (a marker for cytochrome P450 2D6) exhibiting 2- to 3-fold higher plasma concentrations of R(+)-carvedilol compared with extensive metabolizers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5881" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In contrast, plasma levels of S(-)-carvedilol are increased only about 20% to 25% in poor metabolizers, indicating this enantiomer is metabolized to a lesser extent by cytochrome P450 2D6 than R(+)-carvedilol.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5882" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacokinetics of carvedilol do not appear to be different in poor metabolizers of S-mephenytoin (patients deficient in cytochrome P450 2C19).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5883" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Carvedilol is more than 98% bound to plasma proteins, primarily with albumin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5884" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The plasma-protein binding is independent of concentration over the therapeutic range.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5885" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Carvedilol is a basic, lipophilic compound with a steady-state volume of distribution of approximately 115L, indicating substantial distribution into extravascular tissues.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5886" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Plasma clearance ranges from 500 to 700mL/min.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5887" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Steady‑state plasma concentrations of carvedilol and its enantiomers increased proportionally over the 6.25- to 50- mg dose range in subjects with heart failure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5888" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Compared with healthy subjects, subjects with heart failure had increased mean AUC and Cmax values for carvedilol and its enantiomers, with up to 50% to 100% higher values observed in 6subjects with NYHA class IV heart failure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5889" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mean apparent terminal elimination half‑life for carvedilol was similar to that observed in healthy subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5890" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Plasma levels of carvedilol average about 50% higher in the elderly compared with young subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5891" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Compared with healthy subjects, patients with severe liver impairment (cirrhosis) exhibit a 4- to 7-fold increase in carvedilol levels.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5892" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Carvedilol is contraindicated in patients with severe liver impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5893" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Although carvedilol is metabolized primarily by the liver, plasma concentrations of carvedilol have been reported to be increased in patients with renal impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5894" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Based on mean AUC data, approximately 40% to 50% higher plasma concentrations of carvedilol were observed in subjects with hypertension and moderate to severe renal impairment compared with a control group of subjects with hypertension and normal renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5895" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>However, the ranges of AUC values were similar for both groups.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5896" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Changes in mean peak plasma levels were less pronounced, approximately 12% to 26% higher in subjects with impaired renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5897" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Consistent with its high degree of plasma protein‑binding, carvedilol does not appear to be cleared significantly by hemodialysis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5898" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Since carvedilol undergoes substantial oxidative metabolism, the metabolism and pharmacokinetics of carvedilol may be affected by induction or inhibition of cytochrome P450 enzymes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5899" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In a pharmacokinetic trial conducted in 106 Japanese subjects with heart failure, coadministration of small loading and maintenance doses of amiodarone with carvedilol resulted in at least a 2-fold increase in the steady-state trough concentrations of S(-)-carvedilol.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M260" type="Trigger" span="198 8;234 14" str="increase | concentrations"/>
<Mention id="M261" type="Precipitant" span="141 10" str="amiodarone" code="N3RQ532IUT"/>
<Interaction id="I97" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M260" precipitant="M261" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5900" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In a pharmacokinetic trial conducted in 10healthy male subjects, cimetidine (1,000mg per day) increased the steady-state AUC of carvedilol by 30% with no change in Cmax.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M262" type="Trigger" span="94 9;121 3" str="increased | AUC"/>
<Mention id="M263" type="Precipitant" span="65 10" str="cimetidine" code="80061L1WGD"/>
<Interaction id="I98" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M262" precipitant="M263" effect="C54605"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5901" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following concomitant administration of carvedilol (25mg once daily) and digoxin (0.25mg once daily) for 14days, steady-state AUC and trough concentrations of digoxin were increased by 14% and 16%, respectively, in 12subjects with hypertension.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M264" type="Trigger" span="141 14;172 9" str="concentrations | increased"/>
<Mention id="M267" type="Precipitant" span="73 7" str="digoxin" code="73K4184T59"/>
<Mention id="M266" type="Trigger" span="126 3;172 9" str="AUC | increased"/>
<Interaction id="I99" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M264" precipitant="M267" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I100" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M266" precipitant="M267" effect="C54613"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5902" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In 12healthy subjects, combined administration of carvedilol (25mg once daily) and a single dose of glyburide did not result in a clinically relevant pharmacokinetic interaction for either compound.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5903" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A single oral dose of carvedilol 25mg did not alter the pharmacokinetics of a single oral dose of hydrochlorothiazide 25mg in 12subjects with hypertension.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5904" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Likewise, hydrochlorothiazide had no effect on the pharmacokinetics of carvedilol.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5905" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In a pharmacokinetic trial conducted in 8 healthy male subjects, rifampin (600mg daily for 12days) decreased the AUC and Cmax of carvedilol by about 70%.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M268" type="Trigger" span="99 9;121 4" str="decreased | Cmax"/>
<Mention id="M271" type="Precipitant" span="65 8" str="rifampin" code="VJT6J7R4TR"/>
<Mention id="M270" type="Trigger" span="99 17" str="decreased the AUC"/>
<Interaction id="I101" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M268" precipitant="M271" effect="C54606"/>
<Interaction id="I102" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M270" precipitant="M271" effect="C54609"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5906" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In a trial of 12healthy subjects, combined oral administration of carvedilol 25mg once daily and torsemide 5mg once daily for 5days did not result in any significant differences in their pharmacokinetics compared with administration of the drugs alone.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5907" LabelDrug="COREG" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Carvedilol (12.5mg twice daily) did not have an effect on the steady-state prothrombin time ratios and did not alter the pharmacokinetics of R(+)- and S(-)-warfarin following concomitant administration with warfarin in 9healthy volunteers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="food" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="28651003: Orthostatic hypotension (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="food" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="food" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="food" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54604"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ace inhibitor" precipitantCode="N0000175562" effect="91081006: Vasodilatation (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="diuretics" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="42343007: Congestive heart failure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="diuretics" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="43498006: Body fluid retention (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="diuretic" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cyp p450 2d6 enzyme inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000182135" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="rifampin" precipitantCode="VJT6J7R4TR" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="rifampin" precipitantCode="VJT6J7R4TR" effect="C54606"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="rifampin" precipitantCode="VJT6J7R4TR" effect="C54609"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="clonidine" precipitantCode="MN3L5RMN02" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="clonidine" precipitantCode="MN3L5RMN02" effect="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="clonidine" precipitantCode="MN3L5RMN02"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="hypotensive agents" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="hypotensive agents" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="mao inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175744" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="mao inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175744" effect="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="reserpine" precipitantCode="8B1QWR724A" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="reserpine" precipitantCode="8B1QWR724A" effect="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cyclosporine" precipitantCode="83HN0GTJ6D" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="cyclosporine" precipitantCode="83HN0GTJ6D"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="digoxin" precipitantCode="73K4184T59" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="digoxin" precipitantCode="73K4184T59" effect="C54613"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="digoxin" precipitantCode="73K4184T59"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="digitalis glycosides" precipitantCode="F1T8QT9U8B" effect="233917008: Atrioventricular block (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="digitalis glycosides" precipitantCode="F1T8QT9U8B" effect="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="amiodarone" precipitantCode="N3RQ532IUT" effect="36358004: Abnormal cardiac conduction (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="amiodarone" precipitantCode="N3RQ532IUT" effect="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="amiodarone" precipitantCode="N3RQ532IUT" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="amiodarone" precipitantCode="N3RQ532IUT" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="diltiazem" precipitantCode="EE92BBP03H" effect="102594003: Electrocardiogram abnormal (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="diltiazem" precipitantCode="EE92BBP03H" effect="38936003: Abnormal blood pressure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="diltiazem" precipitantCode="EE92BBP03H" effect="422773005: Hemodynamic instability (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="diltiazem" precipitantCode="EE92BBP03H" effect="44808001: Conduction disorder of the heart (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="verapamil" precipitantCode="CJ0O37KU29" effect="102594003: Electrocardiogram abnormal (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="verapamil" precipitantCode="CJ0O37KU29" effect="38936003: Abnormal blood pressure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="verapamil- or diltiazem-type calcium channel blockers" precipitantCode="N0000175566" effect="102594003: Electrocardiogram abnormal (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="verapamil- or diltiazem-type calcium channel blockers" precipitantCode="N0000175566" effect="38936003: Abnormal blood pressure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="insulin" precipitantCode="N0000175944" effect="166922008: Blood glucose abnormal (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="insulin" precipitantCode="N0000175944" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="insulin" precipitantCode="N0000175944" effect="51798006: Decreased glucose level (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="insulin" precipitantCode="N0000175944" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="insulin" precipitantCode="N0000175944"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="oral hypoglycemics" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="166922008: Blood glucose abnormal (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="oral hypoglycemics" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="51798006: Decreased glucose level (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="oral hypoglycemics" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="fluoxetine" precipitantCode="01K63SUP8D" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="paroxetine" precipitantCode="41VRH5220H" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="potent inhibitors of cyp2d6" precipitantCode="N0000182135" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="propafenone" precipitantCode="68IQX3T69U" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="quinidine" precipitantCode="ITX08688JL" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="drug that can deplete catecholamines" precipitantCode="N0000175640" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="drug that can deplete catecholamines" precipitantCode="N0000175640" effect="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="monoamine oxidase inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175744" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="monoamine oxidase inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175744" effect="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cimetidine" precipitantCode="80061L1WGD" effect="C54605"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="desethyl amiodarone" precipitantCode="M31FU99E3Y" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="inhibitors of | p-glycoprotein" precipitantCode="N0000185503" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="inhibitors of cyp2c9" precipitantCode="N0000185504" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cyp2c9 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000185504" effect="36358004: Abnormal cardiac conduction (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cyp2c9 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000185504" effect="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cyp2c9 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000185504" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="fluconazole" precipitantCode="8VZV102JFY" effect="36358004: Abnormal cardiac conduction (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="fluconazole" precipitantCode="8VZV102JFY" effect="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="fluconazole" precipitantCode="8VZV102JFY" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="calcium channel blockers of the verapamil or diltiazem type" precipitantCode="N0000175566" effect="102594003: Electrocardiogram abnormal (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="calcium channel blockers of the verapamil or diltiazem type" precipitantCode="N0000175566" effect="38936003: Abnormal blood pressure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="anesthetic agents that depress myocardial function" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="cyclopropane" precipitantCode="99TB643425"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="ether" precipitantCode="0F5N573A2Y"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="trichloroethylene" precipitantCode="290YE8AR51"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="oral hypoglycemic agents" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="hypoglycemic therapy" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="80394007: Hyperglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="general anesthesia" precipitantCode="N0000175681" effect="736523005: At risk of complication of anesthesia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="phenylephrine" precipitantCode="1WS297W6MV" effect="NO MAP"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>