<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Dilatrate" setid="7ec5ba03-6164-4199-a333-7cd8d7c75e17">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
Allergic reactions to organic nitrates are extremely rare, but they do occur. Isosorbide dinitrate is contraindicated in patients who are allergic to it.</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
As noted above (CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY), multiple studies with ISDN and other nitrates have shown that maintenance of continuous 24-hour plasma levels results in refractory tolerance. Every dosing regimen for organic nitrates including dilatrate®-SR must provide a daily nitrate-free interval to avoid the development of tolerance. To achieve the necessary nitrate-free interval with immediate-release oral ISDN, it appears that at least one of the daily interdose intervals must be at least 14 hours long. The necessary interdose interval for dilatrate®-SR has not been clearly identified, but it must be greater than 18 hours. As noted under Clinical Pharmacology, only one trial has ever studied the use of extended-release isosorbide dinitrate for more than one dose. In that trial, 40 mg of dilatrate®-SR was administered twice daily in doses given 6 hours apart. After 4 weeks, dilatrate®-SR could not be distinguished from placebo. Large controlled studies with other nitrates suggest that no dosing regimen with dilatrate®-SR should be expected to provide more than about 12 hours of continuous antianginal efficacy per day. In clinical trials, immediate-release oral isosorbide dinitrate has been administered in a variety of regimens, with total daily doses ranging from 30 to 480 mg.   Do not exceed 160 mg (4 capsules) per day.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
Drug interactions:  The vasodilating effects of isosorbide dinitrate may be additive with those of other vasodilators. Alcohol, in particular, has been found to exhibit additive effects of this variety.</Section>
<Section name="PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="42232-9">
General:  Severe hypotension, particularly with upright posture, may occur with even small doses of isosorbide dinitrate. This drug should therefore be used with caution in patients who may be volume depleted or who, for whatever reason, are already hypotensive. Hypotension induced by isosorbide dinitrate may be accompanied by paradoxical bradycardia and increased angina pectoris. Nitrate therapy may aggravate the angina caused by hypertrophic cardiomyopathy. As tolerance to isosorbide dinitrate develops, the effect of sublingual nitroglycerin on exercise tolerance, although still observable, is somewhat blunted. Some clinical trials in angina patients have provided nitroglycerin for about 12 continuous hours of every 24-hour day. During the interdosing intervals in some of these trials, anginal attacks have been more easily provoked than before treatment and patients have demonstrated hemodynamic rebound and decreased exercise tolerance. The importance of these observations to the routine, clinical use of controlled-release oral isosorbide dinitrate is not known. In industrial workers who have had long-term exposure to unknown (presumably high) doses of organic nitrates, tolerance clearly occurs. Chest pain, acute myocardial infarction, and even sudden death have occurred during temporary withdrawal of nitrates from these workers demonstrating the existence of true physical dependence.           Information for Patients:  Patients should be told that the antianginal efficacy of isosorbide dinitrate is strongly related to its dosing regimen, so the prescribed schedule of dosing should be followed carefully. In particular, daily headaches sometimes accompany treatment with isosorbide dinitrate. In patients who get these headaches, the headaches are a marker of the activity of the drug. Patients should resist the temptation to avoid headaches by altering the schedule of their treatment with isosorbide dinitrate, since loss of headache may be associated with simultaneous loss of antianginal efficacy. Aspirin and/or acetaminophen, on the other hand, often successfully relieve isosorbide dinitrate-induced headaches with no deleterious effect on isosorbide dinitrate's antianginal efficacy. Treatment with isosorbide dinitrate may be associated with lightheadedness on standing, especially just after rising from a recumbent or seated position. This effect may be more frequent in patients who have also consumed alcohol.           Drug interactions:  The vasodilating effects of isosorbide dinitrate may be additive with those of other vasodilators. Alcohol, in particular, has been found to exhibit additive effects of this variety.           Carcinogenesis, Mutagenesis and Impairment of Fertility:  No long-term studies in animals have been performed to evaluate the carcinogenic potential of isosorbide dinitrate. In a modified two-litter reproduction study, there was no remarkable gross pathology and no altered fertility or gestation among rats fed isosorbide dinitrate at 25 or 100 mg/kg/day.           Pregnancy Category C:  At oral doses 35 and 150 times the daily Maximum Recommended Human Dose (MRHD), isosorbide dinitrate has been shown to cause a dose related increase in embryotoxicity (increase in mummified pups) in rabbits. There are no adequate, well-controlled studies in pregnant women. Isosorbide dinitrate should be used during pregnancy only if the potential benefit justifies the potential risk to the fetus.           Nursing Mothers:  It is not known whether isosorbide dinitrate is excreted in human milk. Because many drugs are excreted in human milk, caution should be exercised when isosorbide dinitrate is administered to a nursing woman.           Pediatric Use:  Safety and effectiveness in pediatric patients have not been established.           Geriatric Use:  Clinical studies of dilatrate®-SR did not include sufficient numbers of subjects aged 65 and over to determine whether they respond differently from younger subjects. Other reported clinical experience has not identified differences in responses between the elderly and younger patients. In general, dose selection for an elderly patient should be cautious, usually starting at the low end of the dosing range, reflecting the greater frequency of decreased hepatic, renal, or cardiac function, and of concomitant disease or other drug therapy.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS SECTION" id="34071-1">
Amplification of the vasodilatory effects of dilatrate® - SR by sildenafil can result in severe hypotension. The time course and dose dependence of this interaction have not been studied. Appropriate supportive care has not been studied, but it seems reasonable to treat this as a nitrate overdose, with elevation of the extremities and with central volume expansion.   The benefits of extended-release oral isosorbide dinitrate in patients with acute myocardial infarction or congestive heart failure have not been established. If one elects to use isosorbide dinitrate in these conditions, careful clinical or hemodynamic monitoring must be used to avoid the hazards of hypotension and tachycardia. Because the effects of extended-release oral isosorbide dinitrate are so difficult to terminate rapidly, this formulation is not recommended in these settings.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
The principal pharmacological action of isosorbide dinitrate is relaxation of vascular smooth muscle and consequent dilatation of peripheral arteries and veins, especially the latter. Dilatation of the veins promotes peripheral pooling of blood and decreases venous return to the heart, thereby reducing left ventricular end-diastolic pressure and pulmonary capillary wedge pressure (preload). Arteriolar relaxation reduces systemic vascular resistance, systolic arterial pressure, and mean arterial pressure (afterload). Dilatation of the coronary arteries also occurs. The relative importance of preload reduction, afterload reduction, and coronary dilatation remains undefined. Dosing regimens for most chronically used drugs are designed to provide plasma concentrations that are continuously greater than a minimally effective concentration. This strategy is inappropriate for organic nitrates. Several well-controlled clinical trials have used exercise testing to assess the antianginal efficacy of continuously-delivered nitrates. In the large majority of these trials, active agents were no more effective than placebo after 24 hours (or less) of continuous therapy. Attempts to overcome nitrate tolerance by dose escalation, even to doses far in excess of those used acutely, have consistently failed. Only after nitrates have been absent from the body for several hours has their antianginal efficacy been restored.         Pharmacokinetics:  The kinetics of absorption of isosorbide dinitrate from dilatrate®-SR sustained release capsules have not been well studied. Studies of immediate-release formulations of ISDN have found highly variable bioavailability (10 to 90%), with extensive first-pass metabolism in the liver. Most such studies have observed progressive increases in bioavailability during chronic therapy; it is not known whether similar increases in bioavailability appear during the course of chronic therapy with dilatrate®-SR sustained release capsules. Once absorbed, the distribution volume of isosorbide dinitrate is 2-4 L/kg and this volume is cleared at the rate of 2-4 L/min, so ISDN's half-life in serum is about an hour. Since the clearance exceeds hepatic blood flow, considerable extrahepatic metabolism must also occur. Clearance is affected primarily by denitration to the 2-mononitrate (15 to 25%) and the 5-mononitrate (75 to 85%). Both metabolites have biological activity, especially the 5-mononitrate. With an overall half-life of about 5 hours, the 5-mononitrate is cleared from the serum by denitration to isosorbide; glucuronidation to the 5-mononitrate glucuronide; and denitration/hydration to sorbitol. The 2-mononitrate has been less well studied, but it appears to participate in the same metabolic pathways with a half-life of about 2 hours. The interdosing interval sufficient to avoid tolerance to ISDN has not been well defined. Studies of nitroglycerin (an organic nitrate with a very short half-life) have shown that dosing intervals of 10-12 hours are usually sufficient to prevent or attenuate tolerance. Dosing intervals that have succeeded in avoiding tolerance during trials of moderate doses (e.g., 30 mg) of immediate release ISDN have generally been somewhat longer (at least 14 hours), but this is consistent with the longer half-lives of ISDN and its active metabolites. An interdosing interval sufficient to avoid tolerance with dilatrate®-SR has not been demonstrated. In an eccentric dosing study, 40 mg capsules of dilatrate®-SR were administered daily at 0800 and 1400 hours. After two weeks of this regimen, dilatrate®-SR was statistically indistinguishable from placebo. Thus, the necessary interdosing interval sufficient to avoid tolerance remains unknown, but it must be greater than 18 hours. Few well-controlled clinical trials of organic nitrates have been designed to detect rebound or withdrawal effects. In one such trial, however, subjects receiving nitroglycerin had less exercise tolerance at the end of the daily interdosing interval than the parallel group receiving placebo. The incidence, magnitude, and clinical significance of similar phenomena in patients receiving ISDN have not been studied.           Clinical trials:  In clinical trials, extended-release oral isosorbide dinitrate has been administered in a variety of regimens, with total daily doses ranging from 40 to 160 mg. A controlled trial using a single 40 mg sustained release oral dose of isosorbide dinitrate (dilatrate®-SR) has demonstrated effective reductions in exercise-related angina for up to 8 hours. Antianginal activity is present about 1 hour after dosing. Adequate multiple-dose trials of dilatrate®-SR sustained release capsules have not been reported.  Most controlled trials of multiple-dose immediate-release oral ISDN taken every 12 hours (or more frequently) for several weeks have shown statistically significant antianginal efficacy for only 2 hours after dosing. Once-daily regimens, and regimens with one daily interdosing interval of at least 14 hours (e.g., a regimen providing doses at 0800, 1400 and 1800 hours), have shown efficacy after the first dose of each day that was similar to that shown in the single dose studies cited above. The efficacy of subsequent doses has not been demonstrated. From large, well-controlled studies of other nitrates, it is reasonable to believe that the maximal achievable daily duration of antianginal effect from isosorbide dinitrate is about 12 hours. No dosing regimen for dilatrate®-SR sustained release capsules has actually been shown to achieve this duration of effect.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="1465" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Isosorbide dinitrate is contraindicated in patients who are allergic to it.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1466" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Do not use dilatrate®-SR in patients who are taking certain drugs for erectile dysfunction (phosphodiesterase inhibitors), such as sildenafil, tadalafil, vardenafil, or avanafil.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M11" type="Trigger" span="0 10" str="Do not use"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="169 8" str="avanafil" code="DR5S136IVO"/>
<Mention id="M4" type="Precipitant" span="60 30" str="drugs for erectile dysfunction" code="N0000009040"/>
<Mention id="M6" type="Precipitant" span="92 28" str="phosphodiesterase inhibitors" code="N0000000128"/>
<Mention id="M8" type="Precipitant" span="131 10" str="sildenafil" code="3M7OB98Y7H"/>
<Mention id="M10" type="Precipitant" span="143 9" str="tadalafil" code="742SXX0ICT"/>
<Mention id="M12" type="Precipitant" span="154 10" str="vardenafil" code="UCE6F4125H"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M11" precipitant="M2"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M11" precipitant="M4"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M11" precipitant="M6"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M11" precipitant="M8"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M11" precipitant="M10"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M11" precipitant="M12"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1467" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Concomitant use can cause severe hypotension, syncope, or myocardial ischemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1468" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Do not use dilatrate®-SR in patients who are taking the soluble guanylate cyclase stimulator riociguat.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M15" type="Trigger" span="0 10" str="Do not use"/>
<Mention id="M14" type="Precipitant" span="93 9" str="riociguat" code="RU3FE2Y4XI"/>
<Mention id="M16" type="Precipitant" span="56 46" str="soluble guanylate cyclase stimulator riociguat" code="RU3FE2Y4XI"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M15" precipitant="M14"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M15" precipitant="M16"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1469" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>As noted above (CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY), multiple studies with ISDN and other nitrates have shown that maintenance of continuous 24-hour plasma levels results in refractory tolerance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1470" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Every dosing regimen for organic nitrates including dilatrate®-SR must provide a daily nitrate-free interval to avoid the development of tolerance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1471" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>To achieve the necessary nitrate-free interval with immediate-release oral ISDN, it appears that at least one of the daily interdose intervals must be at least 14 hours long.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1472" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The necessary interdose interval for dilatrate®-SR has not been clearly identified, but it must be greater than 18 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1473" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>As noted under Clinical Pharmacology, only one trial has ever studied the use of extended-release isosorbide dinitrate for more than one dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1474" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In that trial, 40 mg of dilatrate®-SR was administered twice daily in doses given 6 hours apart.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1475" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>After 4 weeks, dilatrate®-SR could not be distinguished from placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1476" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Large controlled studies with other nitrates suggest that no dosing regimen with dilatrate®-SR should be expected to provide more than about 12 hours of continuous antianginal efficacy per day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1477" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In clinical trials, immediate-release oral isosorbide dinitrate has been administered in a variety of regimens, with total daily doses ranging from 30 to 480 mg. Do not exceed 160 mg (4 capsules) per day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1478" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Drug Interactions Concomitant use of dilatrate®-SR with phosphodiesterase inhibitors in any form is contraindicated.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M17" type="Trigger" span="0 17" str="Drug Interactions "/>
<Mention id="M18" type="Trigger" span="100 15" str=" contraindicated"/>
<Mention id="M19" type="Precipitant" span="56 28" str="phosphodiesterase inhibitors" code="N0000000128"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M17;M18" precipitant="M19"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1479" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant use of dilatrate®-SR with riociguat, a soluble guanylate cyclase stimulator, is contraindicated.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M20" type="Trigger" span="92 15" str="contraindicated"/>
<Mention id="M21" type="Precipitant" span="38 9" str="riociguat" code="RU3FE2Y4XI"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M20" precipitant="M21"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1480" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The vasodilating effects of isosorbide dinitrate may be additive with those of other vasodilators.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M22" type="Trigger" span="17 7;56 8" str="effects | additive"/>
<Mention id="M23" type="Precipitant" span="85 12" str="vasodilators" code="N0000175940"/>
<Mention id="M24" type="SpecificInteraction" span="4 20;56 8" str="vasodilating effects | additive" code="91081006: Vasodilatation (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M22" precipitant="M23" effect="M24"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1481" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Alcohol, in particular, has been found to exhibit additive effects of this variety.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M25" type="Trigger" span="50 16" str="additive effects"/>
<Mention id="M26" type="Precipitant" span="0 7" str="Alcohol" code="3K9958V90M"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M25" precipitant="M26"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1482" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>General Severe hypotension, particularly with upright posture, may occur with even small doses of isosorbide dinitrate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1483" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>This drug should therefore be used with caution in patients who may be volume depleted or who, for whatever reason, are already hypotensive.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1484" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Hypotension induced by isosorbide dinitrate may be accompanied by paradoxical bradycardia and increased angina pectoris.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1485" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Nitrate therapy may aggravate the angina caused by hypertrophic cardiomyopathy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1486" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>As tolerance to isosorbide dinitrate develops, the effect of sublingual nitroglycerin on exercise tolerance, although still observable, is somewhat blunted.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1487" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Some clinical trials in angina patients have provided nitroglycerin for about 12 continuous hours of every 24-hour day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1488" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>During the interdosing intervals in some of these trials, anginal attacks have been more easily provoked than before treatment and patients have demonstrated hemodynamic rebound and decreased exercise tolerance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1489" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The importance of these observations to the routine, clinical use of controlled-release oral isosorbide dinitrate is not known.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1490" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In industrial workers who have had long-term exposure to unknown (presumably high) doses of organic nitrates, tolerance clearly occurs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1491" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Chest pain, acute myocardial infarction, and even sudden death have occurred during temporary withdrawal of nitrates from these workers demonstrating the existence of true physical dependence.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1492" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Information for Patients Patients should be told that the antianginal efficacy of isosorbide dinitrate is strongly related to its dosing regimen, so the prescribed schedule of dosing should be followed carefully.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1493" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In particular, daily headaches sometimes accompany treatment with isosorbide dinitrate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1494" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In patients who get these headaches, the headaches are a marker of the activity of the drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1495" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Patients should resist the temptation to avoid headaches by altering the schedule of their treatment with isosorbide dinitrate, since loss of headache may be associated with simultaneous loss of antianginal efficacy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1496" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Aspirin and/or acetaminophen, on the other hand, often successfully relieve isosorbide dinitrate-induced headaches with no deleterious effect on isosorbide dinitrate's antianginal efficacy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1497" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Treatment with isosorbide dinitrate may be associated with lightheadedness on standing, especially just after rising from a recumbent or seated position.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1498" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>This effect may be more frequent in patients who have also consumed alcohol.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M27" type="Trigger" span="5 27" str="effect may be more frequent"/>
<Mention id="M28" type="Precipitant" span="68 7" str="alcohol" code="3K9958V90M"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M27" precipitant="M28"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1499" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Carcinogenesis, Mutagenesis and Impairment of Fertility No long-term studies in animals have been performed to evaluate the carcinogenic potential of isosorbide dinitrate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1500" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In a modified two-litter reproduction study, there was no remarkable gross pathology and no altered fertility or gestation among rats fed isosorbide dinitrate at 25 or 100 mg/kg/day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1501" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Pregnancy Category C At oral doses 35 and 150 times the daily Maximum Recommended Human Dose (MRHD), isosorbide dinitrate has been shown to cause a dose related increase in embryotoxicity (increase in mummified pups) in rabbits.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1502" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>There are no adequate, well-controlled studies in pregnant women.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1503" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Isosorbide dinitrate should be used during pregnancy only if the potential benefit justifies the potential risk to the fetus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1504" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Nursing Mothers It is not known whether isosorbide dinitrate is excreted in human milk.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1505" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because many drugs are excreted in human milk, caution should be exercised when isosorbide dinitrate is administered to a nursing woman.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1506" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Pediatric Use Safety and effectiveness in pediatric patients have not been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1507" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Geriatric Use Clinical studies of dilatrate®-SR did not include sufficient numbers of subjects aged 65 and over to determine whether they respond differently from younger subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1508" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Other reported clinical experience has not identified differences in responses between the elderly and younger patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1509" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In general, dose selection for an elderly patient should be cautious, usually starting at the low end of the dosing range, reflecting the greater frequency of decreased hepatic, renal, or cardiac function, and of concomitant disease or other drug therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1510" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Amplification of the vasodilatory effects of dilatrate® -SR by sildenafil can result in severe hypotension.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M29" type="Trigger" span="0 16;34 7" str="Amplification of | effects"/>
<Mention id="M33" type="Precipitant" span="63 10" str="sildenafil" code="3M7OB98Y7H"/>
<Mention id="M31" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 41" str="Amplification of the vasodilatory effects" code="91081006: Vasodilatation (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M32" type="Trigger" span="78 9" str="result in"/>
<Mention id="M34" type="SpecificInteraction" span="88 18" str="severe hypotension" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M29" precipitant="M33" effect="M31"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M32" precipitant="M33" effect="M34"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1511" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The time course and dose dependence of this interaction have not been studied.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1512" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Appropriate supportive care has not been studied, but it seems reasonable to treat this as a nitrate overdose, with elevation of the extremities and with central volume expansion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1513" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The benefits of extended-release oral isosorbide dinitrate in patients with acute myocardial infarction or congestive heart failure have not been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1514" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>If one elects to use isosorbide dinitrate in these conditions, careful clinical or hemodynamic monitoring must be used to avoid the hazards of hypotension and tachycardia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1515" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Because the effects of extended-release oral isosorbide dinitrate are so difficult to terminate rapidly, this formulation is not recommended in these settings.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1516" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The principal pharmacological action of isosorbide dinitrate is relaxation of vascular smooth muscle and consequent dilatation of peripheral arteries and veins, especially the latter.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1517" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Dilatation of the veins promotes peripheral pooling of blood and decreases venous return to the heart, thereby reducing left ventricular end-diastolic pressure and pulmonary capillary wedge pressure (preload).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1518" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Arteriolar relaxation reduces systemic vascular resistance, systolic arterial pressure, and mean arterial pressure (afterload).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1519" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Dilatation of the coronary arteries also occurs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1520" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The relative importance of preload reduction, afterload reduction, and coronary dilatation remains undefined.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1521" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Dosing regimens for most chronically used drugs are designed to provide plasma concentrations that are continuously greater than a minimally effective concentration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1522" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This strategy is inappropriate for organic nitrates.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1523" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Several well-controlled clinical trials have used exercise testing to assess the antianginal efficacy of continuously-delivered nitrates.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1524" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In the large majority of these trials, active agents were no more effective than placebo after 24 hours (or less) of continuous therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1525" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Attempts to overcome nitrate tolerance by dose escalation, even to doses far in excess of those used acutely, have consistently failed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1526" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Only after nitrates have been absent from the body for several hours has their antianginal efficacy been restored.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1527" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Pharmacokinetics The kinetics of absorption of isosorbide dinitrate from dilatrate®-SR sustained release capsules have not been well studied.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1528" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Studies of immediate-release formulations of ISDN have found highly variable bioavailability (10 to 90%), with extensive first-pass metabolism in the liver.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1529" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Most such studies have observed progressive increases in bioavailability during chronic therapy; it is not known whether similar increases in bioavailability appear during the course of chronic therapy with dilatrate®-SR sustained release capsules.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1530" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Once absorbed, the distribution volume of isosorbide dinitrate is 2-4 L/kg and this volume is cleared at the rate of 2-4 L/min, so ISDN's half-life in serum is about an hour.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1531" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Since the clearance exceeds hepatic blood flow, considerable extrahepatic metabolism must also occur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1532" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Clearance is affected primarily by denitration to the 2-mononitrate (15 to 25%) and the 5-mononitrate (75 to 85%).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1533" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Both metabolites have biological activity, especially the 5-mononitrate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1534" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>With an overall half-life of about 5 hours, the 5-mononitrate is cleared from the serum by denitration to isosorbide; glucuronidation to the 5-mononitrate glucuronide; and denitration/hydration to sorbitol.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1535" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The 2-mononitrate has been less well studied, but it appears to participate in the same metabolic pathways with a half-life of about 2 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1536" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The interdosing interval sufficient to avoid tolerance to ISDN has not been well defined.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1537" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Studies of nitroglycerin (an organic nitrate with a very short half-life) have shown that dosing intervals of 10-12 hours are usually sufficient to prevent or attenuate tolerance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1538" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Dosing intervals that have succeeded in avoiding tolerance during trials of moderate doses (e.g., 30 mg) of immediate release ISDN have generally been somewhat longer (at least 14 hours), but this is consistent with the longer half-lives of ISDN and its active metabolites.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1539" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>An interdosing interval sufficient to avoid tolerance with dilatrate®-SR has not been demonstrated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1540" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In an eccentric dosing study, 40 mg capsules of dilatrate®-SR were administered daily at 0800 and 1400 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1541" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>After two weeks of this regimen, dilatrate®-SR was statistically indistinguishable from placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1542" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Thus, the necessary interdosing interval sufficient to avoid tolerance remains unknown, but it must be greater than 18 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1543" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Few well-controlled clinical trials of organic nitrates have been designed to detect rebound or withdrawal effects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1544" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In one such trial, however, subjects receiving nitroglycerin had less exercise tolerance at the end of the daily interdosing interval than the parallel group receiving placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1545" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The incidence, magnitude, and clinical significance of similar phenomena in patients receiving ISDN have not been studied.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1546" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Clinical Trials In clinical trials, extended-release oral isosorbide dinitrate has been administered in a variety of regimens, with total daily doses ranging from 40 to 160 mg. A controlled trial using a single 40 mg sustained-release oral dose of isosorbide dinitrate (dilatrate®-SR) has demonstrated effective reductions in exercise-related angina for up to 8 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1547" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Antianginal activity is present about 1 hour after dosing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1548" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Adequate multiple-dose trials of dilatrate®-SR sustained release capsules have not been reported.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1549" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Most controlled trials of multiple-dose immediate-release oral ISDN taken every 12 hours (or more frequently) for several weeks have shown statistically significant antianginal efficacy for only 2 hours after dosing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1550" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Once-daily regimens, and regimens with one daily interdosing interval of at least 14 hours (e.g., a regimen providing doses at 0800, 1400 and 1800 hours), have shown efficacy after the first dose of each day that was similar to that shown in the single dose studies cited above.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1551" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The efficacy of subsequent doses has not been demonstrated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1552" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>From large, well-controlled studies of other nitrates, it is reasonable to believe that the maximal achievable daily duration of antianginal effect from isosorbide dinitrate is about 12 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1553" LabelDrug="Dilatrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No dosing regimen for dilatrate®-SR sustained release capsules has actually been shown to achieve this duration of effect.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="avanafil" precipitantCode="DR5S136IVO"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="drugs for erectile dysfunction" precipitantCode="N0000009040"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="phosphodiesterase inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000000128"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sildenafil" precipitantCode="3M7OB98Y7H" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sildenafil" precipitantCode="3M7OB98Y7H" effect="91081006: Vasodilatation (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="sildenafil" precipitantCode="3M7OB98Y7H"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="tadalafil" precipitantCode="742SXX0ICT"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="vardenafil" precipitantCode="UCE6F4125H"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="riociguat" precipitantCode="RU3FE2Y4XI"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="soluble guanylate cyclase stimulator riociguat" precipitantCode="RU3FE2Y4XI"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="vasodilators" precipitantCode="N0000175940" effect="91081006: Vasodilatation (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="alcohol" precipitantCode="3K9958V90M"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>