<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" setid="08f23f6e-150d-45ea-098e-f2edf64c21a1">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
Dopamine hydrochloride should not be used in patientswith pheochromocytoma. Dopamine should not beadministered in the presence of uncorrected tachyarrhythmias or ventricularfibrillation.</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
Do NOT administer if solution is darker than slightly yellow or discolored in any other way. Do NOT administer unless solution is clear and container is undamaged. Discard unused portion. Dextrose solutions without electrolytes should not be administered simultaneously with blood through the same infusion set because of the possibility that pseudoagglutination of red cells may occur. Do NOT add sodium bicarbonate or other alkalinizing substance, since dopamine is inactivated in alkaline solution. Dopamine Hydrochloride in 5% Dextrose Injection should be infused into a large vein whenever possible to prevent the infiltration of perivascular tissue adjacent to the infusion site. Extravasation may cause necrosis and sloughing of the surrounding tissue. Large veins of the antecubital fossa are preferred to veins of the dorsum of the hand or ankle. Less suitable infusion sites should be used only when larger veins are unavailable and the patient’s condition requires immediate attention. The physician should switch to a more suitable site as soon as possible and the infusion site in use should be continuously monitored for free flow. The less concentrated 800 mcg/mL solution may be preferred when fluid expansion is not a problem. The more concentrated 1600 mcg/mL or 3200 mcg/mL solutions, may be preferred in patients with fluid retention or when a slower rate of infusion is desired.   Rate of Administration: Administration into an umbilical artery catheter is not recommended.  Dopamine in 5% Dextrose Injection should not be infused through ordinary I.V. apparatus, regulated only by gravity and mechanical clamps. Only an infusion pump, preferably a volumetric pump, should be used.  Each patient must be individually titrated to the desired hemodynamic or renal response to dopamine. In titrating to the desired increase in systolic blood pressure, the optimum dosage rate for renal response may be exceeded, thus necessitating a reduction in rate after the hemodynamic condition is stabilized. If a disproportionate rise in diastolic pressure (i.e., a marked decrease in pulse pressure) is observed in patients receiving dopamine, the infusion rate should be decreased and the patient observed carefully for further evidence of predominant vasoconstrictor activity, unless such an effect is desired. Administration rates greater than 50 mcg/kg/min have safely been used in adults in advanced circulatory decompensation states. If unnecessary fluid expansion is of concern, adjustment of drug concentration may be preferred over increasing the flow rate of a less concentrated dilution. When discontinuing the infusion, it may be necessary to gradually decrease the dose of dopamine HCl while expanding the blood volume with I.V. fluids to prevent the development of marked hypotension.   Suggested Regimen:     When appropriate, increase blood volume with whole blood or plasma until central venous pressure is 10 to 15 cm H2O or pulmonary wedge pressure is 14 to 18 mm Hg.   Begin infusion of dopamine hydrochloride solution at doses of 2 to 5 mcg/kg/min in adult or pediatric patients who are likely to respond to modest increments of heart force and renal perfusion. In more seriously ill patients, begin infusion of dopamine hydrochloride at doses of 5 mcg/kg/min and increase gradually, using 5 to 10 mcg/kg/min increments, up to a rate of 20 to 50 mcg/kg/min as needed. If doses in excess of 50 mcg/kg/min are required, check urine output frequently. Should urinary flow begin to decrease in the absence of hypotension, reduction of dopamine dosage should be considered. More than 50% of adult patients have been satisfactorily maintained on doses less than 20 mcg/kg/min. In patients who do not respond to these doses with adequate arterial pressures or urine flow, additional increments of dopamine may be given in an effort to produce an appropriate arterial pressure and central perfusion.   Treatment of all patients requires constant evaluation of therapy in terms of blood volume, augmentation of cardiac contractility, urine flow, cardiac output, blood pressure, and distribution of peripheral perfusion.  Dosage of dopamine should be adjusted according to the patient’s response. Diminution of established urine flow rate, increasing tachycardia or development of new dysrhythmias are reasons to consider decreasing or temporarily suspending the dosage.   As with all potent intravenously administered drugs, care should be taken to control the rate of infusion so as to avoid inadvertent administration of a bolus of the drug.    800 mcg/mL Dosing Chart for Dopamine (mL/hr) Infusion Rate      Infusion rate    (mcg/kg/min)       Patient Body Weight (kg)       10   20   30   40   50   60   70   80   90   100                  2.5   1.9   3.8   5.6   7.5   9.4   11.3   13.1   15   16.9   18.8     5   3.8   7.5   11.3   15   18.8   22.5   26.3   30   33.8   37.5     10   7.5   15   22.5   30   37.5   45   52.5   60   67.5   75     15   11.3   22.5   33.8   45   56.3   67.5   78.8   90   101.3   112.5     20   15   30   45   60   75   90   105   120   135   150     25   18.8   37.5   56.3   75   93.8   112.5   131.3   150   168.8   187.5     30   22.5   45   67.5   90   112.5   135   157.5   180   202.5   225     35   26.3   52.5   78.8   105   131.3   157.5   183.8   210   236.3   262.5     40   30   60   90   120   150   180   210   240   270   300     45   33.8   67.5   101.3   135   168.8   202.5   236.3   270   303.8   337.5     50   37.5   75   112.5   150   187.5   225   262.5   300   337.5   375      1600 mcg/mL Dosing Chart for Dopamine (mL/hr) Infusion Rate      Infusion rate    (mcg/kg/min)       Patient Body Weight (kg)       10   20   30   40   50   60   70   80   90   100                  2.5   0.9   1.9   2.8   3.8   4.7   5.6   6.6   7.5   8.4   9.4     5   1.9   3.8   5.6   7.5   9.4   11.3   13.1   15   16.9   18.8     10   3.8   7.5   11.3   15   18.8   22.5   26.3   30   33.8   37.5     15   5.6   11.3   16.9   22.5   28.1   33.8   39.4   45   50.6   56.3     20   7.5   15   22.5   30   37.5   45   52.5   60   67.5   75     25   9.4   18.8   28.1   37.5   46.9   56.3   65.6   75   84.4   93.8     30   11.3   22.5   33.8   45   56.3   67.5   78.8   90   101.3   112.5     35   13.1   26.3   39.4   52.5   65.6   78.8   91.9   105   118.1   131.3     40   15   30   45   60   75   90   105   120   135   150     45   16.9   33.8   50.6   67.5   84.4   101.3   118.1   135   151.9   168.8     50   18.8   37.5   56.3   75   93.8   112.5   131.3   150   168.8   187.5      3200 mcg/mL Dosing Chart for Dopamine (mL/hr) Infusion Rate      Infusion rate    (mcg/kg/min)       Patient Body Weight (kg)       10   20   30   40   50   60   70   80   90   100                  2.5   0.5   0.9   1.4   1.9   2.3   2.8   3.3   3.8   4.2   4.7     5   0.9   1.9   2.8   3.8   4.7   5.6   6.6   7.5   8.4   9.4     10   1.9   3.8   5.6   7.5   9.4   11.3   13.1   15   16.9   18.8     15   2.8   5.6   8.4   11.3   14.1   16.9   19.7   22.5   25.3   28.1     20   3.8   7.5   11.3   15   18.8   22.5   26.3   30   33.8   37.5     25   4.7   9.4   14.1   18.8   23.4   28.1   32.8   37.5   42.2   46.9     30   5.6   11.3   16.9   22.5   28.1   33.8   39.4   45   50.6   56.3     35   6.6   13.1   19.7   26.3   32.8   39.4   45.9   52.5   59.1   65.6     40   7.5   15   22.5   30   37.5   45   52.5   60   67.5   75     45   8.4   16.9   25.3   33.8   42.2   50.6   59.1   67.5   75.9   84.4     50   9.4   18.8   28.1   37.5   46.9   56.3   65.6   75   84.4   93.8     Parenteral drug products should be visually inspected for particulate matter and discoloration prior to administration, whenever solution and container permit.   INSTRUCTIONS FOR USE     To Open   Tear outer wrap at notch and remove solution container. Some opacity of the plastic due to moisture absorption during the sterilization process may be observed. This is normal and does not affect the solution quality or safety. The opacity will diminish gradually.   Preparation for Administration     (Use aseptic technique)     Close flow control clamp of administration set.   Remove cover from outlet port at bottom of container.   Insert piercing pin of administration set into port with a twisting motion until the set is firmly seated.  NOTE: See full directions on administration set carton.   Suspend container from hanger.   Squeeze and release drip chamber to establish proper fluid level in chamber.   Open flow control clamp and clear air from set. Close clamp.   Attach set to venipuncture device. If device is not indwelling, prime and make venipuncture.   Regulate rate of administration with an infusion pump, preferably a volumetric pump.     WARNING: Do not use flexible container in series connections.</Section>
<Section name="PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="42232-9">
General:   Solutions containing dextrose should be used with caution in patients with known subclinical or overt diabetes mellitus.   Fluid and Electrolyte Balance: Excess administration of potassium-free solutions may result in significant hypokalemia. The intravenous administration of these solutions can cause fluid and/or solute overloading resulting in dilution of serum electrolyte concentrations, overhydration, congested states or pulmonary edema.   Careful Monitoring Required: Close monitoring of the following indices ─ urine flow, cardiac output and blood pressure ─ during dopamine infusion is necessary as in the case of any adrenergic agent.   Hypoxia, Hypercapnia, Acidosis: These conditions, which may also reduce the effectiveness and/or increase the incidence of adverse effects of dopamine, must be identified and corrected prior to, or concurrently with, administration of dopamine HCl.   Ventricular Arrhythmias: If an increased number of ectopic beats are observed the dose should be reduced if possible.   Hypotension: At lower infusion rates, if hypotension occurs, the infusion rate should be rapidly increased until adequate blood pressure is obtained. If hypotension persists, dopamine HCl should be discontinued and a more potent vasoconstrictor agent such as norepinephrine should be administered.   Occlusive Vascular Disease: Patients with a history of occlusive vascular disease (e.g., arteriosclerosis, arterial embolism, Raynaud’s disease, cold injury such as frostbite, diabetic endarteritis, and Buerger’s disease) should be closely monitored for any changes in color or temperature of the skin of the extremities. If a change in skin color or temperature occurs and is thought to be the result of compromised circulation to the extremities, the benefits of continued dopamine infusion should be weighed against the risk of possible necrosis. These changes may be reversed by decreasing the rate or discontinuing the infusion entirely.   Extravasation: Dopamine Hydrochloride in 5% Dextrose Injection, USP should be infused into a large vein whenever possible to prevent the possibility of infiltration of perivascular tissue adjacent to the infusion site. Extravasation may cause necrosis and sloughing of surrounding tissue. Large veins of the antecubital fossa are preferred to veins of the dorsum of the hand or ankle. Administration into an umbilical arterial catheter is not recommended. Less suitable infusion sites should be used only when larger veins are unavailable and the patient’s condition requires immediate attention. The physician should switch to a more suitable site as soon as possible and the infusion site in use should be continuously monitored for free flow.       IMPORTANT ─ Antidote for Peripheral Ischemia: To prevent sloughing and necrosis in ischemic areas, the area should be infiltrated as soon as possible with 10 to 15 mL of 0.9% Sodium Chloride Injection, USP, containing from 5 to 10 mg of Regitine® (brand of phentolamine) an adrenergic blocking agent. Pediatric dosage of Regitine® should be 0.1 ─ 0.2 mg/kg up to a maximum of 10 mg per dose. A syringe with a fine hypodermic needle should be used, and the solution liberally infiltrated throughout the ischemic area. Sympathetic blockade with phentolamine causes immediate and conspicuous local hyperemic changes if the area is infiltrated within 12 hours. Therefore, phentolamine should be given as soon as possible after the extravasation is noted.       Laboratory Tests: Infusion of dopamine suppresses pituitary secretion of thyroid-stimulating hormone, growth hormone, and prolactin.   Weaning: When discontinuing the infusion, it may be necessary to gradually decrease the dose of dopamine HCl while expanding blood volume with IV fluids. Sudden cessation may result in marked hypotension.   Drug Interactions: Cyclopropane or halogenated hydrocarbon anesthetics increase cardiac autonomic irritability and may sensitize the myocardium to the action of certain intravenously administered catecholamines, such as dopamine. This interaction appears to be related both to pressor activity and to the β-adrenergic stimulating properties of these catecholamines, and may produce ventricular arrhythmias and hypertension. Therefore, EXTREME CAUTION should be exercised when administering dopamine HCl to patients receiving cyclopropane or halogenated hydrocarbon anesthetics. Results of studies in animals indicate that dopamine-induced ventricular arrhythmias during anesthesia can be reversed by propranolol. Because dopamine is metabolized by monoamine oxidase (MAO), inhibition of this enzyme prolongs and potentiates the effect of dopamine. Patients who have been treated with MAO inhibitors within two to three weeks prior to the administration of dopamine should receive initial doses of dopamine hydrochloride no greater than one-tenth (1/10) of the usual dose. Concurrent administration of low-dose dopamine HCl and diuretic agents may produce an additive or potentiating effect on urine flow. Tricyclic antidepressants may potentiate the cardiovascular effects of adrenergic agents. Cardiac effects of dopamine are antagonized by β-adrenergic blocking agents, such as propranolol and metoprolol. The peripheral vasoconstriction caused by high doses of dopamine HCl is antagonized by α-adrenergic blocking agents. Dopamine-induced renal and mesenteric vasodilation is not antagonized by either α- or β-adrenergic blocking agents. Butyrophenones (such as haloperidol) and phenothiazines can suppress the dopaminergic renal and mesenteric vasodilation induced with low-dose dopamine infusion. The concomitant use of vasopressors, vasoconstricting agents (such as ergonovine) and some oxytocic drugs may result in severe hypertension. Administration of phenytoin to patients receiving dopamine HCl has been reported to lead to hypotension and bradycardia. It is suggested that in patients receiving dopamine HCl, alternatives to phenytoin should be considered if anticonvulsant therapy is needed.   Carcinogenesis, Mutagenesis, Impairment of Fertility: Long term animal studies have not been performed to evaluate the carcinogenic potential of dopamine HCl. Dopamine HCl at doses approaching maximal solubility showed no clear genotoxic potential in the Ames test. Although there was a reproducible dose-dependent increase in the number of revertant colonies with strains TA100 and TA98, both with and without metabolic activation, the small increase was considered inconclusive evidence of mutagenicity. In the L5178Y TK+/- mouse lymphoma assay, dopamine HCl at the highest concentrations used of 750 μg/mL without metabolic activation, and 3000 μg/mL with activation, was toxic and associated with increases in mutant frequencies when compared to untreated and solvent controls; at the lower concentrations no increases over controls were noted. No clear evidence of clastogenic potential was reported in the  in vivo mouse or male rat bone marrow micronucleus test when the animals were treated intravenously with up to 224 mg/kg and 30 mg/kg of dopamine HCl, respectively.   Pregnancy:   Pregnancy Category C: Teratogenic Effects: Teratogenicity studies in rats and rabbits at dopamine HCl dosages up to 6 mg/kg/day intravenously during organogenesis produced no detectable teratogenic or embryotoxic effects, although maternal toxicity consisting of mortalities, decreased body weight gain, and pharmacotoxic signs were observed in rats. In a published study, dopamine HCl administered at 10 mg/kg subcutaneously for 30 days, markedly prolonged metestrus and increased mean pituitary and ovary weights in female rats. Similar administration to pregnant rats throughout gestation or for 5 days starting on gestation day 10 or 15 resulted in decreased body weight gains, increased mortalities and slight increases in cataract formation among the offspring. There are no adequate and well-controlled studies in pregnant women, and it is not known if dopamine HCl crosses the placental barrier. Dopamine HCl should be used during pregnancy only if the potential benefit justifies the potential risk to the fetus.   Labor and Delivery: In obstetrics, if vasopressor drugs are used to correct hypotension or are added to a local anesthetic solution the interaction with some oxytocic drugs may cause severe hypertension.   Nursing Mothers:  It is not known whether this drug is excreted in human milk. Because many drugs are excreted in human milk, caution should be exercised when dopamine HCl is administered to a nursing mother.   Pediatric Use: Dopamine infusions have been used in patients of every age from birth onwards. There are scattered reports of infusion rates in neonates up to 125 mcg/kg/min, but most reports in pediatric patients describe dosing that is similar (on a mcg/kg/min basis) to that used in adults. Except for vasoconstrictive effects caused by inadvertent infusion of dopamine into the umbilical artery, adverse effects unique to the pediatric population have not been identified, nor have adverse effects identified in adults been found to be more common in pediatric patients.   Geriatric Use: Clinical studies of dopamine injection did not include sufficient numbers of subjects aged 65 and over to determine whether they respond differently from younger subjects. Other reported clinical experience has not identified differences in responses between the elderly and younger patients. In general, dose selection for an elderly patient should be cautious, usually starting at the low end of the dosing range, reflecting the frequency of decreased hepatic, renal or cardiac function, and of concomitant disease or other drug therapy.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS SECTION" id="34071-1">
Do NOT add any alkalinizing substance, since dopamineis inactivated in alkaline solution. Patientswho have been treated with monoamine oxidase (MAO) inhibitors priorto administration of dopamine should receive substantially reduceddosage of the latter. See  PRECAUTIONS, DrugInteractions , below.   Additive medications should not be delivered viathis solution.   Dopamine Hydrochloridein 5% Dextrose Injection, USP contains sodium metabisulfite, a sulfitethat may cause allergic-type reactions including anaphylactic symptomsand life-threatening or less severe asthmatic episodes in certainsusceptible people. The overall prevalence of sulfite sensitivityin the general population is unknown and probably low. Sulfite sensitivityis seen more frequently in asthmatic than in nonasthmatic people.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Dopamine exhibits an inotropic action on the myocardium,resulting in increased cardiac output. It causes less increase inmyocardial oxygen consumption than isoproterenol and the effect ofdopamine usually is not associated with tachyarrhythmia. Reportedclinical studies have revealed that the drug usually increases systolicand pulse pressure without any or only a minor elevating effect ondiastolic pressure. Total peripheral resistance at low and intermediatedoses is usually unchanged. Blood flow to peripheral vascular bedsmay decrease while mesenteric blood flow is increased. The drug alsohas been reported to produce dilation of the renal vasculature whichis accompanied by increases in glomerular filtration rate, renal bloodflow and sodium excretion. Increased urinary output produced by dopamineis usually not associated with decreased urine osmolality. Solutions containing carbohydrate in the form of dextroserestore blood glucose levels and provide calories. Carbohydrate inthe form of dextrose may aid in minimizing liver glycogen depletionand exerts a protein-sparing action. Dextrose injected parenterallyundergoes oxidation to carbon dioxide and water. Water is an essential constituent of all body tissues and accountsfor approximately 70% of total body weight. Average normal adult dailyrequirement ranges from two to three liters (1.0 to 1.5 liters eachfor insensible water loss due to perspiration and urine production). Water balance is maintained by various regulatory mechanisms.Water distribution depends primarily on the concentration of electrolytesand sodium (Na+) plays a major role in maintaining physiologicequilibrium. The reported clearance rate ofdopamine in critically ill infants and children has ranged from 46to 168 mL/kg/min, with the higher values seen in the younger patients.The apparent volume of distribution in neonates is reported as 0.6to 4 L/kg, leading to an elimination half-life of 5 to 11 minutes.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="4234" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Dopamine hydrochloride should not be used in patients with pheochromocytoma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4235" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Dopamine should not be administered in the presence of uncorrected tachyarrhythmias or ventricular fibrillation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4236" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do NOT administer if solution is darker than slightly yellow or discolored in any other way.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4237" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do NOT administer unless solution is clear and container is undamaged.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4238" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dextrose solutions without electrolytes should not be administered simultaneously with blood through the same infusion set because of the possibility that pseudoagglutination of red cells may occur.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M1" type="Trigger" span="40 41;93 29" str="should not be administered simultaneously | through the same infusion set"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="87 5" str="blood" code="B3XJA0OV6T"/>
<Mention id="M3" type="SpecificInteraction" span="155 32" str="pseudoagglutination of red cells" code="302783002: Red blood cell agglutination (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M1" precipitant="M2" effect="M3"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4239" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do NOT add sodium bicarbonate or other alkalinizing substance, since dopamine is inactivated in alkaline solution.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M7" type="Trigger" span="81 11" str="inactivated"/>
<Mention id="M5" type="Precipitant" span="39 22" str="alkalinizing substance" code="N0000009986"/>
<Mention id="M9" type="SpecificInteraction" span="69 23" str="dopamine is inactivated" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M8" type="Precipitant" span="11 18" str="sodium bicarbonate" code="8MDF5V39QO"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M7" precipitant="M5" effect="M9"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M7" precipitant="M8" effect="M9"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4240" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dopamine Hydrochloride in 5% Dextrose Injection should be infused into a large vein whenever possible to prevent the infiltration of perivascular tissue adjacent to the infusion site.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4241" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Extravasation may cause necrosis and sloughing of the surrounding tissue.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4242" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Large veins of the antecubital fossa are preferred to veins of the dorsum of the hand or ankle.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4243" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Less suitable infusion sites should be used only when larger veins are unavailable and the patient's condition requires immediate attention.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4244" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The physician should switch to a more suitable site as soon as possible and the infusion site in use should be continuously monitored for free flow.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4245" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The less concentrated 800 mcg/mL solution may be preferred when fluid expansion is not a problem.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4246" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The more concentrated 1600 mcg/mL or 3200 mcg/mL solutions, may be preferred in patients with fluid retention or when a slower rate of infusion is desired.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4247" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Rate of Administration: Administration into an umbilical artery catheter is not recommended.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4248" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dopamine in 5% Dextrose Injection should not be infused through ordinary intravenous apparatus, regulated only by gravity and mechanical clamps.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4249" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Only an infusion pump, preferably a volumetric pump, should be used.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4250" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Each patient must be individually titrated to the desired hemodynamic or renal response to dopamine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4251" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In titrating to the desired increase in systolic blood pressure, the optimum dosage rate for renal response may be exceeded, thus necessitating a reduction in rate after the hemodynamic condition is stabilized.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4252" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If a disproportionate rise in diastolic pressure (i.e., a marked decrease in pulse pressure) is observed in patients receiving dopamine, the infusion rate should be decreased and the patient observed carefully for further evidence of predominant vasoconstrictor activity, unless such an effect is desired.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4253" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Administration rates greater than 50 mcg/kg/min have safely been used in adults in advanced circulatory decompensation states.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4254" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If unnecessary fluid expansion is of concern, adjustment of drug concentration may be preferred over increasing the flow rate of a less concentrated dilution.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4255" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>When discontinuing the infusion, it may be necessary to gradually decrease the dose of dopamine HCl while expanding the blood volume with intravenous fluids to prevent the development of marked hypotension.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4256" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Suggested Regimen: 1.When appropriate, increase blood volume with whole blood or plasma until central venous pressure is 10 to 15 cm H2O or pulmonary wedge pressure is 14 to 18 mm Hg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4257" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>2.Begin infusion of dopamine hydrochloride solution at doses of 2 to 5 mcg/kg/min in adult or pediatric patients who are likely to respond to modest increments of heart force and renal perfusion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4258" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In more seriously ill patients, begin infusion of dopamine hydrochloride at doses of 5 mcg/kg/min and increase gradually, using 5 to 10 mcg/kg/min increments, up to a rate of 20 to 50 mcg/kg/min as needed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4259" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If doses in excess of 50 mcg/kg/min are required, check urine output frequently.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4260" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Should urinary flow begin to decrease in the absence of hypotension, reduction of dopamine dosage should be considered.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4261" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>More than 50% of adult patients have been satisfactorily maintained on doses less than 20 mcg/kg/min.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4262" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In patients who do not respond to these doses with adequate arterial pressures or urine flow, additional increments of dopamine may be given in an effort to produce an appropriate arterial pressure and central perfusion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4263" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>3.Treatment of all patients requires constant evaluation of therapy in terms of blood volume, augmentation of cardiac contractility, urine flow, cardiac output, blood pressure, and distribution of peripheral perfusion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4264" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dosage of dopamine should be adjusted according to the patient's response.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4265" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Diminution of established urine flow rate, increasing tachycardia or development of new dysrhythmias are reasons to consider decreasing or temporarily suspending the dosage.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4266" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>4.As with all potent intravenously administered drugs, care should be taken to control the rate of infusion so as to avoid inadvertent administration of a bolus of the drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4267" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>800 mcg/mL Dosing Chart for Dopamine (mL/hr) Infusion Rate Infusion rate (mcg/kg/min) Patient Body Weight (kg) 10 20 30 40 50 60 70 80 90 100 2.5 1.9 3.8 5.6 7.5 9.4 11.3 13.1 15 16.9 18.8 5 3.8 7.5 11.3 15 18.8 22.5 26.3 30 33.8 37.5 10 7.5 15 22.5 30 37.5 45 52.5 60 67.5 75 15 11.3 22.5 33.8 45 56.3 67.5 78.8 90 101.3 112.5 20 15 30 45 60 75 90 105 120 135 150 25 18.8 37.5 56.3 75 93.8 112.5 131.3 150 168.8 187.5 30 22.5 45 67.5 90 112.5 135 157.5 180 202.5 225 35 26.3 52.5 78.8 105 131.3 157.5 183.8 210 236.3 262.5 40 30 60 90 120 150 180 210 240 270 300 45 33.8 67.5 101.3 135 168.8 202.5 236.3 270 303.8 337.5 50 37.5 75 112.5 150 187.5 225 262.5 300 337.5 375 1600 mcg/mL Dosing Chart for Dopamine (mL/hr) Infusion Rate Infusion rate Patient Body Weight (kg) (mcg/kg/min) 10 20 30 40 50 60 70 80 90 100 2.5 0.9 1.9 2.8 3.8 4.7 5.6 6.6 7.5 8.4 9.4 5 1.9 3.8 5.6 7.5 9.4 11.3 13.1 15 16.9 18.8 10 3.8 7.5 11.3 15 18.8 22.5 26.3 30 33.8 37.5 15 5.6 11.3 16.9 22.5 28.1 33.8 39.4 45 50.6 56.3 20 7.5 15 22.5 30 37.5 45 52.5 60 67.5 75 25 9.4 18.8 28.1 37.5 46.9 56.3 65.6 75 84.4 93.8 30 11.3 22.5 33.8 45 56.3 67.5 78.8 90 101.3 112.5 35 13.1 26.3 39.4 52.5 65.6 78.8 91.9 105 118.1 131.3 40 15 30 45 60 75 90 105 120 135 150 45 16.9 33.8 50.6 67.5 84.4 101.3 118.1 135 151.9 168.8 50 18.8 37.5 56.3 75 93.8 112.5 131.3 150 168.8 187.5 3200 mcg/mL Dosing Chart for Dopamine (mL/hr) Infusion Rate Infusion rate Patient Body Weight (kg) (mcg/kg/min) 10 20 30 40 50 60 70 80 90 100 2.5 0.5 0.9 1.4 1.9 2.3 2.8 3.3 3.8 4.2 4.7 5 0.9 1.9 2.8 3.8 4.7 5.6 6.6 7.5 8.4 9.4 10 1.9 3.8 5.6 7.5 9.4 11.3 13.1 15 16.9 18.8 15 2.8 5.6 8.4 11.3 14.1 16.9 19.7 22.5 25.3 28.1 20 3.8 7.5 11.3 15 18.8 22.5 26.3 30 33.8 37.5 25 4.7 9.4 14.1 18.8 23.4 28.1 32.8 37.5 42.2 46.9 30 5.6 11.3 16.9 22.5 28.1 33.8 39.4 45 50.6 56.3 35 6.6 13.1 19.7 26.3 32.8 39.4 45.9 52.5 59.1 65.6 40 7.5 15 22.5 30 37.5 45 52.5 60 67.5 75 45 8.4 16.9 25.3 33.8 42.2 50.6 59.1 67.5 75.9 84.4 50 9.4 18.8 28.1 37.5 46.9 56.3 65.6 75 84.4 93.8 Parenteral drug products should be visually inspected for particulate matter and discoloration prior to administration, whenever solution and container permit.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4268" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>General: Solutions containing dextrose should be used with caution in patients with known subclinical or overt diabetes mellitus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4269" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Fluid and Electrolyte Balance: Excess administration of potassium-free solutions may result in significant hypokalemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4270" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The intravenous administration of these solutions can cause fluid and/or solute overloading resulting in dilution of serum electrolyte concentrations, overhydration, congested states or pulmonary edema.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4271" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Careful Monitoring Required: Close monitoring of the following indices ─ urine flow, cardiac output and blood pressure ─ during dopamine infusion is necessary as in the case of any adrenergic agent.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4272" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Hypoxia, Hypercapnia, Acidosis: These conditions, which may also reduce the effectiveness and/or increase the incidence of adverse effects of dopamine, must be identified and corrected prior to, or concurrently with, administration of dopamine HCl.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4273" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Ventricular Arrhythmias: If an increased number of ectopic beats are observed the dose should be reduced if possible.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4274" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Hypotension: At lower infusion rates, if hypotension occurs, the infusion rate should be rapidly increased until adequate blood pressure is obtained.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4275" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>If hypotension persists, dopamine HCl should be discontinued and a more potent vasoconstrictor agent such as norepinephrine should be administered.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4276" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Occlusive Vascular Disease: Patients with a history of occlusive vascular disease (e.g., arteriosclerosis, arterial embolism, Raynaud's disease, cold injury such as frostbite, diabetic endarteritis, and Buerger's disease) should be closely monitored for any changes in color or temperature of the skin of the extremities.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4277" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>If a change in skin color or temperature occurs and is thought to be the result of compromised circulation to the extremities, the benefits of continued dopamine infusion should be weighed against the risk of possible necrosis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4278" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>These changes may be reversed by decreasing the rate or discontinuing the infusion entirely.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4279" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Extravasation: Dopamine Hydrochloride in 5% Dextrose Injection, USP should be infused into a large vein whenever possible to prevent the possibility of infiltration of perivascular tissue adjacent to the infusion site.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4280" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Extravasation may cause necrosis and sloughing of surrounding tissue.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4281" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Administration into an umbilical arterial catheter is not recommended.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4282" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>IMPORTANT ─ Antidote for Peripheral Ischemia: To prevent sloughing and necrosis in ischemic areas, the area should be infiltrated as soon as possible with 10 to 15 mL of 0.9% Sodium Chloride Injection, USP, containing from 5 to 10 mg of Regitine® (brand of phentolamine) an adrenergic blocking agent.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4283" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Pediatric dosage of Regitine® should be 0.1─0.2mg/kg up to a maximum of 10mg per dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4284" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>A syringe with a fine hypodermic needle should be used, and the solution liberally infiltrated throughout the ischemic area.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4285" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Sympathetic blockade with phentolamine causes immediate and conspicuous local hyperemic changes if the area is infiltrated within 12 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4286" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Therefore, phentolamine should be given as soon as possible after the extravasation is noted.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4287" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Laboratory Tests: Infusion of dopamine suppresses pituitary secretion of thyroid’stimulating hormone, growth hormone, and prolactin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4288" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Weaning: When discontinuing the infusion, it may be necessary to gradually decrease the dose of dopamine HCl while expanding blood volume with intravenous fluids.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4289" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Sudden cessation may result in marked hypotension.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4290" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Drug Interactions: Cyclopropane or halogenated hydrocarbon anesthetics increase cardiac autonomic irritability and may sensitize the myocardium to the action of certain intravenously administered catecholamines, such as dopamine.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M19" type="Trigger" span="119 9" str="sensitize"/>
<Mention id="M14" type="Precipitant" span="19 12" str="Cyclopropane" code="99TB643425"/>
<Mention id="M21" type="SpecificInteraction" span="119 24" str="sensitize the myocardium" code="57809008: Myocardial disease (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M18" type="SpecificInteraction" span="71 39" str="increase cardiac autonomic irritability" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M20" type="Precipitant" span="35 35" str="halogenated hydrocarbon anesthetics" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M19" precipitant="M14" effect="M21"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M18" precipitant="M14" effect="M18"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M18" precipitant="M20" effect="M18"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M19" precipitant="M20" effect="M21"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4291" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>This interaction appears to be related both to pressor activity and to the β-adrenergic stimulating properties of these catecholamines, and may produce ventricular arrhythmias and hypertension.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4292" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Therefore, EXTREME CAUTION should be exercised when administering dopamine HCl to patients receiving cyclopropane or halogenated hydrocarbon anesthetics.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M24" type="Trigger" span="11 15" str="EXTREME CAUTION"/>
<Mention id="M23" type="Precipitant" span="101 12" str="cyclopropane" code="99TB643425"/>
<Mention id="M25" type="Precipitant" span="117 35" str="halogenated hydrocarbon anesthetics" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M24" precipitant="M23"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M24" precipitant="M25"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4293" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Results of studies in animals indicate that dopamine-induced ventricular arrhythmias during anesthesia can be reversed by propranolol.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4294" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because dopamine is metabolized by monoamine oxidase (MAO), inhibition of this enzyme prolongs and potentiates the effect of dopamine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4295" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Patients who have been treated with MAO inhibitors within two to three weeks prior to the administration of dopamine should receive initial doses of dopamine hydrochloride no greater than one-tenth (1/10) of the usual dose.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M26" type="Trigger" span="172 50" str="no greater than one-tenth (1/10) of the usual dose"/>
<Mention id="M27" type="Precipitant" span="36 14" str="MAO inhibitors" code="N0000175744"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M26" precipitant="M27" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4296" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Concurrent administration of low-dose dopamine HCl and diuretic agents may produce an additive or potentiating effect on urine flow.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M28" type="Trigger" span="86 31" str="additive or potentiating effect"/>
<Mention id="M29" type="Precipitant" span="55 15" str="diuretic agents" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M30" type="SpecificInteraction" span="86 45" str="additive or potentiating effect on urine flow" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M28" precipitant="M29" effect="M30"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4297" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Tricyclic antidepressants may potentiate the cardiovascular effects of adrenergic agents.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M31" type="Trigger" span="30 10" str="potentiate"/>
<Mention id="M32" type="Precipitant" span="0 25" str="Tricyclic antidepressants" code="N0000175752"/>
<Mention id="M33" type="SpecificInteraction" span="30 37" str="potentiate the cardiovascular effects" code="111970001: Abnormal cardiovascular function (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M31" precipitant="M32" effect="M33"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4298" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Cardiac effects of dopamine are antagonized by β-adrenergic blocking agents, such as propranolol and metoprolol.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M40" type="Trigger" span="32 11" str="antagonized"/>
<Mention id="M35" type="Precipitant" span="101 10" str="metoprolol" code="GEB06NHM23"/>
<Mention id="M42" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 15;32 11" str="Cardiac effects | antagonized" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M38" type="Precipitant" span="85 11" str="propranolol" code="9Y8NXQ24VQ"/>
<Mention id="M41" type="Precipitant" span="47 28" str="β-adrenergic blocking agents" code="N0000175556"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M40" precipitant="M35" effect="M42"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M40" precipitant="M38" effect="M42"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M40" precipitant="M41" effect="M42"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4299" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The peripheral vasoconstriction caused by high doses of dopamine HCl is antagonized by α-adrenergic blocking agents.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M43" type="Trigger" span="72 11" str="antagonized"/>
<Mention id="M44" type="Precipitant" span="87 28" str="α-adrenergic blocking agents" code="N0000175553"/>
<Mention id="M45" type="SpecificInteraction" span="4 27;72 11" str="peripheral vasoconstriction | antagonized" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M43" precipitant="M44" effect="M45"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4300" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Dopamine-induced renal and mesenteric vasodilation is not antagonized by either α- or β-adrenergic blocking agents.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4301" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Butyrophenones (such as haloperidol) and phenothiazines can suppress the dopaminergic renal and mesenteric vasodilation induced with low-dose dopamine infusion.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M52" type="Trigger" span="60 8" str="suppress"/>
<Mention id="M47" type="Precipitant" span="0 14" str="Butyrophenones" code="N0000175741"/>
<Mention id="M54" type="SpecificInteraction" span="60 59" str="suppress the dopaminergic renal and mesenteric vasodilation" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M50" type="Precipitant" span="24 11" str="haloperidol" code="J6292F8L3D"/>
<Mention id="M53" type="Precipitant" span="41 14" str="phenothiazines" code="N0000175746"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M52" precipitant="M47" effect="M54"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M52" precipitant="M50" effect="M54"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M52" precipitant="M53" effect="M54"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4302" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The concomitant use of vasopressors, vasoconstricting agents (such as ergonovine) and some oxytocic drugs may result in severe hypertension.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M64" type="Trigger" span="110 9" str="result in"/>
<Mention id="M56" type="Precipitant" span="70 10" str="ergonovine" code="WH41D8433D"/>
<Mention id="M66" type="SpecificInteraction" span="120 19" str="severe hypertension" code="38341003: Hypertensive disorder, systemic arterial (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M59" type="Precipitant" span="91 14" str="oxytocic drugs" code="N0000175828"/>
<Mention id="M62" type="Precipitant" span="37 23" str="vasoconstricting agents" code="N0000192562"/>
<Mention id="M65" type="Precipitant" span="23 12" str="vasopressors" code="N0000192562"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M64" precipitant="M56" effect="M66"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M64" precipitant="M59" effect="M66"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M64" precipitant="M62" effect="M66"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M64" precipitant="M65" effect="M66"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4303" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Administration of phenytoin to patients receiving dopamine HCl has been reported to lead to hypotension and bradycardia.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M70" type="Trigger" span="84 7" str="lead to"/>
<Mention id="M71" type="Precipitant" span="18 9" str="phenytoin" code="6158TKW0C5"/>
<Mention id="M69" type="SpecificInteraction" span="108 11" str="bradycardia" code="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M72" type="SpecificInteraction" span="92 11" str="hypotension" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M70" precipitant="M71" effect="M69"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M70" precipitant="M71" effect="M72"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4304" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>It is suggested that in patients receiving dopamine HCl, alternatives to phenytoin should be considered if anticonvulsant therapy is needed.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M73" type="Trigger" span="57 12;83 20" str="alternatives | should be considered"/>
<Mention id="M74" type="Precipitant" span="73 9" str="phenytoin" code="6158TKW0C5"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M73" precipitant="M74"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4305" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Carcinogenesis, Mutagenesis, Impairment of Fertility: Long term animal studies have not been performed to evaluate the carcinogenic potential of dopamine HCl.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4306" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Dopamine HCl at doses approaching maximal solubility showed no clear genotoxic potential in the Ames test.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4307" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Although there was a reproducible dose-dependent increase in the number of revertant colonies with strains TA100 and TA98, both with and without metabolic activation, the small increase was considered inconclusive evidence of mutagenicity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4308" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In the L5178Y TK+/- mouse lymphoma assay, dopamine HCl at the highest concentrations used of 750 μg/mL without metabolic activation, and 3000μg/mL with activation, was toxic and associated with increases in mutant frequencies when compared to untreated and solvent controls; at the lower concentrations no increases over controls were noted.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4309" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>No clear evidence of clastogenic potential was reported in the in vivo mouse or male rat bone marrow micronucleus test when the animals were treated intravenously with up to 224 mg/kg and 30 mg/kg of dopamine HCl, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4310" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Pregnancy: Teratogenic Effects: Teratogenicity studies in rats and rabbits at dopamine HCl dosages up to 6 mg/kg/day intravenously during organogenesis produced no detectable teratogenic or embryotoxic effects, although maternal toxicity consisting of mortalities, decreased body weight gain, and pharmacotoxic signs were observed in rats.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4311" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In a published study, dopamine HCl administered at 10 mg/kg subcutaneously for 30 days, markedly prolonged metestrus and increased mean pituitary and ovary weights in female rats.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4312" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Similar administration to pregnant rats throughout gestation or for 5 days starting on gestation day 10 or 15 resulted in decreased body weight gains, increased mortalities and slight increases in cataract formation among the offspring.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4313" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>There are no adequate and well-controlled studies in pregnant women, and it is not known if dopamine HCl crosses the placental barrier.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4314" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Dopamine HCl should be used during pregnancy only if the potential benefit justifies the potential risk to the fetus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4315" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Labor and Delivery: In obstetrics, if vasopressor drugs are used to correct hypotension or are added to a local anesthetic solution the interaction with some oxytocic drugs may cause severe hypertension.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M75" type="Trigger" span="177 5" str="cause"/>
<Mention id="M76" type="Precipitant" span="158 14" str="oxytocic drugs" code="N0000175828"/>
<Mention id="M77" type="SpecificInteraction" span="183 19" str="severe hypertension" code="38341003: Hypertensive disorder, systemic arterial (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M75" precipitant="M76" effect="M77"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4316" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Nursing Mothers: It is not known whether this drug is excreted in human milk.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4317" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because many drugs are excreted in human milk, caution should be exercised when dopamine HCl is administered to a nursing mother.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4318" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Pediatric Use: Dopamine infusions have been used in patients of every age from birth onwards.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4319" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>There are scattered reports of infusion rates in neonates up to 125 mcg/kg/min, but most reports in pediatric patients describe dosing that is similar (on a mcg/kg/min basis) to that used in adults.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4320" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Except for vasoconstrictive effects caused by inadvertent infusion of dopamine into the umbilical artery, adverse effects unique to the pediatric population have not been identified, nor have adverse effects identified in adults been found to be more common in pediatric patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4321" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Geriatric Use: Clinical studies of dopamine injection did not include sufficient numbers of subjects aged 65 and over to determine whether they respond differently from younger subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4322" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Other reported clinical experience has not identified differences in responses between the elderly and younger patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4323" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In general, dose selection for an elderly patient should be cautious, usually starting at the low end of the dosing range, reflecting the frequency of decreased hepatic, renal or cardiac function, and of concomitant disease or other drug therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4324" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Do NOT add any alkalinizing substance, since dopamine is inactivated in alkaline solution.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M78" type="Trigger" span="57 11" str="inactivated"/>
<Mention id="M79" type="Precipitant" span="15 22" str="alkalinizing substance" code="N0000009986"/>
<Mention id="M80" type="SpecificInteraction" span="45 23" str="dopamine is inactivated" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M78" precipitant="M79" effect="M80"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4325" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Patients who have been treated with monoamine oxidase (MAO) inhibitors prior to administration of dopamine should receive substantially reduced dosage of the latter.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M85" type="Trigger" span="136 14" str="reduced dosage"/>
<Mention id="M82" type="Precipitant" span="55 3;60 10" str="MAO | inhibitors" code="N0000175744"/>
<Mention id="M84" type="Precipitant" span="36 34" str="monoamine oxidase (MAO) inhibitors" code="N0000175744"/>
<Mention id="M86" type="Precipitant" span="36 17;60 10" str="monoamine oxidase | inhibitors" code="N0000175744"/>
<Interaction id="I29" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M85" precipitant="M82" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I30" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M85" precipitant="M84" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I31" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M85" precipitant="M86" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4326" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>See PRECAUTIONS, Drug Interactions, below.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4327" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Additive medications should not be delivered via this solution.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M87" type="Trigger" span="21 23" str="should not be delivered"/>
<Mention id="M88" type="Precipitant" span="0 20" str="Additive medications" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I32" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M87" precipitant="M88"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4328" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Dopamine Hydrochloride in 5% Dextrose Injection, USP contains sodium metabisulfite, a sulfite that may cause allergic-type reactions including anaphylactic symptoms and life-threatening or less severe asthmatic episodes in certain susceptible people.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4329" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The overall prevalence of sulfite sensitivity in the general population is unknown and probably low.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4330" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Sulfite sensitivity is seen more frequently in asthmatic than in nonasthmatic people.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4331" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Dopamine exhibits an inotropic action on the myocardium, resulting in increased cardiac output.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4332" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>It causes less increase in myocardial oxygen consumption than isoproterenol and the effect of dopamine usually is not associated with tachyarrhythmia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4333" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Reported clinical studies have revealed that the drug usually increases systolic and pulse pressure without any or only a minor elevating effect on diastolic pressure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4334" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Total peripheral resistance at low and intermediate doses is usually unchanged.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4335" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Blood flow to peripheral vascular beds may decrease while mesenteric blood flow is increased.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4336" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The drug also has been reported to produce dilation of the renal vasculature which is accompanied by increases in glomerular filtration rate, renal blood flow and sodium excretion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4337" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Increased urinary output produced by dopamine is usually not associated with decreased urine osmolality.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4338" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Solutions containing carbohydrate in the form of dextrose restore blood glucose levels and provide calories.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4339" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Carbohydrate in the form of dextrose may aid in minimizing liver glycogen depletion and exerts a protein-sparing action.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4340" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Dextrose injected parenterally undergoes oxidation to carbon dioxide and water.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4341" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Water is an essential constituent of all body tissues and accounts for approximately 70% of total body weight.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4342" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Average normal adult daily requirement ranges from two to three liters (1.0 to 1.5 liters each for insensible water loss due to perspiration and urine production).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4343" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Water balance is maintained by various regulatory mechanisms.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4344" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Water distribution depends primarily on the concentration of electrolytes and sodium (Na+) plays a major role in maintaining physiologic equilibrium.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4345" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The reported clearance rate of dopamine in critically ill infants and children has ranged from 46 to 168mL/kg/min, with the higher values seen in the younger patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4346" LabelDrug="Dopamine Hydrochloride in Dextrose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The apparent volume of distribution in neonates is reported as 0.6 to 4 L/kg, leading to an elimination half-life of 5 to 11 minutes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="blood" precipitantCode="B3XJA0OV6T" effect="302783002: Red blood cell agglutination (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="alkalinizing substance" precipitantCode="N0000009986" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sodium bicarbonate" precipitantCode="8MDF5V39QO" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cyclopropane" precipitantCode="99TB643425" effect="57809008: Myocardial disease (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cyclopropane" precipitantCode="99TB643425" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="cyclopropane" precipitantCode="99TB643425"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="halogenated hydrocarbon anesthetics" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="57809008: Myocardial disease (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="halogenated hydrocarbon anesthetics" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="halogenated hydrocarbon anesthetics" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="mao inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175744" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="diuretic agents" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="tricyclic antidepressants" precipitantCode="N0000175752" effect="111970001: Abnormal cardiovascular function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="metoprolol" precipitantCode="GEB06NHM23" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="propranolol" precipitantCode="9Y8NXQ24VQ" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="β-adrenergic blocking agents" precipitantCode="N0000175556" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="α-adrenergic blocking agents" precipitantCode="N0000175553" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="butyrophenones" precipitantCode="N0000175741" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="haloperidol" precipitantCode="J6292F8L3D" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="phenothiazines" precipitantCode="N0000175746" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ergonovine" precipitantCode="WH41D8433D" effect="38341003: Hypertensive disorder, systemic arterial (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="oxytocic drugs" precipitantCode="N0000175828" effect="38341003: Hypertensive disorder, systemic arterial (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="vasoconstricting agents" precipitantCode="N0000192562" effect="38341003: Hypertensive disorder, systemic arterial (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="vasopressors" precipitantCode="N0000192562" effect="38341003: Hypertensive disorder, systemic arterial (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="phenytoin" precipitantCode="6158TKW0C5" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="phenytoin" precipitantCode="6158TKW0C5" effect="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="phenytoin" precipitantCode="6158TKW0C5"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="mao | inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175744" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="monoamine oxidase (mao) inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175744" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="monoamine oxidase | inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175744" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="additive medications" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>