<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="DYAZIDE" setid="f6eba4b6-9cd0-4c86-46a8-05a202641c89">
<Text><Section name="Boxed Warning section" id="34066-1">
Hyperkalemia: Abnormal elevation of serum potassium levels (greater than or equal to 5.5 mEq/liter) can occur with all potassium-sparing diuretic combinations, including DYAZIDE. Hyperkalemia is more likely to occur in patients with renal impairment and diabetes (even without evidence of renal impairment), and in the elderly or severely ill. Since uncorrected hyperkalemia may be fatal, serum potassium levels must be monitored at frequent intervals especially in patients first receiving DYAZIDE, when dosages are changed or with any illness that may influence renal function.</Section>
<Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
DYAZIDE should not be given to patients receiving other potassium-sparing agents such as spironolactone, amiloride, or other formulations containing triamterene. Concomitant potassium-containing salt substitutes should also not be used. Potassium supplementation should not be used with DYAZIDE except in severe cases of hypokalemia. Such concomitant therapy can be associated with rapid increases in serum potassium levels. If potassium supplementation is used, careful monitoring of the serum potassium level is necessary.          DYAZIDE is contraindicated in patients with anuria, acute and chronic renal insufficiency or significant renal impairment.          Hypersensitivity to either drug in the preparation or to other sulfonamide-derived drugs is a contraindication.          DYAZIDE should not be used in patients with preexisting elevated serum potassium.</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
The usual dose of DYAZIDE is one or two capsules given once daily, with appropriate monitoring of serum potassium and of the clinical effect (see WARNINGS, Hyperkalemia).</Section>
<Section name="DRUG &amp;amp; OR LABORATORY TEST INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34074-5">
Triamterene and quinidine have similar fluorescence spectra; thus, DYAZIDE will interfere with the fluorescent measurement of quinidine.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
Potassium-sparing agents should be used with caution in conjunction with angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE) inhibitors due to an increased risk of hyperkalemia.          Concurrent use with chlorpropamide may increase the risk of severe hyponatremia.          A possible interaction resulting in acute renal failure has been reported in a few patients on DYAZIDE when treated with indomethacin, a nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory agent. Caution is advised in administering nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory agents with DYAZIDE.          Lithium generally should not be given with diuretics because they reduce its renal clearance and increase the risk of lithium toxicity. Read circulars for lithium preparations before use of such concomitant therapy with DYAZIDE.          Thiazides have been shown to decrease arterial responsiveness to norepinephrine (an effect attributed to loss of sodium). This diminution is not sufficient to preclude effectiveness of the pressor agent for therapeutic use. Thiazides have also been shown to increase the paralyzing effect of nondepolarizing muscle relaxants such as tubocurarine (an effect attributed to potassium loss); consequently caution should be observed in patients undergoing surgery.          Concurrent use of hydrochlorothiazide with amphotericin B or corticosteroids or corticotropin (ACTH) may intensify electrolyte imbalance, particularly hypokalemia, although the presence of triamterene minimizes the hypokalemic effect. Thiazides may add to or potentiate the action of other antihypertensive drugs. See INDICATIONS AND USAGE for concomitant use with other antihypertensive drugs. The effect of oral anticoagulants may be decreased when used concurrently with hydrochlorothiazide; dosage adjustments may be necessary. DYAZIDE may raise the level of blood uric acid; dosage adjustments of antigout medication may be necessary to control hyperuricemia and gout. The following agents given together with triamterene may promote serum potassium accumulation and possibly result in hyperkalemia because of the potassium-sparing nature of triamterene, especially in patients with renal insufficiency: blood from blood bank (may contain up to 30 mEq of potassium per liter of plasma or up to 65 mEq per liter of whole blood when stored for more than 10 days); low-salt milk (may contain up to 60 mEq of potassium per liter); potassium-containing medications (such as parenteral penicillin G potassium); salt substitutes (most contain substantial amounts of potassium). Exchange resins, such as sodium polystyrene sulfonate, whether administered orally or rectally, reduce serum potassium levels by sodium replacement of the potassium; fluid retention may occur in some patients because of the increased sodium intake. Chronic or overuse of laxatives may reduce serum potassium levels by promoting excessive potassium loss from the intestinal tract; laxatives may interfere with the potassium-retaining effects of triamterene. The effectiveness of methenamine may be decreased when used concurrently with hydrochlorothiazide because of alkalinization of the urine.</Section>
<Section name="PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="42232-9">
Caution should be exercised when administering DYAZIDE to patients with diabetes, since thiazides may cause hyperglycemia, glycosuria, and alter insulin requirements in diabetes. Also, diabetes mellitus may become manifest during thiazide administration.          Thiazides should be used with caution in patients with impaired hepatic function. They can precipitate hepatic coma in patients with severe liver disease. Potassium depletion induced by the thiazide may be important in this connection. Administer DYAZIDE cautiously and be alert for such early signs of impending coma as confusion, drowsiness, and tremor; if mental confusion increases discontinue DYAZIDE for a few days. Attention must be given to other factors that may precipitate hepatic coma, such as blood in the gastrointestinal tract or preexisting potassium depletion.          Hypokalemia is uncommon with DYAZIDE; but, should it develop, corrective measures should be taken such as potassium supplementation or increased intake of potassium-rich foods. Institute such measures cautiously with frequent determinations of serum potassium levels, especially in patients receiving digitalis or with a history of cardiac arrhythmias. If serious hypokalemia (serum potassium less than 3.0 mEq/L) is demonstrated by repeat serum potassium determinations, DYAZIDE should be discontinued and potassium chloride supplementation initiated. Less serious hypokalemia should be evaluated with regard to other coexisting conditions and treated accordingly.          Electrolyte imbalance, often encountered in such conditions as heart failure, renal disease or cirrhosis of the liver, may also be aggravated by diuretics and should be considered during therapy with DYAZIDE when using high doses for prolonged periods or in patients on a salt-restricted diet. Serum determinations of electrolytes should be performed, and are particularly important if the patient is vomiting excessively or receiving fluids parenterally. Possible fluid and electrolyte imbalance may be indicated by such warning signs as: dry mouth, thirst, weakness, lethargy, drowsiness, restlessness, muscle pain or cramps, muscular fatigue, hypotension, oliguria, tachycardia, and gastrointestinal symptoms.          Although any chloride deficit is generally mild and usually does not require specific treatment except under extraordinary circumstances (as in liver disease or renal disease), chloride replacement may be required in the treatment of metabolic alkalosis. Dilutional hyponatremia may occur in edematous patients in hot weather; appropriate therapy is water restriction, rather than administration of salt, except in rare instances when the hyponatremia is life threatening. In actual salt depletion, appropriate replacement is the therapy of choice.          Triamterene has been found in renal stones in association with the other usual calculus components. DYAZIDE should be used with caution in patients with a history of renal stones.               The normal adult range of serum potassium is 3.5 to 5.0 mEq per liter with 4.5 mEq often being used for a reference point. If hypokalemia should develop, corrective measures should be taken such as potassium supplementation or increased dietary intake of potassium-rich foods. Institute such measures cautiously with frequent determinations of serum potassium levels. Potassium levels persistently above 6 mEq per liter require careful observation and treatment. Serum potassium levels do not necessarily indicate true body potassium concentration. A rise in plasma pH may cause a decrease in plasma potassium concentration and an increase in the intracellular potassium concentration. Discontinue corrective measures for hypokalemia immediately if laboratory determinations reveal an abnormal elevation of serum potassium. Discontinue DYAZIDE and substitute a thiazide diuretic alone until potassium levels return to normal.          DYAZIDE may produce an elevated blood urea nitrogen level, creatinine level or both. This apparently is secondary to a reversible reduction of glomerular filtration rate or a depletion of intravascular fluid volume (prerenal azotemia) rather than renal toxicity; levels usually return to normal when DYAZIDE is discontinued. If azotemia increases, discontinue DYAZIDE. Periodic BUN or serum creatinine determinations should be made, especially in elderly patients and in patients with suspected or confirmed renal insufficiency.          Thiazide may decrease serum PBI levels without sign of thyroid disturbance.          Thiazides should be discontinued before carrying out tests for parathyroid function. Calcium excretion is decreased by thiazides. Pathologic changes in the parathyroid glands with hypercalcemia and hypophosphatemia have been observed in a few patients on prolonged thiazide therapy. The common complications of hyperparathyroidism such as bone resorption and peptic ulceration have not been seen.                 Potassium-sparing agents should be used with caution in conjunction with angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE) inhibitors due to an increased risk of hyperkalemia.          Concurrent use with chlorpropamide may increase the risk of severe hyponatremia.          A possible interaction resulting in acute renal failure has been reported in a few patients on DYAZIDE when treated with indomethacin, a nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory agent. Caution is advised in administering nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory agents with DYAZIDE.          Lithium generally should not be given with diuretics because they reduce its renal clearance and increase the risk of lithium toxicity. Read circulars for lithium preparations before use of such concomitant therapy with DYAZIDE.          Thiazides have been shown to decrease arterial responsiveness to norepinephrine (an effect attributed to loss of sodium). This diminution is not sufficient to preclude effectiveness of the pressor agent for therapeutic use. Thiazides have also been shown to increase the paralyzing effect of nondepolarizing muscle relaxants such as tubocurarine (an effect attributed to potassium loss); consequently caution should be observed in patients undergoing surgery.          Concurrent use of hydrochlorothiazide with amphotericin B or corticosteroids or corticotropin (ACTH) may intensify electrolyte imbalance, particularly hypokalemia, although the presence of triamterene minimizes the hypokalemic effect. Thiazides may add to or potentiate the action of other antihypertensive drugs. See INDICATIONS AND USAGE for concomitant use with other antihypertensive drugs. The effect of oral anticoagulants may be decreased when used concurrently with hydrochlorothiazide; dosage adjustments may be necessary. DYAZIDE may raise the level of blood uric acid; dosage adjustments of antigout medication may be necessary to control hyperuricemia and gout. The following agents given together with triamterene may promote serum potassium accumulation and possibly result in hyperkalemia because of the potassium-sparing nature of triamterene, especially in patients with renal insufficiency: blood from blood bank (may contain up to 30 mEq of potassium per liter of plasma or up to 65 mEq per liter of whole blood when stored for more than 10 days); low-salt milk (may contain up to 60 mEq of potassium per liter); potassium-containing medications (such as parenteral penicillin G potassium); salt substitutes (most contain substantial amounts of potassium). Exchange resins, such as sodium polystyrene sulfonate, whether administered orally or rectally, reduce serum potassium levels by sodium replacement of the potassium; fluid retention may occur in some patients because of the increased sodium intake. Chronic or overuse of laxatives may reduce serum potassium levels by promoting excessive potassium loss from the intestinal tract; laxatives may interfere with the potassium-retaining effects of triamterene. The effectiveness of methenamine may be decreased when used concurrently with hydrochlorothiazide because of alkalinization of the urine.            Triamterene and quinidine have similar fluorescence spectra; thus, DYAZIDE will interfere with the fluorescent measurement of quinidine.               Long-term studies have not been conducted with DYAZIDE (the triamterene/hydrochlorothiazide combination), or with triamterene alone.        Two-year feeding studies in mice and rats, conducted under the auspices of the National Toxicology Program (NTP), treated mice and rats with doses of hydrochlorothiazide up to 600 and 100 mg/kg/day, respectively. On a body-weight basis, these doses are 600 times (in mice) and 100 times (in rats) the Maximum Recommended Human Dose (MRHD) for the hydrochlorothiazide component of DYAZIDE at 50 mg/day (or 1.0 mg/kg/day based on 50 kg individuals). On the basis of body-surface area, these doses are 56 times (in mice) and 21 times (in rats) the MRHD. These studies uncovered no evidence of carcinogenic potential of hydrochlorothiazide in rats or female mice, but there was equivocal evidence of hepatocarcinogenicity in male mice.            Studies of the mutagenic potential of DYAZIDE (the triamterene/hydrochlorothiazide combination), or of triamterene alone have not been performed.        Hydrochlorothiazide was not genotoxic in in vitro assays using strains TA 98, TA 100, TA 1535, TA 1537 and TA 1538 of Salmonella typhimurium (the Ames test); in the Chinese Hamster Ovary (CHO) test for chromosomal aberrations; or in in vivo assays using mouse germinal cell chromosomes, Chinese hamster bone marrow chromosomes, and the Drosophila sex-linked recessive lethal trait gene. Positive test results were obtained in the in vitro CHO Sister Chromatid Exchange (clastogenicity) test, and in the mouse Lymphoma Cell (mutagenicity) assays, using concentrations of hydrochlorothiazide of 43 to 1300 mcg/mL. Positive test results were also obtained in the Aspergillus nidulans nondisjunction assay, using an unspecified concentration of hydrochlorothiazide.            Studies of the effects of DYAZIDE (the triamterene/hydrochlorothiazide combination), or of triamterene alone on animal reproductive function have not been conducted.        Hydrochlorothiazide had no adverse effects on the fertility of mice and rats of either sex in studies wherein these species were exposed, via their diet, to doses of up to 100 and 4 mg/kg/day, respectively, prior to mating and throughout gestation. Corresponding multiples of the MRHD are 100 (mice) and 4 (rats) on the basis of body-weight and 9.4 (mice) and 0.8 (rats) on the basis of body-surface area.                        Animal reproduction studies to determine the potential for fetal harm by DYAZIDE have not been conducted. However, a One Generation Study in the rat approximated composition of DYAZIDE by using a 1:1 ratio of triamterene to hydrochlorothiazide (30:30 mg/kg/day); there was no evidence of teratogenicity at those doses which were, on a body-weight basis, 15 and 30 times, respectively, the MRHD, and on the basis of body-surface area, 3.1 and 6.2 times, respectively, the MRHD. The safe use of DYAZIDE in pregnancy has not been established since there are no adequate and well-controlled studies with DYAZIDE in pregnant women. DYAZIDE should be used during pregnancy only if the potential benefit justifies the risk to the fetus.          Reproduction studies have been performed in rats at doses as high as 20 times the MRHD on the basis of body-weight, and 6 times the human dose on the basis of body-surface area without evidence of harm to the fetus due to triamterene. Because animal reproduction studies are not always predictive of human response, this drug should be used during pregnancy only if clearly needed.          Hydrochlorothiazide was orally administered to pregnant mice and rats during respective periods of major organogenesis at doses up to 3,000 and 1,000 mg/kg/day, respectively. At these doses, which are multiples of the MRHD equal to 3,000 for mice and 1,000 for rats, based on body-weight, and equal to 282 for mice and 206 for rats, based on body-surface area, there was no evidence of harm to the fetus. There are, however, no adequate and well-controlled studies in pregnant women. Because animal reproduction studies are not always predictive of human response, this drug should be used during pregnancy only if clearly needed.              Thiazides and triamterene have been shown to cross the placental barrier and appear in cord blood. The use of thiazides and triamterene in pregnant women requires that the anticipated benefit be weighed against possible hazards to the fetus. These hazards include fetal or neonatal jaundice, pancreatitis, thrombocytopenia, and possible other adverse reactions which have occurred in the adult.            Thiazides and triamterene in combination have not been studied in nursing mothers. Triamterene appears in animal milk; this may occur in humans. Thiazides are excreted in human breast milk. If use of the combination drug product is deemed essential, the patient should stop nursing.          Safety and effectiveness in pediatric patients have not been established.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS SECTION" id="34071-1">
Hyperkalemia: Abnormal elevation of serum potassium levels (greater than or equal to 5.5 mEq/liter) can occur with all potassium-sparing diuretic combinations, including DYAZIDE. Hyperkalemia is more likely to occur in patients with renal impairment and diabetes (even without evidence of renal impairment), and in the elderly or severely ill. Since uncorrected hyperkalemia may be fatal, serum potassium levels must be monitored at frequent intervals especially in patients first receiving DYAZIDE, when dosages are changed or with any illness that may influence renal function.          If hyperkalemia is suspected (warning signs include paresthesias, muscular weakness, fatigue, flaccid paralysis of the extremities, bradycardia, and shock), an electrocardiogram (ECG) should be obtained. However, it is important to monitor serum potassium levels because hyperkalemia may not be associated with ECG changes. If hyperkalemia is present, DYAZIDE should be discontinued immediately and a thiazide alone should be substituted. If the serum potassium exceeds 6.5 mEq/liter more vigorous therapy is required. The clinical situation dictates the procedures to be employed. These include the intravenous administration of calcium chloride solution, sodium bicarbonate solution, and/or the oral or parenteral administration of glucose with a rapid-acting insulin preparation. Cationic exchange resins such as sodium polystyrene sulfonate may be orally or rectally administered. Persistent hyperkalemia may require dialysis. The development of hyperkalemia associated with potassium-sparing diuretics is accentuated in the presence of renal impairment (see CONTRAINDICATIONS section). Patients with mild renal functional impairment should not receive this drug without frequent and continuing monitoring of serum electrolytes. Cumulative drug effects may be observed in patients with impaired renal function. The renal clearances of hydrochlorothiazide and the pharmacologically active metabolite of triamterene, the sulfate ester of hydroxytriamterene, have been shown to be reduced and the plasma levels increased following administration of DYAZIDE to elderly patients and patients with impaired renal function. Hyperkalemia has been reported in diabetic patients with the use of potassium-sparing agents even in the absence of apparent renal impairment. Accordingly, serum electrolytes must be frequently monitored if DYAZIDE is used in diabetic patients.          Potassium-sparing therapy should also be avoided in severely ill patients in whom respiratory or metabolic acidosis may occur. Acidosis may be associated with rapid elevations in serum potassium levels. If DYAZIDE is employed, frequent evaluations of acid/base balance and serum electrolytes are necessary.          Hydrochlorothiazide, a sulfonamide, can cause an idiosyncratic reaction, resulting in acute transient myopia and acute angle-closure glaucoma. Symptoms include acute onset of decreased visual acuity or ocular pain and typically occur within hours to weeks of drug initiation. Untreated acute angle-closure glaucoma can lead to permanent vision loss. The primary treatment is to discontinue hydrochlorothiazide as rapidly as possible. Prompt medical or surgical treatments may need to be considered if the intraocular pressure remains uncontrolled. Risk factors for developing acute angle-closure glaucoma may include a history of sulfonamide or penicillin allergy.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
DYAZIDE is a diuretic/antihypertensive drug product that combines natriuretic and antikaliuretic effects. Each component complements the action of the other. The hydrochlorothiazide component blocks the reabsorption of sodium and chloride ions, and thereby increases the quantity of sodium traversing the distal tubule and the volume of water excreted. A portion of the additional sodium presented to the distal tubule is exchanged there for potassium and hydrogen ions. With continued use of hydrochlorothiazide and depletion of sodium, compensatory mechanisms tend to increase this exchange and may produce excessive loss of potassium, hydrogen, and chloride ions. Hydrochlorothiazide also decreases the excretion of calcium and uric acid, may increase the excretion of iodide, and may reduce glomerular filtration rate. The exact mechanism of the antihypertensive effect of hydrochlorothiazide is not known. The triamterene component of DYAZIDE exerts its diuretic effect on the distal renal tubule to inhibit the reabsorption of sodium in exchange for potassium and hydrogen ions. Its natriuretic activity is limited by the amount of sodium reaching its site of action. Although it blocks the increase in this exchange that is stimulated by mineralocorticoids (chiefly aldosterone), it is not a competitive antagonist of aldosterone and its activity can be demonstrated in adrenalectomized rats and patients with Addison’s disease. As a result, the dose of triamterene required is not proportionally related to the level of mineralocorticoid activity, but is dictated by the response of the individual patients, and the kaliuretic effect of concomitantly administered drugs. By inhibiting the distal tubular exchange mechanism, triamterene maintains or increases the sodium excretion and reduces the excess loss of potassium, hydrogen and chloride ions induced by hydrochlorothiazide. As with hydrochlorothiazide, triamterene may reduce glomerular filtration and renal plasma flow. Via this mechanism it may reduce uric acid excretion although it has no tubular effect on uric acid reabsorption or secretion. Triamterene does not affect calcium excretion. No predictable antihypertensive effect has been demonstrated for triamterene. Duration of diuretic activity and effective dosage range of the hydrochlorothiazide and triamterene components of DYAZIDE are similar. Onset of diuresis with DYAZIDE takes place within 1 hour, peaks at 2 to 3 hours and tapers off during the subsequent 7 to 9 hours. DYAZIDE is well absorbed. Upon administration of a single oral dose to fasted normal male volunteers, the following mean pharmacokinetic parameters were determined:            AUC(0-48)    ng*hrs/mL    (± SD)     Cmax    ng/mL   (± SD)     Median   Tmax    Hrs     Ae   Mg   (± SD)      Triamterene   148.7 (87.9)   46.4 (29.4)   1.1   2.7 (1.4)     hydroxytriamterene   sulfate   1,865 (471)   720 (364)   1.3   19.7 (6.1)     hydrochlorothiazide   834 (177)   135.1 (35.7)   2.0   14.3 (3.8)     where AUC(0-48), Cmax, Tmax and Ae represent area under the plasma concentration versus time plot, maximum plasma concentration, time to reach Cmax, and amount excreted in urine over 48 hours. A capsule of DYAZIDE is bioequivalent to a single-entity 25 mg hydrochlorothiazide tablet and 37.5 mg triamterene capsule used in the double-blind clinical trial below (see Clinical Trials). In a limited study involving 12 subjects, coadministration of DYAZIDE with a high-fat meal resulted in: (1) an increase in the mean bioavailability of triamterene by about 67% (90% confidence interval = 0.99, 1.90), p-hydroxytriamterene sulfate by about 50% (90% confidence interval = 1.06, 1.77), hydrochlorothiazide by about 17% (90% confidence interval = 0.90, 1.34); (2) increases in the peak concentrations of triamterene and p-hydroxytriamterene; and (3) a delay of up to 2 hours in the absorption of the active constituents.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="4094" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Hyperkalemia: Abnormal elevation of serum potassium levels (greater than or equal to 5.5mEq/liter) can occur with all potassium-sparing diuretic combinations, including DYAZIDE.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4095" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Hyperkalemia is more likely to occur in patients with renal impairment and diabetes (even without evidence of renal impairment), and in the elderly or severely ill.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4096" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Since uncorrected hyperkalemia may be fatal, serum potassium levels must be monitored at frequent intervals especially in patients first receiving DYAZIDE, when dosages are changed, or with any illness that may influence renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4097" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>DYAZIDE should not be given to patients receiving other potassium-sparing agents such as spironolactone, amiloride, or other formulations containing triamterene.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M7" type="Trigger" span="8 19" str="should not be given"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="105 9" str="amiloride" code="7DZO8EB0Z3"/>
<Mention id="M4" type="Precipitant" span="125 35" str="formulations containing triamterene" code="WS821Z52LQ"/>
<Mention id="M6" type="Precipitant" span="56 24" str="potassium-sparing agents" code="N0000175418"/>
<Mention id="M8" type="Precipitant" span="89 14" str="spironolactone" code="27O7W4T232"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M7" precipitant="M2"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M7" precipitant="M4"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M7" precipitant="M6"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M7" precipitant="M8"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4098" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Concomitant potassium-containing salt substitutes should also not be used.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M9" type="Trigger" span="50 6;62 11" str="should | not be used"/>
<Mention id="M10" type="Precipitant" span="12 37" str="potassium-containing salt substitutes" code="N0000175600"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M9" precipitant="M10"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4099" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Potassium supplementation should not be used with DYAZIDE except in severe cases of hypokalemia.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M11" type="Trigger" span="26 18" str="should not be used"/>
<Mention id="M12" type="Precipitant" span="0 25" str="Potassium supplementation" code="RWP5GA015D"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M11" precipitant="M12"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4100" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Such concomitant therapy can be associated with rapid increases in serum potassium levels.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4101" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>If potassium supplementation is used, careful monitoring of the serum potassium level is necessary.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M13" type="Trigger" span="38 18" str="careful monitoring"/>
<Mention id="M14" type="Precipitant" span="3 25" str="potassium supplementation" code="RWP5GA015D"/>
<Mention id="M15" type="SpecificInteraction" span="64 21" str="serum potassium level" code="24529006: Potassium disorder (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M13" precipitant="M14" effect="M15"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4102" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>DYAZIDE is contraindicated in patients with anuria, acute and chronic renal insufficiency, or significant renal impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4103" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Hypersensitivity to either drug in the preparation or to other sulfonamide-derived drugs is a contraindication.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4104" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>DYAZIDE should not be used in patients with pre-existing elevated serum potassium.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4105" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The usual dose of DYAZIDE is 1 or 2 capsules given once daily, with appropriate monitoring of serum potassium and of the clinical effect.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4106" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34074-5">
<SentenceText>Triamterene and quinidine have similar fluorescence spectra; thus, DYAZIDE will interfere with the fluorescent measurement of quinidine.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M18" type="SpecificInteraction" span="80 42" str="interfere with the fluorescent measurement" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M17" type="Precipitant" span="16 9" str="quinidine" code="ITX08688JL"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M18" precipitant="M17" effect="M18"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4107" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Potassium-sparing agents should be used with caution in conjunction with angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE) inhibitors due to an increased risk of hyperkalemia.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M25" type="Trigger" span="130 14" str="increased risk"/>
<Mention id="M20" type="Precipitant" span="104 3;109 10" str="ACE | inhibitors" code="N0000175562"/>
<Mention id="M27" type="SpecificInteraction" span="148 12" str="hyperkalemia" code="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M23" type="Precipitant" span="73 46" str="angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE) inhibitors" code="N0000175562"/>
<Mention id="M26" type="Precipitant" span="73 29;109 10" str="angiotensin-converting enzyme | inhibitors" code="N0000175562"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M25" precipitant="M20" effect="M27"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M25" precipitant="M23" effect="M27"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M25" precipitant="M26" effect="M27"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4108" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Concurrent use with chlorpropamide may increase the risk of severe hyponatremia.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M28" type="Trigger" span="39 17" str="increase the risk"/>
<Mention id="M29" type="Precipitant" span="20 14" str="chlorpropamide" code="WTM2C3IL2X"/>
<Mention id="M30" type="SpecificInteraction" span="60 19" str="severe hyponatremia" code="89627008: Hyponatremia (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M28" precipitant="M29" effect="M30"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4109" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>A possible interaction resulting in acute renal failure has been reported in a few patients on DYAZIDE when treated with indomethacin, a nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory agent.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M34" type="Trigger" span="11 11" str="interaction"/>
<Mention id="M32" type="Precipitant" span="121 12" str="indomethacin" code="XXE1CET956"/>
<Mention id="M36" type="SpecificInteraction" span="36 19" str="acute renal failure" code="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M35" type="Precipitant" span="137 36" str="nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory agent" code="N0000175722"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M34" precipitant="M32" effect="M36"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M34" precipitant="M35" effect="M36"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4110" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Caution is advised in administering nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory agents with DYAZIDE.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M37" type="Trigger" span="0 7" str="Caution"/>
<Mention id="M38" type="Precipitant" span="36 37" str="nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory agents" code="N0000175722"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M37" precipitant="M38"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4111" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Lithium generally should not be given with diuretics because they reduce its renal clearance and increase the risk of lithium toxicity.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M39" type="Trigger" span="66 26" str="reduce its renal clearance "/>
<Mention id="M40" type="Trigger" span="126 8" str=" toxicity"/>
<Mention id="M41" type="Precipitant" span="118 7" str="lithium" code="9FN79X2M3F"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M39;M40" precipitant="M41" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4112" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Read circulars for lithium preparations before use of such concomitant therapy with DYAZIDE.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M42" type="Trigger" span="0 14;40 10" str="Read circulars | before use"/>
<Mention id="M43" type="Precipitant" span="19 20" str="lithium preparations" code="9FN79X2M3F"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M42" precipitant="M43"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4113" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Thiazides have been shown to decrease arterial responsiveness to norepinephrine (an effect attributed to loss of sodium).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M44" type="Trigger" span="29 8;47 14" str="decrease | responsiveness"/>
<Mention id="M48" type="Precipitant" span="65 14" str="norepinephrine" code="X4W3ENH1CV"/>
<Mention id="M46" type="SpecificInteraction" span="29 32" str="decrease arterial responsiveness" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M49" type="SpecificInteraction" span="105 14" str="loss of sodium" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M44" precipitant="M48" effect="M46"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M49" precipitant="M48" effect="M49"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4114" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>This diminution is not sufficient to preclude effectiveness of the pressor agent for therapeutic use.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4115" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Thiazides have also been shown to increase the paralyzing effect of nondepolarizing muscle relaxants such as tubocurarine (an effect attributed to potassium loss); consequently, caution should be observed in patients undergoing surgery.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M58" type="SpecificInteraction" span="147 14" str="potassium loss" code="24529006: Potassium disorder (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M54" type="Precipitant" span="68 32" str="nondepolarizing muscle relaxants" code="N0000175737"/>
<Mention id="M59" type="Trigger" span="34 8;58 6" str="increase | effect"/>
<Mention id="M61" type="SpecificInteraction" span="34 30" str="increase the paralyzing effect" code="44695005: Paralysis (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M60" type="Precipitant" span="109 12" str="tubocurarine" code="W9YXS298BM"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M58" precipitant="M54" effect="M58"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M59" precipitant="M54" effect="M61"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M58" precipitant="M60" effect="M58"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M59" precipitant="M60" effect="M61"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4116" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Concurrent use of hydrochlorothiazide with amphotericin B or corticosteroids or corticotropin (ACTH) may intensify electrolyte imbalance, particularly hypokalemia, although the presence of triamterene minimizes the hypokalemic effect.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M90" type="Trigger" span="105 31" str="intensify electrolyte imbalance "/>
<Mention id="M91" type="Trigger" span="151 11" str=" hypokalemia"/>
<Mention id="M68" type="Precipitant" span="95 4" str="ACTH" code="K0U68Q2TXA"/>
<Mention id="M93" type="SpecificInteraction" span="105 31" str="intensify electrolyte imbalance" code="166686006: Electrolytes abnormal (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M89" type="SpecificInteraction" span="151 11" str="hypokalemia" code="43339004: Hypokalemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M76" type="Precipitant" span="43 14" str="amphotericin B" code="7XU7A7DROE"/>
<Mention id="M84" type="Precipitant" span="61 15" str="corticosteroids" code="N0000175576"/>
<Mention id="M92" type="Precipitant" span="80 13" str="corticotropin" code="K0U68Q2TXA"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M90;M91" precipitant="M68" effect="M93"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M90;M91" precipitant="M68" effect="M89"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M90;M91" precipitant="M76" effect="M89"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M90;M91" precipitant="M76" effect="M93"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M90;M91" precipitant="M84" effect="M89"/>
<Interaction id="I29" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M90;M91" precipitant="M84" effect="M93"/>
<Interaction id="I30" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M90;M91" precipitant="M92" effect="M89"/>
<Interaction id="I31" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M90;M91" precipitant="M92" effect="M93"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4117" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Thiazides may add to or potentiate the action of other antihypertensive drugs.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M94" type="Trigger" span="14 20" str="add to or potentiate"/>
<Mention id="M95" type="Precipitant" span="55 22" str="antihypertensive drugs" code="N0000178477"/>
<Mention id="M96" type="SpecificInteraction" span="14 63" str="add to or potentiate the action of other antihypertensive drugs" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I32" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M94" precipitant="M95" effect="M96"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4118" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>See INDICATIONS AND USAGE for concomitant use with other antihypertensive drugs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4119" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The effect of oral anticoagulants may be decreased when used concurrently with hydrochlorothiazide; dosage adjustments may be necessary.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M97" type="Trigger" span="4 6;41 9" str="effect | decreased"/>
<Mention id="M98" type="Precipitant" span="14 19" str="oral anticoagulants" code="N0000175980"/>
<Mention id="M99" type="SpecificInteraction" span="4 46" str="effect of oral anticoagulants may be decreased" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I33" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M97" precipitant="M98" effect="M99"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4120" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>DYAZIDE may raise the level of blood uric acid; dosage adjustments of antigout medication may be necessary to control hyperuricemia and gout.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M110" type="Trigger" span="12 34" str="raise the level of blood uric acid "/>
<Mention id="M111" type="Trigger" span="118 13" str=" hyperuricemia "/>
<Mention id="M112" type="Trigger" span="74 4" str=" gout"/>
<Mention id="M113" type="Precipitant" span="70 19" str="antigout medication" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M104" type="SpecificInteraction" span="74 4" str="gout" code="90560007: Inflammatory disorder due to increased blood urate level (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M109" type="SpecificInteraction" span="118 13" str="hyperuricemia" code="35885006: Hyperuricemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M114" type="SpecificInteraction" span="12 34" str="raise the level of blood uric acid" code="49099001: Increased uric acid level (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I34" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M110;M111;M112" precipitant="M113" effect="M104"/>
<Interaction id="I35" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M110;M111;M112" precipitant="M113" effect="M109"/>
<Interaction id="I36" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M110;M111;M112" precipitant="M113" effect="M114"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4121" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The following agents given together with triamterene may promote serum potassium accumulation and possibly result in hyperkalemia because of the potassium-sparing nature of triamterene, especially in patients with renal insufficiency: blood from blood bank (may contain potassium up to 30mEq/L of plasma or up to 65mEq/L of whole blood when stored for more than 10days); low-salt milk (may contain potassium up to 60mEq/L); potassium-containing medications (such as parenteral penicillin G potassium); salt substitutes (most contain substantial amounts of potassium).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M151" type="Trigger" span="57 36" str="promote serum potassium accumulation "/>
<Mention id="M152" type="Trigger" span="117 12" str=" hyperkalemia"/>
<Mention id="M121" type="Precipitant" span="235 21" str="blood from blood bank" code="B3XJA0OV6T"/>
<Mention id="M150" type="SpecificInteraction" span="117 12" str="hyperkalemia" code="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M154" type="SpecificInteraction" span="57 36" str="promote serum potassium accumulation" code="166689004: Raised serum potassium level (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M129" type="Precipitant" span="371 13" str="low-salt milk" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M137" type="Precipitant" span="477 22" str="penicillin G potassium" code="VL775ZTH4C"/>
<Mention id="M145" type="Precipitant" span="424 32" str="potassium-containing medications" code="RWP5GA015D"/>
<Mention id="M153" type="Precipitant" span="502 16" str="salt substitutes" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I37" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M151;M152" precipitant="M121" effect="M150"/>
<Interaction id="I38" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M151;M152" precipitant="M121" effect="M154"/>
<Interaction id="I39" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M151;M152" precipitant="M129" effect="M150"/>
<Interaction id="I40" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M151;M152" precipitant="M129" effect="M154"/>
<Interaction id="I41" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M151;M152" precipitant="M137" effect="M154"/>
<Interaction id="I42" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M151;M152" precipitant="M137" effect="M150"/>
<Interaction id="I43" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M151;M152" precipitant="M145" effect="M150"/>
<Interaction id="I44" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M151;M152" precipitant="M145" effect="M154"/>
<Interaction id="I45" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M151;M152" precipitant="M153" effect="M150"/>
<Interaction id="I46" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M151;M152" precipitant="M153" effect="M154"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4122" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Exchange resins, such as sodium polystyrene sulfonate, whether administered orally or rectally, reduce serum potassium levels by sodium replacement of the potassium; fluid retention may occur in some patients because of the increased sodium intake.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M180" type="Trigger" span="96 29" str="reduce serum potassium levels "/>
<Mention id="M181" type="Trigger" span="166 15" str=" fluid retention "/>
<Mention id="M182" type="Trigger" span="224 23" str=" increased sodium intake"/>
<Mention id="M168" type="Precipitant" span="0 15" str="Exchange resins" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M174" type="SpecificInteraction" span="166 15" str="fluid retention" code="43498006: Body fluid retention (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M184" type="SpecificInteraction" span="224 23" str="increased sodium intake" code="440921000124100: Excessive sodium intake (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M179" type="SpecificInteraction" span="96 29" str="reduce serum potassium levels" code="712827009: Serum potassium level below reference range (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M183" type="Precipitant" span="25 28" str="sodium polystyrene sulfonate" code="1699G8679Z"/>
<Interaction id="I47" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M180;M181;M182" precipitant="M168" effect="M174"/>
<Interaction id="I48" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M180;M181;M182" precipitant="M168" effect="M184"/>
<Interaction id="I49" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M180;M181;M182" precipitant="M168" effect="M179"/>
<Interaction id="I50" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M180;M181;M182" precipitant="M183" effect="M174"/>
<Interaction id="I51" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M180;M181;M182" precipitant="M183" effect="M179"/>
<Interaction id="I52" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M180;M181;M182" precipitant="M183" effect="M184"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4123" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Chronic or overuse of laxatives may reduce serum potassium levels by promoting excessive potassium loss from the intestinal tract; laxatives may interfere with the potassium-retaining effects of triamterene.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M185" type="Trigger" span="145 14" str="interfere with"/>
<Mention id="M192" type="Precipitant" span="22 9" str="laxatives" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M187" type="SpecificInteraction" span="145 46" str="interfere with the potassium-retaining effects" code="24529006: Potassium disorder (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M190" type="SpecificInteraction" span="36 29" str="reduce serum potassium levels" code="712827009: Serum potassium level below reference range (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M191" type="Trigger" span="79 24" str="excessive potassium loss"/>
<Mention id="M193" type="SpecificInteraction" span="79 50" str="excessive potassium loss from the intestinal tract" code="24529006: Potassium disorder (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I53" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M185" precipitant="M192" effect="M187"/>
<Interaction id="I54" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M190" precipitant="M192" effect="M190"/>
<Interaction id="I55" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M191" precipitant="M192" effect="M193"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4124" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The effectiveness of methenamine may be decreased when used concurrently with hydrochlorothiazide because of alkalinization of the urine.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M196" type="SpecificInteraction" span="109 27" str="alkalinization of the urine" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M198" type="Precipitant" span="21 11" str="methenamine" code="J50OIX95QV"/>
<Mention id="M197" type="Trigger" span="4 13;40 9" str="effectiveness | decreased"/>
<Mention id="M199" type="SpecificInteraction" span="4 45" str="effectiveness of methenamine may be decreased" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I56" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M196" precipitant="M198" effect="M196"/>
<Interaction id="I57" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M197" precipitant="M198" effect="M199"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4125" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Caution should be exercised when administering DYAZIDE to patients with diabetes, since thiazides may cause hyperglycemia, glycosuria, and alter insulin requirements in diabetes.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M200" type="Trigger" span="139 5;153 12" str="alter | requirements"/>
<Mention id="M201" type="Precipitant" span="145 7" str="insulin" code="N0000175944"/>
<Interaction id="I58" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M200" precipitant="M201"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4126" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Also, diabetes mellitus may become manifest during thiazide administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4127" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Thiazides should be used with caution in patients with impaired hepatic function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4128" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>They can precipitate hepatic coma in patients with severe liver disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4129" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Potassium depletion induced by the thiazide may be important in this connection.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4130" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Administer DYAZIDE cautiously and be alert for such early signs of impending coma as confusion, drowsiness, and tremor; if mental confusion increases, discontinue DYAZIDE for a few days.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4131" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Attention must be given to other factors that may precipitate hepatic coma, such as blood in the gastrointestinal tract or pre-existing potassium depletion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4132" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Hypokalemia is uncommon with DYAZIDE; but, should it develop, corrective measures should be taken such as potassium supplementation or increased intake of potassium-rich foods.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4133" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Institute such measures cautiously with frequent determinations of serum potassium levels, especially in patients receiving digitalis or with a history of cardiac arrhythmias.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M202" type="Trigger" span="40 23" str="frequent determinations"/>
<Mention id="M203" type="Precipitant" span="124 9" str="digitalis" code="F1T8QT9U8B"/>
<Mention id="M204" type="SpecificInteraction" span="67 22" str="serum potassium levels" code="24529006: Potassium disorder (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I59" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M202" precipitant="M203" effect="M204"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4134" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>If serious hypokalemia (serum potassium less than 3.0mEq/L) is demonstrated by repeat serum potassium determinations, DYAZIDE should be discontinued and potassium chloride supplementation initiated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4135" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Less serious hypokalemia should be evaluated with regard to other coexisting conditions and treated accordingly.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4136" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Electrolyte imbalance, often encountered in such conditions as heart failure, renal disease, or cirrhosis of the liver, may also be aggravated by diuretics and should be considered during therapy with DYAZIDE when using high doses for prolonged periods or in patients on a salt-restricted diet.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4137" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Serum determinations of electrolytes should be performed and are particularly important if the patient is vomiting excessively or receiving fluids parenterally.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4138" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Possible fluid and electrolyte imbalance may be indicated by such warning signs as: dry mouth, thirst, weakness, lethargy, drowsiness, restlessness, muscle pain or cramps, muscular fatigue, hypotension, oliguria, tachycardia, and gastrointestinal symptoms.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4139" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Although any chloride deficit is generally mild and usually does not require specific treatment except under extraordinary circumstances (as in liver disease or renal disease), chloride replacement may be required in the treatment of metabolic alkalosis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4140" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Dilutional hyponatremia may occur in edematous patients in hot weather; appropriate therapy is water restriction, rather than administration of salt, except in rare instances when the hyponatremia is life threatening.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4141" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In actual salt depletion, appropriate replacement is the therapy of choice.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4142" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Triamterene has been found in renal stones in association with the other usual calculus components.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4143" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>DYAZIDE should be used with caution in patients with a history of renal stones.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4144" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The normal adult range of serum potassium is 3.5 to 5.0mEq/L with 4.5mEq often being used for a reference point.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4145" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>If hypokalemia should develop, corrective measures should be taken such as potassium supplementation or increased dietary intake of potassium-rich foods.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4146" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Institute such measures cautiously with frequent determinations of serum potassium levels.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4147" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Potassium levels persistently above 6mEq/L require careful observation and treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4148" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Serum potassium levels do not necessarily indicate true body potassium concentration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4149" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>A rise in plasma pH may cause a decrease in plasma potassium concentration and an increase in the intracellular potassium concentration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4150" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Discontinue corrective measures for hypokalemia immediately if laboratory determinations reveal an abnormal elevation of serum potassium.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4151" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Discontinue DYAZIDE and substitute a thiazide diuretic alone until potassium levels return to normal.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4152" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>DYAZIDE may produce an elevated blood urea nitrogen (BUN) level, creatinine level, or both.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4153" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>This apparently is secondary to a reversible reduction of glomerular filtration rate or a depletion of intravascular fluid volume (prerenal azotemia) rather than renal toxicity; levels usually return to normal when DYAZIDE is discontinued.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4154" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>If azotemia increases, discontinue DYAZIDE.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4155" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Periodic BUN or serum creatinine determinations should be made, especially in elderly patients and in patients with suspected or confirmed renal insufficiency.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4156" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Thiazide may decrease serum protein-bound iodine (PBI) levels without sign of thyroid disturbance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4157" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Thiazides should be discontinued before carrying out tests for parathyroid function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4158" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Calcium excretion is decreased by thiazides.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4159" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Pathologic changes in the parathyroid glands with hypercalcemia and hypophosphatemia have been observed in a few patients on prolonged thiazide therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4160" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The common complications of hyperparathyroidism such as bone resorption and peptic ulceration have not been seen.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4161" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Long-term studies have not been conducted with DYAZIDE (the triamterene/hydrochlorothiazide combination), or with triamterene alone.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4162" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Two-year feeding studies in mice and rats, conducted under the auspices of the National Toxicology Program (NTP), treated mice and rats with doses of hydrochlorothiazide up to 600and 100mg/kg/day, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4163" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>On a body-weight basis, these doses are 600times (in mice) and 100times (in rats) the Maximum Recommended Human Dose (MRHD) for the hydrochlorothiazide component of DYAZIDE at 50mg/day (or 1.0mg/kg/day based on 50-kg individuals).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4164" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>On the basis of body surface area, these doses are 56times (in mice) and 21times (in rats) the MRHD.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4165" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>These studies uncovered no evidence of carcinogenic potential of hydrochlorothiazide in rats or female mice, but there was equivocal evidence of hepatocarcinogenicity in male mice.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4166" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Studies of the mutagenic potential of DYAZIDE (the triamterene/hydrochlorothiazide combination) or of triamterene alone have not been performed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4167" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Hydrochlorothiazide was not genotoxic in in vitro assays using strains TA98, TA100, TA1535, TA1537, and TA1538 of Salmonella typhimurium (the Ames test); in the Chinese Hamster Ovary (CHO) test for chromosomal aberrations; or in in vivo assays using mouse germinal cell chromosomes, Chinese hamster bone marrow chromosomes, and the Drosophila sex-linked recessive lethal trait gene.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4168" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Positive test results were obtained in the in vitro CHO Sister Chromatid Exchange (clastogenicity) test, and in the mouse Lymphoma Cell (mutagenicity) assays, using concentrations of hydrochlorothiazide of 43 to 1,300mcg/mL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4169" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Positive test results were also obtained in the Aspergillus nidulans nondisjunction assay, using an unspecified concentration of hydrochlorothiazide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4170" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Studies of the effects of DYAZIDE (the triamterene/hydrochlorothiazide combination) or of triamterene alone on animal reproductive function have not been conducted.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4171" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Hydrochlorothiazide had no adverse effects on the fertility of mice and rats of either sex in studies wherein these species were exposed, via their diet, to doses of up to 100 and 4mg/kg/day, respectively, prior to mating and throughout gestation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4172" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Corresponding multiples of the MRHD are 100 (mice) and 4 (rats) on the basis of body weight and 9.4 (mice) and 0.8 (rats) on the basis of body surface area.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4173" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Animal reproduction studies to determine the potential for fetal harm by DYAZIDE have not been conducted.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4174" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>However, a One Generation Study in the rat approximated composition of DYAZIDE by using a 1:1 ratio of triamterene to hydrochlorothiazide (30:30mg/kg/day); there was no evidence of teratogenicity at those doses which were, on a body-weight basis, 15 and 30times, respectively, the MRHD, and on the basis of body surface area, 3.1 and 6.2times, respectively, the MRHD.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4175" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The safe use of DYAZIDE in pregnancy has not been established since there are no adequate and well-controlled studies with DYAZIDE in pregnant women.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4176" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>DYAZIDE should be used during pregnancy only if the potential benefit justifies the risk to the fetus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4177" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Reproduction studies have been performed in rats at doses as high as 20times the MRHD on the basis of body weight, and 6times the human dose on the basis of body surface area without evidence of harm to the fetus due to triamterene.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4178" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because animal reproduction studies are not always predictive of human response, this drug should be used during pregnancy only if clearly needed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4179" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Hydrochlorothiazide was orally administered to pregnant mice and rats during respective periods of major organogenesis at doses up to 3,000 and 1,000mg/kg/day, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4180" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>At these doses, which are multiples of the MRHD equal to 3,000 for mice and 1,000 for rats, based on body weight, and equal to 282 for mice and 206 for rats, based on body surface area, there was no evidence of harm to the fetus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4181" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>There are, however, no adequate and well-controlled studies in pregnant women.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4182" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Thiazides and triamterene have been shown to cross the placental barrier and appear in cord blood.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4183" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The use of thiazides and triamterene in pregnant women requires that the anticipated benefit be weighed against possible hazards to the fetus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4184" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>These hazards include fetal or neonatal jaundice, pancreatitis, thrombocytopenia, and possible other adverse reactions which have occurred in the adult.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4185" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Thiazides and triamterene in combination have not been studied in nursing mothers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4186" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Triamterene appears in animal milk; this may occur in humans.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4187" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Thiazides are excreted in human breast milk.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4188" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>If use of the combination drug product is deemed essential, the patient should stop nursing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4189" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Safety and effectiveness in pediatric patients have not been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4190" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>If hyperkalemia is suspected (warning signs include paresthesias, muscular weakness, fatigue, flaccid paralysis of the extremities, bradycardia, and shock), an electrocardiogram (ECG) should be obtained.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4191" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>However, it is important to monitor serum potassium levels because hyperkalemia may not be associated with ECG changes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4192" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>If hyperkalemia is present, DYAZIDE should be discontinued immediately and a thiazide alone should be substituted.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4193" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>If the serum potassium exceeds 6.5mEq/L more vigorous therapy is required.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4194" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The clinical situation dictates the procedures to be employed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4195" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>These include the intravenous administration of calcium chloride solution, sodium bicarbonate solution, and/or the oral or parenteral administration of glucose with a rapid-acting insulin preparation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4196" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Cationic exchange resins such as sodium polystyrene sulfonate may be orally or rectally administered.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4197" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Persistent hyperkalemia may require dialysis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4198" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The development of hyperkalemia associated with potassium-sparing diuretics is accentuated in the presence of renal impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4199" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Patients with mild renal functional impairment should not receive this drug without frequent and continuing monitoring of serum electrolytes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4200" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Cumulative drug effects may be observed in patients with impaired renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4201" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The renal clearances of hydrochlorothiazide and the pharmacologically active metabolite of triamterene, the sulfate ester of hydroxytriamterene, have been shown to be reduced and the plasma levels increased following administration of DYAZIDE to elderly patients and patients with impaired renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4202" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Hyperkalemia has been reported in diabetic patients with the use of potassium-sparing agents even in the absence of apparent renal impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4203" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Accordingly, serum electrolytes must be frequently monitored if DYAZIDE is used in diabetic patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4204" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Potassium-sparing therapy should also be avoided in severely ill patients in whom respiratory or metabolic acidosis may occur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4205" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Acidosis may be associated with rapid elevations in serum potassium levels.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4206" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>If DYAZIDE is employed, frequent evaluations of acid/base balance and serum electrolytes are necessary.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4207" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Hydrochlorothiazide, a sulfonamide, can cause an idiosyncratic reaction, resulting in acute transient myopia and acute angle-closure glaucoma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4208" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Symptoms include acute onset of decreased visual acuity or ocular pain and typically occur within hours to weeks of drug initiation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4209" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Untreated acute angle-closure glaucoma can lead to permanent vision loss.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4210" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The primary treatment is to discontinue hydrochlorothiazide as rapidly as possible.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4211" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Prompt medical or surgical treatments may need to be considered if the intraocular pressure remains uncontrolled.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4212" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Risk factors for developing acute angle-closure glaucoma may include a history of sulfonamide or penicillin allergy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4213" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>DYAZIDE is a diuretic/antihypertensive drug product that combines natriuretic and antikaliuretic effects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4214" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Each component complements the action of the other.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4215" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The hydrochlorothiazide component blocks the reabsorption of sodium and chloride ions, and thereby increases the quantity of sodium traversing the distal tubule and the volume of water excreted.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4216" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A portion of the additional sodium presented to the distal tubule is exchanged there for potassium and hydrogen ions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4217" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>With continued use of hydrochlorothiazide and depletion of sodium, compensatory mechanisms tend to increase this exchange and may produce excessive loss of potassium, hydrogen, and chloride ions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4218" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Hydrochlorothiazide also decreases the excretion of calcium and uric acid, may increase the excretion of iodide, and may reduce glomerular filtration rate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4219" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The exact mechanism of the antihypertensive effect of hydrochlorothiazide is not known.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4220" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The triamterene component of DYAZIDE exerts its diuretic effect on the distal renal tubule to inhibit the reabsorption of sodium in exchange for potassium and hydrogen ions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4221" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Its natriuretic activity is limited by the amount of sodium reaching its site of action.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4222" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Although it blocks the increase in this exchange that is stimulated by mineralocorticoids (chiefly aldosterone), it is not a competitive antagonist of aldosterone and its activity can be demonstrated in adrenalectomized rats and patients with Addison’s disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4223" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>As a result, the dose of triamterene required is not proportionally related to the level of mineralocorticoid activity, but is dictated by the response of the individual patients, and the kaliuretic effect of concomitantly administered drugs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4224" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>By inhibiting the distal tubular exchange mechanism, triamterene maintains or increases the sodium excretion and reduces the excess loss of potassium, hydrogen and chloride ions induced by hydrochlorothiazide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4225" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>As with hydrochlorothiazide, triamterene may reduce glomerular filtration and renal plasma flow.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4226" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Via this mechanism, it may reduce uric acid excretion although it has no tubular effect on uric acid reabsorption or secretion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4227" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Triamterene does not affect calcium excretion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4228" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No predictable antihypertensive effect has been demonstrated for triamterene.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4229" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Duration of diuretic activity and effective dosage range of the hydrochlorothiazide and triamterene components of DYAZIDE are similar.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4230" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Onset of diuresis with DYAZIDE takes place within 1hour, peaks at 2 to 3hours, and tapers off during the subsequent 7 to 9hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4231" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Upon administration of a single oral dose to fasted normal male volunteers, the following mean pharmacokinetic parameters were determined: AUC(0-48) ng*h/mL (± SD) Cmax ng/mL (± SD) Median Tmax h Ae Mg (± SD) Triamterene 148.7 (87.9) 46.4 (29.4) 1.1 2.7 (1.4) hydroxytriamterene sulfate 1,865 (471) 720 (364) 1.3 19.7 (6.1) hydrochlorothiazide 834 (177) 135.1 (35.7) 2.0 14.3 (3.8) where AUC(0-48), Cmax, Tmax, and Ae represent area under the plasma concentration versus time plot, maximum plasma concentration, time to reach Cmax, and amount excreted in urine over 48hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4232" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A capsule of DYAZIDE is bioequivalent to a single entity 25-mg hydrochlorothiazide tablet and 37.5-mg triamterene capsule used in the double-blind clinical trial below.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4233" LabelDrug="DYAZIDE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In a limited study involving 12subjects, coadministration of DYAZIDE with a high-fat meal resulted in: (1) an increase in the mean bioavailability of triamterene by about 67% (90% confidence interval=0.99, 1.90), p-hydroxytriamterene sulfate by about 50% (90% confidence interval=1.06, 1.77), hydrochlorothiazide by about 17% (90% confidence interval=0.90, 1.34); (2) increases in the peak concentrations of triamterene and p-hydroxytriamterene; and (3) a delay of up to 2hours in the absorption of the active constituents.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M205" type="Trigger" span="110 36" str="increase in the mean bioavailability"/>
<Mention id="M210" type="Precipitant" span="76 13" str="high-fat meal" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M207" type="Trigger" span="368 36" str="increases in the peak concentrations"/>
<Mention id="M209" type="Trigger" span="456 5;485 10" str="delay | absorption"/>
<Interaction id="I60" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M205" precipitant="M210" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I61" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M207" precipitant="M210" effect="C54602"/>
<Interaction id="I62" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M209" precipitant="M210" effect="C54604"/>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="amiloride" precipitantCode="7DZO8EB0Z3"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="formulations containing triamterene" precipitantCode="WS821Z52LQ"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="potassium-sparing agents" precipitantCode="N0000175418"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="spironolactone" precipitantCode="27O7W4T232"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="potassium-containing salt substitutes" precipitantCode="N0000175600"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="potassium supplementation" precipitantCode="RWP5GA015D" effect="24529006: Potassium disorder (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="potassium supplementation" precipitantCode="RWP5GA015D"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="quinidine" precipitantCode="ITX08688JL" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ace | inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175562" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="angiotensin-converting enzyme (ace) inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175562" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="angiotensin-converting enzyme | inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175562" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="chlorpropamide" precipitantCode="WTM2C3IL2X" effect="89627008: Hyponatremia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="indomethacin" precipitantCode="XXE1CET956" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory agent" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory agents" precipitantCode="N0000175722"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="lithium" precipitantCode="9FN79X2M3F" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="lithium preparations" precipitantCode="9FN79X2M3F"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="norepinephrine" precipitantCode="X4W3ENH1CV" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nondepolarizing muscle relaxants" precipitantCode="N0000175737" effect="24529006: Potassium disorder (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nondepolarizing muscle relaxants" precipitantCode="N0000175737" effect="44695005: Paralysis (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="tubocurarine" precipitantCode="W9YXS298BM" effect="24529006: Potassium disorder (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="tubocurarine" precipitantCode="W9YXS298BM" effect="44695005: Paralysis (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="acth" precipitantCode="K0U68Q2TXA" effect="166686006: Electrolytes abnormal (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="acth" precipitantCode="K0U68Q2TXA" effect="43339004: Hypokalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="amphotericin b" precipitantCode="7XU7A7DROE" effect="166686006: Electrolytes abnormal (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="amphotericin b" precipitantCode="7XU7A7DROE" effect="43339004: Hypokalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="corticosteroids" precipitantCode="N0000175576" effect="166686006: Electrolytes abnormal (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="corticosteroids" precipitantCode="N0000175576" effect="43339004: Hypokalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="corticotropin" precipitantCode="K0U68Q2TXA" effect="166686006: Electrolytes abnormal (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="corticotropin" precipitantCode="K0U68Q2TXA" effect="43339004: Hypokalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="antihypertensive drugs" precipitantCode="N0000178477" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="oral anticoagulants" precipitantCode="N0000175980" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="antigout medication" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="35885006: Hyperuricemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="antigout medication" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="49099001: Increased uric acid level (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="antigout medication" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="90560007: Inflammatory disorder due to increased blood urate level (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="blood from blood bank" precipitantCode="B3XJA0OV6T" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="blood from blood bank" precipitantCode="B3XJA0OV6T" effect="166689004: Raised serum potassium level (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="low-salt milk" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="low-salt milk" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="166689004: Raised serum potassium level (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="penicillin g potassium" precipitantCode="VL775ZTH4C" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="penicillin g potassium" precipitantCode="VL775ZTH4C" effect="166689004: Raised serum potassium level (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="potassium-containing medications" precipitantCode="RWP5GA015D" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="potassium-containing medications" precipitantCode="RWP5GA015D" effect="166689004: Raised serum potassium level (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="salt substitutes" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="salt substitutes" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="166689004: Raised serum potassium level (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="exchange resins" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="43498006: Body fluid retention (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="exchange resins" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="440921000124100: Excessive sodium intake (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="exchange resins" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="712827009: Serum potassium level below reference range (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sodium polystyrene sulfonate" precipitantCode="1699G8679Z" effect="43498006: Body fluid retention (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sodium polystyrene sulfonate" precipitantCode="1699G8679Z" effect="440921000124100: Excessive sodium intake (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sodium polystyrene sulfonate" precipitantCode="1699G8679Z" effect="712827009: Serum potassium level below reference range (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="laxatives" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="24529006: Potassium disorder (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="laxatives" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="712827009: Serum potassium level below reference range (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="methenamine" precipitantCode="J50OIX95QV" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="insulin" precipitantCode="N0000175944"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="digitalis" precipitantCode="F1T8QT9U8B" effect="24529006: Potassium disorder (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="high-fat meal" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="high-fat meal" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54602"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="high-fat meal" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54604"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>