<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Effient" setid="5fe9c118-c44b-48d7-a142-9668ae3df0c6">
<Text><Section name="BOXED WARNING SECTION" id="34066-1">
Effient can cause significant, sometimes fatal, bleeding [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1, 5.2) and Adverse Reactions (6.1)] .   Do not use Effient in patients with active pathological bleeding or a history of transient ischemic attack or stroke [see Contraindications (4.1, 4.2)] .   In patients ≥75 years of age, Effient is generally not recommended, because of the increased risk of fatal and intracranial bleeding and uncertain benefit, except in high-risk situations (patients with diabetes or a history of prior MI) where its effect appears to be greater and its use may be considered [see Use in Specific Populations (8.5)] .   Do not start Effient in patients likely to undergo urgent coronary artery bypass graft surgery (CABG). When possible, discontinue Effient at least 7 days prior to any surgery  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)].   Additional risk factors for bleeding include: body weight &amp;lt;60 kg; propensity to bleed; concomitant use of medications that increase the risk of bleeding (e.g., warfarin, heparin, fibrinolytic therapy, chronic use of non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs [NSAIDs])  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)].   Suspect bleeding in any patient who is hypotensive and has recently undergone coronary angiography, percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI), CABG, or other surgical procedures in the setting of Effient  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)].   If possible, manage bleeding without discontinuing Effient. Discontinuing Effient, particularly in the first few weeks after acute coronary syndrome, increases the risk of subsequent cardiovascular events [see Warnings and Precautions (5.3)] .         WARNING: BLEEDING RISK   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.    Effient can cause significant, sometimes fatal, bleeding (5.1, 5.2, 6.1).   Do not use Effient in patients with active pathological bleeding or a history of transient ischemic attack or stroke (4.1, 4.2).   In patients ≥75 years of age, Effient is generally not recommended, except in high-risk patients (diabetes or prior MI), where its use may be considered (8.5).   Do not start Effient in patients likely to undergo urgent coronary artery bypass graft surgery (CABG). When possible, discontinue Effient at least 7 days prior to any surgery (5.2).   Additional risk factors for bleeding include: body weight &amp;lt;60 kg; propensity to bleed; concomitant use of medications that increase the risk of bleeding (5.1).   Suspect bleeding in any patient who is hypotensive and has recently undergone coronary angiography, percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI), CABG, or other surgical procedures in the setting of Effient (5.1).   If possible, manage bleeding without discontinuing Effient. Stopping Effient increases the risk of subsequent cardiovascular events (5.3).</Section>
<Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
Active pathological bleeding (4.1) Prior transient ischemic attack or stroke (4.2) Hypersensitivity to prasugrel or any component of the product (4.3)          Effient is contraindicated in patients with active pathological bleeding such as peptic ulcer or intracranial hemorrhage [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1) and Adverse Reactions (6.1)].          Effient is contraindicated in patients with a history of prior transient ischemic attack (TIA) or stroke. In TRITON-TIMI 38 (TRial to Assess Improvement in Therapeutic Outcomes by Optimizing Platelet InhibitioN with Prasugrel), patients with a history of TIA or ischemic stroke (&amp;gt;3 months prior to enrollment) had a higher rate of stroke on Effient (6.5%; of which 4.2% were thrombotic stroke and 2.3% were intracranial hemorrhage [ICH]) than on clopidogrel (1.2%; all thrombotic). In patients without such a history, the incidence of stroke was 0.9% (0.2% ICH) and 1.0% (0.3% ICH) with Effient and clopidogrel, respectively. Patients with a history of ischemic stroke within 3 months of screening and patients with a history of hemorrhagic stroke at any time were excluded from TRITON-TIMI 38. Patients who experience a stroke or TIA while on Effient generally should have therapy discontinued [see Adverse Reactions (6.1) and Clinical Studies (14)].           Effient is contraindicated in patients with hypersensitivity (e.g., anaphylaxis) to prasugrel or any component of the product [see Adverse Reactions (6.2)].</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
Initiate Effient treatment as a single 60-mg oral loading dose and then continue at 10-mg orally once daily. Patients taking Effient should also take aspirin (75-mg to 325-mg) daily [see Drug Interactions (7.3) and Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)]. Effient may be administered with or without food [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3) and Clinical Studies (14)].       Initiate treatment with a single 60-mg oral loading dose (2). Continue at 10-mg once daily with or without food. Consider 5-mg once daily for patients &amp;lt;60 kg (2). Patients should also take aspirin (75-mg to 325-mg) daily (2).           Dosing in Low Weight Patients  Compared to patients weighing ≥60 kg, patients weighing &amp;lt;60 kg have an increased exposure to the active metabolite of prasugrel and an increased risk of bleeding on a 10-mg once daily maintenance dose. Consider lowering the maintenance dose to 5-mg in patients &amp;lt;60 kg. The effectiveness and safety of the 5-mg dose have not been prospectively studied [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1), Adverse Reactions (6.1), and Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)].</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
Coadministration of Effient and warfarin increases the risk of bleeding [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1) and Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)].          Coadministration of Effient and NSAIDs (used chronically) may increase the risk of bleeding [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)].          Effient can be administered with drugs that are inducers or inhibitors of cytochrome P450 enzymes [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)]. Effient can be administered with aspirin (75-mg to 325-mg per day), heparin, GPIIb/IIIa inhibitors, statins, digoxin, and drugs that elevate gastric pH, including proton pump inhibitors and H2 blockers [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)].</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
CABG-related bleeding: Risk increases in patients receiving Effient who undergo CABG (5.2). Discontinuation of Effient: Premature discontinuation increases risk of stent thrombosis, MI, and death (5.3). Thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura (TTP): TTP has been reported with Effient (5.4). Hypersensitivity: Hypersensitivity including angioedema has been reported with Effient including in patients with a history of hypersensitivity reaction to other thienopyridines (5.5).          Thienopyridines, including Effient, increase the risk of bleeding. With the dosing regimens used in TRITON-TIMI 38, TIMI (Thrombolysis in Myocardial Infarction) Major (clinically overt bleeding associated with a fall in hemoglobin ≥5 g/dL, or intracranial hemorrhage) and TIMI Minor (overt bleeding associated with a fall in hemoglobin of ≥3 g/dL but &amp;lt;5 g/dL) bleeding events were more common on Effient than on clopidogrel [see Adverse Reactions (6.1)]. The bleeding risk is highest initially, as shown in Figure 1 (events through 450 days; inset shows events through 7 days).  Figure 1: Non-CABG-Related TIMI Major or Minor Bleeding Events.  Suspect bleeding in any patient who is hypotensive and has recently undergone coronary angiography, PCI, CABG, or other surgical procedures even if the patient does not have overt signs of bleeding. Do not use Effient in patients with active bleeding, prior TIA or stroke [see Contraindications (4.1, 4.2)]. Other risk factors for bleeding are:  Age ≥75 years. Because of the risk of bleeding (including fatal bleeding) and uncertain effectiveness in patients ≥75 years of age, use of Effient is generally not recommended in these patients, except in high-risk situations (patients with diabetes or history of myocardial infarction) where its effect appears to be greater and its use may be considered [see Adverse Reactions (6.1), Use in Specific Populations (8.5), Clinical Pharmacology (12.3), and Clinical Trials (14)]. CABG or other surgical procedure [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]. Body weight &amp;lt;60 kg. Consider a lower (5-mg) maintenance dose [see Dosage and Administration (2), Adverse Reactions (6.1), and Use in Specific Populations (8.6)].  Propensity to bleed (e.g., recent trauma, recent surgery, recent or recurrent gastrointestinal (GI) bleeding, active peptic ulcer disease, severe hepatic impairment, or moderate to severe renal impairment) [see Adverse Reactions (6.1) and Use in Specific Populations (8.7, 8.8)]. Medications that increase the risk of bleeding (e.g., oral anticoagulants, chronic use of non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs [NSAIDs], and fibrinolytic agents). Aspirin and heparin were commonly used in TRITON-TIMI 38 [see Drug Interactions (7.1, 7.2. 7.3), and Clinical Studies (14)].  Thienopyridines inhibit platelet aggregation for the lifetime of the platelet (7-10 days), so withholding a dose will not be useful in managing a bleeding event or the risk of bleeding associated with an invasive procedure. Because the half-life of prasugrel's active metabolite is short relative to the lifetime of the platelet, it may be possible to restore hemostasis by administering exogenous platelets; however, platelet transfusions within 6 hours of the loading dose or 4 hours of the maintenance dose may be less effective.     Figure 1        Structural Formula             The risk of bleeding is increased in patients receiving Effient who undergo CABG. If possible, Effient should be discontinued at least 7 days prior to CABG. Of the 437 patients who underwent CABG during TRITON-TIMI 38, the rates of CABG-related TIMI Major or Minor bleeding were 14.1% in the Effient group and 4.5% in the clopidogrel group [see Adverse Reactions (6.1)]. The higher risk for bleeding events in patients treated with Effient persisted up to 7 days from the most recent dose of study drug. For patients receiving a thienopyridine within 3 days prior to CABG, the frequencies of TIMI Major or Minor bleeding were 26.7% (12 of 45 patients) in the Effient group, compared with 5.0% (3 of 60 patients) in the clopidogrel group. For patients who received their last dose of thienopyridine within 4 to 7 days prior to CABG, the frequencies decreased to 11.3% (9 of 80 patients) in the prasugrel group and 3.4% (3 of 89 patients) in the clopidogrel group. Do not start Effient in patients likely to undergo urgent CABG. CABG-related bleeding may be treated with transfusion of blood products, including packed red blood cells and platelets; however, platelet transfusions within 6 hours of the loading dose or 4 hours of the maintenance dose may be less effective.          Discontinue thienopyridines, including Effient, for active bleeding, elective surgery, stroke, or TIA. The optimal duration of thienopyridine therapy is unknown. In patients who are managed with PCI and stent placement, premature discontinuation of any antiplatelet medication, including thienopyridines, conveys an increased risk of stent thrombosis, myocardial infarction, and death. Patients who require premature discontinuation of a thienopyridine will be at increased risk for cardiac events. Lapses in therapy should be avoided, and if thienopyridines must be temporarily discontinued because of an adverse event(s), they should be restarted as soon as possible [see Contraindications (4.1, 4.2) and Warnings and Precautions (5.1)].           Thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura (TTP) has been reported with the use of Effient. TTP can occur after a brief exposure (&amp;lt;2 weeks). TTP is a serious condition that can be fatal and requires urgent treatment, including plasmapheresis (plasma exchange). TTP is characterized by thrombocytopenia, microangiopathic hemolytic anemia (schistocytes [fragment red blood cells] seen on peripheral smear), neurological findings, renal dysfunction, and fever [see Adverse Reactions (6.2)].           Hypersensitivity including angioedema has been reported in patients receiving Effient, including patients with a history of hypersensitivity reaction to other thienopyridines [see Contraindications (4.3) and Adverse Reactions (6.2)].</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Prasugrel is an inhibitor of platelet activation and aggregation through the irreversible binding of its active metabolite to the P2Y12 class of ADP receptors on platelets.          Prasugrel produces inhibition of platelet aggregation to 20 μM or 5 μM ADP, as measured by light transmission aggregometry. Following a 60-mg loading dose of Effient, approximately 90% of patients had at least 50% inhibition of platelet aggregation by 1 hour. Maximum platelet inhibition was about 80% (see Figure 2). Mean steady-state inhibition of platelet aggregation was about 70% following 3 to 5 days of dosing at 10-mg daily after a 60-mg loading dose of Effient.  Figure 2: Inhibition (Mean±SD) of 20 μM ADP-induced Platelet Aggregation (IPA) Measured by Light Transmission Aggregometry after Prasugrel 60-mg.  Platelet aggregation gradually returns to baseline values over 5-9 days after discontinuation of prasugrel, this time course being a reflection of new platelet production rather than pharmacokinetics of prasugrel. Discontinuing clopidogrel 75-mg and initiating a prasugrel 10-mg maintenance dose with or without a prasugrel 60-mg loading dose results in a decrease of 14 percentage points in maximum platelet aggregation (MPA) by Day 7. This decrease in MPA is not greater than that typically produced by a 10-mg maintenance dose of prasugrel alone. The relationship between inhibition of platelet aggregation and clinical activity has not been established.  5-mg in Low Body Weight Patients - In patients with stable coronary artery disease, mean platelet inhibition in subjects &amp;lt;60 kg taking 5-mg prasugrel was similar to that of subjects ≥60 kg taking 10-mg prasugrel. The relationship between inhibition of platelet aggregation and clinical activity has not been established.     Figure 3        Figure 3             Prasugrel is a prodrug and is rapidly metabolized to a pharmacologically active metabolite and inactive metabolites. The active metabolite has an elimination half-life of about 7 hours (range 2-15 hours). Healthy subjects, patients with stable atherosclerosis, and patients undergoing PCI show similar pharmacokinetics.  Absorption and Binding - Following oral administration, ≥79% of the dose is absorbed. The absorption and metabolism are rapid, with peak plasma concentrations (Cmax) of the active metabolite occurring approximately 30 minutes after dosing. The active metabolite's exposure (AUC) increases slightly more than proportionally over the dose range of 5 to 60-mg. Repeated daily doses of 10-mg do not lead to accumulation of the active metabolite. In a study of healthy subjects given a single 15-mg dose, the AUC of the active metabolite was unaffected by a high fat, high calorie meal, but Cmax was decreased by 49% and Tmax was increased from 0.5 to 1.5 hours. Effient can be administered without regard to food. The active metabolite is bound about 98% to human serum albumin.  Metabolism and Elimination - Prasugrel is not detected in plasma following oral administration. It is rapidly hydrolyzed in the intestine to a thiolactone, which is then converted to the active metabolite by a single step, primarily by CYP3A4 and CYP2B6 and to a lesser extent by CYP2C9 and CYP2C19. The estimates of apparent volume of distribution of prasugrel's active metabolite ranged from 44 to 68 L and the estimates of apparent clearance ranged from 112 to 166 L/hr in healthy subjects and patients with stable atherosclerosis. The active metabolite is metabolized to two inactive compounds by S-methylation or conjugation with cysteine. The major inactive metabolites are highly bound to human plasma proteins. Approximately 68% of the prasugrel dose is excreted in the urine and 27% in the feces as inactive metabolites.         Specific Populations          Pediatric - Pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics of prasugrel have not been evaluated in a pediatric population [see Use in Specific Populations (8.4)].           Geriatric - In a study of 32 healthy subjects between the ages of 20 and 80 years, age had no significant effect on pharmacokinetics of prasugrel's active metabolite or its inhibition of platelet aggregation. In TRITON-TIMI 38, the mean exposure (AUC) of the active metabolite was 19% higher in patients ≥75 years of age than in patients &amp;lt;75 years of age. In a study in subjects with stable atherosclerosis, the mean exposure (AUC) to the active metabolite of prasugrel in subjects ≥75 years old taking a 5-mg maintenance dose was approximately half that seen in subjects 45 to 64 years old taking a 10-mg maintenance dose. [See Warnings and Precautions (5.1) and Use in Specific Populations (8.5)].           Body Weight - The mean exposure (AUC) to the active metabolite is approximately 30 to 40% higher in subjects with a body weight of &amp;lt;60 kg than in those weighing ≥60 kg. In a study in subjects with stable atherosclerosis, the AUC of the active metabolite on average was 38% lower in subjects &amp;lt;60 kg taking 5-mg (N=34) than in subjects ≥60 kg taking 10-mg (N=38) [see Dosage and Administration (2), Warnings and Precautions (5.1), Adverse Reactions (6.1), and Use in Specific Populations (8.6)].           Gender - Pharmacokinetics of prasugrel's active metabolite are similar in men and women.           Ethnicity - Exposure in subjects of African and Hispanic descent is similar to that in Caucasians. In clinical pharmacology studies, after adjusting for body weight, the AUC of the active metabolite was approximately 19% higher in Chinese, Japanese, and Korean subjects than in Caucasian subjects.           Smoking - Pharmacokinetics of prasugrel's active metabolite are similar in smokers and nonsmokers.           Renal Impairment - Pharmacokinetics of prasugrel's active metabolite and its inhibition of platelet aggregation are similar in patients with moderate renal impairment (CrCL=30 to 50 mL/min) and healthy subjects. In patients with end-stage renal disease, exposure to the active metabolite (both Cmax and AUC (0-tlast)) was about half that in healthy controls and patients with moderate renal impairment [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1) and Use in Specific Populations (8.7)].           Hepatic Impairment - Pharmacokinetics of prasugrel's active metabolite and inhibition of platelet aggregation were similar in patients with mild to moderate hepatic impairment compared to healthy subjects. The pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics of prasugrel's active metabolite in patients with severe hepatic disease have not been studied [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1) and Use in Specific Populations (8.8)].             Drug Interactions          Potential for Other Drugs to Affect Prasugrel          Inhibitors of CYP3A - Ketoconazole (400 mg daily), a selective and potent inhibitor of CYP3A4 and CYP3A5, did not affect prasugrel-mediated inhibition of platelet aggregation or the active metabolite's AUC and Tmax, but decreased the Cmax by 34% to 46%. Therefore, CYP3A inhibitors such as verapamil, diltiazem, indinavir, ciprofloxacin, clarithromycin, and grapefruit juice are not expected to have a significant effect on the pharmacokinetics of the active metabolite of prasugrel [see Drug Interactions (7.3)].           Inducers of Cytochromes P450 - Rifampicin (600 mg daily), a potent inducer of CYP3A and CYP2B6 and an inducer of CYP2C9, CYP2C19, and CYP2C8, did not significantly change the pharmacokinetics of prasugrel's active metabolite or its inhibition of platelet aggregation. Therefore, known CYP3A inducers such as rifampicin, carbamazepine, and other inducers of cytochromes P450 are not expected to have significant effect on the pharmacokinetics of the active metabolite of prasugrel [see Drug Interactions (7.3)].           Drugs that Elevate Gastric pH - Daily coadministration of ranitidine (an H2 blocker) or lansoprazole (a proton pump inhibitor) decreased the Cmax of the prasugrel active metabolite by 14% and 29%, respectively, but did not change the active metabolite's AUC and Tmax. In TRITON-TIMI 38, Effient was administered without regard to coadministration of a proton pump inhibitor or H2 blocker [see Drug Interactions (7.3)].           Statins - Atorvastatin (80 mg daily), a drug metabolized by CYP450 3A4, did not alter the pharmacokinetics of prasugrel's active metabolite or its inhibition of platelet aggregation [see Drug Interactions (7.3)].           Heparin - A single intravenous dose of unfractionated heparin (100 U/kg) did not significantly alter coagulation or the prasugrel-mediated inhibition of platelet aggregation; however, bleeding time was increased compared with either drug alone [see Drug Interactions (7.3)].           Aspirin - Aspirin 150 mg daily did not alter prasugrel-mediated inhibition of platelet aggregation; however, bleeding time was increased compared with either drug alone [see Drug Interactions (7.3)].           Warfarin - A significant prolongation of the bleeding time was observed when prasugrel was coadministered with 15-mg of warfarin [see Drug Interactions (7.1)].             Potential for Prasugrel to Affect Other Drugs          In vitro metabolism studies demonstrate that prasugrel's main circulating metabolites are not likely to cause clinically significant inhibition of CYP1A2, CYP2C9, CYP2C19, CYP2D6, or CYP3A, or induction of CYP1A2 or CYP3A.           Drugs Metabolized by CYP2B6 — Prasugrel is a weak inhibitor of CYP2B6. In healthy subjects, prasugrel decreased exposure to hydroxybupropion, a CYP2B6-mediated metabolite of bupropion, by 23%, an amount not considered clinically significant. Prasugrel is not anticipated to have significant effect on the pharmacokinetics of drugs that are primarily metabolized by CYP2B6, such as halothane, cyclophosphamide, propofol, and nevirapine.           Effect on Digoxin - The potential role of prasugrel as a Pgp substrate was not evaluated. Prasugrel is not an inhibitor of Pgp, as digoxin clearance was not affected by prasugrel coadministration [see Drug Interactions (7.3)].                There is no relevant effect of genetic variation in CYP2B6, CYP2C9, CYP2C19, or CYP3A5 on the pharmacokinetics of prasugrel's active metabolite or its inhibition of platelet aggregation.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="4680" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Effient can cause significant, sometimes fatal, bleeding.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4681" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Do not use Effient in patients with active pathological bleeding or a history of transient ischemic attack or stroke.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4682" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>In patients ≥75 years of age, Effient is generally not recommended, because of the increased risk of fatal and intracranial bleeding and uncertain benefit, except in high-risk situations (patients with diabetes or a history of prior MI) where its effect appears to be greater and its use may be considered.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4683" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Do not start Effient in patients likely to undergo urgent coronary artery bypass graft surgery (CABG).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4684" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>When possible, discontinue Effient at least 7days prior to any surgery.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4685" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Additional risk factors for bleeding include: body weight &lt;60kg; propensity to bleed; concomitant use of medications that increase the risk of bleeding (e.g., warfarin, heparin, fibrinolytic therapy, chronic use of non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs [NSAIDs]).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M16" type="Trigger" span="11 12" str="risk factors"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="178 20" str="fibrinolytic therapy" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M18" type="SpecificInteraction" span="28 8" str="bleeding" code="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M5" type="Precipitant" span="169 7" str="heparin" code="T2410KM04A"/>
<Mention id="M8" type="Precipitant" span="105 46" str="medications that increase the risk of bleeding" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M11" type="Precipitant" span="215 37" str="non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M14" type="Precipitant" span="254 6" str="NSAIDs" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M17" type="Precipitant" span="159 8" str="warfarin" code="5Q7ZVV76EI"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M16" precipitant="M2" effect="M18"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M16" precipitant="M5" effect="M18"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M16" precipitant="M8" effect="M18"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M16" precipitant="M11" effect="M18"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M16" precipitant="M14" effect="M18"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M16" precipitant="M17" effect="M18"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4686" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Suspect bleeding in any patient who is hypotensive and has recently undergone coronary angiography, percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI), CABG, or other surgical procedures in the setting of Effient.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4687" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>If possible, manage bleeding without discontinuing Effient.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4688" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Discontinuing Effient, particularly in the first few weeks after acute coronary syndrome, increases the risk of subsequent cardiovascular events.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4689" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>WARNING: BLEEDING RISK See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4690" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Effient can cause significant, sometimes fatal, bleeding (5.1, 5.2, 6.1).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4691" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Do not use Effient in patients with active pathological bleeding or a history of transient ischemic attack or stroke (4.1, 4.2).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4692" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>In patients ≥75 years of age, Effient is generally not recommended, except in high-risk patients (diabetes or prior MI), where its use may be considered (8.5).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4693" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>When possible, discontinue Effient at least 7days prior to any surgery (5.2).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4694" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Additional risk factors for bleeding include: body weight &lt;60kg; propensity to bleed; concomitant use of medications that increase the risk of bleeding (5.1).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M19" type="Trigger" span="11 12" str="risk factors"/>
<Mention id="M20" type="Precipitant" span="105 46" str="medications that increase the risk of bleeding" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M21" type="SpecificInteraction" span="28 8" str="bleeding" code="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M19" precipitant="M20" effect="M21"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4695" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Suspect bleeding in any patient who is hypotensive and has recently undergone invasive or surgical procedures (5.1).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4696" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Stopping Effient increases the risk of subsequent cardiovascular events (5.3).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4697" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Active pathological bleeding (4.1) Prior transient ischemic attack or stroke (4.2) Hypersensitivity to prasugrel or any component of the product (4.3) Effient is contraindicated in patients with active pathological bleeding such as peptic ulcer or intracranial hemorrhage.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4698" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Effient is contraindicated in patients with a history of prior transient ischemic attack (TIA) or stroke.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4699" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>In TRITON-TIMI 38 (TRial to Assess Improvement in Therapeutic Outcomes by Optimizing Platelet InhibitioN with Prasugrel), patients with a history of TIA or ischemic stroke (&gt;3 months prior to enrollment) had a higher rate of stroke on Effient (6.5%; of which 4.2% were thrombotic stroke and 2.3% were intracranial hemorrhage [ICH]) than on clopidogrel (1.2%; all thrombotic).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4700" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>In patients without such a history, the incidence of stroke was 0.9% (0.2% ICH) and 1.0% (0.3% ICH) with Effient and clopidogrel, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4701" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Patients with a history of ischemic stroke within 3 months of screening and patients with a history of hemorrhagic stroke at any time were excluded from TRITON-TIMI 38.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4702" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Patients who experience a stroke or TIA while on Effient generally should have therapy discontinued.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4703" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Effient is contraindicated in patients with hypersensitivity (e.g., anaphylaxis) to prasugrel or any component of the product.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4704" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Initiate Effient treatment as a single 60-mg oral loading dose and then continue at 10-mg orally once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4705" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Patients taking Effient should also take aspirin(75-mg to 325-mg) daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4706" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Effient may be administered with or without food.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4707" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Initiate treatment with a single 60-mg oral loading dose (2).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4708" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Continue at 10-mg once daily with or without food.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4709" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Consider 5-mg once daily for patients &lt;60kg (2).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4710" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Patients should also take aspirin (75-mg to 325-mg) daily (2).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4711" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Timing of Loading Dose In the clinical trial that established the efficacy and safety of Effient, the loading dose of Effient was not administered until coronary anatomy was established in UA/NSTEMI patients and in STEMI patients presenting more than 12 hours after symptom onset.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4712" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In STEMI patients presenting within 12 hours of symptom onset, the loading dose of Effient was administered at the time of diagnosis, although most received Effient at the time of PCI.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4713" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For the small fraction of patients that required urgent CABG after treatment with Effient, the risk of significant bleeding was substantial.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4714" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Although it is generally recommended that antiplatelet therapy be administered promptly in the management of ACS because many cardiovascular events occur within hours of initial presentation, in a trial of 4033 NSTEMI patients, no clear benefit was observed when Effient loading dose was administered prior to diagnostic coronary angiography compared to at the time of PCI; however, risk of bleeding was increased with early administration in patients undergoing PCI or early CABG.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4715" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dosing in Low Weight Patients Compared to patients weighing ≥60kg, patients weighing &lt;60kg have an increased exposure to the active metabolite of prasugrel and an increased risk of bleeding on a 10-mg once daily maintenance dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4716" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Consider lowering the maintenance dose to 5-mg in patients &lt;60kg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4717" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The effectiveness and safety of the 5-mg dose have not been prospectively studied.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4718" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Opioids: Decreased exposure to prasugrel.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M22" type="Trigger" span="9 18" str="Decreased exposure"/>
<Mention id="M23" type="Precipitant" span="0 7" str="Opioids" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M22" precipitant="M23" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4719" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Consider use of parenteral anti-platelet agent (7.3).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4720" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Coadministration of Effient and warfarin increases the risk of bleeding.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M24" type="Trigger" span="41 18" str="increases the risk"/>
<Mention id="M25" type="Precipitant" span="32 8" str="warfarin" code="5Q7ZVV76EI"/>
<Mention id="M26" type="SpecificInteraction" span="63 8" str="bleeding" code="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M24" precipitant="M25" effect="M26"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4721" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Coadministration of Effient and NSAIDs (used chronically) may increase the risk of bleeding.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M27" type="Trigger" span="62 17" str="increase the risk"/>
<Mention id="M28" type="Precipitant" span="32 6" str="NSAIDs" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M29" type="SpecificInteraction" span="83 8" str="bleeding" code="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M27" precipitant="M28" effect="M29"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4722" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>As with other oral P2Y12 inhibitors, co-administration of opioid agonists delay and reduce the absorption of prasugrel's active metabolite presumably because of slowed gastric emptying.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M30" type="Trigger" span="74 31" str="delay and reduce the absorption"/>
<Mention id="M31" type="Precipitant" span="58 15" str="opioid agonists" code="N0000175690"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M30" precipitant="M31" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4723" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Consider the use of a parenteral anti-platelet agent in acute coronary syndrome patients requiring co-administration of morphine or other opioid agonists.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4724" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Effient can be administered with drugs that are inducers or inhibitors of cytochromeP450 enzymes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4725" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Effient can be administered with aspirin (75-mg to 325-mg per day), heparin, GPIIb/IIIa inhibitors, statins, digoxin, and drugs that elevate gastric pH, including proton pump inhibitors and H2 blockers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4726" LabelDrug="Effient" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>CABG-related bleeding: Risk increases in patients receiving Effient who undergo CABG (5.2).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4727" LabelDrug="Effient" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Discontinuation of Effient: Premature discontinuation increases risk of stent thrombosis, MI, and death (5.3).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4728" LabelDrug="Effient" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura (TTP): TTP has been reported with Effient (5.4).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4729" LabelDrug="Effient" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hypersensitivity: Hypersensitivity including angioedema has been reported with Effient including in patients with a history of hypersensitivity reaction to other thienopyridines (5.5).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4730" LabelDrug="Effient" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Thienopyridines, including Effient, increase the risk of bleeding.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4731" LabelDrug="Effient" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>With the dosing regimens used in TRITON-TIMI 38, TIMI (Thrombolysis in Myocardial Infarction) Major (clinically overt bleeding associated with a fall in hemoglobin ≥5g/dL, or intracranial hemorrhage) and TIMI Minor (overt bleeding associated with a fall in hemoglobin of ≥3g/dL but &lt;5g/dL) bleeding events were more common on Effient than on clopidogrel.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4732" LabelDrug="Effient" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The bleeding risk is highest initially, as shown in Figure 1 (events through 450days; inset shows events through 7days).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4733" LabelDrug="Effient" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Figure1: Non-CABG-Related TIMI Major or Minor Bleeding Events.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4734" LabelDrug="Effient" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Suspect bleeding in any patient who is hypotensive and has recently undergone coronary angiography, PCI, CABG, or other surgical procedures even if the patient does not have overt signs of bleeding.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4735" LabelDrug="Effient" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Do not use Effient in patients with active bleeding, prior TIA or stroke.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4736" LabelDrug="Effient" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Other risk factors for bleeding are: Age ≥75years.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4737" LabelDrug="Effient" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Because of the risk of bleeding (including fatal bleeding) and uncertain effectiveness in patients ≥75years of age, use of Effient is generally not recommended in these patients, except in high-risk situations (patients with diabetes or history of myocardial infarction) where its effect appears to be greater and its use may be considered.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4738" LabelDrug="Effient" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>CABG or other surgical procedure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4739" LabelDrug="Effient" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Consider a lower (5-mg) maintenance dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4740" LabelDrug="Effient" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Propensity to bleed (e.g., recent trauma, recent surgery, recent or recurrent gastrointestinal (GI) bleeding, active peptic ulcer disease, severe hepatic impairment, or moderate to severe renal impairment).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4741" LabelDrug="Effient" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Medications that increase the risk of bleeding (e.g., oral anticoagulants, chronic use of non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs [NSAIDs], and fibrinolytic agents).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M44" type="Trigger" span="17 17" str="increase the risk"/>
<Mention id="M33" type="Precipitant" span="142 19" str="fibrinolytic agents" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M46" type="SpecificInteraction" span="38 8" str="bleeding" code="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M36" type="Precipitant" span="0 46" str="Medications that increase the risk of bleeding" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M39" type="Precipitant" span="90 37" str="non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M42" type="Precipitant" span="129 6" str="NSAIDs" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M45" type="Precipitant" span="54 19" str="oral anticoagulants" code="N0000175980"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M44" precipitant="M33" effect="M46"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M44" precipitant="M36" effect="M46"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M44" precipitant="M39" effect="M46"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M44" precipitant="M42" effect="M46"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M44" precipitant="M45" effect="M46"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4742" LabelDrug="Effient" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Aspirin and heparin were commonly used in TRITON-TIMI 38 [see Drug Interactions (7.1, 7.2.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4743" LabelDrug="Effient" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Thienopyridines inhibit platelet aggregation for the lifetime of the platelet (7-10days), so withholding a dose will not be useful in managing a bleeding event or the risk of bleeding associated with an invasive procedure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4744" LabelDrug="Effient" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Because the half-life of prasugrel's active metabolite is short relative to the lifetime of the platelet, it may be possible to restore hemostasis by administering exogenous platelets; however, platelet transfusions within 6hours of the loading dose or 4hours of the maintenance dose may be less effective.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4745" LabelDrug="Effient" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Figure 1 Structural Formula The risk of bleeding is increased in patients receiving Effient who undergo CABG.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4746" LabelDrug="Effient" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If possible, Effient should be discontinued at least 7days prior to CABG.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4747" LabelDrug="Effient" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Of the 437patients who underwent CABG during TRITON-TIMI 38, the rates of CABG-related TIMI Major or Minor bleeding were 14.1% in the Effient group and 4.5% in the clopidogrel group.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4748" LabelDrug="Effient" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The higher risk for bleeding events in patients treated with Effient persisted up to 7days from the most recent dose of study drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4749" LabelDrug="Effient" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>For patients receiving a thienopyridine within 3days prior to CABG, the frequencies of TIMI Major or Minor bleeding were 26.7% (12 of 45patients) in the Effient group, compared with 5.0% (3 of 60patients) in the clopidogrel group.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4750" LabelDrug="Effient" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>For patients who received their last dose of thienopyridine within 4 to 7days prior to CABG, the frequencies decreased to 11.3% (9 of 80patients) in the prasugrel group and 3.4% (3 of 89patients) in the clopidogrel group.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4751" LabelDrug="Effient" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Do not start Effient in patients likely to undergo urgent CABG.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4752" LabelDrug="Effient" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>CABG-related bleeding may be treated with transfusion of blood products, including packed red blood cells and platelets; however, platelet transfusions within 6hours of the loading dose or 4hours of the maintenance dose may be less effective.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4753" LabelDrug="Effient" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Discontinue thienopyridines, including Effient, for active bleeding, elective surgery, stroke, or TIA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4754" LabelDrug="Effient" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The optimal duration of thienopyridine therapy is unknown.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4755" LabelDrug="Effient" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In patients who are managed with PCI and stent placement, premature discontinuation of any antiplatelet medication, including thienopyridines, conveys an increased risk of stent thrombosis, myocardial infarction, and death.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4756" LabelDrug="Effient" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients who require premature discontinuation of a thienopyridine will be at increased risk for cardiac events.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4757" LabelDrug="Effient" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Lapses in therapy should be avoided, and if thienopyridines must be temporarily discontinued because of an adverse event(s), they should be restarted as soon as possible.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4758" LabelDrug="Effient" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura (TTP) has been reported with the use of Effient.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4759" LabelDrug="Effient" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>TTP can occur after a brief exposure (&lt;2weeks).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4760" LabelDrug="Effient" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>TTP is a serious condition that can be fatal and requires urgent treatment, including plasmapheresis (plasma exchange).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4761" LabelDrug="Effient" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>TTP is characterized by thrombocytopenia, microangiopathic hemolytic anemia (schistocytes [fragment red blood cells] seen on peripheral smear), neurological findings, renal dysfunction, and fever.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4762" LabelDrug="Effient" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hypersensitivity including angioedema has been reported in patients receiving Effient, including patients with a history of hypersensitivity reaction to other thienopyridines.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4763" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Prasugrel is an inhibitor of platelet activation and aggregation through the irreversible binding of its active metabolite to the P2Y12 class of ADPreceptors on platelets.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4764" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Prasugrel produces inhibition of platelet aggregation to 20μM or 5μM ADP, as measured by light transmission aggregometry.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4765" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following a 60-mg loading dose of Effient, approximately 90% of patients had at least 50% inhibition of platelet aggregation by 1hour.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4766" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Maximum platelet inhibition was about 80%.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4767" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Mean steady-state inhibition of platelet aggregation was about 70% following 3to 5days of dosing at 10-mg daily after a 60-mg loading dose of Effient.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4768" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Figure2: Inhibition (Mean±SD) of 20μM ADP-induced Platelet Aggregation(IPA) Measured by Light Transmission Aggregometry after Prasugrel 60-mg. Platelet aggregation gradually returns to baseline values over 5-9 days after discontinuation of prasugrel, this time course being a reflection of new platelet production rather than pharmacokinetics of prasugrel.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4769" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Discontinuing clopidogrel 75-mg and initiating a prasugrel 10-mg maintenance dose with or without a prasugrel 60-mg loading dose results in a decrease of 14 percentage points in maximum platelet aggregation (MPA) by Day 7.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4770" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This decrease in MPA is not greater than that typically produced by a 10-mg maintenance dose of prasugrel alone.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4771" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The relationship between inhibition of platelet aggregation and clinical activity has not been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4772" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>5-mg in Low Body Weight Patients - In patients with stable coronary artery disease, mean platelet inhibition in subjects &lt;60kg taking 5-mg prasugrel was similar to that of subjects ≥60kg taking 10-mg prasugrel.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4773" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Figure 3 Figure 3 Prasugrel is a prodrug and is rapidly metabolized to a pharmacologically active metabolite and inactive metabolites.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4774" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The active metabolite has an elimination half-life of about 7hours (range 2-15hours).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4775" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Healthy subjects, patients with stable atherosclerosis, and patients undergoing PCI show similar pharmacokinetics.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4776" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Absorption and Binding - Following oral administration, ≥79% of the dose is absorbed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4777" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The absorption and metabolism are rapid, with peak plasma concentrations(Cmax) of the active metabolite occurring approximately 30minutes after dosing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4778" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The active metabolite's exposure(AUC) increases slightly more than proportionally over the dose range of 5 to 60-mg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4779" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Repeated daily doses of 10-mg do not lead to accumulation of the active metabolite.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4780" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In a study of healthy subjects given a single 15-mg dose, the AUC of the active metabolite was unaffected by a high fat, high calorie meal, but Cmax was decreased by 49% and Tmax was increased from 0.5 to 1.5hours.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M47" type="Trigger" span="174 18" str="Tmax was increased"/>
<Mention id="M50" type="Precipitant" span="111 27" str="high fat, high calorie meal" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M49" type="Trigger" span="144 18" str="Cmax was decreased"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M47" precipitant="M50" effect="C54604"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M49" precipitant="M50" effect="C54606"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4781" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Effient can be administered without regard to food.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4782" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The active metabolite is bound about 98% to human serum albumin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4783" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Metabolism and Elimination - Prasugrel is not detected in plasma following oral administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4784" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>It is rapidly hydrolyzed in the intestine to a thiolactone, which is then converted to the active metabolite by a single step, primarily by CYP3A4 and CYP2B6 and to a lesser extent by CYP2C9 and CYP2C19.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4785" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The estimates of apparent volume of distribution of prasugrel's active metabolite ranged from 44 to 68L and the estimates of apparent clearance ranged from 112 to 166L/hr in healthy subjects and patients with stable atherosclerosis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4786" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The active metabolite is metabolized to two inactive compounds by S-methylation or conjugation with cysteine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4787" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The major inactive metabolites are highly bound to human plasma proteins.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4788" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Approximately 68% of the prasugrel dose is excreted in the urine and 27% in the feces as inactive metabolites.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4789" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Specific Populations Geriatric - In a study of 32healthy subjects between the ages of 20 and 80years, age had no significant effect on pharmacokinetics of prasugrel's active metabolite or its inhibition of platelet aggregation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4790" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In TRITON-TIMI 38, the mean exposure(AUC) of the active metabolite was 19%higher in patients ≥75years of age than in patients &lt;75years of age.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4791" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In a study in subjects with stable atherosclerosis, the mean exposure (AUC) to the active metabolite of prasugrel in subjects ≥75years old taking a 5-mg maintenance dose was approximately half that seen in subjects 45 to 64 years old taking a 10-mg maintenance dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4792" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Body Weight - The mean exposure(AUC) to the active metabolite is approximately 30 to 40% higher in subjects with a body weight of &lt;60kg than in those weighing ≥60kg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4793" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In a study in subjects with stable atherosclerosis, the AUC of the active metabolite on average was 38% lower in subjects &lt;60kg taking 5-mg (N=34) than in subjects ≥60kg taking 10-mg (N=38).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4794" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Gender - Pharmacokinetics of prasugrel's active metabolite are similar in men and women.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4795" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Ethnicity - Exposure in subjects of African and Hispanic descent is similar to that in Caucasians.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4796" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In clinical pharmacology studies, after adjusting for body weight, the AUC of the active metabolite was approximately 19%higher in Chinese, Japanese, and Korean subjects than in Caucasian subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4797" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Smoking - Pharmacokinetics of prasugrel's active metabolite are similar in smokers and nonsmokers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4798" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Renal Impairment - Pharmacokinetics of prasugrel's active metabolite and its inhibition of platelet aggregation are similar in patients with moderate renal impairment(CrCL=30 to 50mL/min) and healthy subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4799" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In patients with end-stage renal disease, exposure to the active metabolite (both Cmax and AUC (0-tlast)) was about half that in healthy controls and patients with moderate renal impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4800" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Hepatic Impairment - Pharmacokinetics of prasugrel's active metabolite and inhibition of platelet aggregation were similar in patients with mild to moderate hepatic impairment compared to healthy subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4801" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics of prasugrel's active metabolite in patients with severe hepatic disease have not been studied.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4802" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Drug Interactions Potential for Other Drugs to Affect Prasugrel Inhibitors of CYP3A - Ketoconazole(400mg daily), a selective and potent inhibitor of CYP3A4 and CYP3A5, did not affect prasugrel-mediated inhibition of platelet aggregation or the active metabolite's AUC and Tmax, but decreased the Cmax by 34% to 46%.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M55" type="Trigger" span="282 18" str="decreased the Cmax"/>
<Mention id="M52" type="Precipitant" span="64 19" str="Inhibitors of CYP3A" code="N0000191001"/>
<Mention id="M54" type="Precipitant" span="86 12" str="Ketoconazole" code="R9400W927I"/>
<Mention id="M56" type="Precipitant" span="115 51" str="selective and potent inhibitor of CYP3A4 and CYP3A5" code="N0000191001"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M55" precipitant="M52" effect="C54606"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M55" precipitant="M54" effect="C54606"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M55" precipitant="M56" effect="C54606"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4803" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Therefore, CYP3A inhibitors such as verapamil, diltiazem, indinavir, ciprofloxacin, clarithromycin, and grapefruit juice are not expected to have a significant effect on the pharmacokinetics of the active metabolite of prasugrel.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4804" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Inducers of CytochromesP450 - Rifampicin(600mg daily), a potent inducer of CYP3A and CYP2B6 and an inducer of CYP2C9, CYP2C19, and CYP2C8, did not significantly change the pharmacokinetics of prasugrel's active metabolite or its inhibition of platelet aggregation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4805" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Therefore, known CYP3A inducers such as rifampicin, carbamazepine, and other inducers of cytochromesP450 are not expected to have significant effect on the pharmacokinetics of the active metabolite of prasugrel.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4806" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Drugs that Elevate Gastric pH - Daily coadministration of ranitidine(an H2 blocker) or lansoprazole(a proton pump inhibitor) decreased the Cmax of the prasugrel active metabolite by 14% and 29%, respectively, but did not change the active metabolite's AUC and Tmax.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M63" type="Trigger" span="125 18" str="decreased the Cmax"/>
<Mention id="M58" type="Precipitant" span="72 10" str="H2 blocker" code="N0000000151"/>
<Mention id="M60" type="Precipitant" span="87 12" str="lansoprazole" code="0K5C5T2QPG"/>
<Mention id="M62" type="Precipitant" span="102 21" str="proton pump inhibitor" code="N0000175525"/>
<Mention id="M64" type="Precipitant" span="58 10" str="ranitidine" code="884KT10YB7"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M63" precipitant="M58" effect="C54606"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M63" precipitant="M60" effect="C54606"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M63" precipitant="M62" effect="C54606"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M63" precipitant="M64" effect="C54606"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4807" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In TRITON-TIMI 38, Effient was administered without regard to coadministration of a proton pump inhibitor or H2 blocker.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4808" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Statins - Atorvastatin(80mg daily), a drug metabolized by CYP450 3A4, did not alter the pharmacokinetics of prasugrel's active metabolite or its inhibition of platelet aggregation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4809" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Heparin - A single intravenous dose of unfractionated heparin(100U/kg) did not significantly alter coagulation or the prasugrel-mediated inhibition of platelet aggregation; however, bleeding time was increased compared with either drug alone.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M67" type="SpecificInteraction" span="182 27" str="bleeding time was increased" code="123789000: Blood coagulation disorder with prolonged bleeding time (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M66" type="Precipitant" span="54 7" str="heparin" code="T2410KM04A"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M67" precipitant="M66" effect="M67"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4810" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Aspirin - Aspirin 150mg daily did not alter prasugrel-mediated inhibition of platelet aggregation; however, bleeding time was increased compared with either drug alone.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M70" type="SpecificInteraction" span="108 27" str="bleeding time was increased" code="123789000: Blood coagulation disorder with prolonged bleeding time (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M69" type="Precipitant" span="0 7" str="Aspirin" code="R16CO5Y76E"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M70" precipitant="M69" effect="M70"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4811" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Warfarin - A significant prolongation of the bleeding time was observed when prasugrel was coadministered with 15-mg of warfarin.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M73" type="SpecificInteraction" span="25 33" str="prolongation of the bleeding time" code="123789000: Blood coagulation disorder with prolonged bleeding time (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M72" type="Precipitant" span="120 8" str="warfarin" code="5Q7ZVV76EI"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M73" precipitant="M72" effect="M73"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4812" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Potential for Prasugrel to Affect Other Drugs In vitro metabolism studies demonstrate that prasugrel's main circulating metabolites are not likely to cause clinically significant inhibition of CYP1A2, CYP2C9, CYP2C19, CYP2D6, or CYP3A, or induction of CYP1A2 or CYP3A.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4813" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Drugs Metabolized by CYP2B6 - Prasugrel is a weak inhibitor of CYP2B6.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4814" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In healthy subjects, prasugrel decreased exposure to hydroxybupropion, a CYP2B6-mediated metabolite of bupropion, by 23%, an amount not considered clinically significant.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M74" type="Trigger" span="31 18" str="decreased exposure"/>
<Mention id="M75" type="Precipitant" span="53 16" str="hydroxybupropion" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I29" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M74" precipitant="M75" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4815" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Prasugrel is not anticipated to have significant effect on the pharmacokinetics of drugs that are primarily metabolized by CYP2B6, such as halothane, cyclophosphamide, propofol, and nevirapine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4816" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Effect on Digoxin - The potential role of prasugrel as a Pgp substrate was not evaluated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4817" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Prasugrel is not an inhibitor of Pgp, as digoxin clearance was not affected by prasugrel coadministration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4818" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Morphine - Co-administration of 5 mg intravenous morphine with 60 mg loading dose of prasugrel in healthy adults decreased the Cmax of prasugrel's active metabolite by 31% with no change in AUC, Tmax, or inhibition of ADP-induced platelet aggregation.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M76" type="Trigger" span="113 18" str="decreased the Cmax"/>
<Mention id="M77" type="Precipitant" span="37 20" str="intravenous morphine" code="76I7G6D29C"/>
<Interaction id="I30" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M76" precipitant="M77" effect="C54606"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4819" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>ADP induced platelet aggregation was higher up to 2 hours following 60 mg loading dose of prasugrel in stable patients more than 1 year after an ACS who were co-administered morphine.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M80" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 43" str="ADP induced platelet aggregation was higher" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M79" type="Precipitant" span="174 8" str="morphine" code="76I7G6D29C"/>
<Interaction id="I31" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M80" precipitant="M79" effect="M80"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4820" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In the patients with a 2-hour delay in the onset of platelet aggregation (5 of 11), Tmax was delayed and prasugrel active metabolite levels were significantly lower at 30 min (5 vs 120 ng/mL) following co-administration with morphine.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M81" type="Trigger" span="115 49" str="active metabolite levels were significantly lower"/>
<Mention id="M84" type="Precipitant" span="225 8" str="morphine" code="76I7G6D29C"/>
<Mention id="M83" type="Trigger" span="84 16" str="Tmax was delayed"/>
<Interaction id="I32" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M81" precipitant="M84" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I33" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M83" precipitant="M84" effect="C54604"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4821" LabelDrug="Effient" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There is no relevant effect of genetic variation in CYP2B6, CYP2C9, CYP2C19, or CYP3A5 on the pharmacokinetics of prasugrel's active metabolite or its inhibition of platelet aggregation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="fibrinolytic therapy" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="heparin" precipitantCode="T2410KM04A" effect="123789000: Blood coagulation disorder with prolonged bleeding time (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="heparin" precipitantCode="T2410KM04A" effect="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="medications that increase the risk of bleeding" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nsaids" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="warfarin" precipitantCode="5Q7ZVV76EI" effect="123789000: Blood coagulation disorder with prolonged bleeding time (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="warfarin" precipitantCode="5Q7ZVV76EI" effect="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="opioids" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="opioid agonists" precipitantCode="N0000175690" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="fibrinolytic agents" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="oral anticoagulants" precipitantCode="N0000175980" effect="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="high fat, high calorie meal" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54604"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="high fat, high calorie meal" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54606"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="inhibitors of cyp3a" precipitantCode="N0000191001" effect="C54606"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="ketoconazole" precipitantCode="R9400W927I" effect="C54606"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="selective and potent inhibitor of cyp3a4 and cyp3a5" precipitantCode="N0000191001" effect="C54606"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="h2 blocker" precipitantCode="N0000000151" effect="C54606"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="lansoprazole" precipitantCode="0K5C5T2QPG" effect="C54606"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="proton pump inhibitor" precipitantCode="N0000175525" effect="C54606"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="ranitidine" precipitantCode="884KT10YB7" effect="C54606"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="aspirin" precipitantCode="R16CO5Y76E" effect="123789000: Blood coagulation disorder with prolonged bleeding time (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="hydroxybupropion" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="intravenous morphine" precipitantCode="76I7G6D29C" effect="C54606"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="morphine" precipitantCode="76I7G6D29C" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="morphine" precipitantCode="76I7G6D29C" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="morphine" precipitantCode="76I7G6D29C" effect="C54604"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>