<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="FLOLAN" setid="8e4b636e-ee9c-4111-779d-28c8369d283b">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
A large study evaluating the effect of FLOLAN on survival in NYHA Class III and IV patients with congestive heart failure due to severe left ventricular systolic dysfunction was terminated after an interim analysis of 471 patients revealed a higher mortality in patients receiving FLOLAN plus conventional therapy than in those receiving conventional therapy alone. The chronic use of FLOLAN in patients with congestive heart failure due to severe left ventricular systolic dysfunction is therefore contraindicated. Some patients with pulmonary hypertension have developed pulmonary edema during dose initiation, which may be associated with pulmonary veno-occlusive disease. FLOLAN should not be used chronically in patients who develop pulmonary edema during dose initiation. FLOLAN is also contraindicated in patients with known hypersensitivity to the drug or to structurally related compounds.</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
FLOLAN must be reconstituted only with STERILE DILUENT for FLOLAN. Do not dilute reconstituted solutions of FLOLAN or administer with other parenteral solutions or medications (see WARNINGS).          Administer continuous chronic infusion of FLOLAN through a central venous catheter. Temporary peripheral intravenous infusion may be used until central access is established. Initiate chronic infusion of FLOLAN at 2 ng/kg/min and increase in increments of 2 ng/kg/min every 15 minutes or longer until dose-limiting pharmacologic effects are elicited or until a tolerance limit to the drug is established or further increases in the infusion rate are not clinically warranted (see Dosage Adjustments). If dose-limiting pharmacologic effects occur, then decrease the infusion rate until FLOLAN is tolerated. In clinical trials, the most common dose-limiting adverse events were nausea, vomiting, hypotension, sepsis, headache, abdominal pain, or respiratory disorder (most treatment-limiting adverse events were not serious). If the initial infusion rate of 2 ng/kg/min is not tolerated, identify a lower dose that is tolerated by the patient. In the controlled 12-week trial in PAH/SSD, for example, the dose increased from a mean starting dose of 2.2 ng/kg/min. During the first 7 days of treatment, the dose was increased daily to a mean dose of 4.1 ng/kg/min on day 7 of treatment. At the end of week 12, the mean dose was 11.2 ng/kg/min. The mean incremental increase was 2 to 3 ng/kg/min every 3 weeks.        Base changes in the chronic infusion rate on persistence, recurrence, or worsening of the patient's symptoms of pulmonary hypertension and the occurrence of adverse events due to excessive doses of FLOLAN. In general, expect increases in dose from the initial chronic dose. Consider increments in dose if symptoms of PAH persist or recur. Increase the infusion by 1- to 2-ng/kg/min increments at intervals sufficient to allow assessment of clinical response; these intervals should be at least 15 minutes. In clinical trials, incremental increases in dose occurred at intervals of 24 to 48 hours or longer. Following establishment of a new chronic infusion rate, observe the patient, and monitor standing and supine blood pressure and heart rate for several hours to ensure that the new dose is tolerated. During chronic infusion, the occurrence of dose-limiting pharmacological events may necessitate a decrease in infusion rate, but the adverse event may occasionally resolve without dosage adjustment. Make dosage decreases gradually in 2-ng/kg/min decrements every 15 minutes or longer until the dose-limiting effects resolve. Avoid abrupt withdrawal of FLOLAN or sudden large reductions in infusion rates. Except in life-threatening situations (e.g., unconsciousness, collapse, etc.), adjust infusion rates of FLOLAN only under the direction of a physician. In patients receiving lung transplants, doses of FLOLAN were tapered after the initiation of cardiopulmonary bypass.            FLOLAN is administered by continuous intravenous infusion via a central venous catheter using an ambulatory infusion pump. During initiation of treatment, FLOLAN may be administered peripherally. The ambulatory infusion pump used to administer FLOLAN should: (1) be small and lightweight, (2) be able to adjust infusion rates in 2-ng/kg/min increments, (3) have occlusion, end-of-infusion, and low-battery alarms, (4) be accurate to ±6% of the programmed rate, and (5) be positive pressure-driven (continuous or pulsatile) with intervals between pulses not exceeding 3 minutes at infusion rates used to deliver FLOLAN. The reservoir should be made of polyvinyl chloride, polypropylene, or glass. The infusion pump used in the most recent clinical trials was the CADD-1 HFX 5100 (SIMS Deltec). A 60-inch microbore non-DEHP extension set with proximal antisyphon valve, low priming volume (0.9 mL), and in-line 0.22 micron filter was used during clinical trials. To avoid interruptions in drug delivery, the patient should have access to a backup infusion pump and intravenous infusion sets. Consider a multi-lumen catheter if other intravenous therapies are routinely administered. To facilitate extended use at ambient temperatures exceeding 25°C (77°F), a cold pouch with frozen gel packs was used in clinical trials (see DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION: Storage and Stability). The cold pouches and gel packs used in clinical trials were obtained from Palco Labs, Palo Alto, California. Any cold pouch used must be capable of maintaining the temperature of reconstituted FLOLAN between 2° and 8°C for 12 hours.           FLOLAN is stable only when reconstituted with STERILE DILUENT for FLOLAN. FLOLAN must not be reconstituted or mixed with any other parenteral medications or solutions prior to or during administration.  Select a concentration for the solution of FLOLAN that is compatible with the infusion pump being used with respect to minimum and maximum flow rates, reservoir capacity, and the infusion pump criteria listed above. When administered chronically, prepare FLOLAN in a drug delivery reservoir appropriate for the infusion pump with a total reservoir volume of at least 100 mL, using 2 vials of STERILE DILUENT for FLOLAN for use during a 24-hour period. Table 6 gives directions for preparing several different concentrations of FLOLAN.  Table 6. Reconstitution and Dilution Instructions      To make 100 mL of solution with Final Concentration (ng/mL) of:   Directions:     3,000 ng/mL   Dissolve contents of one 0.5-mg vial with 5 mL of STERILE DILUENT for FLOLAN. Withdraw 3 mL and add to sufficient STERILE DILUENT for FLOLAN to make a total of 100 mL.     5,000 ng/mL   Dissolve contents of one 0.5-mg vial with 5 mL of STERILE DILUENT for FLOLAN. Withdraw entire vial contents and add sufficient STERILE DILUENT for FLOLAN to make a total of 100 mL.     10,000 ng/mL   Dissolve contents of two 0.5-mg vials each with 5 mL of STERILE DILUENT for FLOLAN. Withdraw entire vial contents and add sufficient STERILE DILUENT for FLOLAN to make a total of 100 mL.     15,000 ng/mL*   Dissolve contents of one 1.5-mg vial with 5 mL of STERILE DILUENT for FLOLAN. Withdraw entire vial contents and add sufficient STERILE DILUENT for FLOLAN to make a total of 100 mL.      * Higher concentrations may be required for patients who receive FLOLAN long-term.   Generally, 3,000 ng/mL and 10,000 ng/mL are satisfactory concentrations to deliver between 2 to 16 ng/kg/min in adults. Infusion rates may be calculated using the following formula:  Infusion Rate (mL/hr) = [Dose (ng/kg/min) x Weight (kg) x 60 min/hr]    Final Concentration (ng/mL)    Tables 7 through 10 provide infusion delivery rates for doses up to 16 ng/kg/min based upon patient weight, drug delivery rate, and concentration of the solution of FLOLAN to be used. These tables may be used to select the most appropriate concentration of FLOLAN that will result in an infusion rate between the minimum and maximum flow rates of the infusion pump and that will allow the desired duration of infusion from a given reservoir volume. Higher infusion rates, and therefore, more concentrated solutions may be necessary with long-term administration of FLOLAN.  Table 7. Infusion Rates for FLOLAN at a Concentration of 3,000 ng/mL             Patient   Dose or Drug Delivery Rate (ng/kg/min)     Weight (kg)   2   4   6   8   10   12   14   16                 Infusion Delivery Rate (mL/h)                10   ---   ---   1.2   1.6   2.0   2.4   2.8   3.2     20   ---   1.6   2.4   3.2   4.0   4.8   5.6   6.4     30   1.2   2.4   3.6   4.8   6.0   7.2   8.4   9.6     40   1.6   3.2   4.8   6.4   8.0   9.6   11.2   12.8     50   2.0   4.0   6.0   8.0   10.0   12.0   14.0   16.0     60   2.4   4.8   7.2   9.6   12.0   14.4   16.8   19.2     70   2.8   5.6   8.4   11.2   14.0   16.8   19.6   22.4     80   3.2   6.4   9.6   12.8   16.0   19.2   22.4   25.6     90   3.6   7.2   10.8   14.4   18.0   21.6   25.2   28.8     100   4.0   8.0   12.0   16.0   20.0   24.0   28.0   32.0      Table 8. Infusion Rates for FLOLAN at a Concentration of 5,000 ng/mL             Patient   Dose or Drug Delivery Rate (ng/kg/min)     Weight (kg)   2   4   6   8   10   12   14   16                 Infusion Delivery Rate (mL/h)                10   ---   ---   ---   1.0   1.2   1.4   1.7   1.9     20   ---   1.0   1.4   1.9   2.4   2.9   3.4   3.8     30   ---   1.4   2.2   2.9   3.6   4.3   5.0   5.8     40   1.0   1.9   2.9   3.8   4.8   5.8   6.7   7.7     50   1.2   2.4   3.6   4.8   6.0   7.2   8.4   9.6     60   1.4   2.9   4.3   5.8   7.2   8.6   10.1   11.5     70   1.7   3.4   5.0   6.7   8.4   10.1   11.8   13.4     80   1.9   3.8   5.8   7.7   9.6   11.5   13.4   15.4     90   2.2   4.3   6.5   8.6   10.8   13.0   15.1   17.3     100   2.4   4.8   7.2   9.6   12.0   14.4   16.8   19.2      Table 9. Infusion Rates for FLOLAN at a Concentration of 10,000 ng/mL            Patient   Dose or Drug Delivery Rate (ng/kg/min)     Weight (kg)   4   6   8   10   12   14   16          Infusion Delivery Rate (mL/h)         20   ---   ---   1.0   1.2   1.4   1.7   1.9     30   ---   1.1   1.4   1.8   2.2   2.5   2.9     40   1.0   1.4   1.9   2.4   2.9   3.4   3.8     50   1.2   1.8   2.4   3.0   3.6   4.2   4.8     60   1.4   2.2   2.9   3.6   4.3   5.0   5.8     70   1.7   2.5   3.4   4.2   5.0   5.9   6.7     80   1.9   2.9   3.8   4.8   5.8   6.7   7.7     90   2.2   3.2   4.3   5.4   6.5   7.6   8.6     100   2.4   3.6   4.8   6.0   7.2   8.4   9.6      Table 10. Infusion Rates for FLOLAN at a Concentration of 15,000 ng/mL            Patient   Dose or Drug Delivery Rate (ng/kg/min)     Weight (kg)   4   6   8   10   12   14   16          Infusion Delivery Rate (mL/h)         30   ---   ---   1.0   1.2   1.4   1.7   1.9     40   ---   1.0   1.3   1.6   1.9   2.2   2.6     50   ---   1.2   1.6   2.0   2.4   2.8   3.2     60   1.0   1.4   1.9   2.4   2.9   3.4   3.8     70   1.1   1.7   2.2   2.8   3.4   3.9   4.5     80   1.3   1.9   2.6   3.2   3.8   4.5   5.1     90   1.4   2.2   2.9   3.6   4.3   5.0   5.8     100   1.6   2.4   3.2   4.0   4.8   5.6   6.4              Unopened vials of FLOLAN are stable until the date indicated on the package when stored at 15° to 25°C (59° to 77°F) and protected from light in the carton. Unopened vials of STERILE DILUENT for FLOLAN are stable until the date indicated on the package when stored at 15° to 25°C (59° to 77°F). Prior to use, reconstituted solutions of FLOLAN must be protected from light and must be refrigerated at 2° to 8°C (36° to 46°F) if not used immediately. Do not freeze reconstituted solutions of FLOLAN. Discard any reconstituted solution that has been frozen.Discard any reconstituted solution if it has been refrigerated for more than 48 hours.  During use, a single reservoir of reconstituted solution of FLOLAN can be administered at room temperature for a total duration of 8 hours, or it can be used with a cold pouch and administered up to 24 hours with the use of 2 frozen 6-oz gel packs in a cold pouch. When stored or in use, insulate reconstituted FLOLAN from temperatures greater than 25°C (77°F) and less than 0°C (32°F), and do not expose to direct sunlight.        Prior to use at room temperature, 15° to 25°C (59° to 77°F), reconstituted solutions of FLOLAN may be stored refrigerated at 2° to 8°C (36° to 46°F) for no longer than 40 hours. When administered at room temperature, reconstituted solutions may be used for no longer than 8 hours. This 48-hour period allows the patient to reconstitute a 2-day supply (200 mL) of FLOLAN. Each 100-mL daily supply may be divided into 3 equal portions. Two of the portions are stored refrigerated at 2° to 8°C (36° to 46°F) until they are used.          Prior to infusion with the use of a cold pouch, solutions may be stored refrigerated at 2° to 8°C (36° to 46°F) for up to 24 hours. When a cold pouch is employed during the infusion, reconstituted solutions of FLOLAN may be used for no longer than 24 hours. Change gel packs every 12 hours. Reconstituted solutions may be kept at 2° to 8°C (36° to 46°F), either in refrigerated storage or in a cold pouch or a combination of the two, for no more than 48 hours. Inspect parenteral drug products for particulate matter and discoloration prior to administration whenever solution and container permit. If either occurs, do not administer.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
Additional reductions in blood pressure may occur when FLOLAN is administered with diuretics, antihypertensive agents, or other vasodilators. When other antiplatelet agents or anticoagulants are used concomitantly, there is the potential for FLOLAN to increase the risk of bleeding. However, patients receiving infusions of FLOLAN in clinical trials were maintained on anticoagulants without evidence of increased bleeding. In clinical trials, FLOLAN was used with digoxin, diuretics, anticoagulants, oral vasodilators, and supplemental oxygen. In a pharmacokinetic substudy in patients with congestive heart failure receiving furosemide or digoxin in whom therapy with FLOLAN was initiated, apparent oral clearance values for furosemide (n = 23) and digoxin (n = 30) were decreased by 13% and 15%, respectively, on the second day of therapy and had returned to baseline values by day 87. The change in furosemide clearance value is not likely to be clinically significant. However, patients on digoxin may show elevations of digoxin concentrations after initiation of therapy with FLOLAN, which may be clinically significant in patients prone to digoxin toxicity.</Section>
<Section name="PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="42232-9">
FLOLAN should be used only by clinicians experienced in the diagnosis and treatment of pulmonary hypertension. Carefully establish the diagnosis of idiopathic or heritable PAH or PAH/CTD. FLOLAN is a potent pulmonary and systemic vasodilator. Initiate FLOLAN in a setting with adequate personnel and equipment for physiologic monitoring and emergency care. Dose initiation has been performed during right heart catheterization and without cardiac catheterization. During dose initiation, asymptomatic increases in pulmonary artery pressure coincident with increases in cardiac output occurred rarely. In such cases, consider dose reduction, but such an increase does not imply that chronic treatment is contraindicated. FLOLAN is a potent inhibitor of platelet aggregation. Therefore, expect an increased risk for hemorrhagic complications, particularly for patients with other risk factors for bleeding (see PRECAUTIONS: Drug Interactions). During chronic use, deliver FLOLAN continuously on an ambulatory basis through a permanent indwelling central venous catheter. Unless contraindicated, administer anticoagulant therapy to patients receiving FLOLAN to reduce the risk of pulmonary thromboembolism or systemic embolism through a patent foramen ovale. To reduce the risk of infection, use aseptic technique in the reconstitution and administration of FLOLAN and in routine catheter care. Because FLOLAN is metabolized rapidly, even brief interruptions in the delivery of FLOLAN may result in symptoms associated with rebound pulmonary hypertension including dyspnea, dizziness, and asthenia. Intravenous therapy with FLOLAN will likely be needed for prolonged periods, possibly years, so consider the patient's ability to accept and care for a permanent intravenous catheter and infusion pump. Based on clinical trials, the acute hemodynamic response to FLOLAN did not correlate well with improvement in exercise tolerance or survival during chronic use of FLOLAN. Adjust dosage of FLOLAN during chronic use at the first sign of recurrence or worsening of symptoms attributable to pulmonary hypertension or the occurrence of adverse events associated with FLOLAN (see DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION).  Following dosage adjustments, monitor standing and supine blood pressure and heart rate closely for several hours.          Patients receiving FLOLAN should receive the following information. FLOLAN must be reconstituted only with STERILE DILUENT for FLOLAN. FLOLAN is infused continuously through a permanent indwelling central venous catheter via a small, portable infusion pump. Thus, therapy with FLOLAN requires commitment by the patient to drug reconstitution, drug administration, and care of the permanent central venous catheter. Patients must adhere to sterile technique in preparing the drug and in the care of the catheter, and even brief interruptions in the delivery of FLOLAN may result in rapid symptomatic deterioration. A patient’s decision to receive FLOLAN should be based upon the understanding that there is a high likelihood that therapy with FLOLAN will be needed for prolonged periods, possibly years. The patient's ability to accept and care for a permanent intravenous catheter and infusion pump should also be carefully considered.          Additional reductions in blood pressure may occur when FLOLAN is administered with diuretics, antihypertensive agents, or other vasodilators. When other antiplatelet agents or anticoagulants are used concomitantly, there is the potential for FLOLAN to increase the risk of bleeding. However, patients receiving infusions of FLOLAN in clinical trials were maintained on anticoagulants without evidence of increased bleeding. In clinical trials, FLOLAN was used with digoxin, diuretics, anticoagulants, oral vasodilators, and supplemental oxygen. In a pharmacokinetic substudy in patients with congestive heart failure receiving furosemide or digoxin in whom therapy with FLOLAN was initiated, apparent oral clearance values for furosemide (n = 23) and digoxin (n = 30) were decreased by 13% and 15%, respectively, on the second day of therapy and had returned to baseline values by day 87. The change in furosemide clearance value is not likely to be clinically significant. However, patients on digoxin may show elevations of digoxin concentrations after initiation of therapy with FLOLAN, which may be clinically significant in patients prone to digoxin toxicity.          Long-term studies in animals have not been performed to evaluate carcinogenic potential. A micronucleus test in rats revealed no evidence of mutagenicity. The Ames test and DNA elution tests were also negative, although the instability of epoprostenol makes the significance of these tests uncertain. Fertility was not impaired in rats given FLOLAN by subcutaneous injection at doses up to 100 mcg/kg/day (600 mcg/m2/day, 2.5 times the recommended human dose [4.6 ng/kg/min or 245.1 mcg/m2/day, IV] based on body surface area).          Pregnancy Category B. Reproductive studies have been performed in pregnant rats and rabbits at doses up to 100 mcg/kg/day (600 mcg/m2/day in rats, 2.5 times the recommended human dose, and 1,180 mcg/m2/day in rabbits, 4.8 times the recommended human dose based on body surface area) and have revealed no evidence of impaired fertility or harm to the fetus due to FLOLAN. There are, however, no adequate and well-controlled studies in pregnant women. Because animal reproduction studies are not always predictive of human response, this drug should be used during pregnancy only if clearly needed.          The use of FLOLAN during labor, vaginal delivery, or cesarean section has not been adequately studied in humans.          It is not known whether this drug is excreted in human milk. Because many drugs are excreted in human milk, caution should be exercised when FLOLAN is administered to a nursing woman.          Safety and effectiveness in pediatric patients have not been established.          Clinical studies of FLOLAN in pulmonary hypertension did not include sufficient numbers of subjects aged 65 and over to determine whether they respond differently from younger patients. Other reported clinical experience has not identified differences in responses between the elderly and younger patients. In general, dose selection for an elderly patient should be cautious, usually starting at the low end of the dosing range, reflecting the greater frequency of decreased hepatic, renal, or cardiac function and of concomitant disease or other drug therapy.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS SECTION" id="34071-1">
FLOLAN must be reconstituted only as directed using STERILE DILUENT for FLOLAN. FLOLAN must not be reconstituted or mixed with any other parenteral medications or solutions prior to or during administration.         Abrupt withdrawal (including interruptions in drug delivery) or sudden large reductions in dosage of FLOLAN may result in symptoms associated with rebound pulmonary hypertension, including dyspnea, dizziness, and asthenia. In clinical trials, one Class III patient's death was judged attributable to the interruption of FLOLAN. Avoid abrupt withdrawal.          See ADVERSE REACTIONS: Adverse Events Attributable to the Drug Delivery System.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Epoprostenol has 2 major pharmacological actions: (1) direct vasodilation of pulmonary and systemic arterial vascular beds, and (2) inhibition of platelet aggregation. In animals, the vasodilatory effects reduce right- and left-ventricular afterload and increase cardiac output and stroke volume. The effect of epoprostenol on heart rate in animals varies with dose. At low doses, there is vagally mediated bradycardia, but at higher doses, epoprostenol causes reflex tachycardia in response to direct vasodilation and hypotension. No major effects on cardiac conduction have been observed. Additional pharmacologic effects of epoprostenol in animals include bronchodilation, inhibition of gastric acid secretion, and decreased gastric emptying.          Epoprostenol is rapidly hydrolyzed at neutral pH in blood and is also subject to enzymatic degradation. Animal studies using tritium-labeled epoprostenol have indicated a high clearance (93 mL/kg/min), small volume of distribution (357 mL/kg), and a short half-life (2.7 minutes). During infusions in animals, steady-state plasma concentrations of tritium-labeled epoprostenol were reached within 15 minutes and were proportional to infusion rates. No available chemical assay is sufficiently sensitive and specific to assess the in vivo human pharmacokinetics of epoprostenol. The in vitro half-life of epoprostenol in human blood at 37°C and pH 7.4 is approximately 6 minutes; therefore, the in vivo half-life of epoprostenol in humans is expected to be no greater than 6 minutes. The in vitro pharmacologic half-life of epoprostenol in human plasma, based on inhibition of platelet aggregation, was similar for males (n = 954) and females (n = 1,024). Tritium-labeled epoprostenol has been administered to humans in order to identify the metabolic products of epoprostenol. Epoprostenol is metabolized to 2 primary metabolites: 6-keto-PGF1α (formed by spontaneous degradation) and 6,15-diketo-13,14-dihydro-PGF1α (enzymatically formed), both of which have pharmacological activity orders of magnitude less than epoprostenol in animal test systems. The recovery of radioactivity in urine and feces over a 1-week period was 82% and 4% of the administered dose, respectively. Fourteen additional minor metabolites have been isolated from urine, indicating that epoprostenol is extensively metabolized in humans.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="2798" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>FLOLAN is contraindicated in patients with heart failure caused by reduced left ventricular ejection fraction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2799" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>FLOLAN is contraindicated in patients with a hypersensitivity to the drug or any of its ingredients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2800" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Heart failure with reduced ejection fraction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2801" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Hypersensitivity to FLOLAN or any of its ingredients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2802" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Initiate intravenous infusion through a central venous catheter at 2 ng/kg/min.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2803" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Change dose in 1-to 2-ng/kg/min increments at intervals of at least 15 minutes based on clinical response.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2804" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Avoid sudden large dose reductions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2805" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Each vial is for single use only; discard any unused diluent or unused reconstituted solution.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2806" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Select a concentration for the solution of FLOLAN that is compatible with the infusion pump being used with respect to minimum and maximum flow rates, reservoir capacity, and the infusion pump criteria listed below.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2807" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Using aseptic technique, reconstitute FLOLAN only with STERILE DILUENT for FLOLAN or pH 12 STERILE DILUENT for FLOLAN.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2808" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Table1 gives directions for preparing several different concentrations of FLOLAN.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2809" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>See Table 2 for storage and administration time limits for the reconstituted FLOLAN.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2810" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Reconstitution and Dilution Instructions for FLOLAN Using STERILE DILUENT for FLOLAN or pH 12 STERILE DILUENT for FLOLAN.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2811" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>To make 100mL of solution with final concentration of: Directions: 3,000ng/mL Dissolve contents of one 0.5‑mg vial with 5mL of sterile diluent.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2812" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Withdraw 3mL and add to sufficient sterile diluent to make a total of 100mL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2813" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>5,000ng/mL Dissolve contents of one 0.5‑mg vial with 5mL of sterile diluent.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2814" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Withdraw entire vial contents and add sufficient sterile diluent to make a total of 100mL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2815" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>10,000ng/mL Dissolve contents of two 0.5‑mg vials each with 5mL of sterile diluent.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2816" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>15,000ng/mLa Dissolve contents of one 1.5‑mg vial with 5mL of sterile diluent.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2817" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Withdraw entire vial contents and add sufficient sterile diluent to make a total of 100mL. a Higher concentrations may be prepared for patients who receive FLOLAN long-term.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2818" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Storage and Administration Limits for Reconstituted FLOLAN When Using STERILE DILUENT for FLOLAN When Using pH 12 STERILE DILUENT for FLOLAN Stability When used at room temperature, (15°C to 25°C; 59°F to 77°F) reconstituted solutions: are stable for up to 8 hours following reconstitution or removal from refrigerated storage.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2819" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>may be stored for up to 40 hours refrigerated at 2°C to 8°C (36°F to 46°F) before use.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2820" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>When used with a cold pack, reconstituted solutions: are stable for up to 24 hours use.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2821" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>may be stored refrigerated at 2°C to 8°C (36°F to 46°F) before use as long as the total time of refrigerated storage and infusion does not exceed 48 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2822" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Freshly prepared reconstituted solutions or reconstituted solutions that have been stored at 2°C to 8°C (36°F to 46°F) for no longer than 8 days can be administered up to: 72 hours at up to 25°C (77°F).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2823" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Reconstituted solutions can be used immediately.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2824" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Refrigerate at 2°C to 8°C (36°F to 46°F) if not used immediately.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2825" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Initiate intravenous infusions of FLOLAN at 2ng/kg/min.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2826" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Alter the infusion by 1- to 2-ng/kg/min increments at intervals sufficient to allow assessment of clinical response.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2827" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>These intervals should be at least 15minutes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2828" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>During dose initiation, asymptomatic increases in pulmonary artery pressure coincident with increases in cardiac output may occur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2829" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In such cases, consider dose reduction, but such an increase does not imply that chronic treatment is contraindicated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2830" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Base changes in the chronic infusion rate on persistence, recurrence, or worsening of the patient's symptoms of pulmonary hypertension and the occurrence of adverse vasodilatory reactions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2831" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In general, expect progressive increases in dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2832" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If dose-related adverse reactions occur, make dose decreases gradually in 2-ng/kg/min decrements every 15 minutes or longer until the dose-limiting effects resolve.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2833" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Avoid abrupt withdrawal of FLOLAN or sudden large reductions in infusion rates.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2834" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Following establishment of a new chronic infusion rate, measure standing and supine blood pressure for several hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2835" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Taper doses of FLOLAN after initiation of cardiopulmonary bypass in patients receiving lung transplants.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2836" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Initiate FLOLAN in a setting with adequate personnel and equipment for physiologic monitoring and emergency care.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2837" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Inspect parenteral drug products for particulate matter and discoloration prior to administration whenever solution and container permit.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2838" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If either particulate matter or discoloration is noted, do not use.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2839" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Administer continuous chronic infusion of FLOLAN through a central venous catheter.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2840" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Temporary peripheral intravenous infusion may be used until central access is established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2841" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not administer bolus injections of FLOLAN.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2842" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The ambulatory infusion pump used to administer FLOLAN should: (1)be small and lightweight, (2)be able to adjust infusion rates in 2‑ng/kg/min increments, (3)have occlusion, end-of-infusion, and low-battery alarms, (4)be accurate to ±6% of the programmed rate, and (5)be positive-pressure‑driven (continuous or pulsatile) with intervals between pulses not exceeding 3minutes at infusion rates used to deliver FLOLAN.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2843" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The reservoir should be made of polyvinyl chloride, polypropylene, or glass.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2844" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Use a 60-inch microbore non-di-(2-ethylhexyl)phthalate (DEHP) extension set with proximal antisyphon valve, low-priming volume (0.9 mL), and in-line 0.22-micron filter.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2845" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>To avoid interruptions in drug delivery, the patient should have access to a backup infusion pump and intravenous infusion sets.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2846" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not administer or dilute reconstituted solutions of FLOLAN with other parenteral solutions or medications.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M1" type="Trigger" span="0 17" str="Do not administer"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="73 35" str="parenteral solutions or medications" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M1" precipitant="M2"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2847" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Consider a multi‑lumen catheter if other intravenous therapies are routinely administered.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2848" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Select a concentration for the solution of FLOLAN that is compatible with the infusion pump being used with respect to minimum and maximum flow rates, reservoir capacity, and the infusion pump criteria listed above.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2849" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>When administered chronically, prepare FLOLAN in a drug delivery reservoir appropriate for the infusion pump with a total reservoir volume of at least 100 mL, using 2vials of Sterile Diluent for FLOLAN or 2 vials of pH 12 STERILE DILUENT for FLOLAN.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2850" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Generally, 3,000ng/mL and 10,000ng/mL are satisfactory concentrations to deliver between 2 to 16ng/kg/min in adults.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2851" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Higher infusion rates, and therefore, more concentrated solutions may be necessary with long‑term administration of FLOLAN.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2852" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Infusion rates may be calculated using the following formula: Flolan infusion rate formula</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2853" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Pulmonary edema: Discontinue therapy if pulmonary edema occurs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2854" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Rebound pulmonary hypertension: Do not abruptly discontinue or decrease the dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2855" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Vasodilation reactions: Monitor blood pressure and symptoms regularly during initiation and after dose change.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2856" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Increased risk for bleeding: Increased risk for hemorrhagic complications, particularly for patients with other risk factors for bleeding.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2857" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If the patient develops pulmonary edema during initiation with FLOLAN, discontinue therapy and do not readminister.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2858" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Consider the possibility of associated pulmonary veno-occlusive disease in such patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2859" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Avoid abrupt withdrawal (including interruptions in drug delivery) or sudden large reductions in dosage of FLOLAN because symptoms associated with rebound pulmonary hypertension (e.g., dyspnea, dizziness, and asthenia) may occur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2860" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In clinical trials, one ClassIII patient's death was judged attributable to the interruption of FLOLAN.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2861" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>FLOLAN is a potent pulmonary and systemic vasodilator and can cause hypotension and other reactions such as flushing, nausea, vomiting, dizziness, and headache.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2862" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor blood pressure and symptoms regularly during initiation and after dose change.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2863" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>FLOLAN is a potent inhibitor of platelet aggregation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2864" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Therefore, expect an increased risk for hemorrhagic complications, particularly for patients with other risk factors for bleeding.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2865" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Epoprostenol has 2 major pharmacological actions: (1)direct vasodilation of pulmonary and systemic arterial vascular beds and (2)inhibition of platelet aggregation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2866" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Acute Hemodynamic Effects Acute intravenous infusions of FLOLAN for up to 15minutes in patients with idiopathic or heritable PAH or PAH/SSD produce dose‑related increases in cardiac index (CI) and stroke volume (SV) and dose‑related decreases in pulmonary vascular resistance (PVR), total pulmonary resistance (TPR), and mean systemic arterial pressure (SAPm).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2867" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The effects of FLOLAN on mean pulmonary artery pressure (PAPm) were variable and minor.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2868" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In humans, hemodynamic changes due to epoprostenol (e.g., increased heart rate, facial flushing) returned to baseline within 10 minutes of termination of 60-minute infusions of 1 to 16 ng/kg/min.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2869" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This pharmacodynamic behavior is consistent with a short in vivo half-life and rapid clearance in humans, as suggested by the results of animal and in vitro studies.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2870" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In animals, the vasodilatory effects reduce right- and left-ventricular afterload and increase cardiac output and stroke volume.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2871" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The effect of epoprostenol on heart rate in animals varies with dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2872" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>At low doses, there is vagally-mediated bradycardia, but at higher doses, epoprostenol causes reflex tachycardia in response to direct vasodilation and hypotension.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2873" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No major effects on cardiac conduction have been observed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2874" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Additional pharmacologic effects of epoprostenol in animals include bronchodilation, inhibition of gastric acid secretion, and decreased gastric emptying.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2875" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Drug Interaction Studies Additional reductions in blood pressure may occur when FLOLAN is administered with diuretics, antihypertensive agents, or other vasodilators.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M9" type="Trigger" span="25 21" str="Additional reductions"/>
<Mention id="M4" type="Precipitant" span="119 23" str="antihypertensive agents" code="N0000178477"/>
<Mention id="M11" type="SpecificInteraction" span="25 39" str="Additional reductions in blood pressure" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M7" type="Precipitant" span="108 9" str="diuretics" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M10" type="Precipitant" span="153 12" str="vasodilators" code="N0000175940"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M9" precipitant="M4" effect="M11"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M9" precipitant="M7" effect="M11"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M9" precipitant="M10" effect="M11"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2876" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>When other antiplatelet agents or anticoagulants are used concomitantly, there is a potential for FLOLAN to increase the risk of bleeding.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M15" type="Trigger" span="108 17" str="increase the risk"/>
<Mention id="M13" type="Precipitant" span="34 14" str="anticoagulants" code="N0000175980"/>
<Mention id="M17" type="SpecificInteraction" span="129 8" str="bleeding" code="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M16" type="Precipitant" span="11 19" str="antiplatelet agents" code="N0000175578"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M15" precipitant="M13" effect="M17"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M15" precipitant="M16" effect="M17"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2877" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>However, patients receiving infusions of FLOLAN in clinical trials were maintained on anticoagulants without evidence of increased bleeding.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2878" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Absorption/Distribution Epoprostenol is rapidly hydrolyzed at neutral pH in blood and is also subject to enzymatic degradation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2879" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No available chemical assay is sufficiently sensitive and specific to assess the in vivo human pharmacokinetics of epoprostenol.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2880" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Animal studies using tritium‑labeled epoprostenol have indicated a high clearance (93mL/kg/min), small volume of distribution (357mL/kg), and a short half‑life (2.7minutes).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2881" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>During infusions in animals, steady‑state plasma concentrations of tritium‑labeled epoprostenol were reached within 15minutes and were proportional to infusion rates.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2882" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Metabolism Tritium‑labeled epoprostenol has been administered to humans in order to identify the metabolic products of epoprostenol.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2883" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Epoprostenol is metabolized to 2 primary metabolites: 6‑keto-PGF1α (formed by spontaneous degradation) and 6,15-diketo-13,14-dihydro-PGF1α (enzymatically formed), both of which have pharmacological activity orders of magnitude less than epoprostenol in animal test systems.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2884" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The recovery of radioactivity in urine and feces over a 1‑week period was 82% and 4% of the administered dose, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2885" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Fourteen additional minor metabolites have been isolated from urine, indicating that epoprostenol is extensively metabolized in humans.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2886" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Elimination The in vitro half‑life of epoprostenol in human blood at 37°C and pH 7.4 is approximately 6minutes; therefore, the in vivo half‑life of epoprostenol in humans is expected to be no greater than 6minutes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2887" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Drug Interaction Studies In a pharmacokinetic substudy in patients with congestive heart failure receiving furosemide in whom therapy with FLOLAN was initiated, apparent oral clearance values for furosemide (n=23) were decreased by 13% on the second day of therapy and returned to baseline values by Day 87.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M18" type="Trigger" span="170 14;219 9" str="oral clearance | decreased"/>
<Mention id="M19" type="Precipitant" span="107 10" str="furosemide" code="7LXU5N7ZO5"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M18" precipitant="M19" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2888" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The change in furosemide clearance value is not likely to be clinically significant.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2889" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In a pharmacokinetic substudy in patients with congestive heart failure receiving digoxin in whom therapy with FLOLAN was initiated, apparent oral clearance values for digoxin (n=30) were decreased by 15% on the second day of therapy and returned to baseline values by Day 87.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M20" type="Trigger" span="142 14;188 9" str="oral clearance | decreased"/>
<Mention id="M21" type="Precipitant" span="82 7" str="digoxin" code="73K4184T59"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M20" precipitant="M21" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2890" LabelDrug="FLOLAN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Clinical significance of this interaction is not known.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="parenteral solutions or medications" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="antihypertensive agents" precipitantCode="N0000178477" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="diuretics" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="vasodilators" precipitantCode="N0000175940" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="anticoagulants" precipitantCode="N0000175980" effect="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="antiplatelet agents" precipitantCode="N0000175578" effect="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="furosemide" precipitantCode="7LXU5N7ZO5" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="digoxin" precipitantCode="73K4184T59" effect="C54357"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>