<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Letairis" setid="725d4e73-6c83-477a-adc6-0ae4a133a844">
<Text><Section name="BOXED WARNING SECTION" id="34066-1">
Do not administer Letairis to a pregnant female because it may cause fetal harm. Letairis is very likely to produce serious birth defects if used by pregnant females, as this effect has been seen consistently when it is administered to animals [see Contraindications (4.1), Use in Specific Populations (8.1)].       Exclude pregnancy before the initiation of treatment with Letairis. Females of reproductive potential must use acceptable methods of contraception during treatment with Letairis and for one month after treatment. Obtain monthly pregnancy tests during treatment and 1 month after discontinuation of treatment [see Use in Specific Populations (8.6)].     Because of the risk of embryo-fetal toxicity, females can only receive Letairis through a restricted program called the Letairis REMS program [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)].         WARNING: EMBRYO-FETAL TOXICITY   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.    Do not administer Letairis to a pregnant female because it may cause fetal harm (4.1, 5.1, 8.1).   Females of reproductive potential: Exclude pregnancy before the start of treatment, monthly during treatment, and 1 month after stopping treatment. Prevent pregnancy during treatment and for one month after stopping treatment by using acceptable methods of contraception (2.2, 8.6).   For all female patients, Letairis is available only through a restricted program called the Letairis Risk Evaluation and Mitigation Strategy (REMS). (5.2)</Section>
<Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
Pregnancy (4.1) Idiopathic Pulmonary Fibrosis (4.2)         Letairis may cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant female. Letairis is contraindicated in females who are pregnant. Letairis was consistently shown to have teratogenic effects when administered to animals. If this drug is used during pregnancy, or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking this drug, the patient should be apprised of the potential hazard to a fetus [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1, 5.2) and Use in Specific Populations (8.1)].           Letairis is contraindicated in patients with Idiopathic Pulmonary Fibrosis (IPF) including IPF patients with pulmonary hypertension (WHO Group 3) [see Clinical Studies (14.3)].</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
Initiate treatment at 5 mg once daily with or without food, and consider increasing the dose to 10 mg once daily if 5 mg is tolerated (2.1). Tablets should not be split, crushed, or chewed (2.1).          Initiate treatment at 5 mg once daily, and consider increasing the dose to 10 mg once daily if 5 mg is tolerated. Tablets may be administered with or without food. Tablets should not be split, crushed, or chewed. Doses higher than 10 mg once daily have not been studied in patients with pulmonary arterial hypertension (PAH).           Initiate treatment with Letairis in females of reproductive potential only after a negative pregnancy test. Obtain monthly pregnancy tests during treatment [see Use in Specific Populations (8.6)].</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
Multiple dose co-administration of ambrisentan and cyclosporine resulted in an approximately 2-fold increase in ambrisentan exposure in healthy volunteers; therefore, limit the dose of ambrisentan to 5 mg once daily when co-administered with cyclosporine [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)].      Multiple dose co-administration of ambrisentan and cyclosporine resulted in an about 2-fold increase in ambrisentan exposure in healthy volunteers. When co-administered with cyclosporine, limit the dose to 5 mg once daily (7).</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
Fluid retention may require intervention (5.3). If patients develop acute pulmonary edema during initiation of therapy with Letairis, consider underlying pulmonary veno-occlusive disease and discontinue treatment if necessary (5.4). Decreases in sperm count have been observed in patients taking endothelin receptor antagonists (5.5). Decreases in hemoglobin have been observed within the first few weeks; measure hemoglobin at initiation, at 1 month, and periodically thereafter (5.6).           Letairis may cause fetal harm when administered during pregnancy and is contraindicated for use in females who are pregnant. In females of reproductive potential, exclude pregnancy prior to initiation of therapy, ensure use of acceptable contraceptive methods and obtain monthly pregnancy tests [see Dosage and Administration (2.2), and Use in Specific Populations (8.1, 8.6)].   Letairis is only available for females through a restricted program under a REMS [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)].            For all females, Letairis is available only through a restricted program called the Letairis REMS, because of the risk of embryo-fetal toxicity [see  Contraindications (4.1), Warnings and Precautions (5.1), and Use in Specific Populations (8.1, 8.6)].   Notable requirements of the Letairis REMS program include the following:  Prescribers must be certified with the program by enrolling and completing training. All females, regardless of reproductive potential, must enroll in the Letairis REMS program prior to initiating Letairis. Male patients are not enrolled in the REMS. Females of reproductive potential must comply with the pregnancy testing and contraception requirements [see Use in Specific Populations (8.6)].    Pharmacies that dispense Letairis must be certified with the program and must dispense to female patients who are authorized to receive Letairis.  Further information is available at www.letairisrems.com or 1-866-664-5327.          Peripheral edema is a known class effect of endothelin receptor antagonists, and is also a clinical consequence of PAH and worsening PAH. In the placebo-controlled studies, there was an increased incidence of peripheral edema in patients treated with doses of 5 or 10 mg Letairis compared to placebo [see Adverse Reactions (6.1)]. Most edema was mild to moderate in severity, and it occurred with greater frequency and severity in elderly patients. In addition, there have been post-marketing reports of fluid retention in patients with pulmonary hypertension, occurring within weeks after starting Letairis. Patients required intervention with a diuretic, fluid management, or, in some cases, hospitalization for decompensating heart failure. If clinically significant fluid retention develops, with or without associated weight gain, further evaluation should be undertaken to determine the cause, such as Letairis or underlying heart failure, and the possible need for specific treatment or discontinuation of Letairis therapy.          If patients develop acute pulmonary edema during initiation of therapy with vasodilating agents such as Letairis, the possibility of PVOD should be considered, and if confirmed Letairis should be discontinued.          Decreased sperm counts have been observed in human and animal studies with another endothelin receptor antagonist and in animal fertility studies with ambrisentan. Letairis may have an adverse effect on spermatogenesis. Counsel patients about potential effects on fertility [see Special Populations (8.6) and Nonclinical Toxicology (13.1) ].          Decreases in hemoglobin concentration and hematocrit have followed administration of other endothelin receptor antagonists and were observed in clinical studies with Letairis. These decreases were observed within the first few weeks of treatment with Letairis, and stabilized thereafter. The mean decrease in hemoglobin from baseline to end of treatment for those patients receiving Letairis in the 12-week placebo-controlled studies was 0.8 g/dL. Marked decreases in hemoglobin (&amp;gt;15% decrease from baseline resulting in a value below the lower limit of normal) were observed in 7% of all patients receiving Letairis (and 10% of patients receiving 10 mg) compared to 4% of patients receiving placebo. The cause of the decrease in hemoglobin is unknown, but it does not appear to result from hemorrhage or hemolysis. In the long-term open-label extension of the two pivotal clinical studies, mean decreases from baseline (ranging from 0.9 to 1.2 g/dL) in hemoglobin concentrations persisted for up to 4 years of treatment. There have been postmarketing reports of decreases in hemoglobin concentration and hematocrit that have resulted in anemia requiring transfusion. Measure hemoglobin prior to initiation of Letairis, at one month, and periodically thereafter. Initiation of Letairis therapy is not recommended for patients with clinically significant anemia. If a clinically significant decrease in hemoglobin is observed and other causes have been excluded, consider discontinuing Letairis.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Endothelin-1 (ET-1) is a potent autocrine and paracrine peptide. Two receptor subtypes, ETA and ETB, mediate the effects of ET-1 in the vascular smooth muscle and endothelium. The primary actions of ETA are vasoconstriction and cell proliferation, while the predominant actions of ETB are vasodilation, antiproliferation, and ET-1 clearance. In patients with PAH, plasma ET-1 concentrations are increased as much as 10-fold and correlate with increased mean right atrial pressure and disease severity. ET-1 and ET-1 mRNA concentrations are increased as much as 9-fold in the lung tissue of patients with PAH, primarily in the endothelium of pulmonary arteries. These findings suggest that ET-1 may play a critical role in the pathogenesis and progression of PAH. Ambrisentan is a high affinity (Ki=0.011 nM) ETA receptor antagonist with a high selectivity for the ETA versus ETB receptor (&amp;gt;4000-fold). The clinical impact of high selectivity for ETA is not known.                 Cardiac Electrophysiology    In a randomized, positive- and placebo-controlled, parallel-group study, healthy subjects received either Letairis 10 mg daily followed by a single dose of 40 mg, placebo followed by a single dose of moxifloxacin 400 mg, or placebo alone. Letairis 10 mg daily had no significant effect on the QTc interval. The 40 mg dose of Letairis increased mean QTc at tmax by 5 ms with an upper 95% confidence limit of 9 ms. For patients receiving Letairis 5–10 mg daily and not taking metabolic inhibitors, no significant QT prolongation is expected.            The pharmacokinetics of ambrisentan (S-ambrisentan) in healthy subjects are dose proportional. The absolute bioavailability of ambrisentan is not known. Ambrisentan is absorbed with peak concentrations occurring approximately 2 hours after oral administration in healthy subjects and PAH patients. Food does not affect its bioavailability. In vitro studies indicate that ambrisentan is a substrate of P-gp. Ambrisentan is highly bound to plasma proteins (99%). The elimination of ambrisentan is predominantly by non-renal pathways, but the relative contributions of metabolism and biliary elimination have not been well characterized. In plasma, the AUC of 4-hydroxymethyl ambrisentan accounts for approximately 4% relative to parent ambrisentan AUC. The in vivo inversion of S-ambrisentan to R-ambrisentan is negligible. The mean oral clearance of ambrisentan is 38 mL/min and 19 mL/min in healthy subjects and in PAH patients, respectively. Although ambrisentan has a 15-hour terminal half-life, the mean trough concentration of ambrisentan at steady-state is about 15% of the mean peak concentration and the accumulation factor is about 1.2 after long-term daily dosing, indicating that the effective half-life of ambrisentan is about 9 hours.         Drug Interactions          In vitro studies  Studies with human liver tissue indicate that ambrisentan is metabolized by CYP3A, CYP2C19, and uridine 5'-diphosphate glucuronosyltransferases (UGTs) 1A9S, 2B7S, and 1A3S. In vitro studies suggest that ambrisentan is a substrate of the Organic Anion Transporting Polypeptides OATP1B1 and OATP1B3, and a substrate but not an inhibitor of P-glycoprotein (P-gp). Drug interactions might be expected because of these factors; however, a clinically relevant interaction has been demonstrated only with cyclosporine [see Drug Interactions (7)]. Ambrisentan does not inhibit or induce drug metabolizing enzymes at clinically relevant concentrations.           In vivo studies  The effects of other drugs on ambrisentan pharmacokinetics and the effects of ambrisentan on the exposure to other drugs are shown in Figure 2 and Figure 3, respectively. Figure 2 Effects of Other Drugs on Ambrisentan Pharmacokinetics    * Omeprazole: based on population pharmacokinetic analysis in PAH patients ** Rifampin: AUC and Cmax were measured at steady-state. On Day 3 of co-administration a transient 2-fold increase in AUC was noted that was no longer evident by Day 7. Day 7 results are presented. Figure 3 Effects of Ambrisentan on Other Drugs    * Active metabolite of mycophenolate mofetil ** GMR (95% CI) for INR     Figure 2        Figure 3</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="2460" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Do not administer Letairis to a pregnant female because it may cause fetal harm.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2461" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Letairis is very likely to produce serious birth defects if used by pregnant females, as this effect has been seen consistently when it is administered to animals.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2462" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Exclude pregnancy before the initiation of treatment with Letairis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2463" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Females of reproductive potential must use acceptable methods of contraception during treatment with Letairis and for one month after treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2464" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Obtain monthly pregnancy tests during treatment and 1 month after discontinuation of treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2465" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Because of the risk of embryo-fetal toxicity, females can only receive Letairis through a restricted program called the Letairis REMS program.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2466" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>WARNING: EMBRYO-FETAL TOXICITY See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2467" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Do not administer Letairis to a pregnant female because it may cause fetal harm (4.1, 5.1, 8.1).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2468" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Females of reproductive potential: Exclude pregnancy before the start of treatment, monthly during treatment, and 1 month after stopping treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2469" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Prevent pregnancy during treatment and for one month after stopping treatment by using acceptable methods of contraception (2.2, 8.6).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2470" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>For all female patients, Letairis is available only through a restricted program called the Letairis Risk Evaluation and Mitigation Strategy (REMS) (5.2).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2471" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Pregnancy (4.1) Idiopathic Pulmonary Fibrosis (4.2) Letairis may cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant female.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2472" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Letairis is contraindicated in females who are pregnant.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2473" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Letairis was consistently shown to have teratogenic effects when administered to animals.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2474" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>If this drug is used during pregnancy, or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking this drug, the patient should be apprised of the potential hazard to a fetus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2475" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Letairis is contraindicated in patients with Idiopathic Pulmonary Fibrosis (IPF), including IPF patients with pulmonary hypertension (WHO Group 3).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2476" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Initiate treatment at 5 mg once daily (2.1).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2477" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Titrate at 4-week intervals as needed and tolerated (2.1).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2478" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not split, crush, or chew tablets (2.1).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2479" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Initiate treatment at 5 mg once daily, with or without tadalafil 20 mg once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2480" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>At 4-week intervals, either the dose of Letairis or tadalafil can be increased, as needed and tolerated, to Letairis 10 mg or tadalafil 40 mg. Do not split, crush, or chew tablets.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2481" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Initiate treatment with Letairis in females of reproductive potential only after a negative pregnancy test.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2482" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Obtain monthly pregnancy tests during treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2483" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Multiple dose coadministration of ambrisentan and cyclosporine resulted in an approximately 2-fold increase in ambrisentan exposure in healthy volunteers; therefore, limit the dose of ambrisentan to 5 mg once daily when coadministered with cyclosporine.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M1" type="Trigger" span="99 8;123 8" str="increase | exposure "/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Trigger" span="166 14" str=" limit the dose"/>
<Mention id="M3" type="Precipitant" span="50 12" str="cyclosporine" code="83HN0GTJ6D"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M1;M2" precipitant="M3" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2484" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Cyclosporine increases ambrisentan exposure; limit ambrisentan dose to 5 mg once daily (7).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M4" type="Trigger" span="13 9;35 8" str="increases | exposure "/>
<Mention id="M5" type="Trigger" span="45 5;63 4" str=" limit | dose"/>
<Mention id="M6" type="Precipitant" span="0 12" str="Cyclosporine" code="83HN0GTJ6D"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M4;M5" precipitant="M6" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2485" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Fluid retention may require intervention (5.3).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2486" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If patients develop acute pulmonary edema during initiation of therapy with Letairis, consider underlying pulmonary veno-occlusive disease and discontinue treatment if necessary (5.4).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2487" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Decreases in sperm count have been observed in patients taking endothelin receptor antagonists (5.5).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2488" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Decreases in hemoglobin have been observed within the first few weeks; measure hemoglobin at initiation, at 1 month, and periodically thereafter (5.6).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2489" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Letairis may cause fetal harm when administered during pregnancy and is contraindicated for use in females who are pregnant.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2490" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In females of reproductive potential, exclude pregnancy prior to initiation of therapy, ensure use of acceptable contraceptive methods, and obtain monthly pregnancy tests.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2491" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Letairis is only available for females through a restricted program under a REMS.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2492" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>For all females, Letairis is available only through a restricted program called the Letairis REMS, because of the risk of embryo-fetal toxicity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2493" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Notable requirements of the Letairis REMS program include the following: Prescribers must be certified with the program by enrolling and completing training.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2494" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>All females, regardless of reproductive potential, must enroll in the Letairis REMS program prior to initiating Letairis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2495" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Male patients are not enrolled in the REMS.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2496" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Females of reproductive potential must comply with the pregnancy testing and contraception requirements.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2497" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Pharmacies that dispense Letairis must be certified with the program and must dispense to female patients who are authorized to receive Letairis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2498" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Further information is available at www.letairisrems.com or 1-866-664-5327.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2499" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Peripheral edema is a known class effect of endothelin receptor antagonists, and is also a clinical consequence of PAH and worsening PAH.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2500" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In the placebo-controlled studies, there was an increased incidence of peripheral edema in patients treated with doses of 5 or 10 mg Letairis compared to placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2501" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Most edema was mild to moderate in severity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2502" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In addition, there have been postmarketing reports of fluid retention in patients with pulmonary hypertension, occurring within weeks after starting Letairis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2503" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients required intervention with a diuretic, fluid management, or, in some cases, hospitalization for decompensating heart failure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2504" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If clinically significant fluid retention develops, with or without associated weight gain, further evaluation should be undertaken to determine the cause, such as Letairis or underlying heart failure, and the possible need for specific treatment or discontinuation of Letairis therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2505" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Peripheral edema/fluid retention is more common with Letairis plus tadalafil than with Letairis or tadalafil alone.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2506" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If patients develop acute pulmonary edema during initiation of therapy with vasodilating agents such as Letairis, the possibility of PVOD should be considered, and if confirmed Letairis should be discontinued.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2507" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Decreased sperm counts have been observed in human and animal studies with another endothelin receptor antagonist and in animal fertility studies with ambrisentan.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2508" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Letairis may have an adverse effect on spermatogenesis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2509" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Counsel patients about potential effects on fertility.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2510" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Decreases in hemoglobin concentration and hematocrit have followed administration of other endothelin receptor antagonists and were observed in clinical studies with Letairis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2511" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>These decreases were observed within the first few weeks of treatment with Letairis, and stabilized thereafter.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2512" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The mean decrease in hemoglobin from baseline to end of treatment for those patients receiving Letairis in the 12-week placebo-controlled studies was 0.8 g/dL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2513" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Marked decreases in hemoglobin (&gt;15% decrease from baseline resulting in a value below the lower limit of normal) were observed in 7% of all patients receiving Letairis (and 10% of patients receiving 10 mg) compared to 4% of patients receiving placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2514" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The cause of the decrease in hemoglobin is unknown, but it does not appear to result from hemorrhage or hemolysis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2515" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In the long-term open-label extension of the two pivotal clinical studies, mean decreases from baseline (ranging from 0.9 to 1.2 g/dL) in hemoglobin concentrations persisted for up to 4 years of treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2516" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There have been postmarketing reports of decreases in hemoglobin concentration and hematocrit that have resulted in anemia requiring transfusion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2517" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Measure hemoglobin prior to initiation of Letairis, at one month, and periodically thereafter.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2518" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Initiation of Letairis therapy is not recommended for patients with clinically significant anemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2519" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If a clinically significant decrease in hemoglobin is observed and other causes have been excluded, consider discontinuing Letairis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2520" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Endothelin-1 (ET-1) is a potent autocrine and paracrine peptide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2521" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Two receptor subtypes, ETA and ETB, mediate the effects of ET-1 in the vascular smooth muscle and endothelium.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2522" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The primary actions of ETA are vasoconstriction and cell proliferation, while the predominant actions of ETB are vasodilation, antiproliferation, and ET-1 clearance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2523" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In patients with PAH, plasma ET-1 concentrations are increased as much as 10-fold and correlate with increased mean right atrial pressure and disease severity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2524" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>ET-1 and ET-1 mRNA concentrations are increased as much as 9-fold in the lung tissue of patients with PAH, primarily in the endothelium of pulmonary arteries.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2525" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>These findings suggest that ET-1 may play a critical role in the pathogenesis and progression of PAH.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2526" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Ambrisentan is a high-affinity (Ki=0.011 nM) ETA receptor antagonist with a high selectivity for the ETA versus ETB receptor (&gt;4000-fold).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2527" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The clinical impact of high selectivity for ETA is not known.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2528" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Cardiac Electrophysiology In a randomized, positive- and placebo-controlled, parallel-group study, healthy subjects received either Letairis 10 mg daily followed by a single dose of 40 mg, placebo followed by a single dose of moxifloxacin 400 mg, or placebo alone.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2529" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Letairis 10 mg daily had no significant effect on the QTc interval.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2530" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The 40 mg dose of Letairis increased mean QTc at tmax by 5 ms with an upper 95% confidence limit of 9 ms. For patients receiving Letairis 5–10 mg daily and not taking metabolic inhibitors, no significant QT prolongation is expected.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2531" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>N-terminal pro-B-type natriuretic peptide (NT-proBNP) In AMBITION, the decrease in NT-proBNP in patients on Letairis plus tadalafil was observed early (Week 4) and was sustained, with a reduction of 63% on Letairis plus tadalafil, 50% on Letairis alone, and 41% on tadalafil alone at Week 24.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2532" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacokinetics of ambrisentan (S-ambrisentan) in healthy subjects is dose proportional.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2533" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The absolute bioavailability of ambrisentan is not known.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2534" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Ambrisentan is absorbed with peak concentrations occurring approximately 2 hours after oral administration in healthy subjects and PAH patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2535" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Food does not affect its bioavailability.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2536" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In vitro studies indicate that ambrisentan is a substrate of P-gp.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2537" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Ambrisentan is highly bound to plasma proteins (99%).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2538" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The elimination of ambrisentan is predominantly by non-renal pathways, but the relative contributions of metabolism and biliary elimination have not been well characterized.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2539" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In plasma, the AUC of 4-hydroxymethyl ambrisentan accounts for approximately 4% relative to parent ambrisentan AUC.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2540" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The in vivo inversion of S-ambrisentan to R-ambrisentan is negligible.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2541" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mean oral clearance of ambrisentan is 38 mL/min and 19 mL/min in healthy subjects and in PAH patients, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2542" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Although ambrisentan has a 15-hour terminal half-life, the mean trough concentration of ambrisentan at steady-state is about 15% of the mean peak concentration and the accumulation factor is about 1.2 after long-term daily dosing, indicating that the effective half-life of ambrisentan is about 9 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2543" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Drug Interactions In Vitro Studies Studies with human liver tissue indicate that ambrisentan is metabolized by CYP3A, CYP2C19, and uridine 5'-diphosphate glucuronosyltransferases (UGTs) 1A9S, 2B7S, and 1A3S.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2544" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In vitro studies suggest that ambrisentan is a substrate of the Organic Anion Transporting Polypeptides OATP1B1 and OATP1B3, and P-glycoprotein (P-gp).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2545" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Drug interactions might be expected because of these factors; however, a clinically relevant interaction has been demonstrated only with cyclosporine.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M7" type="Trigger" span="73 31" str="clinically relevant interaction"/>
<Mention id="M8" type="Precipitant" span="137 12" str="cyclosporine" code="83HN0GTJ6D"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M7" precipitant="M8"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2546" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In vitro studies found ambrisentan to have little to no inhibition of human hepatic transporters.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2547" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Ambrisentan demonstrated weak dose-dependent inhibition of OATP1B1, OATP1B3, and NTCP (IC50 of 47 µM, 45 µM, and approximately 100 µM, respectively) and no transporter-specific inhibition of BSEP, BRCP, P-gp, or MRP2.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2548" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Ambrisentan does not inhibit or induce drug metabolizing enzymes at clinically relevant concentrations.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2549" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In Vivo Studies The effects of other drugs on ambrisentan pharmacokinetics and the effects of ambrisentan on the exposure to other drugs are shown in Figure 2 and Figure 3, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2550" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Figure 2 Effects of Other Drugs on Ambrisentan Pharmacokinetics * Omeprazole: based on population pharmacokinetic analysis in PAH patients** Rifampin: AUC and Cmax were measured at steady-state.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M11" type="Trigger" span="9 25;47 16" str="Effects of Other Drugs on | Pharmacokinetics"/>
<Mention id="M10" type="Precipitant" span="66 10" str="Omeprazole" code="KG60484QX9"/>
<Mention id="M12" type="Precipitant" span="141 8" str="Rifampin" code="VJT6J7R4TR"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M11" precipitant="M10"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M11" precipitant="M12"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2551" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>On Day 3 of coadministration a transient 2-fold increase in AUC was noted that was no longer evident by Day 7.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2552" LabelDrug="Letairis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Figure 3 Effects of Ambrisentan on Other Drugs * Active metabolite of mycophenolate mofetil** GMR (95% CI) for INR Figure 2 Figure 3</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M13" type="Trigger" span="9 10;32 14" str="Effects of | on Other Drugs"/>
<Mention id="M14" type="Precipitant" span="70 21" str="mycophenolate mofetil" code="9242ECW6R0"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M13" precipitant="M14"/>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cyclosporine" precipitantCode="83HN0GTJ6D" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="cyclosporine" precipitantCode="83HN0GTJ6D"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="omeprazole" precipitantCode="KG60484QX9"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="rifampin" precipitantCode="VJT6J7R4TR"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="mycophenolate mofetil" precipitantCode="9242ECW6R0"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>