<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" setid="f21512ea-c7c3-4766-b976-b2c0b5616bf0">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
Lidocaine hydrochloride is contraindicated in patients with a known history of hypersensitivity to local anesthetics of the amide type. Lidocaine should not be used in patients with Stokes-Adams syndrome, Wolff-Parkinson-White syndrome, or with severe degrees of sinoatrial, atrioventricular, or intraventricular block. Solutions containing dextrose may be contraindicated in patients with known allergy to corn or corn products.</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
Therapy of ventricular arrhythmias is often initiated with a single IV bolus of 50 to 100 mg of lidocaine hydrochloride injection. Following acute treatment by bolus in patients in whom arrhythmias tend to recur and who are incapable of receiving oral antiarrhythmic agents, intravenous infusion of Lidocaine Hydrochloride and 5% Dextrose Injection, USP is administered continuously at the rate of 1 to 4 mg/min (20 to 50 mcg/kg/min in the average 70 kg adult). The 0.4% solution (4 mg/mL) can be given at a rate of 15 to 60 mL/hr (0.25 to 1 mL/min). The 0.8% solution (8 mg/mL) can be given at a rate of 7.5 to 30 mL/hr (0.12 to 0.5 mL/min). Precise dose is determined by patient response. “Pharmacokinetic data indicate reduced elimination of lidocaine after prolonged infusion (24 hours) with resultant prolongation of the half-life to approximately three times that seen following a single administration. Failure to adjust the rate of infusion in keeping with this altered ability to eliminate lidocaine may result in toxic accumulation of the drug in the patient’s serum.”  LeLorier, et al., Pharmacokinetics of lidocaine after prolonged intravenous infusions in uncomplicated myocardial infarction, Ann Int. Med. 87:700-702.   Intravenous infusions of lidocaine hydrochloride must be administered under constant ECG monitoring to avoid potential overdosage and toxicity. Intravenous infusion should be terminated as soon as the patient’s basic cardiac rhythm appears to be stable or at the earliest signs of toxicity. It should rarely be necessary to continue intravenous infusions beyond 24 hours. As soon as possible and when indicated, patients should be changed to an oral antiarrhythmic agent for maintenance therapy.  Caution: When administering lidocaine hydrochloride by continuous infusion, it is advisable to closely monitor the infusion rate. Administer Lidocaine Hydrochloride and 5% Dextrose Injection, USP only with a calibrated infusion device.  Pediatric: Although controlled clinical studies to establish pediatric dosing schedules have not been conducted, the American Heart Association’s Standards and Guidelines recommends a bolus dose of 1 mg/kg followed by an infusion rate of 30 µg/kg/min. American Heart Association, Standards and Guidelines for Cardiopulmonary Resuscitation (CPR) and Emergency Cardiac Care (ECC), JAMA Vol. 244. No. 5: 453-509.   Lidocaine hydrochloride should not be added to blood transfusion assemblies. Parenteral drug products should be inspected visually for particulate matter and discoloration prior to administration whenever solution and container permit. Use of a final filter is recommended during administration of all parenteral solutions, where possible. All injections in VIAFLEX Plus plastic containers are intended for intravenous administration using sterile equipment. Because dosages of this drug are titrated to response, no additives should be made to Lidocaine Hydrochloride and 5% Dextrose Injection, USP.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
Lidocaine should be used with caution in patients with digitalis toxicity accompanied by atrioventricular block (see Contraindications).  Coadministration of propranolol or cimetidine with lidocaine has been reported to reduce the clearance of lidocaine from the plasma and may result in toxic accumulation of the drug.  When lidocaine is administered with other antiarrhythmic drugs such as amiodarone, phenytoin, procainamide, propranolol or quinidine, the cardiac effects may be additive or antagonistic and toxic effects may be additive. Phenytoin may stimulate the hepatic metabolism of lidocaine, but the clinical significance of this effect is not known.</Section>
<Section name="PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="42232-9">
Caution should be employed in the repeated use of lidocaine hydrochloride in patients with severe liver or renal disease because accumulation may occur and lead to toxic phenomena, since lidocaine hydrochloride is metabolized mainly in the liver and excreted by the kidneys. The drug should also be used with caution in patients with hypovolemia and shock, and in all forms of heart block (see Contraindications and Warnings). In patients with sinus bradycardia or incomplete heart block, the administration of lidocaine hydrochloride intravenously for the elimination of ventricular ectopic beats without prior acceleration in heart rate (e.g., by isoproterenol or by electric pacing) may promote more frequent and serious ventricular arrhythmias or complete heart block (see Contraindications). Most potent anesthetic agents, local anesthetics of the amide type, which includes lidocaine, and muscle relaxants of both depolarizing and non-depolarizing types, have been associated with malignant hyperthermia. Care should be taken in the administration of intravenous fluids in patients with compromised myocardial function to avoid fluid overload or disturbances of serum electrolyte concentrations which might interfere with cardiac conduction or result in congestive heart failure. Do not administer unless solution is clear and seal is intact.          Clinical evaluation and periodic laboratory determinations are necessary to monitor changes in fluid balance, electrolyte concentrations, and acid-base balance during prolonged parenteral therapy or whenever the condition of the patient warrants such evaluation.          Lidocaine should be used with caution in patients with digitalis toxicity accompanied by atrioventricular block (see Contraindications).  Coadministration of propranolol or cimetidine with lidocaine has been reported to reduce the clearance of lidocaine from the plasma and may result in toxic accumulation of the drug.  When lidocaine is administered with other antiarrhythmic drugs such as amiodarone, phenytoin, procainamide, propranolol or quinidine, the cardiac effects may be additive or antagonistic and toxic effects may be additive. Phenytoin may stimulate the hepatic metabolism of lidocaine, but the clinical significance of this effect is not known.          Long term animal studies have not been performed to evaluate carcinogenic potential, mutagenic potential or the effect on fertility of lidocaine hydrochloride.               Reproduction studies have been performed in rats at doses up to five times the maximum human dose and have revealed no significant findings. There are, however, no adequate and well-controlled studies in pregnant women. Because animal reproduction studies are not always predictive of human response, lidocaine hydrochloride should be used during pregnancy only if clearly needed.            It is not known whether this drug is excreted in human milk. Because many drugs are excreted in human milk, caution should be exercised when lidocaine hydrochloride is administered to a nursing woman.          Safety and effectiveness in pediatric patients have not been established.          Clinical studies of Lidocaine Hydrochloride did not include sufficient numbers of subjects aged 65 and over to determine whether they respond differently from younger subjects. Other reported clinical experience has not identified differences in responses between the elderly and younger patients. In general, dose selection for an elderly patient should be cautious, usually starting at the low end of the dosing range, reflecting the greater frequency of decreased hepatic, renal, or cardiac function, and of concomitant disease or other drug therapy.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS SECTION" id="34071-1">
Constant monitoring with an electrocardiograph is essential to the proper administration of lidocaine hydrochloride intravenously. Signs of excessive depression of cardiac conductivity, such as prolongation of the PR interval, widening of the QRS interval and the appearance or aggravation of arrhythmias, should be followed by prompt cessation of the intravenous infusion of this agent. It is mandatory to have emergency resuscitative equipment and drugs immediately available to manage adverse reactions involving cardiovascular, respiratory, or central nervous systems.  Occasional acceleration of ventricular rate may occur when lidocaine hydrochloride is administered to patients with atrial fibrillation. Evidence for proper usage in children is limited. Anaphylactic reactions may occur following administration of lidocaine hydrochloride. (See ADVERSE REACTIONS).  In the case of severe reaction, discontinue the use of the drug. Administer Lidocaine Hydrochloride and 5% Dextrose Injection, USP only with a calibrated infusion device.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Lidocaine hydrochloride exerts an antiarrhythmic effect by increasing the electrical stimulation threshold of the ventricle during diastole. In usual therapeutic doses, lidocaine hydrochloride produces no change in myocardial contractility, in systemic arterial pressure, or in absolute refractory period. About 90% of an administered dose of the drug is metabolized in the liver. The remaining 10% is excreted unchanged via the kidneys. Lidocaine toxicity is related to systemic blood levels. The decreased clearance and longer half-life of lidocaine should be taken into consideration with prolonged (24 hour) infusions. Constant rate of infusion may result in toxic accumulation of lidocaine. Infusion should be reduced approximately one-half to compensate for decreased rate of clearance and concomitant or prior administration of propranolol may further increase blood concentrations by as much as 30% (See Drug Interactions).</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="1086" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Hypersensitivity reactions, including anaphylactic reactions, have been reported with lidocaine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1087" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Lidocaine hydrochloride is contraindicated in patients with a history of hypersensitivity to local anesthetics of the amide type.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1088" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Lidocaine is contraindicated in patients with Stokes-Adams syndrome, Wolff-Parkinson-White syndrome, or with severe degrees of sinoatrial, atrioventricular, or intraventricular block.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1089" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Therapy of ventricular arrhythmias is often initiated with a single IV bolus of 1.0 to 1.5 mg/kg at a rate of 25 to 50 mg/min. of lidocaine hydrochloride injection.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1090" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Following acute treatment by bolus in patients in whom arrhythmias tend to recur and who are incapable of receiving oral antiarrhythmic agents, intravenous infusion of Lidocaine Hydrochloride and 5% Dextrose Injection, USP is administered continuously at the rate of 1 to 4 mg/min (0.020 to 0.050 mg/kg/min in the average 70 kg adult).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1091" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The 0.4% solution (4 mg/mL) can be given at a rate of 15 to 60 mL/hr (0.25 to 1 mL/min).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1092" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The 0.8% solution (8 mg/mL) can be given at a rate of 7.5 to 30 mL/hr (0.12 to 0.5 mL/min).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1093" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Precise dosage regimen is determined by patient characteristics and response.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1094" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Infusion rate should be reduced by approximately one-half to compensate for decreased rate of clearance after prolonged infusion (24 hours).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1095" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Failure to adjust the rate of infusion in keeping with this altered ability to eliminate lidocaine may result in toxic accumulation of the drug in the patient’s serum.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1096" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Intravenous infusions of lidocaine hydrochloride must be administered under constant ECG monitoring to avoid potential overdosage and toxicity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1097" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Intravenous infusion should be terminated as soon as the patient’s basic cardiac rhythm appears to be stable or at the earliest signs of toxicity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1098" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>It should rarely be necessary to continue intravenous infusions beyond 24 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1099" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>As soon as possible and when indicated, patients should be changed to an oral antiarrhythmic agent for maintenance therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1100" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Caution: When administering lidocaine hydrochloride by continuous infusion, it is advisable to closely monitor the infusion rate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1101" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Administer Lidocaine Hydrochloride and 5% Dextrose Injection, USP only with a calibrated infusion device.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1102" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Pediatric: Clinical studies to establish pediatric dosing schedules have not been conducted.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1103" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The usual dosage is a bolus dose of 1 mg/kg followed by an infusion rate of 20 mcg to 50 mcg/kg/min.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1104" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The bolus dose should be repeated if infusion is not initiated within 15 minutes of the initial bolus dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1105" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Hepatic impairment is likely to decrease clearance and increase exposure level of lidocaine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1106" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Administer lidocaine at lower maintenance infusion rate with close monitoring of toxicity in patients with hepatic impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1107" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Renal Impairment: In patients with severe renal impairment (eGFR less than 30 mL/min/1.73 m2), administer lidocaine at lower maintenance infusion rate with close monitoring of toxicity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1108" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Lidocaine is incompatible with the following due to precipitate formation (includes but is not limited to): Amphotericin Cephazolin sodium Phenytoin sodium Parenteral drug products should be inspected visually for particulate matter and discoloration prior to administration whenever solution and container permit.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1109" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not administer unless solution is clear, the seal is intact, and the container is undamaged.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1110" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Some opacity of the container plastic due to moisture absorption during the sterilization process may be observed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1111" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>This is normal and does not affect solution quality or safety.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1112" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Use of a final filter is recommended during administration of all parenteral solutions, where possible.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1113" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Lidocaine must not be infused simultaneously through the same tubing with other medicinal products without first verifying their compatibility.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1114" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Set the vent to the close position on a vented intravenous administration set to prevent air embolism.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1115" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>All injections in VIAFLEX Plus plastic containers are intended for intravenous administration using sterile equipment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1116" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Because dosages of this drug are titrated to response, no additives should be made to Lidocaine Hydrochloride and 5% Dextrose Injection, USP.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1117" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Digitalis derivatives: Monitor toxicity when lidocaine is used in patients with digitalis toxicity accompanied by supraventricular arrhythmia and/or atrioventricular block.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M16" type="Trigger" span="23 7" str="Monitor"/>
<Mention id="M8" type="Precipitant" span="80 9" str="digitalis" code="F1T8QT9U8B"/>
<Mention id="M12" type="SpecificInteraction" span="149 22" str="atrioventricular block" code="233917008: Atrioventricular block (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M15" type="SpecificInteraction" span="114 27" str="supraventricular arrhythmia" code="72654001: Supraventricular arrhythmia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M18" type="SpecificInteraction" span="31 8" str="toxicity" code="75478009: Poisoning (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M17" type="Precipitant" span="0 21" str="Digitalis derivatives" code="F1T8QT9U8B"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M16" precipitant="M8" effect="M12"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M16" precipitant="M8" effect="M15"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M16" precipitant="M8" effect="M18"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M16" precipitant="M17" effect="M12"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M16" precipitant="M17" effect="M15"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M16" precipitant="M17" effect="M18"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1118" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>When lidocaine is administered with other antiarrhythmic drugs such as amiodarone, phenytoin, procainamide, propranolol or quinidine, the cardiac effects may be additive or antagonistic and toxic effects may be additive.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M70" type="Trigger" span="146 23" str="effects may be additive"/>
<Mention id="M26" type="Precipitant" span="71 10" str="amiodarone" code="N3RQ532IUT"/>
<Mention id="M66" type="SpecificInteraction" span="138 15;173 12" str="cardiac effects | antagonistic" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M72" type="SpecificInteraction" span="190 29" str="toxic effects may be additive" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M69" type="SpecificInteraction" span="138 31" str="cardiac effects may be additive" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M35" type="Precipitant" span="42 20" str="antiarrhythmic drugs" code="N0000178311"/>
<Mention id="M44" type="Precipitant" span="83 9" str="phenytoin" code="6158TKW0C5"/>
<Mention id="M53" type="Precipitant" span="94 12" str="procainamide" code="L39WTC366D"/>
<Mention id="M62" type="Precipitant" span="108 11" str="propranolol" code="9Y8NXQ24VQ"/>
<Mention id="M71" type="Precipitant" span="123 9" str="quinidine" code="ITX08688JL"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M70" precipitant="M26" effect="M66"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M70" precipitant="M26" effect="M72"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M70" precipitant="M26" effect="M69"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M70" precipitant="M35" effect="M66"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M70" precipitant="M35" effect="M72"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M70" precipitant="M35" effect="M69"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M70" precipitant="M44" effect="M69"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M70" precipitant="M44" effect="M66"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M70" precipitant="M44" effect="M72"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M70" precipitant="M53" effect="M69"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M70" precipitant="M53" effect="M66"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M70" precipitant="M53" effect="M72"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M70" precipitant="M62" effect="M69"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M70" precipitant="M62" effect="M72"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M70" precipitant="M62" effect="M66"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M70" precipitant="M71" effect="M66"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M70" precipitant="M71" effect="M69"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M70" precipitant="M71" effect="M72"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1119" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant treatment with drugs which are inhibitors of CYP1A2 and/or CYP3A4 has the potential to increase lidocaine plasma levels by decreasing lidocaine clearance and thereby prolonging the elimination half-life.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M81" type="Trigger" span="99 8;118 13" str="increase | plasma levels"/>
<Mention id="M78" type="Precipitant" span="43 13;71 6" str="inhibitors of | CYP3A4" code="N0000182141"/>
<Mention id="M79" type="Trigger" span="135 10;156 9" str="decreasing | clearance"/>
<Mention id="M83" type="Trigger" span="178 36" str="prolonging the elimination half-life"/>
<Mention id="M84" type="Precipitant" span="43 20" str="inhibitors of CYP1A2" code="N0000182138"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M81" precipitant="M78" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M79" precipitant="M78" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M83" precipitant="M78" effect="C54603"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M79" precipitant="M84" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I29" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M81" precipitant="M84" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I30" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M83" precipitant="M84" effect="C54603"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1120" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor toxicity when administering lidocaine with CYP1A2 and/or CYP3A4 inhibitors.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M87" type="Trigger" span="0 16" str="Monitor toxicity"/>
<Mention id="M86" type="Precipitant" span="51 6;72 10" str="CYP1A2 | inhibitors" code="N0000182138"/>
<Mention id="M88" type="Precipitant" span="65 17" str="CYP3A4 inhibitors" code="N0000182141"/>
<Interaction id="I31" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M87" precipitant="M86" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I32" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M87" precipitant="M88" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1121" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant use of lidocaineat steady-state concentrations of the CYP1A2 inhibitor fluvoxamine increases intravenous lidocaine plasma AUC and Cmax by 71% and 22%, and decreases MEGX AUC and Cmax by 54% and 65%.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M93" type="Trigger" span="95 9;142 4" str="increases | Cmax"/>
<Mention id="M92" type="Precipitant" span="66 16" str="CYP1A2 inhibitor" code="N0000182138"/>
<Mention id="M95" type="Trigger" span="95 9;134 3" str="increases | AUC"/>
<Mention id="M96" type="Precipitant" span="83 11" str="fluvoxamine" code="O4L1XPO44W"/>
<Interaction id="I33" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M93" precipitant="M92" effect="C54602"/>
<Interaction id="I34" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M95" precipitant="M92" effect="C54605"/>
<Interaction id="I35" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M93" precipitant="M96" effect="C54602"/>
<Interaction id="I36" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M95" precipitant="M96" effect="C54605"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1122" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Fluvoxamine decreases the plasma clearance of lidocaine by 41%-60% and prolonged the mean half-life by one hour.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M97" type="Trigger" span="12 30" str="decreases the plasma clearance"/>
<Mention id="M100" type="Precipitant" span="0 11" str="Fluvoxamine" code="O4L1XPO44W"/>
<Mention id="M99" type="Trigger" span="71 28" str="prolonged the mean half-life"/>
<Interaction id="I37" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M97" precipitant="M100" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I38" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M99" precipitant="M100" effect="C54603"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1123" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor toxicity when coadministering these medications.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1124" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant use of lidocaine with propofol, a hypnotic agent and CYP3A4 inhibitor, may increase lidocaine plasma levels by reducing lidocaine clearance.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M104" type="Trigger" span="87 8;106 13" str="increase | plasma levels "/>
<Mention id="M105" type="Trigger" span="123 8;142 9" str=" reducing | clearance"/>
<Mention id="M103" type="Precipitant" span="65 16" str="CYP3A4 inhibitor" code="N0000182141"/>
<Mention id="M106" type="Precipitant" span="34 8" str="propofol" code="YI7VU623SF"/>
<Interaction id="I39" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M104;M105" precipitant="M103" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I40" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M104;M105" precipitant="M106" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1125" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor toxicity when coadministering lidocaine with propofol.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M107" type="Trigger" span="0 16" str="Monitor toxicity"/>
<Mention id="M108" type="Precipitant" span="53 8" str="propofol" code="YI7VU623SF"/>
<Interaction id="I41" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M107" precipitant="M108" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1126" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant treatment with drugs which are inducers of CYP1A2 and/or CYP3A4 (e.g., phenytoin) has the potential to decrease lidocaine plasma levels and higher doses may be required.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M115" type="Trigger" span="115 8;134 13" str="decrease | plasma levels "/>
<Mention id="M116" type="Trigger" span="152 28" str=" higher doses may be required"/>
<Mention id="M111" type="Precipitant" span="43 11;69 6" str="inducers of | CYP3A4" code="N0000185506"/>
<Mention id="M114" type="Precipitant" span="43 18" str="inducers of CYP1A2" code="N0000191266"/>
<Mention id="M117" type="Precipitant" span="83 9" str="phenytoin" code="6158TKW0C5"/>
<Interaction id="I42" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M115;M116" precipitant="M111" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I43" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M115;M116" precipitant="M114" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I44" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M115;M116" precipitant="M117" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1127" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant use of lidocaine with a weak CYP1A2 and CYP3A4 inhibitor has been reported to increase lidocaine plasma levels by 24% – 75% and may result in toxic accumulation of the drug.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M118" type="Trigger" span="90 8;109 13" str="increase | plasma levels "/>
<Mention id="M119" type="Trigger" span="154 18" str=" toxic accumulation"/>
<Mention id="M120" type="Precipitant" span="36 32" str="weak CYP1A2 and CYP3A4 inhibitor" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I45" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M118;M119" precipitant="M120" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1128" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor toxicity when coadministering lidocaine with cimetidine.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M121" type="Trigger" span="0 16" str="Monitor toxicity"/>
<Mention id="M122" type="Precipitant" span="53 10" str="cimetidine" code="80061L1WGD"/>
<Interaction id="I46" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M121" precipitant="M122" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1129" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Beta-adrenergic blockers (e.g. propranolol): Concomitant use of lidocaine with beta-adrenergic blockers may increase lidocaine plasma levels by decreasing hepatic blood flow and thereby decrease lidocaine clearance.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M128" type="SpecificInteraction" span="144 29" str="decreasing hepatic blood flow" code="764268008: Inadequate peripheral blood flow (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M131" type="Precipitant" span="79 24" str="beta-adrenergic blockers" code="N0000175556"/>
<Mention id="M134" type="Precipitant" span="31 11" str="propranolol" code="9Y8NXQ24VQ"/>
<Mention id="M132" type="Trigger" span="108 8;127 13" str="increase | plasma levels "/>
<Mention id="M133" type="Trigger" span="186 8;205 9" str=" decrease | clearance"/>
<Interaction id="I47" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M128" precipitant="M131" effect="M128"/>
<Interaction id="I48" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M128" precipitant="M134" effect="M128"/>
<Interaction id="I49" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M132;M133" precipitant="M131" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I50" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M132;M133" precipitant="M134" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1130" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor for toxicity when coadministering lidocaine with drugs that decrease hepatic blood flow.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M135" type="Trigger" span="0 20" str="Monitor for toxicity"/>
<Mention id="M136" type="Precipitant" span="57 38" str="drugs that decrease hepatic blood flow" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I51" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M135" precipitant="M136" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1131" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>If malignant hyperthermia develops, discontinue administration immediately and institute therapeutic countermeasures as clinically indicated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1132" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Lidocaine hydrochloride should not be added to blood transfusion assemblies because of the possibilities of pseudoagglutination or hemolysis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1133" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Clinical evaluation and periodic laboratory determinations are necessary to monitor changes in fluid balance, electrolyte concentrations, and acid-base balance during prolonged parenteral therapy or whenever the condition of the patient warrants such evaluation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1134" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Long term animal studies have not been performed to evaluate carcinogenic potential, mutagenic potential or the effect on fertility of lidocaine hydrochloride.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1135" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Reproduction studies have been performed in rats at doses up to five times the maximum human dose and have revealed no significant findings.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1136" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>There are, however, no adequate and well-controlled studies in pregnant women.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1137" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because animal reproduction studies are not always predictive of human response, physicians should carefully consider the potential risks and benefits for each specific patient before prescribing lidocaine hydrochloride.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1138" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Lidocaine may cross the placental barrier.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1139" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Published studies have reported a range of lidocaine milk: plasma ratios between 0.4-1.1.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1140" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Limited data available on lidocaine’s effects on the breastfed child have not revealed a consistent pattern of associated adverse events.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1141" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The development and health benefits of breastfeeding should be considered along with the mother’s clinical need for lidocaine and any potential adverse effects on the breastfed infant from lidocaine or from the underlying maternal condition.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1142" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Safety and effectiveness in pediatric patients have not been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1143" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Clinical studies of Lidocaine Hydrochloride did not include sufficient numbers of subjects aged 65 and over to determine whether they respond differently from younger subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1144" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Other reported clinical experience has not identified differences in responses between the elderly and younger patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1145" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In general, dose selection for an elderly patient should be cautious, usually starting at the low end of the dosing range, reflecting the greater frequency of decreased hepatic, renal, or cardiac function, and of concomitant disease or other drug therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1146" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Constant monitoring with an electrocardiograph is essential to the administration of lidocaine hydrochloride intravenously.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1147" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Signs of excessive depression of cardiac conductivity, such as prolongation of the PR interval, widening of the QRS interval and the appearance or aggravation of arrhythmias, should be followed by prompt cessation of the intravenous infusion of this agent.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1148" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>It is mandatory to have emergency resuscitative equipment and drugs immediately available to manage adverse reactions involving cardiovascular, respiratory, or central nervous systems.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1149" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Central nervous system adverse reactions are associated with venous plasma levels above 6.0 μg free base per mL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1150" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Hypersensitivity, including anaphylaxis, has been reported with lidocaine-containing solutions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1151" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Stop the infusion immediately if signs of hypersensitivity develop.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1152" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Acceleration of ventricular rate may occur in patients with atrial fibrillation or flutter treated with lidocaine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1153" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>In patients with sinus bradycardia or incomplete heart block, the administration of lidocaine hydrochloride intravenously for the elimination of ventricular ectopic beats without prior acceleration in heart r ate (e.g., by isoproterenol or by electric pacing) may promote more frequent and serious ventricular arrhythmias or complete heart block.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1154" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Because lidocaine is metabolized mainly in the liver and excreted by the kidneys, patients with renal or hepatic insufficiency may be at increased risk for toxicity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1155" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Lidocaine hydrochloride exerts an antiarrhythmic effect by increasing the electrical stimulation threshold of the ventricle during diastole.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1156" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In usual therapeutic doses, lidocaine hydrochloride produces no change in myocardial contractility, in systemic arterial pressure, or in absolute refractory period.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1157" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Central nervous system adverse reactions become apparent with increasing venous plasma levels above 6.0 μg free base per mL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1158" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The plasma protein binding of lidocaine is dependent on drug concentration, and the fraction bound decreases with increasing concentration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1159" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>At concentrations of 1 to 4 micrograms of free base per milliliter 60 to 80 percent of lidocaine is protein bound.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1160" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Binding is also dependent on the plasma concentration of alpha-1-acid glycoprotein.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1161" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Lidocaine crosses the blood-brain and placental barriers, presumably by passive diffusion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1162" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Approximately 90% of lidocaine administered is excreted in the form of various metabolites, and less than 10% is excreted unchanged.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1163" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Biotransformation includes oxidative N-dealkylation, ring hydroxylation, cleavage of the amide linkage, and conjugation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1164" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>CYP1A2 and CYP3A4 mediated N-dealkylation, a major pathway of biotransformation, yields the metabolites monoethyl glycine xylidide (MEGX) and glycine xylidide (GX).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1165" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacological/toxicological actions of these metabolites are similar to, but less potent than, those of lidocaine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1166" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The primary metabolite in urine is a conjugate of 4-hydroxy-2,6-dimethylaniline.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1167" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The elimination half-life of lidocaine following an intravenous bolus injection is typically 1.5 to 2.0 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1168" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Hepatic Impairment Because of the rapid rate at which lidocaine is metabolized, any condition that affects liver function may alter lidocaine kinetics.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1169" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The half-life may be prolonged two-fold or more in patients with liver dysfunction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1170" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Renal Impairment Mild or moderate renal impairment does not affect lidocaine kinetics; while in patients with severe renal dysfunction, lidocaine clearance is decreased by half and the accumulation of GX increased 1.5-fold.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1171" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Lidocaine toxicity is related to systemic blood levels.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1172" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The decreased clearance and longer half-life of lidocaine should be taken into consideration with prolonged (24 hour) infusions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1173" LabelDrug="Lidocaine Hydrochloride and Dextrose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Constant rate of infusion may result in toxic accumulation of lidocaine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="digitalis" precipitantCode="F1T8QT9U8B" effect="233917008: Atrioventricular block (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="digitalis" precipitantCode="F1T8QT9U8B" effect="72654001: Supraventricular arrhythmia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="digitalis" precipitantCode="F1T8QT9U8B" effect="75478009: Poisoning (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="digitalis derivatives" precipitantCode="F1T8QT9U8B" effect="233917008: Atrioventricular block (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="digitalis derivatives" precipitantCode="F1T8QT9U8B" effect="72654001: Supraventricular arrhythmia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="digitalis derivatives" precipitantCode="F1T8QT9U8B" effect="75478009: Poisoning (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="amiodarone" precipitantCode="N3RQ532IUT" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="antiarrhythmic drugs" precipitantCode="N0000178311" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="phenytoin" precipitantCode="6158TKW0C5" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="phenytoin" precipitantCode="6158TKW0C5" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="procainamide" precipitantCode="L39WTC366D" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="propranolol" precipitantCode="9Y8NXQ24VQ" effect="764268008: Inadequate peripheral blood flow (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="propranolol" precipitantCode="9Y8NXQ24VQ" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="propranolol" precipitantCode="9Y8NXQ24VQ" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="quinidine" precipitantCode="ITX08688JL" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="inhibitors of | cyp3a4" precipitantCode="N0000182141" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="inhibitors of | cyp3a4" precipitantCode="N0000182141" effect="C54603"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="inhibitors of cyp1a2" precipitantCode="N0000182138" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="inhibitors of cyp1a2" precipitantCode="N0000182138" effect="C54603"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cyp1a2 | inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000182138" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cyp3a4 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000182141" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cyp1a2 inhibitor" precipitantCode="N0000182138" effect="C54602"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cyp1a2 inhibitor" precipitantCode="N0000182138" effect="C54605"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="fluvoxamine" precipitantCode="O4L1XPO44W" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="fluvoxamine" precipitantCode="O4L1XPO44W" effect="C54602"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="fluvoxamine" precipitantCode="O4L1XPO44W" effect="C54603"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="fluvoxamine" precipitantCode="O4L1XPO44W" effect="C54605"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cyp3a4 inhibitor" precipitantCode="N0000182141" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="propofol" precipitantCode="YI7VU623SF" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="inducers of | cyp3a4" precipitantCode="N0000185506" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="inducers of cyp1a2" precipitantCode="N0000191266" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="weak cyp1a2 and cyp3a4 inhibitor" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cimetidine" precipitantCode="80061L1WGD" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="beta-adrenergic blockers" precipitantCode="N0000175556" effect="764268008: Inadequate peripheral blood flow (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="beta-adrenergic blockers" precipitantCode="N0000175556" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="drugs that decrease hepatic blood flow" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54355"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>