<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Lidocaine" setid="f1b26274-a55e-4321-b96c-ce0df830f205">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
Lidocaine Hydrochloride Injection, USP is contraindicated in patients with a known history of hypersensitivity to local anesthetics of the amide type.  Lidocaine Hydrochloride Injection, USP should not be used in patients with STOKES-ADAMS syndrome, Wolff-Parkinson-White syndrome, or with severe degrees of sinoatrial, atrioventricular or intraventricular block.</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
For Direct Injection –The usual dose is 50 to 100 mg administered intravenously under ECG monitoring.  This dose may be administered at the rate of approximately 25 to 50 mg/min.  Sufficient time should be allowed to enable a slow circulation to carry the drug to the site of action.  If the initial injection of 50 to 100 mg does not produce a desired response, a second dose may be repeated after 5 minutes. NO MORE THAN 200 TO 300 MG OF LIDOCAINE HYDROCHLORIDE INJECTION, USP SHOULD BE ADMINISTERED DURING A ONE HOUR PERIOD. This product is for  DIRECT INJECTION ONLY.   For continuous infusion protocol, see prescribing information for lidocaine hydrochloride, USP for infusion solution.          Although controlled clinical studies to establish pediatric dosing schedules have not been conducted, the American Heart Association’s  Standards and Guidelines recommends a bolus dose of 1 mg/kg followed by an infusion rate of 30 mcg/kg/min. This product is for  DIRECT INJECTION ONLY .  For continuous infusion protocol, see prescribing information for lidocaine hydrochloride, USP for infusion solution.          It is recommended that chemical disinfection be accomplished by wiping the vial thoroughly with cotton or gauze that has been moistened with either 91% isopropyl alcohol or 70% ethyl alcohol, just prior to use.  Store at 20° to 25°C (68° to 77°F) [see USP Controlled Room Temperature]. Parenteral drug products should be inspected visually for particulate matter and discoloration prior to administration, whenever solution and container permit.           For Direct Injection –The usual dose is 50 to 100 mg administered intravenously under ECG monitoring.  This dose may be administered at the rate of approximately 25 to 50 mg/min.  Sufficient time should be allowed to enable a slow circulation to carry the drug to the site of action.  If the initial injection of 50 to 100 mg does not produce a desired response, a second dose may be repeated after 5 minutes. NO MORE THAN 200 TO 300 MG OF LIDOCAINE HYDROCHLORIDE INJECTION, USP SHOULD BE ADMINISTERED DURING A ONE HOUR PERIOD. This product is for  DIRECT INJECTION ONLY.   For continuous infusion protocol, see prescribing information for lidocaine hydrochloride, USP for infusion solution.       Although controlled clinical studies to establish pediatric dosing schedules have not been conducted, the American Heart Association’s  Standards and Guidelines recommends a bolus dose of 1 mg/kg followed by an infusion rate of 30 mcg/kg/min. This product is for  DIRECT INJECTION ONLY .  For continuous infusion protocol, see prescribing information for lidocaine hydrochloride, USP for infusion solution.       It is recommended that chemical disinfection be accomplished by wiping the vial thoroughly with cotton or gauze that has been moistened with either 91% isopropyl alcohol or 70% ethyl alcohol, just prior to use.  Store at 20° to 25°C (68° to 77°F) [see USP Controlled Room Temperature]. Parenteral drug products should be inspected visually for particulate matter and discoloration prior to administration, whenever solution and container permit.</Section>
<Section name="PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="42232-9">
The safe use of Lidocaine Hydrochloride Injection, USP requires careful ECG observation in an environment equipped and by persons trained for resuscitation.        Caution should be employed in the repeated use of Lidocaine Hydrochloride Injection, USP in patients with severe liver or renal disease because accumulation may occur and lead to toxic phenomena since Lidocaine Hydrochloride Injection, USP is metabolized mainly in the liver and excreted by the kidneys.  This drug should also be used with caution in patients with hypovolemia and shock and all forms of heart block (see   CONTRAINDICATIONS  and   WARNINGS  ). In patients with sinus bradycardia or incomplete heart block, the administration of Lidocaine Hydrochloride Injection, USP intravenously or the elimination of ventricular ectopic beats without prior acceleration in heart rate may promote more frequent and serious ventricular arrhythmias or complete heart block.  (See   CONTRAINDICATIONS  .) Many potent anesthetic drugs, neuromuscular blocking agents and possibly amide local anesthetics may serve as triggering agents for the fulminant hypermetabolic process termed malignant hyperthermia.  Key to successful outcome of fulminant hypermetabolism is early recognition of premonitory signs, i.e., unexplained or unexpected tachycardia and increased metabolic rate as evidenced by respiratory and/or metabolic acidosis.  Treatment includes administration of oxygen and discontinuation of lidocaine hydrochloride administration and where necessary administration of dantrolene sodium.  For additional information on management, see prescribing information for dantrolene sodium.          The effect of Lidocaine Hydrochloride Injection, USP for the management of cardiac arrhythmias is potentiated with the simultaneous or prior administration of propranolol. Lidocaine Hydrochloride Injection, USP should be used with caution in patients with digitalis toxicity accompanied by atrioventricular block.  (See   CONTRAINDICATIONS  .) Drug interaction was studied with several beta-blockers (propranolol, metoprolol, nadolol, and pindolol).  Pretreatment with propranolol, metoprolol and nadolol increased the serum concentration of lidocaine.  Pretreatment with pindolol did not affect the serum concentration of lidocaine.          Studies of Lidocaine Hydrochloride Injection, USP in animals to evaluate the carcinogenic and mutagenic potential or the effect on fertility have not been conducted.          Reproductive studies have been performed in the rat at doses up to 5 times the human dose and have revealed no evidence of impaired fertility or harm to the fetus due to Lidocaine Hydrochloride Injection, USP.  There are, however, no adequate and well controlled studies in pregnant women.  Because animal reproduction studies are not always predictive of human response, this drug should be used in pregnancy only if clearly needed.          The effects of Lidocaine Hydrochloride Injection, USP solution on the mother and the fetus, when used in the management of cardiac arrhythmias during labor and delivery, are not known.  Lidocaine Hydrochloride Injection, USP readily crosses the placental barrier.          It is not known whether this drug is excreted in human milk.  Because many drugs are excreted in human milk, caution should be exercised when Lidocaine Hydrochloride Injection, USP is administered to a nursing woman.          Safety and effectiveness in children have not been established by controlled clinical studies.  (See   DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION  .)         Caution should be employed in the repeated use of Lidocaine Hydrochloride Injection, USP in patients with severe liver or renal disease because accumulation may occur and lead to toxic phenomena since Lidocaine Hydrochloride Injection, USP is metabolized mainly in the liver and excreted by the kidneys.  This drug should also be used with caution in patients with hypovolemia and shock and all forms of heart block (see   CONTRAINDICATIONS  and   WARNINGS  ). In patients with sinus bradycardia or incomplete heart block, the administration of Lidocaine Hydrochloride Injection, USP intravenously or the elimination of ventricular ectopic beats without prior acceleration in heart rate may promote more frequent and serious ventricular arrhythmias or complete heart block.  (See   CONTRAINDICATIONS  .) Many potent anesthetic drugs, neuromuscular blocking agents and possibly amide local anesthetics may serve as triggering agents for the fulminant hypermetabolic process termed malignant hyperthermia.  Key to successful outcome of fulminant hypermetabolism is early recognition of premonitory signs, i.e., unexplained or unexpected tachycardia and increased metabolic rate as evidenced by respiratory and/or metabolic acidosis.  Treatment includes administration of oxygen and discontinuation of lidocaine hydrochloride administration and where necessary administration of dantrolene sodium.  For additional information on management, see prescribing information for dantrolene sodium.       The effect of Lidocaine Hydrochloride Injection, USP for the management of cardiac arrhythmias is potentiated with the simultaneous or prior administration of propranolol. Lidocaine Hydrochloride Injection, USP should be used with caution in patients with digitalis toxicity accompanied by atrioventricular block.  (See   CONTRAINDICATIONS  .) Drug interaction was studied with several beta-blockers (propranolol, metoprolol, nadolol, and pindolol).  Pretreatment with propranolol, metoprolol and nadolol increased the serum concentration of lidocaine.  Pretreatment with pindolol did not affect the serum concentration of lidocaine.       Studies of Lidocaine Hydrochloride Injection, USP in animals to evaluate the carcinogenic and mutagenic potential or the effect on fertility have not been conducted.       Reproductive studies have been performed in the rat at doses up to 5 times the human dose and have revealed no evidence of impaired fertility or harm to the fetus due to Lidocaine Hydrochloride Injection, USP.  There are, however, no adequate and well controlled studies in pregnant women.  Because animal reproduction studies are not always predictive of human response, this drug should be used in pregnancy only if clearly needed.       The effects of Lidocaine Hydrochloride Injection, USP solution on the mother and the fetus, when used in the management of cardiac arrhythmias during labor and delivery, are not known.  Lidocaine Hydrochloride Injection, USP readily crosses the placental barrier.       It is not known whether this drug is excreted in human milk.  Because many drugs are excreted in human milk, caution should be exercised when Lidocaine Hydrochloride Injection, USP is administered to a nursing woman.       Safety and effectiveness in children have not been established by controlled clinical studies.  (See   DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION  .)</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS SECTION" id="34071-1">
Constant monitoring of the electrocardiogram and blood pressure is essential in the proper administration of Lidocaine Hydrochloride Injection, USP intravenously.  If hypotension or excessive depression of cardiac conductivity (such as prolongation of the PR interval and QRS complex and the appearance of aggravation of arrhythmias) is seen, administration of Lidocaine Hydrochloride Injection, USP should be discontinued. Emergency resuscitative equipment and drugs must be immediately available to manage possible adverse reactions involving the cardiovascular, respiratory, or central nervous system. Occasional acceleration of ventricular rate may occur when Lidocaine Hydrochloride Injection, USP is administered to patients with atrial fibrillation. Toxicity may be manifest as central nervous system depression (sedation) or irritability (twitching), which may progress to frank convulsions accompanied by respiratory depression and/or arrest.  Early recognition of premonitory signs, assurance of adequate oxygenation and (where necessary) establishment of artificial airway with ventilatory support are essential to management of the problem.  Should convulsions persist despite ventilatory support,  small doses of anticonvulsant drugs may be used intravenously.  Examples of such drugs include benzodiazepines (e.g., diazepam, lorazepam), or an ultrashort acting barbiturate (e.g., thiopental or thiamylal).  If the patient is under anesthesia, a short-acting muscle relaxant (succinylcholine) may be used.  Longer acting drugs should be used only when recurrent convulsions are evidenced.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Lidocaine hydrochloride exerts its antiarrhythmic effect by raising the electrical stimulation threshold of the ventricle during diastole.  In usual therapeutic doses, lidocaine hydrochloride produces no change in myocardial contractility, systemic arterial pressure or in absolute refractory period. Onset of action is rapid after an intravenous bolus with a duration of action of approximately 15 to 20 minutes. Approximately 90% of an administered dose of lidocaine hydrochloride is metabolized in the liver.  The remainder (10%) of the drug is excreted unchanged in the urine.  Pharmacokinetic data indicate reduced elimination of lidocaine after prolonged (24 hours) infusion with resultant prolongation of the half-life to approximately three times that seen following a single administration.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="7388" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Lidocaine Hydrochloride Injection, USP is contraindicated in patients with a known history of hypersensitivity to local anesthetics of the amide type.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7389" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Lidocaine Hydrochloride Injection, USP should not be used in patients with STOKES-ADAMS syndrome, Wolff-Parkinson-White syndrome, or with severe degrees of sinoatrial, atrioventricular or intraventricular block.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7390" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For Direct Injection –The usual dose is 50 to 100 mg administered intravenously under ECG monitoring.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7391" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>This dose may be administered at the rate of approximately 25 to 50 mg/min.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7392" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Sufficient time should be allowed to enable a slow circulation to carry the drug to the site of action.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7393" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If the initial injection of 50 to 100 mg does not produce a desired response, a second dose may be repeated after 5 minutes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7394" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>NO MORE THAN 200 TO 300 MG OF LIDOCAINE HYDROCHLORIDE INJECTION, USP SHOULD BE ADMINISTERED DURING A ONE HOUR PERIOD.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7395" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>This product is for DIRECT INJECTION ONLY.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7396" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For continuous infusion protocol, see prescribing information for lidocaine hydrochloride, USP for infusion solution.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7397" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Although controlled clinical studies to establish pediatric dosing schedules have not been conducted, the American Heart Association’s Standards and Guidelines recommends a bolus dose of 1 mg/kg followed by an infusion rate of 30 mcg/kg/min.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7398" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>It is recommended that chemical disinfection be accomplished by wiping the vial thoroughly with cotton or gauze that has been moistened with either 91% isopropyl alcohol or 70% ethyl alcohol, just prior to use.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7399" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Store at 20° to 25°C (68° to 77°F).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7400" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Parenteral drug products should be inspected visually for particulate matter and discoloration prior to administration, whenever solution and container permit.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7401" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The safe use of Lidocaine Hydrochloride Injection, USP requires careful ECG observation in an environment equipped and by persons trained for resuscitation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7402" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Caution should be employed in the repeated use of Lidocaine Hydrochloride Injection, USP in patients with severe liver or renal disease because accumulation may occur and lead to toxic phenomena since Lidocaine Hydrochloride Injection, USP is metabolized mainly in the liver and excreted by the kidneys.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7403" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>This drug should also be used with caution in patients with hypovolemia and shock and all forms of heart block.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7404" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In patients with sinus bradycardia or incomplete heart block, the administration of Lidocaine Hydrochloride Injection, USP intravenously or the elimination of ventricular ectopic beats without prior acceleration in heart rate may promote more frequent and serious ventricular arrhythmias or complete heart block.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7405" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Many potent anesthetic drugs, neuromuscular blocking agents and possibly amide local anesthetics may serve as triggering agents for the fulminant hypermetabolic process termed malignant hyperthermia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7406" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Key to successful outcome of fulminant hypermetabolism is early recognition of premonitory signs, i.e., unexplained or unexpected tachycardia and increased metabolic rate as evidenced by respiratory and/or metabolic acidosis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7407" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Treatment includes administration of oxygen and discontinuation of lidocaine hydrochloride administration and where necessary administration of dantrolene sodium.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7408" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>For additional information on management, see prescribing information for dantrolene sodium.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M1" type="Trigger" span="42 27" str="see prescribing information"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="74 17" str="dantrolene sodium" code="287M0347EV"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M1" precipitant="M2"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7409" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The effect of Lidocaine Hydrochloride Injection, USP for the management of cardiac arrhythmias is potentiated with the simultaneous or prior administration of propranolol.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M3" type="Trigger" span="98 11" str="potentiated"/>
<Mention id="M4" type="Precipitant" span="159 11" str="propranolol" code="9Y8NXQ24VQ"/>
<Mention id="M5" type="SpecificInteraction" span="61 33" str="management of cardiac arrhythmias" code="698247007: Cardiac arrhythmia (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M3" precipitant="M4" effect="M5"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7410" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Lidocaine Hydrochloride Injection, USP should be used with caution in patients with digitalis toxicity accompanied by atrioventricular block.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M6" type="Trigger" span="59 7" str="caution"/>
<Mention id="M7" type="Precipitant" span="84 9" str="digitalis" code="F1T8QT9U8B"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M6" precipitant="M7"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7411" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Drug interaction was studied with several beta-blockers (propranolol, metoprolol, nadolol, and pindolol).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7412" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Pretreatment with propranolol, metoprolol and nadolol increased the serum concentration of lidocaine.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M12" type="Trigger" span="54 33" str="increased the serum concentration"/>
<Mention id="M9" type="Precipitant" span="31 10" str="metoprolol" code="GEB06NHM23"/>
<Mention id="M11" type="Precipitant" span="46 7" str="nadolol" code="FEN504330V"/>
<Mention id="M13" type="Precipitant" span="18 11" str="propranolol" code="9Y8NXQ24VQ"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M12" precipitant="M9" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M12" precipitant="M11" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M12" precipitant="M13" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7413" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Pretreatment with pindolol did not affect the serum concentration of lidocaine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7414" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Studies of Lidocaine Hydrochloride Injection, USP in animals to evaluate the carcinogenic and mutagenic potential or the effect on fertility have not been conducted.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7415" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Reproductive studies have been performed in the rat at doses up to 5 times the human dose and have revealed no evidence of impaired fertility or harm to the fetus due to Lidocaine Hydrochloride Injection, USP.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7416" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>There are, however, no adequate and well controlled studies in pregnant women.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7417" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because animal reproduction studies are not always predictive of human response, this drug should be used in pregnancy only if clearly needed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7418" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The effects of Lidocaine Hydrochloride Injection, USP solution on the mother and the fetus, when used in the management of cardiac arrhythmias during labor and delivery, are not known.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7419" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Lidocaine Hydrochloride Injection, USP readily crosses the placental barrier.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7420" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>It is not known whether this drug is excreted in human milk.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7421" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because many drugs are excreted in human milk, caution should be exercised when Lidocaine Hydrochloride Injection, USP is administered to a nursing woman.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7422" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Safety and effectiveness in children have not been established by controlled clinical studies.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7423" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Constant monitoring of the electrocardiogram and blood pressure is essential in the proper administration of Lidocaine Hydrochloride Injection, USP intravenously.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7424" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>If hypotension or excessive depression of cardiac conductivity (such as prolongation of the PR interval and QRS complex and the appearance of aggravation of arrhythmias) is seen, administration of Lidocaine Hydrochloride Injection, USP should be discontinued.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7425" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Emergency resuscitative equipment and drugs must be immediately available to manage possible adverse reactions involving the cardiovascular, respiratory, or central nervous system.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7426" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Occasional acceleration of ventricular rate may occur when Lidocaine Hydrochloride Injection, USP is administered to patients with atrial fibrillation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7427" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Toxicity may be manifest as central nervous system depression (sedation) or irritability (twitching), which may progress to frank convulsions accompanied by respiratory depression and/or arrest.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7428" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Early recognition of premonitory signs, assurance of adequate oxygenation and (where necessary) establishment of artificial airway with ventilatory support are essential to management of the problem.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7429" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Should convulsions persist despite ventilatory support, small doses of anticonvulsant drugs may be used intravenously.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7430" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Examples of such drugs include benzodiazepines (e.g., diazepam, lorazepam), or an ultrashort acting barbiturate (e.g., thiopental or thiamylal).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7431" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>If the patient is under anesthesia, a short-acting muscle relaxant (succinylcholine) may be used.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7432" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Longer acting drugs should be used only when recurrent convulsions are evidenced.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7433" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Lidocaine hydrochloride exerts its antiarrhythmic effect by raising the electrical stimulation threshold of the ventricle during diastole.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7434" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In usual therapeutic doses, lidocaine hydrochloride produces no change in myocardial contractility, systemic arterial pressure or in absolute refractory period.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7435" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Onset of action is rapid after an intravenous bolus with a duration of action of approximately 15 to 20 minutes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7436" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Approximately 90% of an administered dose of lidocaine hydrochloride is metabolized in the liver.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7437" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The remainder (10%) of the drug is excreted unchanged in the urine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7438" LabelDrug="Lidocaine" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Pharmacokinetic data indicate reduced elimination of lidocaine after prolonged (24 hours) infusion with resultant prolongation of the half-life to approximately three times that seen following a single administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="dantrolene sodium" precipitantCode="287M0347EV"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="propranolol" precipitantCode="9Y8NXQ24VQ" effect="698247007: Cardiac arrhythmia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="propranolol" precipitantCode="9Y8NXQ24VQ" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="digitalis" precipitantCode="F1T8QT9U8B"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="metoprolol" precipitantCode="GEB06NHM23" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="nadolol" precipitantCode="FEN504330V" effect="C54355"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>