<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Lithostat" setid="6660b616-a82d-9109-19ce-2bdf9747acea">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
Acetohydroxamic acid should not be used in:  patients whose physical state and disease are amenable to definitive surgery and appropriate antimicrobial agents patients whose urine is infected by non-urease producing organisms patients whose urinary infections can be controlled by culture-specific oral antimicrobial agents patients whose renal function is poor (i.e., serum creatinine more than 2.5 mg/dl and/or creatinine clearance less than 20 ml/min) female patients who do not evidence a satisfactory method of contraception patients who are pregnant  Acetohydroxamic acid may cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. AHA was teratogenic (retarded and/or clubbed rear leg at 750 mg/kg and above and exencephaly and encephalocele at 1,500 mg/kg) when given intraperitoneally to rats. AHA is contraindicated in women who are or may become pregnant. If this drug is used during pregnancy, or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking this drug, the patient should be informed of the potential hazard to the fetus.</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
AHA should be administered orally, one tablet 3-4 times a day in a total daily dose of 10-15 mg/kg/day. The recommended starting dose is 12 mg/kg/day, administered at 6-8 hour intervals at a time when the stomach is empty. The maximum daily dose should be no more than 1.5 grams, regardless of body weight. The dosage should be reduced in patients with reduced renal function. Patients whose serum creatinine is greater than 1.8 mg/dl should take no more than 1.0 gm/day; such patients should be dosed at q-12-h intervals. Further reductions in dosage to prevent the accumulation of toxic concentrations in the blood may also be desirable. Insufficient data exists to accurately characterize the optimum dose and/or dose interval in patients with moderate degrees of renal insufficiency. Patients with advanced renal insufficiency (i.e., serum creatinine more than 2.5 mg/dl) should not be treated with AHA. The risk of accumulation of toxic blood levels of AHA seems to be greater than the chances for a beneficial effect in such patients. In children an initial dose of 10 mg/kg/day is recommended. Close monitoring of the patient’s clinical condition and hematologic status is recommended. Titration of the dose to higher or lower levels may be required to obtain an optimum therapeutic effect and/or to reduce the risk of side effects.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
AHA has been used concomitantly with insulin, oral and parenteral antibiotics, and progestational agents. No clinically significant interactions have been noted, but until wider clinical experience is obtained, AHA should be used with caution in patients receiving other therapeutic agents. AHA taken in association with alcoholic beverages has resulted in a rash. (See Adverse Reactions.) AHA chelates heavy metals-notably iron. The absorption of iron and AHA from the intestinal lumen may be reduced when both drugs are taken concomitantly. When iron administration is indicated, intramuscular iron is probably the product of choice.</Section>
<Section name="PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="42232-9">
Hematologic Effects: Bone marrow depression (leukopenia, anemia, and thrombocytopenia) has occurred in experimental animals receiving large doses of AHA, but has not been seen in man to date. AHA is a known inhibitor of DNA synthesis and also chelates metals - notably iron. Its bone marrow suppressant effect is probably related to its ability to inhibit DNA synthesis, but anemia could also be related to depletion of iron stores. To date, the only clinical effect noted has been hemolysis, with a decrease in the circulating red blood cells, hemoglobin and hematocrit. Abnormalities in platelet or white blood cell count have not been noted. However, clinical monitoring of the platelet and white cell count is recommended. Monitoring Liver Function: Abnormalities of liver function have not been reported to date. However, a chloro-benzene derivative of acetohydroxamic acid caused significant liver dysfunction in an unrelated study. Therefore, close monitoring of liver function is recommended. (See Carcinogenesis for discussion of possible hepatic carcinogenesis.) Use In Patients With Renal Impairment: Since AHA is eliminated primarily by the kidneys, patients with significantly impaired renal function should be closely monitored, and a reduction of daily dose may be needed to avoid excessive drug accumulation. (See Dosage and Administration.)</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS SECTION" id="34071-1">
A Coombs negative hemolytic anemia has occurred in patients receiving AHA. Gastrointestinal upset characterized by nausea, vomiting, anorexia and generalized malaise have accompanied the most severe forms of hemolytic anemia. Approximately 15% of patients receiving AHA have had only laboratory findings of an anemia. However, most patients developed a mild reticulocytosis. The untoward reactions have reverted to normal following cessation of treatment. A complete blood count, including a reticulocyte count, is recommended after two weeks of treatment. If the reticulocyte count exceeds 6%, a reduced dosage should be entertained. A CBC and reticulocyte count are recommended at 3-month intervals for the duration of treatment.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
AHA reversibly inhibits the bacterial enzyme urease, thereby inhibiting the hydrolysis of urea and production of ammonia in urine infected with urea-splitting organisms. The reduced ammonia levels and decreased pH enhance the effectiveness of antimicrobial agents and allow an increased cure rate of these infections. AHA is well absorbed from the gastrointestinal tract after oral administration; peak blood levels occur from 0.25 to 1 hour after dosing. The compound is distributed throughout body water, and there is no known binding to any tissue. AHA chelates with dietary iron within the gut. This reaction may interfere with absorption of AHA and with iron. Concomitant hypochromic anemia should be treated with intramuscular iron. In rodents, the metabolic fate of AHA is well known; 55% is excreted unchanged in urine, 25% is excreted as acetamide or acetate and 7% is excreted by the lungs as carbon dioxide. Less than 1% is excreted in the feces. Approximately 5% of the administered dose is unaccounted for. In rodents, AHA shows a dose-related change in pharmacokinetics; with increasing dose, there is an increase in the half-life and an increase in the percent of the administered dose recovered in urine as unchanged AHA. Pharmacokinetics in man are generally similar to rodents including the dose-related increase in half-life, but they are not as well characterized as in the rodent. Thirty-six to sixty-five percent (36-65%) of the oral dosage is excreted unchanged in the urine. It is unaltered AHA in the urine that provides the therapeutic effect, but the precise concentration of AHA in urine that is necessary to inhibit urease is incompletely delineated. Therapeutic benefit may be obtained from concentrations as low as 8 mcg/ml; higher concentrations (i.e., 30 mcg/ml) are expected to provide more complete inhibition of urease. The plasma half-life of AHA is approximately 5-10 hours in subjects with normal renal function and is prolonged in patients with reduced renal function. Acetohydroxamic acid has been evaluated clinically in patients with urea-splitting urinary infections, often accompanied by struvite stone disease, that were recalcitrant to other forms of medical and surgical management. In these clinical trials, AHA reduced the pathologically elevated urinary ammonia and pH levels that result from the hydrolysis of urea by the enzyme, urease. AHA does not acidify urine directly nor does it have a direct antibacterial effect. The usefulness of reducing ammonia levels and decreasing urinary pH is suggested by single (not yet replicated) clinical trials in which urease inhibition 1) allowed successful antibiotic treatment of urea-splitting Proteus infections after surgical removal of struvite stones in patients not cured by 3 months of antibacterial treatment alone, and 2) reduced the rate of stone growth in patients who were not candidates for surgical removal of stones.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="1554" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Acetohydroxamic acid should not be used in: patients whose physical state and disease are amenable to definitive surgery and appropriate antimicrobial agents patients whose urine is infected by non-urease producing organisms patients whose urinary infections can be controlled by culture-specific oral antimicrobial agents patients whose renal function is poor (i.e., serum creatinine more than 2.5 mg/dl and/or creatinine clearance less than 20 ml/min) female patients who do not evidence a satisfactory method of contraception patients who are pregnant Acetohydroxamic acid may cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1555" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>AHA was teratogenic (retarded and/or clubbed rear leg at 750 mg/kg and above and exencephaly and encephalocele at 1,500 mg/kg) when given intraperitoneally to rats.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1556" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>AHA is contraindicated in women who are or may become pregnant.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1557" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>If this drug is used during pregnancy, or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking this drug, the patient should be informed of the potential hazard to the fetus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1558" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>AHA should be administered orally, one tablet 3-4 times a day in a total daily dose of 10-15 mg/kg/day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1559" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommended starting dose is 12 mg/kg/day, administered at 6-8 hour intervals at a time when the stomach is empty.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1560" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The maximum daily dose should be no more than 1.5 grams, regardless of body weight.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1561" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The dosage should be reduced in patients with reduced renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1562" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Patients whose serum creatinine is greater than 1.8 mg/dl should take no more than 1.0 gm/day; such patients should be dosed at q-12-h intervals.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1563" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Further reductions in dosage to prevent the accumulation of toxic concentrations in the blood may also be desirable.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1564" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Insufficient data exists to accurately characterize the optimum dose and/or dose interval in patients with moderate degrees of renal insufficiency.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1565" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Patients with advanced renal insufficiency (i.e., serum creatinine more than 2.5 mg/dl) should not be treated with AHA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1566" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The risk of accumulation of toxic blood levels of AHA seems to be greater than the chances for a beneficial effect in such patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1567" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In children an initial dose of 10 mg/kg/day is recommended.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1568" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Close monitoring of the patient’s clinical condition and hematologic status is recommended.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1569" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Titration of the dose to higher or lower levels may be required to obtain an optimum therapeutic effect and/or to reduce the risk of side effects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1570" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>AHA has been used concomitantly with insulin, oral and parenteral antibiotics, and progestational agents.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1571" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>No clinically significant interactions have been noted, but until wider clinical experience is obtained, AHA should be used with caution in patients receiving other therapeutic agents.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1572" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>AHA taken in association with alcoholic beverages has resulted in a rash.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M1" type="Trigger" span="54 11" str="resulted in"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="30 19" str="alcoholic beverages" code="3K9958V90M"/>
<Mention id="M3" type="SpecificInteraction" span="68 4" str="rash" code="271807003: Eruption of skin (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M1" precipitant="M2" effect="M3"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1573" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The absorption of iron and AHA from the intestinal lumen may be reduced when both drugs are taken concomitantly.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M6" type="Trigger" span="4 10;64 7" str="absorption | reduced"/>
<Mention id="M7" type="Precipitant" span="18 4" str="iron" code="E1UOL152H7"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M6" precipitant="M7" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M6" precipitant="M7" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1574" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>When iron administration is indicated, intramuscular iron is probably the product of choice.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1575" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Hematologic Effects: Bone marrow depression (leukopenia, anemia, and thrombocytopenia) has occurred in experimental animals receiving large doses of AHA, but has not been seen in man to date.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1576" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>AHA is a known inhibitor of DNA synthesis and also chelates metals - notably iron.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1577" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Its bone marrow suppressant effect is probably related to its ability to inhibit DNA synthesis, but anemia could also be related to depletion of iron stores.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1578" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>To date, the only clinical effect noted has been hemolysis, with a decrease in the circulating red blood cells, hemoglobin and hematocrit.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1579" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Abnormalities in platelet or white blood cell count have not been noted.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1580" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>However, clinical monitoring of the platelet and white cell count is recommended.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1581" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Monitoring Liver Function: Abnormalities of liver function have not been reported to date.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1582" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>However, a chloro-benzene derivative of acetohydroxamic acid caused significant liver dysfunction in an unrelated study.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1583" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Therefore, close monitoring of liver function is recommended.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1584" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Use In Patients With Renal Impairment: Since AHA is eliminated primarily by the kidneys, patients with significantly impaired renal function should be closely monitored, and a reduction of daily dose may be needed to avoid excessive drug accumulation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1585" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>A Coombs negative hemolytic anemia has occurred in patients receiving AHA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1586" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Gastrointestinal upset characterized by nausea, vomiting, anorexia and generalized malaise have accompanied the most severe forms of hemolytic anemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1587" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Approximately 15% of patients receiving AHA have had only laboratory findings of an anemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1588" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>However, most patients developed a mild reticulocytosis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1589" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The untoward reactions have reverted to normal following cessation of treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1590" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>A complete blood count, including a reticulocyte count, is recommended after two weeks of treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1591" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>If the reticulocyte count exceeds 6%, a reduced dosage should be entertained.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1592" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>A CBC and reticulocyte count are recommended at 3-month intervals for the duration of treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1593" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>AHA reversibly inhibits the bacterial enzyme urease, thereby inhibiting the hydrolysis of urea and production of ammonia in urine infected with urea-splitting organisms.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1594" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The reduced ammonia levels and decreased pH enhance the effectiveness of antimicrobial agents and allow an increased cure rate of these infections.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1595" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>AHA is well absorbed from the gastrointestinal tract after oral administration; peak blood levels occur from 0.25 to 1 hour after dosing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1596" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The compound is distributed throughout body water, and there is no known binding to any tissue.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1597" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>AHA chelates with dietary iron within the gut.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1598" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This reaction may interfere with absorption of AHA and with iron.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M10" type="Trigger" span="18 25" str="interfere with absorption"/>
<Mention id="M11" type="Precipitant" span="60 4" str="iron" code="E1UOL152H7"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M10" precipitant="M11" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M10" precipitant="M11" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1599" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Concomitant hypochromic anemia should be treated with intramuscular iron.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1600" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In rodents, the metabolic fate of AHA is well known; 55% is excreted unchanged in urine, 25% is excreted as acetamide or acetate and 7% is excreted by the lungs as carbon dioxide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1601" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Approximately 5% of the administered dose is unaccounted for.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1602" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In rodents, AHA shows a dose-related change in pharmacokinetics; with increasing dose, there is an increase in the half-life and an increase in the percent of the administered dose recovered in urine as unchanged AHA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1603" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Pharmacokinetics in man are generally similar to rodents including the dose-related increase in half-life, but they are not as well characterized as in the rodent.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1604" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Thirty-six to sixty-five percent (36-65%) of the oral dosage is excreted unchanged in the urine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1605" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>It is unaltered AHA in the urine that provides the therapeutic effect, but the precise concentration of AHA in urine that is necessary to inhibit urease is incompletely delineated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1606" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Therapeutic benefit may be obtained from concentrations as low as 8 mcg/ml; higher concentrations (i.e., 30 mcg/ml) are expected to provide more complete inhibition of urease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1607" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The plasma half-life of AHA is approximately 5-10 hours in subjects with normal renal function and is prolonged in patients with reduced renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1608" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Acetohydroxamic acid has been evaluated clinically in patients with urea-splitting urinary infections, often accompanied by struvite stone disease, that were recalcitrant to other forms of medical and surgical management.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1609" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In these clinical trials, AHA reduced the pathologically elevated urinary ammonia and pH levels that result from the hydrolysis of urea by the enzyme, urease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1610" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>AHA does not acidify urine directly nor does it have a direct antibacterial effect.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1611" LabelDrug="Lithostat" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The usefulness of reducing ammonia levels and decreasing urinary pH is suggested by single (not yet replicated) clinical trials in which urease inhibition 1) allowed successful antibiotic treatment of urea-splitting Proteus infections after surgical removal of struvite stones in patients not cured by 3 months of antibacterial treatment alone, and 2) reduced the rate of stone growth in patients who were not candidates for surgical removal of stones.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="alcoholic beverages" precipitantCode="3K9958V90M" effect="271807003: Eruption of skin (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="iron" precipitantCode="E1UOL152H7" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="iron" precipitantCode="E1UOL152H7" effect="C54358"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>