<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Losartan Potassium" setid="46c2cb4b-eb65-45f5-891f-5e574adc962d">
<Text><Section name="Boxed Warning section" id="34066-1">
When used in pregnancy during the second and third trimesters, drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause injury and even death to the developing fetus. When pregnancy is detected, losartan potassium tablets should be discontinued as soon as possible. See WARNINGS, Fetal/Neonatal Morbidity and Mortality.</Section>
<Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
Losartan potassium tablets are contraindicated in patients who are hypersensitive to any component of this product.</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
Losartan potassium tablets may be administered with other antihypertensive agents, and with or without food. Dosing must be individualized. The usual starting dose of losartan potassium tablets is 50 mg once daily, with 25 mg used in patients with possible depletion of intravascular volume (e.g., patients treated with diuretics) (see WARNINGS, Hypotension — Volume-Depleted Patients) and patients with a history of hepatic impairment (see PRECAUTIONS, General). Losartan potassium tablets can be administered once or twice daily with total daily doses ranging from 25 mg to 100 mg. If the antihypertensive effect measured at trough using once-a-day dosing is inadequate, a twice-a-day regimen at the same total daily dose or an increase in dose may give a more satisfactory response. The effect of losartan is substantially present within one week but in some studies the maximal effect occurred in 3-6 weeks (see CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY, Pharmacodynamics and Clinical Effects, Hypertension). If blood pressure is not controlled by losartan potassium tablets alone, a low dose of a diuretic may be added. Hydrochlorothiazide has been shown to have an additive effect (see CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY, Pharmacodynamics and Clinical Effects, Hypertension). No initial dosage adjustment is necessary for elderly patients or for patients with renal impairment, including patients on dialysis.          The usual recommended starting dose is 0.7 mg/kg once daily (up to 50 mg total) administered as a tablet or a suspension (see Preparation of Suspension). Dosage should be adjusted according to blood pressure response. Doses above 1.4 mg/kg (or in excess of 100 mg) daily have not been studied in pediatric patients. (See CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY, Pharmacokinetics, Special Populations and Pharmacodynamics and Clinical Effects, and WARNINGS, Hypotension — Volume-Depleted Patients.) Losartan potassium tablets are not recommended in pediatric patients &amp;lt;6 years of age or in pediatric patients with glomerular filtration rate &amp;lt;30 mL/min/1.73 m2 (see CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY, Pharmacokinetics, Special Populations, Pharmacodynamics and Clinical Effects, and PRECAUTIONS).          Add 10 mL of Purified Water USP to an 8 ounce (240 mL) amber polyethylene terephthalate (PET) bottle containing ten 50 mg losartan potassium tablets. Immediately shake for at least 2 minutes. Let the concentrate stand for 1 hour and then shake for 1 minute to disperse the tablet contents. Separately prepare a 50/50 volumetric mixture of Ora-Plus™ Trademark of Paddock Laboratories, Inc.  and Ora-Sweet SF™. Add 190 mL of the 50/50 Ora-Plus™/Ora-Sweet SF™ mixture to the tablet and water slurry in the PET bottle and shake for 1 minute to disperse the ingredients. The suspension should be refrigerated at 2-8°C (36-46°F) and can be stored for up to 4 weeks. Shake the suspension prior to each use and return promptly to the refrigerator.          The usual starting dose is 50 mg of losartan potassium tablets once daily. Hydrochlorothiazide 12.5 mg daily should be added and/or the dose of losartan potassium tablets should be increased to 100 mg once daily followed by an increase in hydrochlorothiazide to 25 mg once daily based on blood pressure response (see CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY, Pharmacodynamics and Clinical Effects, Reduction in the Risk of Stroke).          The usual starting dose is 50 mg once daily. The dose should be increased to 100 mg once daily based on blood pressure response (see CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY, Pharmacodynamics and Clinical Effects, Nephropathy in Type 2 Diabetic Patients). Losartan potassium tablets may be administered with insulin and other commonly used hypoglycemic agents (e.g., sulfonylureas, glitazones and glucosidase inhibitors).</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
Losartan, administered for 12 days, did not affect the pharmacokinetics or pharmacodynamics of a single dose of warfarin. Losartan did not affect the pharmacokinetics of oral or intravenous digoxin. There is no pharmacokinetic interaction between losartan and hydrochlorothiazide. Coadministration of losartan and cimetidine led to an increase of about 18% in AUC of losartan but did not affect the pharmacokinetics of its active metabolite. Coadministration of losartan and phenobarbital led to a reduction of about 20% in the AUC of losartan and that of its active metabolite. A somewhat greater interaction (approximately 40% reduction in the AUC of active metabolite and approximately 30% reduction in the AUC of losartan) has been reported with rifampin. Fluconazole, an inhibitor of cytochrome P450 2C9, decreased the AUC of the active metabolite by approximately 40%, but increased the AUC of losartan by approximately 70% following multiple doses. Conversion of losartan to its active metabolite after intravenous administration is not affected by ketoconazole, an inhibitor of P450 3A4. The AUC of active metabolite following oral losartan was not affected by erythromycin, another inhibitor of P450 3A4, but the AUC of losartan was increased by 30%.       No significant drug-drug pharmacokinetic interactions have been found in interaction studies with hydrochlorothiazide, digoxin, warfarin, cimetidine and phenobarbital. Rifampin, an inducer of drug metabolism, decreased the concentrations of losartan and its active metabolite. (See CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY, Drug Interactions.) In humans, two inhibitors of P450 3A4 have been studied. Ketoconazole did not affect the conversion of losartan to the active metabolite after intravenous administration of losartan, and erythromycin had no clinically significant effect after oral administration. Fluconazole, an inhibitor of P450 2C9, decreased active metabolite concentration and increased losartan concentration. The pharmacodynamic consequences of concomitant use of losartan and inhibitors of P450 2C9 have not been examined. Subjects who do not metabolize losartan to active metabolite have been shown to have a specific, rare defect in cytochrome P450 2C9. These data suggest that the conversion of losartan to its active metabolite is mediated primarily by P450 2C9 and not P450 3A4. As with other drugs that block angiotensin II or its effects, concomitant use of potassium-sparing diuretics (e.g., spironolactone, triamterene, amiloride), potassium supplements, or salt substitutes containing potassium may lead to increases in serum potassium.  Lithium: As with other drugs which affect the excretion of sodium, lithium excretion may be reduced. Therefore, serum lithium levels should be monitored carefully if lithium salts are to be co-administered with angiotensin II receptor antagonists.   Non-Steroidal Anti-Inflammatory Drugs (NSAIDs) Including Selective Cyclooxygenase-2 Inhibitors (COX-2 Inhibitors): In patients who are elderly, volume-depleted (including those on diuretic therapy), or with compromised renal function, co-administration of NSAIDs, including selective COX-2 inhibitors, with angiotensin II receptor antagonists (including losartan) may result in deterioration of renal function, including possible acute renal failure. These effects are usually reversible. Monitor renal function periodically in patients receiving losartan and NSAID therapy. The antihypertensive effect of angiotensin II receptor antagonists, including losartan, may be attenuated by NSAIDs, including selective COX-2 inhibitors.</Section>
<Section name="PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="42232-9">
Hypersensitivity: Angioedema. See ADVERSE REACTIONS, Post-Marketing Experience.          Based on pharmacokinetic data which demonstrate significantly increased plasma concentrations of losartan in cirrhotic patients, a lower dose should be considered for patients with impaired liver function (see DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION and CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY, Pharmacokinetics).          As a consequence of inhibiting the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system, changes in renal function have been reported in susceptible individuals treated with losartan potassium tablets; in some patients, these changes in renal function were reversible upon discontinuation of therapy. In patients whose renal function may depend on the activity of the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system (e.g., patients with severe congestive heart failure), treatment with angiotensin converting enzyme inhibitors has been associated with oliguria and/or progressive azotemia and (rarely) with acute renal failure and/or death. Similar outcomes have been reported with losartan potassium tablets. In studies of ACE inhibitors in patients with unilateral or bilateral renal artery stenosis, increases in serum creatinine or blood urea nitrogen (BUN) have been reported. Similar effects have been reported with losartan potassium tablets; in some patients, these effects were reversible upon discontinuation of therapy.          Electrolyte imbalances are common in patients with renal impairment, with or without diabetes, and should be addressed. In a clinical study conducted in type 2 diabetic patients with proteinuria, the incidence of hyperkalemia was higher in the group treated with losartan potassium tablets as compared to the placebo group; however, few patients discontinued therapy due to hyperkalemia (see ADVERSE REACTIONS).           Pregnancy: Female patients of childbearing age should be told about the consequences of second- and third-trimester exposure to drugs that act on the renin-angiotensin system, and they should also be told that these consequences do not appear to have resulted from intrauterine drug exposure that has been limited to the first trimester. These patients should be asked to report pregnancies to their physicians as soon as possible.  Potassium Supplements: A patient receiving losartan potassium tablets should be told not to use potassium supplements or salt substitutes containing potassium without consulting the prescribing physician (see PRECAUTIONS, Drug Interactions).          No significant drug-drug pharmacokinetic interactions have been found in interaction studies with hydrochlorothiazide, digoxin, warfarin, cimetidine and phenobarbital. Rifampin, an inducer of drug metabolism, decreased the concentrations of losartan and its active metabolite. (See CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY, Drug Interactions.) In humans, two inhibitors of P450 3A4 have been studied. Ketoconazole did not affect the conversion of losartan to the active metabolite after intravenous administration of losartan, and erythromycin had no clinically significant effect after oral administration. Fluconazole, an inhibitor of P450 2C9, decreased active metabolite concentration and increased losartan concentration. The pharmacodynamic consequences of concomitant use of losartan and inhibitors of P450 2C9 have not been examined. Subjects who do not metabolize losartan to active metabolite have been shown to have a specific, rare defect in cytochrome P450 2C9. These data suggest that the conversion of losartan to its active metabolite is mediated primarily by P450 2C9 and not P450 3A4. As with other drugs that block angiotensin II or its effects, concomitant use of potassium-sparing diuretics (e.g., spironolactone, triamterene, amiloride), potassium supplements, or salt substitutes containing potassium may lead to increases in serum potassium.  Lithium: As with other drugs which affect the excretion of sodium, lithium excretion may be reduced. Therefore, serum lithium levels should be monitored carefully if lithium salts are to be co-administered with angiotensin II receptor antagonists.   Non-Steroidal Anti-Inflammatory Drugs (NSAIDs) Including Selective Cyclooxygenase-2 Inhibitors (COX-2 Inhibitors): In patients who are elderly, volume-depleted (including those on diuretic therapy), or with compromised renal function, co-administration of NSAIDs, including selective COX-2 inhibitors, with angiotensin II receptor antagonists (including losartan) may result in deterioration of renal function, including possible acute renal failure. These effects are usually reversible. Monitor renal function periodically in patients receiving losartan and NSAID therapy. The antihypertensive effect of angiotensin II receptor antagonists, including losartan, may be attenuated by NSAIDs, including selective COX-2 inhibitors.          Losartan potassium was not carcinogenic when administered at maximally tolerated dosages to rats and mice for 105 and 92 weeks, respectively. Female rats given the highest dose (270 mg/kg/day) had a slightly higher incidence of pancreatic acinar adenoma. The maximally tolerated dosages (270 mg/kg/day in rats, 200 mg/kg/day in mice) provided systemic exposures for losartan and its pharmacologically active metabolite that were approximately 160- and 90-times (rats) and 30- and 15-times (mice) the exposure of a 50 kg human given 100 mg per day. Losartan potassium was negative in the microbial mutagenesis and V-79 mammalian cell mutagenesis assays and in the in vitro alkaline elution and in vitro and in vivo chromosomal aberration assays. In addition, the active metabolite showed no evidence of genotoxicity in the microbial mutagenesis, in vitro alkaline elution, and in vitro chromosomal aberration assays. Fertility and reproductive performance were not affected in studies with male rats given oral doses of losartan potassium up to approximately 150 mg/kg/day. The administration of toxic dosage levels in females (300/200 mg/kg/day) was associated with a significant (p&amp;lt;0.05) decrease in the number of corpora lutea/female, implants/female, and live fetuses/female at C-section. At 100 mg/kg/day only a decrease in the number of corpora lutea/female was observed. The relationship of these findings to drug-treatment is uncertain since there was no effect at these dosage levels on implants/pregnant female, percent post-implantation loss, or live animals/litter at parturition. In nonpregnant rats dosed at 135 mg/kg/day for 7 days, systemic exposure (AUCs) for losartan and its active metabolite were approximately 66 and 26 times the exposure achieved in man at the maximum recommended human daily dosage (100 mg).          Pregnancy Categories C (first trimester) and D (second and third trimesters). See WARNINGS, Fetal/Neonatal Morbidity and Mortality.          It is not known whether losartan is excreted in human milk, but significant levels of losartan and its active metabolite were shown to be present in rat milk. Because of the potential for adverse effects on the nursing infant, a decision should be made whether to discontinue nursing or discontinue the drug, taking into account the importance of the drug to the mother.          Antihypertensive effects of losartan potassium tablets have been established in hypertensive pediatric patients aged 6 to 16 years. There are no data on the effect of losartan potassium tablets on blood pressure in pediatric patients under the age of 6 or in pediatric patients with glomerular filtration rate &amp;lt;30 mL/min/1.73 m2 (see CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY, Pharmacokinetics, Special Populations and Pharmacodynamics and Clinical Effects, and DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION).          Of the total number of patients receiving losartan potassium tablets in controlled clinical studies for hypertension, 391 patients (19%) were 65 years and over, while 37 patients (2%) were 75 years and over. In a controlled clinical study for renal protection in type 2 diabetic patients with proteinuria, 248 patients (33%) were 65 years and over. In a controlled clinical study for the reduction in the combined risk of cardiovascular death, stroke and myocardial infarction in hypertensive patients with left ventricular hypertrophy, 2857 patients (62%) were 65 years and over, while 808 patients (18%) were 75 years and over. No overall differences in effectiveness or safety were observed between these patients and younger patients, but greater sensitivity of some older individuals cannot be ruled out.          In the LIFE study, Black patients with hypertension and left ventricular hypertrophy had a lower risk of stroke on atenolol than on losartan potassium tablets. Given the difficulty in interpreting subset differences in large trials, it cannot be known whether the observed difference is the result of chance. However, the LIFE study does not provide evidence that the benefits of losartan potassium tablets on reducing the risk of cardiovascular events in hypertensive patients with left ventricular hypertrophy apply to Black patients. (See CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY, Pharmacodynamics and Clinical Effects; Reduction in the Risk of Stroke.)</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS SECTION" id="34071-1">
Drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause fetal and neonatal morbidity and death when administered to pregnant women. Several dozen cases have been reported in the world literature in patients who were taking angiotensin converting enzyme inhibitors. When pregnancy is detected, losartan potassium tablets should be discontinued as soon as possible. The use of drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system during the second and third trimesters of pregnancy has been associated with fetal and neonatal injury, including hypotension, neonatal skull hypoplasia, anuria, reversible or irreversible renal failure, and death. Oligohydramnios has also been reported, presumably resulting from decreased fetal renal function; oligohydramnios in this setting has been associated with fetal limb contractures, craniofacial deformation, and hypoplastic lung development. Prematurity, intrauterine growth retardation, and patent ductus arteriosus have also been reported, although it is not clear whether these occurrences were due to exposure to the drug. These adverse effects do not appear to have resulted from intrauterine drug exposure that has been limited to the first trimester. Mothers whose embryos and fetuses are exposed to an angiotensin II receptor antagonist only during the first trimester should be so informed. Nonetheless, when patients become pregnant, physicians should have the patient discontinue the use of losartan potassium tablets as soon as possible. Rarely (probably less often than once in every thousand pregnancies), no alternative to an angiotensin II receptor antagonist will be found. In these rare cases, the mothers should be apprised of the potential hazards to their fetuses, and serial ultrasound examinations should be performed to assess the intra-amniotic environment. If oligohydramnios is observed, losartan potassium tablets should be discontinued unless they are considered life-saving for the mother. Contraction stress testing (CST), a non-stress test (NST), or biophysical profiling (BPP) may be appropriate, depending upon the week of pregnancy. Patients and physicians should be aware, however, that oligohydramnios may not appear until after the fetus has sustained irreversible injury. Infants with histories of in utero exposure to an angiotensin II receptor antagonist should be closely observed for hypotension, oliguria, and hyperkalemia. If oliguria occurs, attention should be directed toward support of blood pressure and renal perfusion. Exchange transfusion or dialysis may be required as means of reversing hypotension and/or substituting for disordered renal function. Losartan potassium tablets have been shown to produce adverse effects in rat fetuses and neonates, including decreased body weight, delayed physical and behavioral development, mortality and renal toxicity. With the exception of neonatal weight gain (which was affected at doses as low as 10 mg/kg/day), doses associated with these effects exceeded 25 mg/kg/day (approximately three times the maximum recommended human dose of 100 mg on a mg/m2 basis). These findings are attributed to drug exposure in late gestation and during lactation. Significant levels of losartan and its active metabolite were shown to be present in rat fetal plasma during late gestation and in rat milk.          In patients who are intravascularly volume-depleted (e.g., those treated with diuretics), symptomatic hypotension may occur after initiation of therapy with losartan potassium tablets. These conditions should be corrected prior to administration of losartan potassium tablets, or a lower starting dose should be used (see DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION).</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Angiotensin II [formed from angiotensin I in a reaction catalyzed by angiotensin converting enzyme (ACE, kininase II)], is a potent vasoconstrictor, the primary vasoactive hormone of the renin-angiotensin system and an important component in the pathophysiology of hypertension. It also stimulates aldosterone secretion by the adrenal cortex. Losartan and its principal active metabolite block the vasoconstrictor and aldosterone-secreting effects of angiotensin II by selectively blocking the binding of angiotensin II to the AT1 receptor found in many tissues, (e.g., vascular smooth muscle, adrenal gland). There is also an AT2 receptor found in many tissues but it is not known to be associated with cardiovascular homeostasis. Both losartan and its principal active metabolite do not exhibit any partial agonist activity at the AT1 receptor and have much greater affinity (about 1000-fold) for the AT1 receptor than for the AT2 receptor. In vitro binding studies indicate that losartan is a reversible, competitive inhibitor of the AT1 receptor. The active metabolite is 10 to 40 times more potent by weight than losartan and appears to be a reversible, non-competitive inhibitor of the AT1 receptor. Neither losartan nor its active metabolite inhibits ACE (kininase II, the enzyme that converts angiotensin I to angiotensin II and degrades bradykinin); nor do they bind to or block other hormone receptors or ion channels known to be important in cardiovascular regulation.               Losartan is an orally active agent that undergoes substantial first-pass metabolism by cytochrome P450 enzymes. It is converted, in part, to an active carboxylic acid metabolite that is responsible for most of the angiotensin II receptor antagonism that follows losartan treatment. Losartan metabolites have been identified in human plasma and urine. In addition to the active carboxylic acid metabolite, several inactive metabolites are formed. Following oral and intravenous administration of 14C-labeled losartan potassium, circulating plasma radioactivity is primarily attributed to losartan and its active metabolite. In vitro studies indicate that cytochrome P450 2C9 and 3A4 are involved in the biotransformation of losartan to its metabolites. Minimal conversion of losartan to the active metabolite (less than 1% of the dose compared to 14% of the dose in normal subjects) was seen in about one percent of individuals studied. The terminal half-life of losartan is about 2 hours and of the metabolite is about 6-9 hours.  The pharmacokinetics of losartan and its active metabolite are linear with oral losartan doses up to 200 mg and do not change over time. Neither losartan nor its metabolite accumulate in plasma upon repeated once-daily dosing. Following oral administration, losartan is well absorbed (based on absorption of radiolabeled losartan) and undergoes substantial first-pass metabolism; the systemic bioavailability of losartan is approximately 33%. About 14% of an orally-administered dose of losartan is converted to the active metabolite. Mean peak concentrations of losartan and its active metabolite are reached in 1 hour and in 3-4 hours, respectively. While maximum plasma concentrations of losartan and its active metabolite are approximately equal, the AUC of the metabolite is about 4 times as great as that of losartan. A meal slows absorption of losartan and decreases its Cmax but has only minor effects on losartan AUC or on the AUC of the metabolite (about 10% decreased). The pharmacokinetics of losartan and its active metabolite were also determined after IV doses of each component separately in healthy volunteers. The volume of distribution of losartan and the active metabolite is about 34 liters and 12 liters, respectively. Total plasma clearance of losartan and the active metabolite is about 600 mL/min and 50 mL/min, respectively, with renal clearance of about 75 mL/min and 25 mL/min, respectively. After single doses of losartan administered orally, about 4% of the dose is excreted unchanged in the urine and about 6% is excreted in urine as active metabolite. Biliary excretion contributes to the elimination of losartan and its metabolites. Following oral 14C-labeled losartan, about 35% of radioactivity is recovered in the urine and about 60% in the feces. Following an intravenous dose of 14C-labeled losartan, about 45% of radioactivity is recovered in the urine and 50% in the feces. Both losartan and its active metabolite are highly bound to plasma proteins, primarily albumin, with plasma free fractions of 1.3% and 0.2%, respectively. Plasma protein binding is constant over the concentration range achieved with recommended doses. Studies in rats indicate that losartan crosses the blood-brain barrier poorly, if at all.           Pediatric: Pharmacokinetic parameters after multiple doses of losartan (average dose 0.7 mg/kg, range 0.36 to 0.97 mg/kg) as a tablet to 25 hypertensive patients aged 6 to 16 years are shown in Table 1 below. Pharmacokinetics of losartan and its active metabolite were generally similar across the studied age groups and similar to historical pharmacokinetic data in adults. The principal pharmacokinetic parameters in adults and children are shown in the table below.  Table 1: Pharmacokinetic Parameters in Hypertensive Adults and Children Age 6-16 Following Multiple Dosing         Adults given 50 mg once daily for 7 daysN=12 Age 6-16 given 0.7 mg/kg once daily for 7 daysN=25      Parent Active Metabolite Parent Active Metabolite   AUC0-24 Mean ± standard deviation(ng•h/mL) 442 ± 173 1685 ± 452 368 ± 169 1866 ± 1076   CMAX (ng/mL)  224 ± 82 212 ± 73 141 ± 88 222 ± 127   T1/2 (h)Harmonic mean and standard deviation  2.1 ± 0.70 7.4 ± 2.4 2.3 ± 0.8 5.6 ± 1.2   TPEAK (h)Median  0.9 3.5 2.0 4.1   CLREN (mL/min)  56 ± 23 20 ± 3 53 ± 33 17 ± 8    The bioavailability of the suspension formulation was compared with losartan tablets in healthy adults. The suspension and tablet are similar in their bioavailability with respect to both losartan and the active metabolite (see DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION, Preparation of Suspension).  Geriatric and Gender: Losartan pharmacokinetics have been investigated in the elderly (65-75 years) and in both genders. Plasma concentrations of losartan and its active metabolite are similar in elderly and young hypertensives. Plasma concentrations of losartan were about twice as high in female hypertensives as male hypertensives, but concentrations of the active metabolite were similar in males and females. No dosage adjustment is necessary (see DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION).  Race: Pharmacokinetic differences due to race have not been studied (see also PRECAUTIONS, Race and  CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY, Pharmacodynamics and Clinical Effects, Reduction in the Risk of Stroke, Race).  Renal Insufficiency: Following oral administration, plasma concentrations and AUCs of losartan and its active metabolite are increased by 50-90% in patients with mild (creatinine clearance of 50 to 74 mL/min) or moderate (creatinine clearance 30 to 49 mL/min) renal insufficiency. In this study, renal clearance was reduced by 55-85% for both losartan and its active metabolite in patients with mild or moderate renal insufficiency. Neither losartan nor its active metabolite can be removed by hemodialysis. No dosage adjustment is necessary for patients with renal impairment unless they are volume-depleted (see WARNINGS, Hypotension — Volume-Depleted Patients and DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION).  Hepatic Insufficiency: Following oral administration in patients with mild to moderate alcoholic cirrhosis of the liver, plasma concentrations of losartan and its active metabolite were, respectively, 5-times and about 1.7-times those in young male volunteers. Compared to normal subjects the total plasma clearance of losartan in patients with hepatic insufficiency was about 50% lower and the oral bioavailability was about 2-times higher. A lower starting dose is recommended for patients with a history of hepatic impairment (see DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION).            Losartan, administered for 12 days, did not affect the pharmacokinetics or pharmacodynamics of a single dose of warfarin. Losartan did not affect the pharmacokinetics of oral or intravenous digoxin. There is no pharmacokinetic interaction between losartan and hydrochlorothiazide. Coadministration of losartan and cimetidine led to an increase of about 18% in AUC of losartan but did not affect the pharmacokinetics of its active metabolite. Coadministration of losartan and phenobarbital led to a reduction of about 20% in the AUC of losartan and that of its active metabolite. A somewhat greater interaction (approximately 40% reduction in the AUC of active metabolite and approximately 30% reduction in the AUC of losartan) has been reported with rifampin. Fluconazole, an inhibitor of cytochrome P450 2C9, decreased the AUC of the active metabolite by approximately 40%, but increased the AUC of losartan by approximately 70% following multiple doses. Conversion of losartan to its active metabolite after intravenous administration is not affected by ketoconazole, an inhibitor of P450 3A4. The AUC of active metabolite following oral losartan was not affected by erythromycin, another inhibitor of P450 3A4, but the AUC of losartan was increased by 30%.               Losartan inhibits the pressor effect of angiotensin II (as well as angiotensin I) infusions. A dose of 100 mg inhibits the pressor effect by about 85% at peak with 25-40% inhibition persisting for 24 hours. Removal of the negative feedback of angiotensin II causes a 2- to 3-fold rise in plasma renin activity and consequent rise in angiotensin II plasma concentration in hypertensive patients. Losartan does not affect the response to bradykinin, whereas ACE inhibitors increase the response to bradykinin. Aldosterone plasma concentrations fall following losartan administration. In spite of the effect of losartan on aldosterone secretion, very little effect on serum potassium was observed. In a single-dose study in normal volunteers, losartan had no effects on glomerular filtration rate, renal plasma flow or filtration fraction. In multiple-dose studies in hypertensive patients, there were no notable effects on systemic or renal prostaglandin concentrations, fasting triglycerides, total cholesterol or HDL-cholesterol or fasting glucose concentrations. There was a small uricosuric effect leading to a minimal decrease in serum uric acid (mean decrease &amp;lt;0.4 mg/dL) during chronic oral administration. The antihypertensive effects of losartan potassium tablets were demonstrated principally in 4 placebo-controlled, 6- to 12-week trials of dosages from 10 to 150 mg per day in patients with baseline diastolic blood pressures of 95-115. The studies allowed comparisons of two doses (50-100 mg/day) as once-daily or twice-daily regimens, comparisons of peak and trough effects, and comparisons of response by gender, age, and race. Three additional studies examined the antihypertensive effects of losartan and hydrochlorothiazide in combination. The 4 studies of losartan monotherapy included a total of 1075 patients randomized to several doses of losartan and 334 to placebo. The 10- and 25-mg doses produced some effect at peak (6 hours after dosing) but small and inconsistent trough (24 hour) responses. Doses of 50, 100 and 150 mg once daily gave statistically significant systolic/diastolic mean decreases in blood pressure, compared to placebo in the range of 5.5-10.5/3.5-7.5 mmHg, with the 150-mg dose giving no greater effect than 50-100 mg. Twice-daily dosing at 50-100 mg/day gave consistently larger trough responses than once-daily dosing at the same total dose. Peak (6 hour) effects were uniformly, but moderately, larger than trough effects, with the trough-to-peak ratio for systolic and diastolic responses 50-95% and 60-90%, respectively. Addition of a low dose of hydrochlorothiazide (12.5 mg) to losartan 50 mg once daily resulted in placebo-adjusted blood pressure reductions of 15.5/9.2 mmHg. Analysis of age, gender, and race subgroups of patients showed that men and women, and patients over and under 65, had generally similar responses. Losartan potassium tablets were effective in reducing blood pressure regardless of race, although the effect was somewhat less in Black patients (usually a low-renin population). The effect of losartan is substantially present within one week but in some studies the maximal effect occurred in 3-6 weeks. In long-term follow-up studies (without placebo control) the effect of losartan appeared to be maintained for up to a year. There is no apparent rebound effect after abrupt withdrawal of losartan. There was essentially no change in average heart rate in losartan-treated patients in controlled trials.          The antihypertensive effect of losartan was studied in one trial enrolling 177 hypertensive pediatric patients aged 6 to 16 years old. Children who weighed &amp;lt;50 kg received 2.5, 25 or 50 mg of losartan daily and patients who weighed ≥50 kg received 5, 50 or 100 mg of losartan daily. Children in the lowest dose group were given losartan in a suspension formulation (see DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION, Preparation of Suspension). The majority of the children had hypertension associated with renal and urogenital disease. The sitting diastolic blood pressure (SiDBP) on entry into the study was higher than the 95th percentile level for the patient’s age, gender, and height. At the end of three weeks, losartan reduced systolic and diastolic blood pressure, measured at trough, in a dose-dependent manner. Overall, the two higher doses (25 to 50 mg in patients &amp;lt;50 kg; 50 to 100 mg in patients ≥50 kg) reduced diastolic blood pressure by 5 to 6 mmHg more than the lowest dose used (2.5 mg in patients &amp;lt;50 kg; 5 mg in patients ≥50 kg). The lowest dose, corresponding to an average daily dose of 0.07 mg/kg, did not appear to offer consistent antihypertensive efficacy. When patients were randomized to continue losartan at the two higher doses or to placebo after 3 weeks of therapy, trough diastolic blood pressure rose in patients on placebo between 5 and 7 mmHg more than patients randomized to continuing losartan. When the low dose of losartan was randomly withdrawn, the rise in trough diastolic blood pressure was the same in patients receiving placebo and in those continuing losartan, again suggesting that the lowest dose did not have significant antihypertensive efficacy. Overall, no significant differences in the overall antihypertensive effect of losartan were detected when the patients were analyzed according to age (&amp;lt;, ≥12 years old) or gender. While blood pressure was reduced in all racial subgroups examined, too few non-White patients were enrolled to compare the dose-response of losartan in the non-White subgroup.          The Losartan Intervention For Endpoint reduction in hypertension (LIFE) study was a multinational, double-blind study comparing losartan potassium tablets and atenolol in 9193 hypertensive patients with ECG-documented left ventricular hypertrophy. Patients with myocardial infarction or stroke within six months prior to randomization were excluded. Patients were randomized to receive once daily losartan potassium tablets 50 mg or atenolol 50 mg. If goal blood pressure (&amp;lt;140/90 mmHg) was not reached, hydrochlorothiazide (12.5 mg) was added first and, if needed, the dose of losartan potassium tablets or atenolol was then increased to 100 mg once daily. If necessary, other antihypertensive treatments (e.g., increase in dose of hydrochlorothiazide therapy to 25 mg or addition of other diuretic therapy, calcium-channel blockers, alpha-blockers, or centrally acting agents, but not ACE inhibitors, angiotensin II antagonists, or beta-blockers) were added to the treatment regimen to reach the goal blood pressure. Of the randomized patients, 4963 (54%) were female and 533 (6%) were Black. The mean age was 67 with 5704 (62%) age ≥65. At baseline, 1195 (13%) had diabetes, 1326 (14%) had isolated systolic hypertension, 1469 (16%) had coronary heart disease, and 728 (8%) had cerebrovascular disease. Baseline mean blood pressure was 174/98 mmHg in both treatment groups. The mean length of follow-up was 4.8 years. At the end of study or at the last visit before a primary endpoint, 77% of the group treated with losartan potassium tablets and 73% of the group treated with atenolol were still taking study medication. Of the patients still taking study medication, the mean doses of losartan potassium tablets and atenolol were both about 80 mg/day, and 15% were taking atenolol or losartan as monotherapy, while 77% were also receiving hydrochlorothiazide (at a mean dose of 20 mg/day in each group). Blood pressure reduction measured at trough was similar for both treatment groups but blood pressure was not measured at any other time of the day. At the end of study or at the last visit before a primary endpoint, the mean blood pressures were 144.1/81.3 mmHg for the group treated with losartan potassium tablets and 145.4/80.9 mmHg for the group treated with atenolol [the difference in systolic blood pressure (SBP) of 1.3 mmHg was significant (p&amp;lt;0.001), while the difference of 0.4 mmHg in diastolic blood pressure (DBP) was not significant (p=0.098)]. The primary endpoint was the first occurrence of cardiovascular death, nonfatal stroke, or nonfatal myocardial infarction. Patients with non-fatal events remained in the trial, so that there was also an examination of the first event of each type even if it was not the first event (e.g., a stroke following an initial myocardial infarction would be counted in the analysis of stroke). Treatment with losartan potassium tablets resulted in a 13% reduction (p=0.021) in risk of the primary endpoint compared to the atenolol group (see Figure 1 and Table 2); this difference was primarily the result of an effect on fatal and nonfatal stroke. Treatment with losartan potassium tablets reduced the risk of stroke by 25% relative to atenolol (p=0.001) (see Figure 2 and Table 2).  Figure 1. Kaplan-Meier estimates of the primary endpoint of time to cardiovascular death, nonfatal stroke, or nonfatal myocardial infarction in the groups treated with losartan potassium tablets and atenolol. The Risk Reduction is adjusted for baseline Framingham risk score and level of electrocardiographic left ventricular hypertrophy.   Figure 2. Kaplan-Meier estimates of the time to fatal/nonfatal stroke in the groups treated with losartan potassium tablets and atenolol. The Risk Reduction is adjusted for baseline Framingham risk score and level of electrocardiographic left ventricular hypertrophy.  Table 2 shows the results for the primary composite endpoint and the individual endpoints. The primary endpoint was the first occurrence of stroke, myocardial infarction or cardiovascular death, analyzed using an intention-to-treat (ITT) approach. The table shows the number of events for each component in two different ways. The Components of Primary Endpoint (as a first event) counts only the events that define the primary endpoint, while the Secondary Endpoints count all first events of a particular type, whether or not they were preceded by a different type of event.  Table 2: Incidence of Primary Endpoint Events              Losartan Atenolol Risk ReductionAdjusted for baseline Framingham risk score and level of electrocardiographic left ventricular hypertrophy  95% CI p-Value        N (%) RateRate per 1000 patient-years of follow-up  N (%) Rate              Primary Composite Endpoint  508 (11)  23.8  588 (13)  27.9  13%  2% to 23%  0.021    Components of Primary Composite Endpoint (as a first event)         Stroke (nonfatalFirst report of an event, in some cases the patient died subsequently to the event reported) 209 (5)    286 (6)                  Myocardial infarction (nonfatal) 174 (4)    168 (4)                  Cardiovascular mortality 125 (3)    134 (3)                Secondary Endpoints (any time in study)         Stroke (fatal/nonfatal) 232 (5) 10.8 309 (7) 14.5 25% 11% to 37% 0.001      Myocardial infarction (fatal/nonfatal) 198 (4) 9.2 188 (4) 8.7 -7% -13% to 12% 0.491      Cardiovascular mortality 204 (4) 9.2 234 (5) 10.6 11% -7% to 27% 0.206        Due to CHD 125 (3) 5.6 124 (3) 5.6 -3% -32% to 20% 0.839        Due to Stroke 40 (1) 1.8 62 (1) 2.8 35% 4% to 67% 0.032        OtherDeath due to heart failure, non-coronary vascular disease, pulmonary embolism, or a cardiovascular cause other than stroke or coronary heart disease  39 (1) 1.8 48 (1) 2.2 16% -28% to 45% 0.411    Although the LIFE study favored losartan potassium tablets over atenolol with respect to the primary endpoint (p=0.021), this result is from a single study and, therefore, is less compelling than the difference between losartan potassium tablets and placebo. Although not measured directly, the difference between losartan potassium tablets and placebo is compelling because there is evidence that atenolol is itself effective (vs. placebo) in reducing cardiovascular events, including stroke, in hypertensive patients. Other clinical endpoints of the LIFE study were: total mortality, hospitalization for heart failure or angina pectoris, coronary or peripheral revascularization procedures, and resuscitated cardiac arrest. There were no significant differences in the rates of these endpoints between the losartan potassium tablets and atenolol groups. For the primary endpoint and stroke, the effects of losartan potassium tablets in patient subgroups defined by age, gender, race and presence or absence of isolated systolic hypertension (ISH), diabetes, and history of cardiovascular disease (CVD) are shown in Figure 3 below. Subgroup analyses can be difficult to interpret and it is not known whether these represent true differences or chance effects.  Figure 3. Primary Endpoint Events† within Demographic Subgroups           In the LIFE study, Black patients treated with atenolol were at lower risk of experiencing the primary composite endpoint compared with Black patients treated with losartan potassium tablets. In the subgroup of Black patients (n=533; 6% of the LIFE study patients), there were 29 primary endpoints among 263 patients on atenolol (11%, 26 per 1000 patient-years) and 46 primary endpoints among 270 patients (17%, 42 per 1000 patient-years) on losartan potassium tablets. This finding could not be explained on the basis of differences in the populations other than race or on any imbalances between treatment groups. In addition, blood pressure reductions in both treatment groups were consistent between Black and non-Black patients. Given the difficulty in interpreting subset differences in large trials, it cannot be known whether the observed difference is the result of chance. However, the LIFE study provides no evidence that the benefits of losartan potassium tablets on reducing the risk of cardiovascular events in hypertensive patients with left ventricular hypertrophy apply to Black patients.          The Reduction of Endpoints in NIDDM with the Angiotensin II Receptor Antagonist Losartan (RENAAL) study was a randomized, placebo-controlled, double-blind, multicenter study conducted worldwide in 1513 patients with type 2 diabetes with nephropathy (defined as serum creatinine 1.3 to 3.0 mg/dl in females or males ≤60 kg and 1.5 to 3.0 mg/dl in males &amp;gt;60 kg and proteinuria [urinary albumin to creatinine ratio ≥300 mg/g]). Patients were randomized to receive losartan potassium tablets 50 mg once daily or placebo on a background of conventional antihypertensive therapy excluding ACE inhibitors and angiotensin II antagonists. After one month, investigators were instructed to titrate study drug to 100 mg once daily if the trough blood pressure goal (140/90 mmHg) was not achieved. Overall, 72% of patients received the 100-mg daily dose more than 50% of the time they were on study drug. Because the study was designed to achieve equal blood pressure control in both groups, other antihypertensive agents (diuretics, calcium-channel blockers, alpha- or beta-blockers, and centrally acting agents) could be added as needed in both groups. Patients were followed for a mean duration of 3.4 years. The study population was diverse with regard to race (Asian 16.7%, Black 15.2%, Hispanic 18.3%, White 48.6%). Overall, 63.2% of the patients were men, and 66.4% were under the age of 65 years. Almost all of the patients (96.6%) had a history of hypertension, and the patients entered the trial with a mean serum creatinine of 1.9 mg/dl and mean proteinuria (urinary albumin/creatinine) of 1808 mg/g at baseline. The primary endpoint of the study was the time to first occurrence of any one of the following events: doubling of serum creatinine, end-stage renal disease (ESRD) (need for dialysis or transplantation), or death. Treatment with losartan potassium tablets resulted in a 16% risk reduction in this endpoint (see Figure 4 and Table 3). Treatment with losartan potassium tablets also reduced the occurrence of sustained doubling of serum creatinine by 25% and ESRD by 29% as separate endpoints, but had no effect on overall mortality (see Table 3). The mean baseline blood pressures were 152/82 mmHg for losartan potassium tablets plus conventional antihypertensive therapy and 153/82 mmHg for placebo plus conventional antihypertensive therapy. At the end of the study, the mean blood pressures were 143/76 mmHg for the group treated with losartan potassium tablets and 146/77 mmHg for the group treated with placebo.  Figure 4. Kaplan-Meier curve for the primary composite endpoint of doubling of serum creatinine, end stage renal disease (need for dialysis or transplantation) or death.   Table 3: Incidence of Primary Endpoint Events          Incidence Risk Reduction 95% C.I. p-Value        Losartan Placebo             Primary Composite Endpoint  43.5%  47.1%  16.1%  2.3% to 27.9%  0.022    Doubling of Serum Creatinine, ESRD and Death Occurring as a First Event      Doubling of Serum Creatinine 21.6% 26.0%               ESRD 8.5% 8.5%               Death 13.4% 12.6%             Overall Incidence of Doubling of Serum Creatinine, ESRD and Death      Doubling of Serum Creatinine 21.6% 26.0% 25.3% 7.8% to 39.4% 0.006      ESRD 19.6% 25.5% 28.6% 11.5% to 42.4% 0.002      Death 21.0% 20.3% -1.7% -26.9% to 18.6% 0.884    The secondary endpoints of the study were change in proteinuria, change in the rate of progression of renal disease, and the composite of morbidity and mortality from cardiovascular causes (hospitalization for heart failure, myocardial infarction, revascularization, stroke, hospitalization for unstable angina, or cardiovascular death). Compared with placebo, losartan potassium tablets significantly reduced proteinuria by an average of 34%, an effect that was evident within 3 months of starting therapy, and significantly reduced the rate of decline in glomerular filtration rate during the study by 13%, as measured by the reciprocal of the serum creatinine concentration. There was no significant difference in the incidence of the composite endpoint of cardiovascular morbidity and mortality. The favorable effects of losartan potassium tablets were seen in patients also taking other anti-hypertensive medications (angiotensin II receptor antagonists and angiotensin converting enzyme inhibitors were not allowed), oral hypoglycemic agents and lipid-lowering agents.  For the primary endpoint and ESRD, the effects of losartan potassium tablets in patient subgroups defined by age, gender and race are shown in Table 4 below. Subgroup analyses can be difficult to interpret and it is not known whether these represent true differences or chance effects.  Table 4: Efficacy Outcomes within Demographic Subgroups             Primary Composite Endpoint ESRD      No. of Patients LosartanEvent Rate% PlaceboEvent Rate% Hazard Ratio(95% CI) LosartanEvent Rate% PlaceboEvent Rate% Hazard Ratio(95% CI)   Overall Results 1513 43.5 47.1 0.839 (0.721, 0.977) 19.6 25.5 0.714 (0.576, 0.885)   Age              &amp;lt;65 years 1005 44.1 49.0 0.784 (0.653, 0.941) 21.1 28.5 0.670 (0.521, 0.863)       ≥65 years 508 42.3 43.5 0.978 (0.749, 1.277) 16.5 19.6 0.847 (0.560, 1.281)   Gender              Female 557 47.8 54.1 0.762 (0.603, 0.962) 22.8 32.8 0.601 (0.436, 0.828)       Male 956 40.9 43.3 0.892 (0.733, 1.085) 17.5 21.5 0.809 (0.605, 1.081)   Race              Asian 252 41.9 54.8 0.655 (0.453, 0.947) 18.8 27.4 0.625 (0.367, 1.066)       Black 230 40.0 39.0 0.983 (0.647, 1.495) 17.6 21.0 0.831 (0.456, 1.516)       Hispanic 277 55.0 54.0 1.003 (0.728, 1.380) 30.0 28.5 1.024 (0.661, 1.586)       White 735 40.5 43.2 0.809 (0.645, 1.013) 16.2 23.9 0.596 (0.427, 0.831)            Image of Figure 1        Image of Figure 2        Image of Figure 3        Image of Figure 4</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="5451" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>When used in pregnancy during the second and third trimesters, drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause injury and even death to the developing fetus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5452" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>When pregnancy is detected, losartan potassium tablets should be discontinued as soon as possible.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5453" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>See WARNINGS, Fetal/Neonatal Morbidity andMortality.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5454" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Losartan potassium tablets are contraindicated in patients who are hypersensitive to any component of this product.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5455" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Losartan potassium tablets may be administered with other antihypertensive agents, and with or without food.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5456" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The usual starting dose of losartan potassium tablets is 50mg once daily, with 25mg used in patients with possible depletion of intravascular volume (e.g., patients treated with diuretics).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M3" type="SpecificInteraction" span="115 33" str="depletion of intravascular volume" code="28560003: Hypovolemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="178 9" str="diuretics" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M3" precipitant="M2" effect="M3"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5457" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Losartan potassium tablets can be administered once or twice daily with total daily doses ranging from 25mg to 100mg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5458" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If the antihypertensive effect measured at trough using once-a-day dosing is inadequate, a twice-a-day regimen at the same total daily dose or an increase in dose may give a more satisfactory response.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5459" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The effect of losartan is substantially present within one week but in some studies the maximal effect occurred in 3-6weeks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5460" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If blood pressure is not controlled by losartan potassium tablets alone, a low dose of a diuretic may be added.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5461" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Hydrochlorothiazide has been shown to have an additive effect.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5462" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>No initial dosage adjustment is necessary for elderly patients or for patients with renal impairment, including patients on dialysis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5463" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The usual recommended starting dose is 0.7mg/kg once daily (up to 50mg total) administered as a tablet or a suspension.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5464" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dosage should be adjusted according to blood pressure response.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5465" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Doses above 1.4mg/kg (or in excess of 100mg) daily have not been studied in pediatric patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5466" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Losartan potassium tablets are not recommended in pediatric patients &lt;6years of age or in pediatric patients with glomerular filtration rate &lt;30mL/min/1.73m2.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5467" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Add 10 mL of Purified Water USP to an 8ounce (240mL) amber polyethylene terephthalate (PET) bottle containing ten 50mg losartan potassium tablets.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5468" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Immediately shake for at least 2minutes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5469" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Let the concentrate stand for 1hour and then shake for 1minute to disperse the tablet contents.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5470" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Separately prepare a 50/50 volumetric mixture of Ora-Plus™ Trademark of Paddock Laboratories, Inc. and Ora-SweetSF™.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5471" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Add 190mL of the 50/50 Ora-Plus™/Ora-SweetSF™ mixture to the tablet and water slurry in the PET bottle and shake for 1minute to disperse the ingredients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5472" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The suspension should be refrigerated at 2-8°C (36-46°F) and can be stored for up to 4weeks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5473" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Shake the suspension prior to each use and return promptly to the refrigerator.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5474" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The usual starting dose is 50mg of losartan potassium tablets once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5475" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Hydrochlorothiazide 12.5mg daily should be added and/or the dose of losartan potassium tablets should be increased to 100mg once daily followed by an increase in hydrochlorothiazide to 25mg once daily based on blood pressure response.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5476" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The usual starting dose is 50mg once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5477" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The dose should be increased to 100mg once daily based on blood pressure response.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5478" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Losartan potassium tablets may be administered with insulin and other commonly used hypoglycemic agents (e.g., sulfonylureas, glitazones and glucosidase inhibitors).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5479" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Losartan, administered for 12 days, did not affect the pharmacokinetics or pharmacodynamics of a single dose of warfarin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5480" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Losartan did not affect the pharmacokinetics of oral or intravenous digoxin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5481" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>There is no pharmacokinetic interaction between losartan and hydrochlorothiazide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5482" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Coadministration of losartan and cimetidine led to an increase of about 18% in AUC of losartan but did not affect the pharmacokinetics of its active metabolite.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M4" type="Trigger" span="54 8;79 3" str="increase | AUC"/>
<Mention id="M5" type="Precipitant" span="33 10" str="cimetidine" code="80061L1WGD"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M4" precipitant="M5" effect="C54605"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5483" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Coadministration of losartan and phenobarbital led to a reduction of about 20% in the AUC of losartan and that of its active metabolite.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M6" type="Trigger" span="56 9;86 3" str="reduction | AUC"/>
<Mention id="M7" type="Precipitant" span="33 13" str="phenobarbital" code="YQE403BP4D"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M6" precipitant="M7" effect="C54609"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5484" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>A somewhat greater interaction (approximately 40% reduction in the AUC of active metabolite and approximately 30% reduction in the AUC of losartan) has been reported with rifampin.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M8" type="Trigger" span="50 9;67 3" str="reduction | AUC"/>
<Mention id="M9" type="Precipitant" span="171 8" str="rifampin" code="VJT6J7R4TR"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M8" precipitant="M9" effect="C54609"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5485" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Fluconazole, an inhibitor of cytochrome P450 2C9, decreased the AUC of the active metabolite by approximately 40%, but increased the AUC of losartan by approximately 70% following multiple doses.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M18" type="Trigger" span="119 17" str="increased the AUC"/>
<Mention id="M17" type="Precipitant" span="0 11" str="Fluconazole" code="8VZV102JFY"/>
<Mention id="M20" type="Trigger" span="50 42" str="decreased the AUC of the active metabolite"/>
<Mention id="M21" type="Precipitant" span="16 32" str="inhibitor of cytochrome P450 2C9" code="N0000185504"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M18" precipitant="M17" effect="C54605"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M18" precipitant="M17" effect="C54605"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M20" precipitant="M17" effect="C54609"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M20" precipitant="M17" effect="C54609"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M18" precipitant="M21" effect="C54605"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M20" precipitant="M21" effect="C54609"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5486" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Conversion of losartan to its active metabolite after intravenous administration is not affected by ketoconazole, an inhibitor of P4503A4.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5487" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The AUC of active metabolite following oral losartan was not affected by erythromycin, another inhibitor of P4503A4, but the AUC of losartan was increased by 30%.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M22" type="Trigger" span="4 3;145 9" str="AUC | increased"/>
<Mention id="M23" type="Precipitant" span="73 12" str="erythromycin" code="63937KV33D"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M22" precipitant="M23" effect="C54605"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5488" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>No significant drug-drug pharmacokinetic interactions have been found in interaction studies with hydrochlorothiazide, digoxin, warfarin, cimetidine and phenobarbital.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5489" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Rifampin, an inducer of drug metabolism, decreased the concentrations of losartan and its active metabolite.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M24" type="Trigger" span="41 28" str="decreased the concentrations"/>
<Mention id="M25" type="Precipitant" span="0 8" str="Rifampin" code="VJT6J7R4TR"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M24" precipitant="M25" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5490" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>In humans, two inhibitors of P4503A4 have been studied.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5491" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Ketoconazole did not affect the conversion of losartan to the active metabolite after intravenous administration of losartan, and erythromycin had no clinically significant effect after oral administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5492" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Fluconazole, an inhibitor of P450 2C9, decreased active metabolite concentration and increased losartan concentration.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M34" type="Trigger" span="85 9;67 13" str="increased | concentration"/>
<Mention id="M33" type="Precipitant" span="0 11" str="Fluconazole" code="8VZV102JFY"/>
<Mention id="M36" type="Trigger" span="39 41" str="decreased active metabolite concentration"/>
<Mention id="M37" type="Precipitant" span="16 21" str="inhibitor of P450 2C9" code="N0000185504"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M34" precipitant="M33" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M34" precipitant="M33" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M36" precipitant="M33" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M36" precipitant="M33" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M34" precipitant="M37" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M36" precipitant="M37" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5493" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The pharmacodynamic consequences of concomitant use of losartan and inhibitors of P4502C9 have not been examined.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5494" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Subjects who do not metabolize losartan to active metabolite have been shown to have a specific, rare defect in cytochrome P4502C9.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5495" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>These data suggest that the conversion of losartan to its active metabolite is mediated primarily by P4502C9 and not P4503A4.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5496" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>As with other drugs that block angiotensinII or its effects, concomitant use of potassium-sparing diuretics (e.g., spironolactone, triamterene, amiloride), potassium supplements, or salt substitutes containing potassium may lead to increases in serum potassium.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M53" type="Trigger" span="224 7" str="lead to"/>
<Mention id="M39" type="Precipitant" span="144 9" str="amiloride" code="7DZO8EB0Z3"/>
<Mention id="M55" type="SpecificInteraction" span="232 28" str="increases in serum potassium" code="166689004: Raised serum potassium level (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M42" type="Precipitant" span="156 21" str="potassium supplements" code="RWP5GA015D"/>
<Mention id="M45" type="Precipitant" span="80 27" str="potassium-sparing diuretics" code="N0000175418"/>
<Mention id="M48" type="Precipitant" span="182 37" str="salt substitutes containing potassium" code="N0000175600"/>
<Mention id="M51" type="Precipitant" span="115 14" str="spironolactone" code="27O7W4T232"/>
<Mention id="M54" type="Precipitant" span="131 11" str="triamterene" code="WS821Z52LQ"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M53" precipitant="M39" effect="M55"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M53" precipitant="M42" effect="M55"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M53" precipitant="M45" effect="M55"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M53" precipitant="M48" effect="M55"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M53" precipitant="M51" effect="M55"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M53" precipitant="M54" effect="M55"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5497" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Lithium: As with other drugs which affect the excretion of sodium, lithium excretion may be reduced.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M56" type="Trigger" span="75 24" str="excretion may be reduced"/>
<Mention id="M57" type="Precipitant" span="67 7" str="lithium" code="9FN79X2M3F"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M56" precipitant="M57" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5498" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Therefore, serum lithium levels should be monitored carefully if lithium salts are to be co-administered with angiotensin II receptor antagonists.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M58" type="Trigger" span="25 36" str="levels should be monitored carefully"/>
<Mention id="M59" type="Precipitant" span="17 7" str="lithium" code="9FN79X2M3F"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M58" precipitant="M59"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5499" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Non-Steroidal Anti-Inflammatory Drugs (NSAIDs) Including Selective Cyclooxygenase-2 Inhibitors (COX-2 Inhibitors): In patients who are elderly, volume-depleted (including those on diuretic therapy), or with compromised renal function, co-administration of NSAIDs, including selective COX-2 inhibitors, with angiotensin II receptor antagonists (including losartan) may result in deterioration of renal function, including possible acute renal failure.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M87" type="Trigger" span="368 9" str="result in"/>
<Mention id="M64" type="Precipitant" span="96 16" str="COX-2 Inhibitors" code="N0000008288"/>
<Mention id="M86" type="SpecificInteraction" span="430 19" str="acute renal failure" code="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M89" type="SpecificInteraction" span="378 31" str="deterioration of renal function" code="236423003: Renal impairment (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M70" type="Precipitant" span="0 37" str="Non-Steroidal Anti-Inflammatory Drugs" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M76" type="Precipitant" span="39 6" str="NSAIDs" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M82" type="Precipitant" span="274 26" str="selective COX-2 inhibitors" code="N0000008288"/>
<Mention id="M88" type="Precipitant" span="57 37" str="Selective Cyclooxygenase-2 Inhibitors" code="N0000008288"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M87" precipitant="M64" effect="M86"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M87" precipitant="M64" effect="M89"/>
<Interaction id="I29" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M87" precipitant="M70" effect="M89"/>
<Interaction id="I30" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M87" precipitant="M70" effect="M86"/>
<Interaction id="I31" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M87" precipitant="M76" effect="M86"/>
<Interaction id="I32" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M87" precipitant="M76" effect="M89"/>
<Interaction id="I33" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M87" precipitant="M82" effect="M86"/>
<Interaction id="I34" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M87" precipitant="M82" effect="M89"/>
<Interaction id="I35" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M87" precipitant="M88" effect="M86"/>
<Interaction id="I36" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M87" precipitant="M88" effect="M89"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5500" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor renal function periodically in patients receiving losartan and NSAID therapy.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M90" type="Trigger" span="0 7" str="Monitor"/>
<Mention id="M91" type="Precipitant" span="71 5" str="NSAID" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M92" type="SpecificInteraction" span="8 14" str="renal function" code="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I37" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M90" precipitant="M91" effect="M92"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5501" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The antihypertensive effect of angiotensin II receptor antagonists, including losartan, may be attenuated by NSAIDs, including selective COX-2 inhibitors.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M96" type="Trigger" span="21 6;95 10" str="effect | attenuated"/>
<Mention id="M94" type="Precipitant" span="109 6" str="NSAIDs" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M98" type="SpecificInteraction" span="4 23;95 10" str="antihypertensive effect | attenuated" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M97" type="Precipitant" span="127 26" str="selective COX-2 inhibitors" code="N0000008288"/>
<Interaction id="I38" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M96" precipitant="M94" effect="M98"/>
<Interaction id="I39" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M96" precipitant="M97" effect="M98"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5502" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>See ADVERSE REACTIONS, Post-Marketing Experience.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5503" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Based on pharmacokinetic data which demonstrate significantly increased plasma concentrations of losartan in cirrhotic patients, a lower dose should be considered for patients with impaired liver function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5504" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>As a consequence of inhibiting the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system, changes in renal function have been reported in susceptible individuals treated with losartan potassium tablets; in some patients, these changes in renal function were reversible upon discontinuation of therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5505" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In patients whose renal function may depend on the activity of the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system (e.g., patients with severe congestive heart failure), treatment with angiotensin converting enzyme inhibitors has been associated with oliguria and/or progressive azotemia and (rarely) with acute renal failure and/or death.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5506" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Similar outcomes have been reported with losartan potassium tablets.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5507" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In studies of ACE inhibitors in patients with unilateral or bilateral renal artery stenosis, increases in serum creatinine or blood urea nitrogen (BUN) have been reported.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5508" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Similar effects have been reported with losartan potassium tablets; in some patients, these effects were reversible upon discontinuation of therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5509" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Electrolyte imbalances are common in patients with renal impairment, with or without diabetes, and should be addressed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5510" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In a clinical study conducted in type2 diabetic patients with proteinuria, the incidence of hyperkalemia was higher in the group treated with losartan potassium tablets as compared to the placebo group; however, few patients discontinued therapy due to hyperkalemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5511" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Pregnancy: Female patients of childbearing age should be told about the consequences of second- and third-trimester exposure to drugs that act on the renin-angiotensin system, and they should also be told that these consequences do not appear to have resulted from intrauterine drug exposure that has been limited to the first trimester.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5512" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>These patients should be asked to report pregnancies to their physicians as soon as possible.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5513" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Potassium Supplements: A patient receiving losartan potassium tablets should be told not to use potassium supplements or salt substitutes containing potassium without consulting the prescribing physician.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M101" type="Trigger" span="85 10" str="not to use"/>
<Mention id="M100" type="Precipitant" span="96 21" str="potassium supplements" code="RWP5GA015D"/>
<Mention id="M102" type="Precipitant" span="121 37" str="salt substitutes containing potassium" code="N0000175600"/>
<Interaction id="I40" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M101" precipitant="M100"/>
<Interaction id="I41" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M101" precipitant="M102"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5514" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Losartan potassium was not carcinogenic when administered at maximally tolerated dosages to rats and mice for 105 and 92weeks, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5515" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Female rats given the highest dose (270mg/kg/day) had a slightly higher incidence of pancreatic acinar adenoma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5516" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The maximally tolerated dosages (270mg/kg/day in rats, 200mg/kg/day in mice) provided systemic exposures for losartan and its pharmacologically active metabolite that were approximately 160- and 90-times (rats) and 30- and 15-times (mice) the exposure of a 50kg human given 100mg per day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5517" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Losartan potassium was negative in the microbial mutagenesis and V-79 mammalian cell mutagenesis assays and in the invitro alkaline elution and invitro and invivo chromosomal aberration assays.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5518" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In addition, the active metabolite showed no evidence of genotoxicity in the microbial mutagenesis, invitro alkaline elution, and invitro chromosomal aberration assays.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5519" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Fertility and reproductive performance were not affected in studies with male rats given oral doses of losartan potassium up to approximately 150mg/kg/day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5520" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The administration of toxic dosage levels in females (300/200mg/kg/day) was associated with a significant (p&lt;0.05) decrease in the number of corpora lutea/female, implants/female, and live fetuses/female at C-section.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5521" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>At 100mg/kg/day only a decrease in the number of corpora lutea/female was observed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5522" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The relationship of these findings to drug-treatment is uncertain since there was no effect at these dosage levels on implants/pregnant female, percent post-implantation loss, or live animals/litter at parturition.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5523" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In nonpregnant rats dosed at 135mg/kg/day for 7days, systemic exposure (AUCs) for losartan and its active metabolite were approximately 66 and 26times the exposure achieved in man at the maximum recommended human daily dosage (100mg).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5524" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Pregnancy CategoriesC (first trimester) and D (second and third trimesters).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5525" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>It is not known whether losartan is excreted in human milk, but significant levels of losartan and its active metabolite were shown to be present in rat milk.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5526" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because of the potential for adverse effects on the nursing infant, a decision should be made whether to discontinue nursing or discontinue the drug, taking into account the importance of the drug to the mother.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5527" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Antihypertensive effects of losartan potassium tablets have been established in hypertensive pediatric patients aged 6 to 16years.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5528" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>There are no data on the effect of losartan potassium tablets on blood pressure in pediatric patients under the age of 6 or in pediatric patients with glomerular filtration rate &lt;30mL/min/1.73m2.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5529" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Of the total number of patients receiving losartan potassium tablets in controlled clinical studies for hypertension, 391 patients (19%) were 65 years and over, while 37 patients (2%) were 75 years and over.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5530" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In a controlled clinical study for renal protection in type2 diabetic patients with proteinuria, 248 patients (33%) were 65 years and over.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5531" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In a controlled clinical study for the reduction in the combined risk of cardiovascular death, stroke and myocardial infarction in hypertensive patients with left ventricular hypertrophy, 2857 patients (62%) were 65 years and over, while 808 patients (18%) were 75 years and over.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5532" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>No overall differences in effectiveness or safety were observed between these patients and younger patients, but greater sensitivity of some older individuals cannot be ruled out.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5533" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In the LIFE study, Black patients with hypertension and left ventricular hypertrophy had a lower risk of stroke on atenolol than on losartan potassium tablets.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5534" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Given the difficulty in interpreting subset differences in large trials, it cannot be known whether the observed difference is the result of chance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5535" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>However, the LIFE study does not provide evidence that the benefits of losartan potassium tablets on reducing the risk of cardiovascular events in hypertensive patients with left ventricular hypertrophy apply to Black patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5536" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause fetal and neonatal morbidity and death when administered to pregnant women.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5537" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Several dozen cases have been reported in the world literature in patients who were taking angiotensin converting enzyme inhibitors.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5538" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The use of drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system during the second and third trimesters of pregnancy has been associated with fetal and neonatal injury, including hypotension, neonatal skull hypoplasia, anuria, reversible or irreversible renal failure, and death.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5539" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Oligohydramnios has also been reported, presumably resulting from decreased fetal renal function; oligohydramnios in this setting has been associated with fetal limb contractures, craniofacial deformation, and hypoplastic lung development.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5540" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Prematurity, intrauterine growth retardation, and patent ductus arteriosus have also been reported, although it is not clear whether these occurrences were due to exposure to the drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5541" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>These adverse effects do not appear to have resulted from intrauterine drug exposure that has been limited to the first trimester.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5542" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Mothers whose embryos and fetuses are exposed to an angiotensinII receptor antagonist only during the first trimester should be so informed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5543" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Nonetheless, when patients become pregnant, physicians should have the patient discontinue the use of losartan potassium tablets as soon as possible.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5544" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Rarely (probably less often than once in every thousand pregnancies), no alternative to an angiotensinII receptor antagonist will be found.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5545" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>In these rare cases, the mothers should be apprised of the potential hazards to their fetuses, and serial ultrasound examinations should be performed to assess the intra-amniotic environment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5546" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>If oligohydramnios is observed, losartan potassium tablets should be discontinued unless they are considered life-saving for the mother.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5547" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Contraction stress testing (CST), a non-stress test (NST), or biophysical profiling (BPP) may be appropriate, depending upon the week of pregnancy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5548" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Patients and physicians should be aware, however, that oligohydramnios may not appear until after the fetus has sustained irreversible injury.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5549" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Infants with histories of in utero exposure to an angiotensinII receptor antagonist should be closely observed for hypotension, oliguria, and hyperkalemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5550" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>If oliguria occurs, attention should be directed toward support of blood pressure and renal perfusion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5551" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Exchange transfusion or dialysis may be required as means of reversing hypotension and/or substituting for disordered renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5552" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Losartan potassium tablets have been shown to produce adverse effects in rat fetuses and neonates, including decreased body weight, delayed physical and behavioral development, mortality and renal toxicity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5553" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>With the exception of neonatal weight gain (which was affected at doses as low as 10mg/kg/day), doses associated with these effects exceeded 25mg/kg/day (approximately three times the maximum recommended human dose of 100mg on a mg/m2 basis).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5554" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>These findings are attributed to drug exposure in late gestation and during lactation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5555" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Significant levels of losartan and its active metabolite were shown to be present in rat fetal plasma during late gestation and in rat milk.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5556" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>In patients who are intravascularly volume-depleted (e.g., those treated with diuretics), symptomatic hypotension may occur after initiation of therapy with losartan potassium tablets.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M105" type="SpecificInteraction" span="90 23" str="symptomatic hypotension" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M104" type="Precipitant" span="78 9" str="diuretics" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I42" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M105" precipitant="M104" effect="M105"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5557" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>These conditions should be corrected prior to administration of losartan potassium tablets, or a lower starting dose should be used.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5558" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>AngiotensinII [formed from angiotensinI in a reaction catalyzed by angiotensin converting enzyme (ACE, kininaseII)], is a potent vasoconstrictor, the primary vasoactive hormone of the renin-angiotensin system and an important component in the pathophysiology of hypertension.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5559" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>It also stimulates aldosterone secretion by the adrenal cortex.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5560" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Losartan and its principal active metabolite block the vasoconstrictor and aldosterone-secreting effects of angiotensinII by selectively blocking the binding of angiotensinII to the AT1 receptor found in many tissues, (e.g., vascular smooth muscle, adrenal gland).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5561" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There is also an AT2 receptor found in many tissues but it is not known to be associated with cardiovascular homeostasis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5562" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Both losartan and its principal active metabolite do not exhibit any partial agonist activity at the AT1 receptor and have much greater affinity (about 1000-fold) for the AT1 receptor than for the AT2 receptor.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5563" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Invitro binding studies indicate that losartan is a reversible, competitive inhibitor of the AT1 receptor.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5564" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The active metabolite is 10 to 40times more potent by weight than losartan and appears to be a reversible, non-competitive inhibitor of the AT1 receptor.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5565" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Neither losartan nor its active metabolite inhibits ACE (kininaseII, the enzyme that converts angiotensinI to angiotensinII and degrades bradykinin); nor do they bind to or block other hormone receptors or ion channels known to be important in cardiovascular regulation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5566" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Losartan is an orally active agent that undergoes substantial first-pass metabolism by cytochrome P450 enzymes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5567" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>It is converted, in part, to an active carboxylic acid metabolite that is responsible for most of the angiotensinII receptor antagonism that follows losartan treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5568" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Losartan metabolites have been identified in human plasma and urine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5569" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In addition to the active carboxylic acid metabolite, several inactive metabolites are formed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5570" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following oral and intravenous administration of 14C-labeled losartan potassium, circulating plasma radioactivity is primarily attributed to losartan and its active metabolite.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5571" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Invitro studies indicate that cytochrome P450 2C9 and 3A4 are involved in the biotransformation of losartan to its metabolites.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5572" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Minimal conversion of losartan to the active metabolite (less than 1% of the dose compared to 14% of the dose in normal subjects) was seen in about one percent of individuals studied.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5573" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The terminal half-life of losartan is about 2hours and of the metabolite is about 6-9hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5574" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacokinetics of losartan and its active metabolite are linear with oral losartan doses up to 200mg and do not change over time.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5575" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Neither losartan nor its metabolite accumulate in plasma upon repeated once-daily dosing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5576" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following oral administration, losartan is well absorbed (based on absorption of radiolabeled losartan) and undergoes substantial first-pass metabolism; the systemic bioavailability of losartan is approximately 33%.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5577" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>About 14% of an orally-administered dose of losartan is converted to the active metabolite.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5578" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Mean peak concentrations of losartan and its active metabolite are reached in 1hour and in 3-4hours, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5579" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>While maximum plasma concentrations of losartan and its active metabolite are approximately equal, the AUC of the metabolite is about 4times as great as that of losartan.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5580" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A meal slows absorption of losartan and decreases its Cmax but has only minor effects on losartan AUC or on the AUC of the metabolite (about 10% decreased).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M106" type="Trigger" span="7 16" str="slows absorption"/>
<Mention id="M111" type="Precipitant" span="2 4" str="meal" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M108" type="Trigger" span="40 18" str="decreases its Cmax"/>
<Mention id="M110" type="Trigger" span="98 3;145 9" str="AUC | decreased"/>
<Interaction id="I43" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M106" precipitant="M111" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I44" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M108" precipitant="M111" effect="C54606"/>
<Interaction id="I45" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M110" precipitant="M111" effect="C54609"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5581" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacokinetics of losartan and its active metabolite were also determined after IV doses of each component separately in healthy volunteers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5582" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The volume of distribution of losartan and the active metabolite is about 34liters and 12liters, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5583" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Total plasma clearance of losartan and the active metabolite is about 600mL/min and 50mL/min, respectively, with renal clearance of about 75mL/min and 25mL/min, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5584" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>After single doses of losartan administered orally, about 4% of the dose is excreted unchanged in the urine and about 6% is excreted in urine as active metabolite.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5585" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Biliary excretion contributes to the elimination of losartan and its metabolites.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5586" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following oral 14C-labeled losartan, about 35% of radioactivity is recovered in the urine and about 60% in the feces.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5587" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following an intravenous dose of 14C-labeled losartan, about 45% of radioactivity is recovered in the urine and 50% in the feces.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5588" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Both losartan and its active metabolite are highly bound to plasma proteins, primarily albumin, with plasma free fractions of 1.3% and 0.2%, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5589" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Plasma protein binding is constant over the concentration range achieved with recommended doses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5590" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Studies in rats indicate that losartan crosses the blood-brain barrier poorly, if at all.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5591" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Pediatric: Pharmacokinetic parameters after multiple doses of losartan (average dose 0.7mg/kg, range 0.36 to 0.97mg/kg) as a tablet to 25hypertensive patients aged 6 to 16years are shown in Table1 below.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5592" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Pharmacokinetics of losartan and its active metabolite were generally similar across the studied age groups and similar to historical pharmacokinetic data in adults.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5593" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The principal pharmacokinetic parameters in adults and children are shown in the table below.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5594" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Table1: Pharmacokinetic Parameters in Hypertensive Adults and Children Age6-16 Following Multiple Dosing Adults given 50mg once daily for 7daysN=12 Age6-16 given 0.7mg/kg once daily for 7daysN=25 Parent Active Metabolite Parent Active Metabolite AUC0-24 Mean ± standard deviation(ng•h/mL) 442 ± 173 1685 ± 452 368 ± 169 1866 ± 1076 CMAX (ng/mL) 224 ± 82 212 ± 73 141 ± 88 222 ± 127 T1/2 (h)Harmonic mean and standard deviation 2.1 ± 0.70 7.4 ± 2.4 2.3 ± 0.8 5.6 ± 1.2 TPEAK (h)Median 0.9 3.5 2.0 4.1 CLREN (mL/min) 56 ± 23 20 ± 3 53 ± 33 17 ± 8 The bioavailability of the suspension formulation was compared with losartan tablets in healthy adults.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5595" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The suspension and tablet are similar in their bioavailability with respect to both losartan and the active metabolite.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5596" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Geriatric and Gender: Losartan pharmacokinetics have been investigated in the elderly (65-75years) and in both genders.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5597" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Plasma concentrations of losartan and its active metabolite are similar in elderly and young hypertensives.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5598" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Plasma concentrations of losartan were about twice as high in female hypertensives as male hypertensives, but concentrations of the active metabolite were similar in males and females.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5599" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No dosage adjustment is necessary.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5600" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Race: Pharmacokinetic differences due to race have not been studied.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5601" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Renal Insufficiency: Following oral administration, plasma concentrations and AUCs of losartan and its active metabolite are increased by 50-90% in patients with mild (creatinine clearance of 50 to 74mL/min) or moderate (creatinine clearance 30 to 49mL/min) renal insufficiency.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5602" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In this study, renal clearance was reduced by 55-85% for both losartan and its active metabolite in patients with mild or moderate renal insufficiency.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5603" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Neither losartan nor its active metabolite can be removed by hemodialysis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5604" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No dosage adjustment is necessary for patients with renal impairment unless they are volume-depleted.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5605" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Hepatic Insufficiency: Following oral administration in patients with mild to moderate alcoholic cirrhosis of the liver, plasma concentrations of losartan and its active metabolite were, respectively, 5-times and about 1.7-times those in young male volunteers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5606" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Compared to normal subjects the total plasma clearance of losartan in patients with hepatic insufficiency was about 50% lower and the oral bioavailability was about 2-times higher.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5607" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A lower starting dose is recommended for patients with a history of hepatic impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5608" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Losartan inhibits the pressor effect of angiotensinII (as well as angiotensinI) infusions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5609" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A dose of 100mg inhibits the pressor effect by about 85% at peak with 25-40% inhibition persisting for 24hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5610" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Removal of the negative feedback of angiotensinII causes a 2- to 3-fold rise in plasma renin activity and consequent rise in angiotensinII plasma concentration in hypertensive patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5611" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Losartan does not affect the response to bradykinin, whereas ACE inhibitors increase the response to bradykinin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5612" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Aldosterone plasma concentrations fall following losartan administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5613" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In spite of the effect of losartan on aldosterone secretion, very little effect on serum potassium was observed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5614" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In a single-dose study in normal volunteers, losartan had no effects on glomerular filtration rate, renal plasma flow or filtration fraction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5615" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In multiple-dose studies in hypertensive patients, there were no notable effects on systemic or renal prostaglandin concentrations, fasting triglycerides, total cholesterol or HDL-cholesterol or fasting glucose concentrations.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5616" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There was a small uricosuric effect leading to a minimal decrease in serum uric acid (mean decrease &lt;0.4mg/dL) during chronic oral administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5617" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The antihypertensive effects of losartan potassium tablets were demonstrated principally in 4placebo-controlled, 6- to 12-week trials of dosages from 10 to 150mg per day in patients with baseline diastolic blood pressures of 95-115.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5618" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The studies allowed comparisons of two doses (50-100mg/day) as once-daily or twice-daily regimens, comparisons of peak and trough effects, and comparisons of response by gender, age, and race.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5619" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Three additional studies examined the antihypertensive effects of losartan and hydrochlorothiazide in combination.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5620" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The 4 studies of losartan monotherapy included a total of 1075 patients randomized to several doses of losartan and 334 to placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5621" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The 10- and 25-mg doses produced some effect at peak (6hours after dosing) but small and inconsistent trough (24hour) responses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5622" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Doses of 50, 100 and 150mg once daily gave statistically significant systolic/diastolic mean decreases in blood pressure, compared to placebo in the range of 5.5-10.5/3.5-7.5mmHg, with the 150-mg dose giving no greater effect than 50-100mg. Twice-daily dosing at 50-100mg/day gave consistently larger trough responses than once-daily dosing at the same total dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5623" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Peak (6hour) effects were uniformly, but moderately, larger than trough effects, with the trough-to-peak ratio for systolic and diastolic responses 50-95% and 60-90%, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5624" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Addition of a low dose of hydrochlorothiazide (12.5mg) to losartan 50mg once daily resulted in placebo-adjusted blood pressure reductions of 15.5/9.2mmHg.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M112" type="Trigger" span="83 11" str="resulted in"/>
<Mention id="M113" type="Precipitant" span="26 19" str="hydrochlorothiazide" code="0J48LPH2TH"/>
<Mention id="M114" type="SpecificInteraction" span="112 25" str="blood pressure reductions" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I46" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M112" precipitant="M113" effect="M114"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5625" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Analysis of age, gender, and race subgroups of patients showed that men and women, and patients over and under 65, had generally similar responses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5626" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Losartan potassium tablets were effective in reducing blood pressure regardless of race, although the effect was somewhat less in Black patients (usually a low-renin population).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5627" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In long-term follow-up studies (without placebo control) the effect of losartan appeared to be maintained for up to a year.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5628" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There is no apparent rebound effect after abrupt withdrawal of losartan.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5629" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There was essentially no change in average heart rate in losartan-treated patients in controlled trials.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5630" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The antihypertensive effect of losartan was studied in one trial enrolling 177hypertensive pediatric patients aged 6 to 16years old.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5631" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Children who weighed &lt;50kg received 2.5, 25 or 50mg of losartan daily and patients who weighed ≥50kg received 5, 50 or 100mg of losartan daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5632" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Children in the lowest dose group were given losartan in a suspension formulation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5633" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The majority of the children had hypertension associated with renal and urogenital disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5634" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The sitting diastolic blood pressure (SiDBP) on entry into the study was higher than the 95th percentile level for the patient’s age, gender, and height.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5635" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>At the end of three weeks, losartan reduced systolic and diastolic blood pressure, measured at trough, in a dose-dependent manner.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5636" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Overall, the two higher doses (25 to 50mg in patients &lt;50kg; 50 to 100mg in patients ≥50kg) reduced diastolic blood pressure by 5 to 6mmHg more than the lowest dose used (2.5mg in patients &lt;50kg; 5mg in patients ≥50kg).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5637" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The lowest dose, corresponding to an average daily dose of 0.07mg/kg, did not appear to offer consistent antihypertensive efficacy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5638" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>When patients were randomized to continue losartan at the two higher doses or to placebo after 3weeks of therapy, trough diastolic blood pressure rose in patients on placebo between 5 and 7mmHg more than patients randomized to continuing losartan.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5639" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>When the low dose of losartan was randomly withdrawn, the rise in trough diastolic blood pressure was the same in patients receiving placebo and in those continuing losartan, again suggesting that the lowest dose did not have significant antihypertensive efficacy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5640" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Overall, no significant differences in the overall antihypertensive effect of losartan were detected when the patients were analyzed according to age (&lt;,≥12years old) or gender.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5641" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>While blood pressure was reduced in all racial subgroups examined, too few non-White patients were enrolled to compare the dose-response of losartan in the non-White subgroup.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5642" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The Losartan Intervention For Endpoint reduction in hypertension (LIFE) study was a multinational, double-blind study comparing losartan potassium tablets and atenolol in 9193 hypertensive patients with ECG-documented left ventricular hypertrophy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5643" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Patients with myocardial infarction or stroke within six months prior to randomization were excluded.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5644" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Patients were randomized to receive once daily losartan potassium tablets 50mg or atenolol 50mg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5645" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>If goal blood pressure (&lt;140/90mmHg) was not reached, hydrochlorothiazide (12.5mg) was added first and, if needed, the dose of losartan potassium tablets or atenolol was then increased to 100mg once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5646" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>If necessary, other antihypertensive treatments (e.g., increase in dose of hydrochlorothiazide therapy to 25mg or addition of other diuretic therapy, calcium-channel blockers, alpha-blockers, or centrally acting agents, but not ACE inhibitors, angiotensin II antagonists, or beta-blockers) were added to the treatment regimen to reach the goal blood pressure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5647" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Of the randomized patients, 4963 (54%) were female and 533 (6%) were Black.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5648" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mean age was 67 with 5704 (62%) age ≥65.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5649" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>At baseline, 1195 (13%) had diabetes, 1326 (14%) had isolated systolic hypertension, 1469 (16%) had coronary heart disease, and 728 (8%) had cerebrovascular disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5650" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Baseline mean blood pressure was 174/98mmHg in both treatment groups.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5651" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mean length of follow-up was 4.8years.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5652" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>At the end of study or at the last visit before a primary endpoint, 77% of the group treated with losartan potassium tablets and 73% of the group treated with atenolol were still taking study medication.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5653" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Of the patients still taking study medication, the mean doses of losartan potassium tablets and atenolol were both about 80mg/day, and 15% were taking atenolol or losartan as monotherapy, while 77% were also receiving hydrochlorothiazide (at a mean dose of 20mg/day in each group).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5654" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Blood pressure reduction measured at trough was similar for both treatment groups but blood pressure was not measured at any other time of the day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5655" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>At the end of study or at the last visit before a primary endpoint, the mean blood pressures were 144.1/81.3mmHg for the group treated with losartan potassium tablets and 145.4/80.9mmHg for the group treated with atenolol [the difference in systolic blood pressure (SBP) of 1.3mmHg was significant (p&lt;0.001), while the difference of 0.4mmHg in diastolic blood pressure (DBP) was not significant (p=0.098)].</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5656" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The primary endpoint was the first occurrence of cardiovascular death, nonfatal stroke, or nonfatal myocardial infarction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5657" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Patients with non-fatal events remained in the trial, so that there was also an examination of the first event of each type even if it was not the first event (e.g., a stroke following an initial myocardial infarction would be counted in the analysis of stroke).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5658" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Treatment with losartan potassium tablets resulted in a 13% reduction (p=0.021) in risk of the primary endpoint compared to the atenolol group ; this difference was primarily the result of an effect on fatal and nonfatal stroke.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5659" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Treatment with losartan potassium tablets reduced the risk of stroke by 25% relative to atenolol (p=0.001).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5660" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Kaplan-Meier estimates of the primary endpoint of time to cardiovascular death, nonfatal stroke, or nonfatal myocardial infarction in the groups treated with losartan potassium tablets and atenolol.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5661" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The Risk Reduction is adjusted for baseline Framingham risk score and level of electrocardiographic left ventricular hypertrophy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5662" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Kaplan-Meier estimates of the time to fatal/nonfatal stroke in the groups treated with losartan potassium tablets and atenolol.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5663" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Table2 shows the results for the primary composite endpoint and the individual endpoints.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5664" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The primary endpoint was the first occurrence of stroke, myocardial infarction or cardiovascular death, analyzed using an intention-to-treat (ITT) approach.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5665" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The table shows the number of events for each component in two different ways.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5666" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The Components of Primary Endpoint (as a first event) counts only the events that define the primary endpoint, while the Secondary Endpoints count all first events of a particular type, whether or not they were preceded by a different type of event.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5667" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Table2: Incidence of Primary Endpoint Events Losartan Atenolol Risk ReductionAdjusted for baseline Framingham risk score and level of electrocardiographic left ventricular hypertrophy 95% CI p-Value N (%) RateRate per 1000 patient-years of follow-up N (%) Rate Primary Composite Endpoint 508 (11) 23.8 588 (13) 27.9 13% 2% to 23% 0.021 Components of Primary Composite Endpoint (as a first event) Stroke (nonfatalFirst report of an event, in some cases the patient died subsequently to the event reported) 209 (5) 286 (6) Myocardial infarction (nonfatal) 174 (4) 168 (4) Cardiovascular mortality 125 (3) 134 (3) Secondary Endpoints (any time in study) Stroke (fatal/nonfatal) 232 (5) 10.8 309 (7) 14.5 25% 11% to 37% 0.001 Myocardial infarction (fatal/nonfatal) 198 (4) 9.2 188 (4) 8.7 -7% -13% to 12% 0.491 Cardiovascular mortality 204 (4) 9.2 234 (5) 10.6 11% -7% to 27% 0.206 Due to CHD 125 (3) 5.6 124 (3) 5.6 -3% -32% to 20% 0.839 Due to Stroke 40 (1) 1.8 62 (1) 2.8 35% 4% to 67% 0.032 OtherDeath due to heart failure, non-coronary vascular disease, pulmonary embolism, or a cardiovascular cause other than stroke or coronary heart disease 39 (1) 1.8 48 (1) 2.2 16% -28% to 45% 0.411 Although the LIFE study favored losartan potassium tablets over atenolol with respect to the primary endpoint (p=0.021), this result is from a single study and, therefore, is less compelling than the difference between losartan potassium tablets and placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5668" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Although not measured directly, the difference between losartan potassium tablets and placebo is compelling because there is evidence that atenolol is itself effective (vs. placebo) in reducing cardiovascular events, including stroke, in hypertensive patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5669" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Other clinical endpoints of the LIFE study were: total mortality, hospitalization for heart failure or angina pectoris, coronary or peripheral revascularization procedures, and resuscitated cardiac arrest.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5670" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There were no significant differences in the rates of these endpoints between the losartan potassium tablets and atenolol groups.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5671" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>For the primary endpoint and stroke, the effects of losartan potassium tablets in patient subgroups defined by age, gender, race and presence or absence of isolated systolic hypertension (ISH), diabetes, and history of cardiovascular disease (CVD) are shown in Figure3 below.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5672" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Subgroup analyses can be difficult to interpret and it is not known whether these represent true differences or chance effects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5673" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Primary Endpoint Events† within Demographic Subgroups In the LIFE study, Black patients treated with atenolol were at lower risk of experiencing the primary composite endpoint compared with Black patients treated with losartan potassium tablets.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5674" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In the subgroup of Black patients (n=533; 6% of the LIFE study patients), there were 29 primary endpoints among 263 patients on atenolol (11%, 26 per 1000 patient-years) and 46 primary endpoints among 270 patients (17%, 42 per 1000 patient-years) on losartan potassium tablets.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5675" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This finding could not be explained on the basis of differences in the populations other than race or on any imbalances between treatment groups.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5676" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In addition, blood pressure reductions in both treatment groups were consistent between Black and non-Black patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5677" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>However, the LIFE study provides no evidence that the benefits of losartan potassium tablets on reducing the risk of cardiovascular events in hypertensive patients with left ventricular hypertrophy apply to Black patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5678" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The Reduction of Endpoints in NIDDM with the AngiotensinII Receptor Antagonist Losartan(RENAAL) study was a randomized, placebo-controlled, double-blind, multicenter study conducted worldwide in 1513 patients with type2 diabetes with nephropathy (defined as serum creatinine 1.3 to 3.0mg/dl in females or males ≤60kg and 1.5 to 3.0mg/dl in males &gt;60kg and proteinuria [urinary albumin to creatinine ratio ≥300mg/g]).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5679" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Patients were randomized to receive losartan potassium tablets 50mg once daily or placebo on a background of conventional antihypertensive therapy excluding ACE inhibitors and angiotensinII antagonists.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5680" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>After one month, investigators were instructed to titrate study drug to 100mg once daily if the trough blood pressure goal (140/90mmHg) was not achieved.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5681" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Overall, 72% of patients received the 100-mg daily dose more than 50% of the time they were on study drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5682" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Because the study was designed to achieve equal blood pressure control in both groups, other antihypertensive agents (diuretics, calcium-channel blockers, alpha- or beta-blockers, and centrallyacting agents) could be added as needed in both groups.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5683" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Patients were followed for a mean duration of 3.4years.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5684" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The study population was diverse with regard to race (Asian 16.7%, Black 15.2%, Hispanic 18.3%, White 48.6%).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5685" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Overall, 63.2% of the patients were men, and 66.4% were under the age of 65 years.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5686" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Almost all of the patients (96.6%) had a history of hypertension, and the patients entered the trial with a mean serum creatinine of 1.9mg/dl and mean proteinuria (urinary albumin/creatinine) of 1808mg/g at baseline.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5687" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The primary endpoint of the study was the time to first occurrence of any one of the following events: doubling of serum creatinine, end-stage renal disease (ESRD) (need for dialysis or transplantation), or death.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5688" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Treatment with losartan potassium tablets resulted in a 16%risk reduction in this endpoint.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5689" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Treatment with losartan potassium tablets also reduced the occurrence of sustained doubling of serum creatinine by 25% and ESRD by 29% as separate endpoints, but had no effect on overall mortality.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5690" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mean baseline blood pressures were 152/82mmHg for losartan potassium tablets plus conventional antihypertensive therapy and 153/82mmHg for placebo plus conventional antihypertensive therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5691" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>At the end of the study, the mean blood pressures were 143/76mmHg for the group treated with losartan potassium tablets and 146/77mmHg for the group treated with placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5692" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Kaplan-Meier curve for the primary composite endpoint of doubling of serum creatinine, end stage renal disease (need for dialysis or transplantation) or death.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5693" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Table3: Incidence of Primary Endpoint Events Incidence Risk Reduction 95% C.I. p-Value Losartan Placebo Primary Composite Endpoint 43.5% 47.1% 16.1% 2.3% to 27.9% 0.022 Doubling of Serum Creatinine, ESRD and Death Occurring as a First Event Doubling of Serum Creatinine 21.6% 26.0% ESRD 8.5% 8.5% Death 13.4% 12.6% Overall Incidence of Doubling of Serum Creatinine, ESRD and Death Doubling of Serum Creatinine 21.6% 26.0% 25.3% 7.8% to 39.4% 0.006 ESRD 19.6% 25.5% 28.6% 11.5% to 42.4% 0.002 Death 21.0% 20.3% -1.7% -26.9% to 18.6% 0.884 The secondary endpoints of the study were change in proteinuria, change in the rate of progression of renal disease, and the composite of morbidity and mortality from cardiovascular causes (hospitalization for heart failure, myocardial infarction, revascularization, stroke, hospitalization for unstable angina, or cardiovascular death).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5694" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Compared with placebo, losartan potassium tablets significantly reduced proteinuria by an average of 34%, an effect that was evident within 3 months of starting therapy, and significantly reduced the rate of decline in glomerular filtration rate during the study by 13%, as measured by the reciprocal of the serum creatinine concentration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5695" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There was no significant difference in the incidence of the composite endpoint of cardiovascular morbidity and mortality.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5696" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The favorable effects of losartan potassium tablets were seen in patients also taking other anti-hypertensive medications (angiotensinII receptor antagonists and angiotensin converting enzyme inhibitors were not allowed), oral hypoglycemic agents and lipid-lowering agents.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5697" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>For the primary endpoint and ESRD, the effects of losartan potassium tablets in patient subgroups defined by age, gender and race are shown in Table4 below.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5698" LabelDrug="Losartan Potassium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Table4: Efficacy Outcomes within Demographic Subgroups Primary Composite Endpoint ESRD No. of Patients LosartanEvent Rate% PlaceboEvent Rate% Hazard Ratio(95% CI) LosartanEvent Rate% PlaceboEvent Rate% Hazard Ratio(95% CI) Overall Results 1513 43.5 47.1 0.839 (0.721, 0.977) 19.6 25.5 0.714 (0.576, 0.885) Age &lt;65 years 1005 44.1 49.0 0.784 (0.653, 0.941) 21.1 28.5 0.670 (0.521, 0.863) ≥65 years 508 42.3 43.5 0.978 (0.749, 1.277) 16.5 19.6 0.847 (0.560, 1.281) Gender Female 557 47.8 54.1 0.762 (0.603, 0.962) 22.8 32.8 0.601 (0.436, 0.828) Male 956 40.9 43.3 0.892 (0.733, 1.085) 17.5 21.5 0.809 (0.605, 1.081) Race Asian 252 41.9 54.8 0.655 (0.453, 0.947) 18.8 27.4 0.625 (0.367, 1.066) Black 230 40.0 39.0 0.983 (0.647, 1.495) 17.6 21.0 0.831 (0.456, 1.516) Hispanic 277 55.0 54.0 1.003 (0.728, 1.380) 30.0 28.5 1.024 (0.661, 1.586) White 735 40.5 43.2 0.809 (0.645, 1.013) 16.2 23.9 0.596 (0.427, 0.831) Image of Figure 1 Image of Figure 2 Image of Figure 3 Image of Figure 4</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="diuretics" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="28560003: Hypovolemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="diuretics" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cimetidine" precipitantCode="80061L1WGD" effect="C54605"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="phenobarbital" precipitantCode="YQE403BP4D" effect="C54609"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="rifampin" precipitantCode="VJT6J7R4TR" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="rifampin" precipitantCode="VJT6J7R4TR" effect="C54609"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="fluconazole" precipitantCode="8VZV102JFY" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="fluconazole" precipitantCode="8VZV102JFY" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="fluconazole" precipitantCode="8VZV102JFY" effect="C54605"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="fluconazole" precipitantCode="8VZV102JFY" effect="C54609"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="inhibitor of cytochrome p450 2c9" precipitantCode="N0000185504" effect="C54605"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="inhibitor of cytochrome p450 2c9" precipitantCode="N0000185504" effect="C54609"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="erythromycin" precipitantCode="63937KV33D" effect="C54605"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="inhibitor of p450 2c9" precipitantCode="N0000185504" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="inhibitor of p450 2c9" precipitantCode="N0000185504" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="amiloride" precipitantCode="7DZO8EB0Z3" effect="166689004: Raised serum potassium level (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="potassium supplements" precipitantCode="RWP5GA015D" effect="166689004: Raised serum potassium level (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="potassium supplements" precipitantCode="RWP5GA015D"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="potassium-sparing diuretics" precipitantCode="N0000175418" effect="166689004: Raised serum potassium level (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="salt substitutes containing potassium" precipitantCode="N0000175600" effect="166689004: Raised serum potassium level (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="salt substitutes containing potassium" precipitantCode="N0000175600"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="spironolactone" precipitantCode="27O7W4T232" effect="166689004: Raised serum potassium level (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="triamterene" precipitantCode="WS821Z52LQ" effect="166689004: Raised serum potassium level (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="lithium" precipitantCode="9FN79X2M3F" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="lithium" precipitantCode="9FN79X2M3F"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cox-2 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000008288" effect=" 39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cox-2 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000008288" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cox-2 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000008288" effect="236423003: Renal impairment (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect=" 39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="236423003: Renal impairment (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nsaids" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect=" 39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nsaids" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nsaids" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="236423003: Renal impairment (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nsaids" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="selective cox-2 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000008288" effect=" 39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="selective cox-2 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000008288" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="selective cox-2 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000008288" effect="236423003: Renal impairment (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="selective cox-2 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000008288" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="selective cyclooxygenase-2 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000008288" effect=" 39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="selective cyclooxygenase-2 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000008288" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="selective cyclooxygenase-2 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000008288" effect="236423003: Renal impairment (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nsaid" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="meal" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="meal" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54606"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="meal" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54609"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="hydrochlorothiazide" precipitantCode="0J48LPH2TH" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>