<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Micardis" setid="cfb9309f-e0df-4a55-9542-0e869fce05fb">
<Text><Section name="BOXED WARNING SECTION" id="34066-1">
When pregnancy is detected, discontinue MICARDIS as soon as possible [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]   .    Drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause injury and death to the developing fetus [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)].            WARNING:  FETAL TOXICITY    See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.    When pregnancy is detected, discontinue MICARDIS as soon as possible (5.1)      Drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause injury and death to the developing fetus (5.1)</Section>
<Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
MICARDIS is contraindicated in patients with known hypersensitivity (e.g., anaphylaxis or angioedema) to telmisartan or any other component of this product  [see Adverse Reactions (6.2)] .   Do not co-administer aliskiren with MICARDIS in patients with diabetes [see Drug Interactions (7)].         Known hypersensitivity (e.g., anaphylaxis or angioedema) to telmisartan or any other component of this product (4)  Do not co-administer aliskiren with MICARDIS in patients with diabetes (4)</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
May be administered with or without food (2.1)  When used for cardiovascular risk reduction, monitoring of blood pressure is recommended, and if appropriate, adjustment of medications that lower blood pressure may be necessary (2.2)       Indication   Starting Dose   Dose Range    Hypertension (2.1)  40 mg once daily 40 to 80 mg once daily   Cardiovascular Risk Reduction (2.2)  80 mg once daily 80 mg once daily            Dosage must be individualized.  The usual starting dose of MICARDIS tablets is 40 mg once a day.  Blood pressure response is dose-related over the range of 20 to 80 mg  [see Clinical Studies (14.1)] . Most of the antihypertensive effect is apparent within 2 weeks and maximal reduction is generally attained after 4 weeks.  When additional blood pressure reduction beyond that achieved with 80 mg MICARDIS is required, a diuretic may be added. No initial dosage adjustment is necessary for elderly patients or patients with renal impairment, including those on hemodialysis. Patients on dialysis may develop orthostatic hypotension; their blood pressure should be closely monitored. MICARDIS tablets may be administered with other antihypertensive agents. MICARDIS tablets may be administered with or without food.          The recommended dose of MICARDIS tablets is 80 mg once a day and can be administered with or without food. It is not known whether doses lower than 80 mg of telmisartan are effective in reducing the risk of cardiovascular morbidity and mortality. When initiating MICARDIS therapy for cardiovascular risk reduction, monitoring of blood pressure is recommended, and if appropriate, adjustment of medications that lower blood pressure may be necessary.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
Aliskiren: Do not co-administer aliskiren with MICARDIS in patients with diabetes. Avoid use of aliskiren with MICARDIS in patients with renal impairment (GFR &amp;lt;60 mL/min).   Digoxin : When MICARDIS was co-administered with digoxin, median increases in digoxin peak plasma concentration (49%) and in trough concentration (20%) were observed. Therefore, monitor digoxin levels when initiating, adjusting, and discontinuing telmisartan for the purpose of keeping the digoxin level within the therapeutic range.   Lithium : Reversible increases in serum lithium concentrations and toxicity have been reported during concomitant administration of lithium with angiotensin II receptor antagonists including MICARDIS. Therefore, monitor serum lithium levels during concomitant use.   Non-Steroidal Anti-Inflammatory Agents including Selective Cyclooxygenase-2 Inhibitors (COX-2 Inhibitors): In patients who are elderly, volume-depleted (including those on diuretic therapy), or with compromised renal function, co-administration of NSAIDs, including selective COX-2 inhibitors, with angiotensin II receptor antagonists, including telmisartan, may result in deterioration of renal function, including possible acute renal failure. These effects are usually reversible. Monitor renal function periodically in patients receiving telmisartan and NSAID therapy. The antihypertensive effect of angiotensin II receptor antagonists, including telmisartan may be attenuated by NSAIDs including selective COX-2 inhibitors.   Ramipril and Ramiprilat : Co-administration of telmisartan 80 mg once daily and ramipril 10 mg once daily to healthy subjects increases steady-state Cmax and AUC of ramipril 2.3- and 2.1-fold, respectively, and Cmax and AUC of ramiprilat 2.4- and 1.5-fold, respectively. In contrast, Cmax and AUC of telmisartan decrease by 31% and 16%, respectively. When co-administering telmisartan and ramipril, the response may be greater because of the possibly additive pharmacodynamic effects of the combined drugs, and also because of the increased exposure to ramipril and ramiprilat in the presence of telmisartan. Concomitant use of MICARDIS and ramipril is not recommended.   Other Drugs : Co-administration of telmisartan did not result in a clinically significant interaction with acetaminophen, amlodipine, glyburide, simvastatin, hydrochlorothiazide, warfarin, or ibuprofen. Telmisartan is not metabolized by the cytochrome P450 system and had no effects  in vitro on cytochrome P450 enzymes, except for some inhibition of CYP2C19. Telmisartan is not expected to interact with drugs that inhibit cytochrome P450 enzymes; it is also not expected to interact with drugs metabolized by cytochrome P450 enzymes, except for possible inhibition of the metabolism of drugs metabolized by CYP2C19.       NSAIDS: Increased risk of renal impairment and loss of anti-hypertensive effect (7)  Do not co-administer aliskiren with MICARDIS in patients with diabetes (7)</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
Avoid fetal or neonatal exposure (5.1)  Hypotension: Correct any volume or salt depletion before initiating therapy.  Observe for signs and symptoms of hypotension (5.2)  Monitor carefully in patients with impaired hepatic (5.4) or renal function (5.5)  Avoid concomitant use of an ACE inhibitor and angiotensin receptor blocker (5.6)              Pregnancy Category D     Use of drugs that act on the renin-angiotensin system during the second and third trimesters of pregnancy reduces fetal renal function and increases fetal and neonatal morbidity and death. Resulting oligohydramnios can be associated with fetal lung hypoplasia and skeletal deformations. Potential neonatal adverse effects include skull hypoplasia, anuria, hypotension, renal failure, and death. When pregnancy is detected, discontinue MICARDIS as soon as possible  [see Use in Specific Populations (8.1)] .           In patients with an activated renin-angiotensin system, such as volume- or salt-depleted patients (e.g., those being treated with high doses of diuretics), symptomatic hypotension may occur after initiation of therapy with MICARDIS.  Either correct this condition prior to administration of MICARDIS, or start treatment under close medical supervision with a reduced dose. If hypotension does occur, the patient should be placed in the supine position and, if necessary, given an intravenous infusion of normal saline.  A transient hypotensive response is not a contraindication to further treatment, which usually can be continued without difficulty once the blood pressure has stabilized.          Hyperkalemia may occur in patients on ARBs, particularly in patients with advanced renal impairment, heart failure, on renal replacement therapy, or on potassium supplements, potassium-sparing diuretics, potassium-containing salt substitutes or other drugs that increase potassium levels. Consider periodic determinations of serum electrolytes to detect possible electrolyte imbalances, particularly in patients at risk.          As the majority of telmisartan is eliminated by biliary excretion, patients with biliary obstructive disorders or hepatic insufficiency can be expected to have reduced clearance.  Initiate telmisartan at low doses and titrate slowly in these patients  [see Use in Specific Populations (8.6) and Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)] .          As a consequence of inhibiting the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system, anticipate changes in renal function in susceptible individuals.  In patients whose renal function may depend on the activity of the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system (e.g., patients with severe congestive heart failure or renal dysfunction), treatment with angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE) inhibitors and angiotensin receptor antagonists has been associated with oliguria and/or progressive azotemia and (rarely) with acute renal failure and/or death. Similar results have been reported with MICARDIS  [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)] . In studies of ACE inhibitors in patients with unilateral or bilateral renal artery stenosis, increases in serum creatinine or blood urea nitrogen were observed.  There has been no long term use of MICARDIS in patients with unilateral or bilateral renal artery stenosis, but anticipate an effect similar to that seen with ACE inhibitors.          As a consequence of inhibiting the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system, changes in renal function (including acute renal failure) have been reported.   Dual blockade of the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system (e.g., by adding an ACE-inhibitor to an angiotensin II receptor antagonist) should include close monitoring of renal function. The ONTARGET trial enrolled 25,620 patients ≥55 years old with atherosclerotic disease or diabetes with end-organ damage, randomizing them to telmisartan only, ramipril only, or the combination, and followed them for a median of 56 months. Patients receiving the combination of MICARDIS and ramipril did not obtain any additional benefit compared to monotherapy, but experienced an increased incidence of renal dysfunction (e.g., acute renal failure) compared with groups receiving telmisartan alone or ramipril alone.  Concomitant use of MICARDIS and ramipril is not recommended.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Angiotensin II is formed from angiotensin I in a reaction catalyzed by angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE, kininase II). Angiotensin II is the principal pressor agent of the renin-angiotensin system, with effects that include vasoconstriction, stimulation of synthesis and release of aldosterone, cardiac stimulation, and renal reabsorption of sodium.  Telmisartan blocks the vasoconstrictor and aldosterone-secreting effects of angiotensin II by selectively blocking the binding of angiotensin II to the AT1 receptor in many tissues, such as vascular smooth muscle and the adrenal gland.  Its action is therefore independent of the pathways for angiotensin II synthesis. There is also an AT2 receptor found in many tissues, but AT2 is not known to be associated with cardiovascular homeostasis. Telmisartan has much greater affinity (&amp;gt;3,000 fold) for the AT1 receptor than for the AT2 receptor. Blockade of the renin-angiotensin system with ACE inhibitors, which inhibit the biosynthesis of angiotensin II from angiotensin I, is widely used in the treatment of hypertension. ACE inhibitors also inhibit the degradation of bradykinin, a reaction also catalyzed by ACE. Because telmisartan does not inhibit ACE (kininase II), it does not affect the response to bradykinin. Whether this difference has clinical relevance is not yet known. Telmisartan does not bind to or block other hormone receptors or ion channels known to be important in cardiovascular regulation. Blockade of the angiotensin II receptor inhibits the negative regulatory feedback of angiotensin II on renin secretion, but the resulting increased plasma renin activity and angiotensin II circulating levels do not overcome the effect of telmisartan on blood pressure.          In normal volunteers, a dose of telmisartan 80 mg inhibited the pressor response to an intravenous infusion of angiotensin II by about 90% at peak plasma concentrations with approximately 40% inhibition persisting for 24 hours. Plasma concentration of angiotensin II and plasma renin activity (PRA) increased in a dose-dependent manner after single administration of telmisartan to healthy subjects and repeated administration to hypertensive patients. The once-daily administration of up to 80 mg telmisartan to healthy subjects did not influence plasma aldosterone concentrations. In multiple dose studies with hypertensive patients, there were no clinically significant changes in electrolytes (serum potassium or sodium), or in metabolic function (including serum levels of cholesterol, triglycerides, HDL, LDL, glucose, or uric acid). In 30 hypertensive patients with normal renal function treated for 8 weeks with telmisartan 80 mg or telmisartan 80 mg in combination with hydrochlorothiazide 12.5 mg, there were no clinically significant changes from baseline in renal blood flow, glomerular filtration rate, filtration fraction, renovascular resistance, or creatinine clearance.          Following oral administration, peak concentrations (Cmax) of telmisartan are reached in 0.5 to 1 hour after dosing. Food slightly reduces the bioavailability of telmisartan, with a reduction in the area under the plasma concentration-time curve (AUC) of about 6% with the 40 mg tablet and about 20% after a 160 mg dose. The absolute bioavailability of telmisartan is dose dependent. At 40 and 160 mg the bioavailability was 42% and 58%, respectively. The pharmacokinetics of orally administered telmisartan are nonlinear over the dose range 20 to 160 mg, with greater than proportional increases of plasma concentrations (Cmax and AUC) with increasing doses. Telmisartan shows bi-exponential decay kinetics with a terminal elimination half life of approximately 24 hours. Trough plasma concentrations of telmisartan with once daily dosing are about 10% to 25% of peak plasma concentrations. Telmisartan has an accumulation index in plasma of 1.5 to 2.0 upon repeated once daily dosing.   Distribution  Telmisartan is highly bound to plasma proteins (&amp;gt;99.5%), mainly albumin and α1 - acid glycoprotein. Plasma protein binding is constant over the concentration range achieved with recommended doses. The volume of distribution for telmisartan is approximately 500 liters indicating additional tissue binding.   Metabolism and Elimination  Following either intravenous or oral administration of 14C-labeled telmisartan, most of the administered dose (&amp;gt;97%) was eliminated unchanged in feces via biliary excretion; only minute amounts were found in the urine (0.91% and 0.49% of total radioactivity, respectively). Telmisartan is metabolized by conjugation to form a pharmacologically inactive acyl glucuronide; the glucuronide of the parent compound is the only metabolite that has been identified in human plasma and urine. After a single dose, the glucuronide represents approximately 11% of the measured radioactivity in plasma. The cytochrome P450 isoenzymes are not involved in the metabolism of telmisartan. Total plasma clearance of telmisartan is &amp;gt;800 mL/min. Terminal half-life and total clearance appear to be independent of dose.   Specific Populations    Renal Insufficiency  No dosage adjustment is necessary in patients with decreased renal function. Telmisartan is not removed from blood by hemofiltration  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.5) and Dosage and Administration (2.1)] .   Hepatic Insufficiency  In patients with hepatic insufficiency, plasma concentrations of telmisartan are increased, and absolute bioavailability approaches 100%  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.4) and Use in Specific Populations (8.6)] .   Gender  Plasma concentrations of telmisartan are generally 2 to 3 times higher in females than in males. In clinical trials, however, no significant increases in blood pressure response or in the incidence of orthostatic hypotension were found in women. No dosage adjustment is necessary.   Geriatric Patients  The pharmacokinetics of telmisartan do not differ between the elderly and those younger than 65 years  [see Dosage and Administration (2.1)] .   Pediatric Patients  Telmisartan pharmacokinetics have not been investigated in patients &amp;lt;18 years of age.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="2989" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>When pregnancy is detected, discontinue MICARDIS as soon as possible.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2990" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause injury and death to the developing fetus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2991" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>WARNING: FETAL TOXICITY See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2992" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>When pregnancy is detected, discontinue MICARDIS as soon as possible (5.1, 8.1) Drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause injury and death to the developing fetus (5.1, 8.1)</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2993" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>MICARDIS is contraindicated in patients with known hypersensitivity (e.g., anaphylaxis or angioedema) to telmisartan or any other component of this product.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2994" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Do not co-administer aliskiren with MICARDIS in patients with diabetes.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M1" type="Trigger" span="0 20" str="Do not co-administer"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="21 9" str="aliskiren" code="502FWN4Q32"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M1" precipitant="M2"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2995" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Known hypersensitivity (e.g., anaphylaxis or angioedema) to telmisartan or any other component of this product (4) Do not co-administer aliskiren with MICARDIS in patients with diabetes (4)</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M3" type="Trigger" span="115 20" str="Do not co-administer"/>
<Mention id="M4" type="Precipitant" span="136 9" str="aliskiren" code="502FWN4Q32"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M3" precipitant="M4"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2996" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>May be administered with or without food (2.1) When used for cardiovascular risk reduction, monitoring of blood pressure is recommended, and if appropriate, adjustment of medications that lower blood pressure may be necessary (2.2) Indication Starting Dose Dose Range Hypertension (2.1) 40 mg once daily 40 to 80 mg once daily Cardiovascular Risk Reduction (2.2) 80 mg once daily 80 mg once daily Dosage must be individualized.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2997" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The usual starting dose of MICARDIS tablets is 40 mg once a day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2998" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Blood pressure response is dose-related over the range of 20 to 80 mg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2999" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Most of the antihypertensive effect is apparent within 2 weeks and maximal reduction is generally attained after 4 weeks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3000" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>When additional blood pressure reduction beyond that achieved with 80 mg MICARDIS is required, a diuretic may be added.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3001" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>No initial dosage adjustment is necessary for elderly patients or patients with renal impairment, including those on hemodialysis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3002" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Patients on dialysis may develop orthostatic hypotension; their blood pressure should be closely monitored.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3003" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>MICARDIS tablets may be administered with other antihypertensive agents.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3004" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>MICARDIS tablets may be administered with or without food.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3005" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommended dose of MICARDIS tablets is 80 mg once a day and can be administered with or without food.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3006" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>It is not known whether doses lower than 80 mg of telmisartan are effective in reducing the risk of cardiovascular morbidity and mortality.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3007" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>When initiating MICARDIS therapy for cardiovascular risk reduction, monitoring of blood pressure is recommended, and if appropriate, adjustment of medications that lower blood pressure may be necessary.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M5" type="Trigger" span="133 25" str="adjustment of medications"/>
<Mention id="M6" type="Precipitant" span="147 37" str="medications that lower blood pressure" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M7" type="SpecificInteraction" span="164 20" str="lower blood pressure" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M5" precipitant="M6" effect="M7"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3008" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Aliskiren: Do not co-administer aliskiren with MICARDIS in patients with diabetes.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M8" type="Trigger" span="11 20" str="Do not co-administer"/>
<Mention id="M9" type="Precipitant" span="32 9" str="aliskiren" code="502FWN4Q32"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M8" precipitant="M9"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3009" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Avoid use of aliskiren with MICARDIS in patients with renal impairment (GFR &lt;60 mL/min).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M10" type="Trigger" span="0 9" str="Avoid use"/>
<Mention id="M11" type="Precipitant" span="13 9" str="aliskiren" code="502FWN4Q32"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M10" precipitant="M11"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3010" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Digoxin : When MICARDIS was co-administered with digoxin, median increases in digoxin peak plasma concentration (49%) and in trough concentration (20%) were observed.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M12" type="Trigger" span="65 9;125 20" str="increases | trough concentration"/>
<Mention id="M15" type="Precipitant" span="49 7" str="digoxin" code="73K4184T59"/>
<Mention id="M14" type="Trigger" span="65 9;86 25" str="increases | peak plasma concentration"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M12" precipitant="M15" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M14" precipitant="M15" effect="C54610"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3011" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Therefore, monitor digoxin levels when initiating, adjusting, and discontinuing telmisartan for the purpose of keeping the digoxin level within the therapeutic range.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M16" type="Trigger" span="11 7;27 6" str="monitor | levels"/>
<Mention id="M17" type="Precipitant" span="19 7" str="digoxin" code="73K4184T59"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M16" precipitant="M17"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3012" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Lithium : Reversible increases in serum lithium concentrations and toxicity have been reported during concomitant administration of lithium with angiotensin II receptor antagonists including MICARDIS.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M18" type="Trigger" span="21 18;48 14" str="increases in serum | concentrations "/>
<Mention id="M19" type="Trigger" span="67 8" str=" toxicity"/>
<Mention id="M20" type="Precipitant" span="40 7" str="lithium" code="9FN79X2M3F"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M18;M19" precipitant="M20" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3013" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Therefore, monitor serum lithium levels during concomitant use.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M21" type="Trigger" span="11 7;33 6" str="monitor | levels"/>
<Mention id="M22" type="Precipitant" span="25 7" str="lithium" code="9FN79X2M3F"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M21" precipitant="M22"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3014" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Non-Steroidal Anti-Inflammatory Agents including Selective Cyclooxygenase-2 Inhibitors (COX-2 Inhibitors): In patients who are elderly, volume-depleted (including those on diuretic therapy), or with compromised renal function, co-administration of NSAIDs, including selective COX-2 inhibitors, with angiotensin II receptor antagonists, including telmisartan, may result in deterioration of renal function, including possible acute renal failure.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M50" type="Trigger" span="363 9" str="result in"/>
<Mention id="M27" type="Precipitant" span="88 16" str="COX-2 Inhibitors" code="N0000008288"/>
<Mention id="M52" type="SpecificInteraction" span="425 19" str="acute renal failure" code="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M49" type="SpecificInteraction" span="373 31" str="deterioration of renal function" code="236423003: Renal impairment (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M33" type="Precipitant" span="0 38" str="Non-Steroidal Anti-Inflammatory Agents" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M39" type="Precipitant" span="248 6" str="NSAIDs" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M45" type="Precipitant" span="266 26" str="selective COX-2 inhibitors" code="N0000008288"/>
<Mention id="M51" type="Precipitant" span="49 37" str="Selective Cyclooxygenase-2 Inhibitors" code="N0000008288"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M50" precipitant="M27" effect="M52"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M50" precipitant="M27" effect="M49"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M50" precipitant="M33" effect="M52"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M50" precipitant="M33" effect="M49"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M50" precipitant="M39" effect="M49"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M50" precipitant="M39" effect="M52"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M50" precipitant="M45" effect="M49"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M50" precipitant="M45" effect="M52"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M50" precipitant="M51" effect="M49"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M50" precipitant="M51" effect="M52"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3015" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor renal function periodically in patients receiving telmisartan and NSAID therapy.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M53" type="Trigger" span="0 7" str="Monitor"/>
<Mention id="M54" type="Precipitant" span="74 5" str="NSAID" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M55" type="SpecificInteraction" span="8 14" str="renal function" code="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M53" precipitant="M54" effect="M55"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3016" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The antihypertensive effect of angiotensin II receptor antagonists, including telmisartan may be attenuated by NSAIDs including selective COX-2 inhibitors.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M59" type="Trigger" span="21 6;97 10" str="effect | attenuated"/>
<Mention id="M57" type="Precipitant" span="111 6" str="NSAIDs" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M61" type="SpecificInteraction" span="4 23;97 10" str="antihypertensive effect | attenuated" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M60" type="Precipitant" span="128 26" str="selective COX-2 inhibitors" code="N0000008288"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M59" precipitant="M57" effect="M61"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M59" precipitant="M60" effect="M61"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3017" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>NSAIDs: Increased risk of renal impairment and loss of anti-hypertensive effect (7) Do not co-administer aliskiren with MICARDIS in patients with diabetes (7)</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M65" type="Trigger" span="8 14" str="Increased risk"/>
<Mention id="M66" type="Precipitant" span="0 6" str="NSAIDs" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M64" type="SpecificInteraction" span="26 16" str="renal impairment" code="236423003: Renal impairment (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M67" type="SpecificInteraction" span="47 32" str="loss of anti-hypertensive effect" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M68" type="Trigger" span="84 20" str="Do not co-administer"/>
<Mention id="M69" type="Precipitant" span="105 9" str="aliskiren" code="502FWN4Q32"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M65" precipitant="M66" effect="M64"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M65" precipitant="M66" effect="M67"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M68" precipitant="M69"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3018" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Avoid fetal or neonatal exposure (5.1) Hypotension: Correct any volume or salt depletion before initiating therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3019" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Observe for signs and symptoms of hypotension (5.2) Monitor carefully in patients with impaired hepatic (5.4) or renal function (5.5) Avoid concomitant use of an ACE inhibitor and angiotensin receptor blocker (5.6) Use of drugs that act on the renin-angiotensin system during the second and third trimesters of pregnancy reduces fetal renal function and increases fetal and neonatal morbidity and death.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M70" type="Trigger" span="134 5" str="Avoid"/>
<Mention id="M71" type="Precipitant" span="162 13" str="ACE inhibitor" code="N0000175562"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M70" precipitant="M71"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3020" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Resulting oligohydramnios can be associated with fetal lung hypoplasia and skeletal deformations.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3021" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Potential neonatal adverse effects include skull hypoplasia, anuria, hypotension, renal failure, and death.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3022" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In patients with an activated renin-angiotensin system, such as volume- or salt-depleted patients (e.g., those being treated with high doses of diuretics), symptomatic hypotension may occur after initiation of therapy with MICARDIS.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M74" type="SpecificInteraction" span="156 23" str="symptomatic hypotension" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M73" type="Precipitant" span="144 9" str="diuretics" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M74" precipitant="M73" effect="M74"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3023" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Either correct this condition prior to administration of MICARDIS, or start treatment under close medical supervision with a reduced dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3024" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If hypotension does occur, the patient should be placed in the supine position and, if necessary, given an intravenous infusion of normal saline.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3025" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>A transient hypotensive response is not a contraindication to further treatment, which usually can be continued without difficulty once the blood pressure has stabilized.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3026" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hyperkalemia may occur in patients on ARBs, particularly in patients with advanced renal impairment, heart failure, on renal replacement therapy, or on potassium supplements, potassium-sparing diuretics, potassium-containing salt substitutes or other drugs that increase potassium levels.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M84" type="Trigger" span="0 12" str="Hyperkalemia"/>
<Mention id="M76" type="Precipitant" span="251 36" str="drugs that increase potassium levels" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M86" type="SpecificInteraction" span="-1 12" str="hyperkalemia" code="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M79" type="Precipitant" span="152 21" str="potassium supplements" code="RWP5GA015D"/>
<Mention id="M82" type="Precipitant" span="204 37" str="potassium-containing salt substitutes" code="N0000175600"/>
<Mention id="M85" type="Precipitant" span="175 27" str="potassium-sparing diuretics" code="N0000175418"/>
<Interaction id="I29" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M84" precipitant="M76" effect="M86"/>
<Interaction id="I30" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M84" precipitant="M79" effect="M86"/>
<Interaction id="I31" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M84" precipitant="M82" effect="M86"/>
<Interaction id="I32" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M84" precipitant="M85" effect="M86"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3027" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Consider periodic determinations of serum electrolytes to detect possible electrolyte imbalances, particularly in patients at risk.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3028" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>As the majority of telmisartan is eliminated by biliary excretion, patients with biliary obstructive disorders or hepatic insufficiency can be expected to have reduced clearance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3029" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Initiate telmisartan at low doses and titrate slowly in these patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3030" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>As a consequence of inhibiting the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system, anticipate changes in renal function in susceptible individuals.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3031" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In patients whose renal function may depend on the activity of the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system (e.g., patients with severe congestive heart failure or renal dysfunction), treatment with angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE) inhibitors and angiotensin receptor antagonists has been associated with oliguria and/or progressive azotemia and (rarely) with acute renal failure and/or death.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3032" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Similar results have been reported with MICARDIS.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3033" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In studies of ACE inhibitors in patients with unilateral or bilateral renal artery stenosis, increases in serum creatinine or blood urea nitrogen were observed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3034" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There has been no long-term use of MICARDIS in patients with unilateral or bilateral renal artery stenosis, but anticipate an effect similar to that seen with ACE inhibitors.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3035" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Dual blockade of the RAS with angiotensin-receptor blockers, ACE inhibitors, or aliskiren is associated with increased risks of hypotension, hyperkalemia, and changes in renal function (including acute renal failure) compared to monotherapy.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M131" type="Trigger" span="93 15" str="associated with "/>
<Mention id="M132" type="Trigger" span="109 15" str=" increased risks"/>
<Mention id="M101" type="Precipitant" span="61 14" str="ACE inhibitors" code="N0000175562"/>
<Mention id="M134" type="SpecificInteraction" span="141 12" str="hyperkalemia" code="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M122" type="SpecificInteraction" span="159 25" str="changes in renal function" code="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M126" type="SpecificInteraction" span="196 19" str="acute renal failure" code="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M130" type="SpecificInteraction" span="128 11" str="hypotension" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M117" type="Precipitant" span="80 9" str="aliskiren" code="502FWN4Q32"/>
<Mention id="M133" type="Precipitant" span="0 24" str="Dual blockade of the RAS" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I33" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M131;M132" precipitant="M101" effect="M134"/>
<Interaction id="I34" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M131;M132" precipitant="M101" effect="M122"/>
<Interaction id="I35" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M131;M132" precipitant="M101" effect="M126"/>
<Interaction id="I36" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M131;M132" precipitant="M101" effect="M130"/>
<Interaction id="I37" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M131;M132" precipitant="M117" effect="M134"/>
<Interaction id="I38" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M131;M132" precipitant="M117" effect="M130"/>
<Interaction id="I39" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M131;M132" precipitant="M117" effect="M122"/>
<Interaction id="I40" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M131;M132" precipitant="M117" effect="M126"/>
<Interaction id="I41" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M131;M132" precipitant="M133" effect="M122"/>
<Interaction id="I42" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M131;M132" precipitant="M133" effect="M126"/>
<Interaction id="I43" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M131;M132" precipitant="M133" effect="M130"/>
<Interaction id="I44" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M131;M132" precipitant="M133" effect="M134"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3036" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The ONTARGET trial enrolled 25,620 patients ≥55 years old with atherosclerotic disease or diabetes with end-organ damage, randomizing them to telmisartan only, ramipril only, or the combination, and followed them for a median of 56 months.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3037" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients receiving the combination of MICARDIS and ramipril did not obtain any additional benefit compared to monotherapy, but experienced an increased incidence of renal dysfunction (e.g., acute renal failure) compared with groups receiving telmisartan alone or ramipril alone.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M138" type="Trigger" span="142 19" str="increased incidence"/>
<Mention id="M139" type="Precipitant" span="51 8" str="ramipril" code="L35JN3I7SJ"/>
<Mention id="M137" type="SpecificInteraction" span="165 17" str="renal dysfunction" code="236423003: Renal impairment (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M140" type="SpecificInteraction" span="190 19" str="acute renal failure" code="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I45" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M138" precipitant="M139" effect="M137"/>
<Interaction id="I46" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M138" precipitant="M139" effect="M140"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3038" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In most patients no benefit has been associated with using two RAS inhibitors concomitantly.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3039" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In general, avoid combined use of RAS inhibitors.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M141" type="Trigger" span="12 5" str="avoid"/>
<Mention id="M142" type="Precipitant" span="34 14" str="RAS inhibitors" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I47" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M141" precipitant="M142"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3040" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Closely monitor blood pressure, renal function, and electrolytes in patients on MICARDIS and other agents that affect the RAS.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M149" type="Trigger" span="0 15" str="Closely monitor"/>
<Mention id="M150" type="Precipitant" span="99 26" str="agents that affect the RAS" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M145" type="SpecificInteraction" span="32 14" str="renal function" code="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M148" type="SpecificInteraction" span="52 12" str="electrolytes" code="166686006: Electrolytes abnormal (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M151" type="SpecificInteraction" span="16 14" str="blood pressure" code="38936003: Abnormal blood pressure (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I48" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M149" precipitant="M150" effect="M145"/>
<Interaction id="I49" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M149" precipitant="M150" effect="M148"/>
<Interaction id="I50" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M149" precipitant="M150" effect="M151"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3041" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Avoid concomitant use of aliskiren with MICARDIS in patients with renal impairment (GFR &lt;60 mL/min/1.73 m2).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M152" type="Trigger" span="0 5" str="Avoid"/>
<Mention id="M153" type="Precipitant" span="25 9" str="aliskiren" code="502FWN4Q32"/>
<Interaction id="I51" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M152" precipitant="M153"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3042" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Angiotensin II is formed from angiotensin I in a reaction catalyzed by angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE, kininase II).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3043" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Angiotensin II is the principal pressor agent of the renin-angiotensin system, with effects that include vasoconstriction, stimulation of synthesis and release of aldosterone, cardiac stimulation, and renal reabsorption of sodium.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3044" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Telmisartan blocks the vasoconstrictor and aldosterone-secreting effects of angiotensin II by selectively blocking the binding of angiotensin II to the AT1 receptor in many tissues, such as vascular smooth muscle and the adrenal gland.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3045" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Its action is therefore independent of the pathways for angiotensin II synthesis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3046" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There is also an AT2 receptor found in many tissues, but AT2 is not known to be associated with cardiovascular homeostasis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3047" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Telmisartan has much greater affinity (&gt;3,000 fold) for the AT1 receptor than for the AT2 receptor.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3048" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Blockade of the renin-angiotensin system with ACE inhibitors, which inhibit the biosynthesis of angiotensin II from angiotensin I, is widely used in the treatment of hypertension.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3049" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>ACE inhibitors also inhibit the degradation of bradykinin, a reaction also catalyzed by ACE.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3050" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Because telmisartan does not inhibit ACE (kininase II), it does not affect the response to bradykinin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3051" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Whether this difference has clinical relevance is not yet known.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3052" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Telmisartan does not bind to or block other hormone receptors or ion channels known to be important in cardiovascular regulation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3053" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Blockade of the angiotensin II receptor inhibits the negative regulatory feedback of angiotensin II on renin secretion, but the resulting increased plasma renin activity and angiotensin II circulating levels do not overcome the effect of telmisartan on blood pressure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3054" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In normal volunteers, a dose of telmisartan 80 mg inhibited the pressor response to an intravenous infusion of angiotensin II by about 90% at peak plasma concentrations with approximately 40% inhibition persisting for 24 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3055" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Plasma concentration of angiotensin II and plasma renin activity (PRA) increased in a dose-dependent manner after single administration of telmisartan to healthy subjects and repeated administration to hypertensive patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3056" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The once-daily administration of up to 80 mg telmisartan to healthy subjects did not influence plasma aldosterone concentrations.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3057" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In multiple dose studies with hypertensive patients, there were no clinically significant changes in electrolytes (serum potassium or sodium), or in metabolic function (including serum levels of cholesterol, triglycerides, HDL, LDL, glucose, or uric acid).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3058" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In 30 hypertensive patients with normal renal function treated for 8 weeks with telmisartan 80 mg or telmisartan 80 mg in combination with hydrochlorothiazide 12.5 mg, there were no clinically significant changes from baseline in renal blood flow, glomerular filtration rate, filtration fraction, renovascular resistance, or creatinine clearance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3059" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Absorption: Following oral administration, peak concentrations (Cmax) of telmisartan are reached in 0.5 to 1 hour after dosing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3060" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Food slightly reduces the bioavailability of telmisartan, with a reduction in the area under the plasma concentration-time curve (AUC) of about 6% with the 40 mg tablet and about 20% after a 160 mg dose.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M154" type="Trigger" span="14 27" str="reduces the bioavailability"/>
<Mention id="M159" type="Precipitant" span="0 4" str="Food" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M156" type="Trigger" span="65 9;130 3" str="reduction | AUC"/>
<Mention id="M158" type="Trigger" span="65 63" str="reduction in the area under the plasma concentration-time curve"/>
<Interaction id="I52" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M154" precipitant="M159" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I53" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M156" precipitant="M159" effect="C54609"/>
<Interaction id="I54" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M158" precipitant="M159" effect="C54609"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3061" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The absolute bioavailability of telmisartan is dose dependent.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3062" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>At 40 and 160 mg the bioavailability was 42% and 58%, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3063" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacokinetics of orally administered telmisartan are nonlinear over the dose range 20 to 160 mg, with greater than proportional increases of plasma concentrations (Cmax and AUC) with increasing doses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3064" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Telmisartan shows bi-exponential decay kinetics with a terminal elimination half-life of approximately 24 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3065" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Trough plasma concentrations of telmisartan with once daily dosing are about 10% to 25% of peak plasma concentrations.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3066" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Telmisartan has an accumulation index in plasma of 1.5 to 2.0 upon repeated once daily dosing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3067" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Distribution Telmisartan is highly bound to plasma proteins (&gt;99.5%), mainly albumin and α1 - acid glycoprotein.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3068" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Plasma protein binding is constant over the concentration range achieved with recommended doses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3069" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The volume of distribution for telmisartan is approximately 500 liters indicating additional tissue binding.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3070" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Metabolism and Elimination Following either intravenous or oral administration of 14C-labeled telmisartan, most of the administered dose (&gt;97%) was eliminated unchanged in feces via biliary excretion; only minute amounts were found in the urine (0.91% and 0.49% of total radioactivity, respectively).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3071" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Telmisartan is metabolized by conjugation to form a pharmacologically inactive acyl glucuronide; the glucuronide of the parent compound is the only metabolite that has been identified in human plasma and urine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3072" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>After a single dose, the glucuronide represents approximately 11% of the measured radioactivity in plasma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3073" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The cytochrome P450 isoenzymes are not involved in the metabolism of telmisartan.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3074" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Total plasma clearance of telmisartan is &gt;800 mL/min.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3075" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Terminal half-life and total clearance appear to be independent of dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3076" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Specific Populations Renal Insufficiency No dosage adjustment is necessary in patients with decreased renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3077" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Telmisartan is not removed from blood by hemofiltration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3078" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Hepatic Insufficiency In patients with hepatic insufficiency, plasma concentrations of telmisartan are increased, and absolute bioavailability approaches 100%.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3079" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Gender Plasma concentrations of telmisartan are generally 2 to 3 times higher in females than in males.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3080" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In clinical trials, however, no significant increases in blood pressure response or in the incidence of orthostatic hypotension were found in women.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3081" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Geriatric Patients The pharmacokinetics of telmisartan do not differ between the elderly and those younger than 65 years.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3082" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Pediatric Patients Telmisartan pharmacokinetics have not been investigated in patients &lt;18 years of age.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3083" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Drug Interaction Studies Telmisartan Ramipril and Ramiprilat: Co-administration of telmisartan 80 mg once daily and ramipril 10 mg once daily to healthy subjects increases steady-state Cmax and AUC of ramipril 2.3- and 2.1-fold, respectively, and Cmax and AUC of ramiprilat 2.4- and 1.5-fold, respectively.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M160" type="Trigger" span="162 27" str="increases steady-state Cmax"/>
<Mention id="M163" type="Precipitant" span="116 8" str="ramipril" code="L35JN3I7SJ"/>
<Mention id="M166" type="Trigger" span="162 9;194 3" str="increases | AUC"/>
<Mention id="M164" type="Trigger" span="162 9;185 4" str="increases | Cmax"/>
<Mention id="M167" type="Precipitant" span="263 10" str="ramiprilat" code="6N5U4QFC3G"/>
<Interaction id="I55" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M160" precipitant="M163" effect="C54610"/>
<Interaction id="I56" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M166" precipitant="M163" effect="C54613"/>
<Interaction id="I57" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M164" precipitant="M167" effect="C54610"/>
<Interaction id="I58" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M166" precipitant="M167" effect="C54613"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3084" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In contrast, Cmax and AUC of telmisartan decrease by 31% and 16%, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3085" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>When co-administering telmisartan and ramipril, the response may be greater because of the possibly additive pharmacodynamic effects of the combined drugs, and also because of the increased exposure to ramipril and ramiprilat in the presence of telmisartan.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M172" type="Trigger" span="52 23" str="response may be greater "/>
<Mention id="M173" type="Trigger" span="100 32" str=" additive pharmacodynamic effects"/>
<Mention id="M177" type="Precipitant" span="38 8" str="ramipril" code="L35JN3I7SJ"/>
<Mention id="M171" type="SpecificInteraction" span="52 23" str="response may be greater" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M175" type="SpecificInteraction" span="100 32" str="additive pharmacodynamic effects" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M178" type="Trigger" span="180 18" str="increased exposure"/>
<Mention id="M179" type="Precipitant" span="215 10" str="ramiprilat" code="6N5U4QFC3G"/>
<Interaction id="I59" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M172;M173" precipitant="M177" effect="M171"/>
<Interaction id="I60" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M172;M173" precipitant="M177" effect="M175"/>
<Interaction id="I61" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M178" precipitant="M177" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I62" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M178" precipitant="M179" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3086" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Other Drugs: Co-administration of telmisartan did not result in a clinically significant interaction with acetaminophen, amlodipine, glyburide, simvastatin, hydrochlorothiazide, warfarin, or ibuprofen.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3087" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Telmisartan is not metabolized by the cytochrome P450 system and had no effects in vitro on cytochrome P450 enzymes, except for some inhibition of CYP2C19.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3088" LabelDrug="Micardis" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Telmisartan is not expected to interact with drugs that inhibit cytochrome P450 enzymes; it is also not expected to interact with drugs metabolized by cytochrome P450 enzymes, except for possible inhibition of the metabolism of drugs metabolized by CYP2C19.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M180" type="Trigger" span="196 28" str="inhibition of the metabolism"/>
<Mention id="M181" type="Precipitant" span="228 28" str="drugs metabolized by CYP2C19" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I63" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M180" precipitant="M181" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="aliskiren" precipitantCode="502FWN4Q32" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="aliskiren" precipitantCode="502FWN4Q32" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="aliskiren" precipitantCode="502FWN4Q32" effect="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="aliskiren" precipitantCode="502FWN4Q32" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="aliskiren" precipitantCode="502FWN4Q32"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="medications that lower blood pressure" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="digoxin" precipitantCode="73K4184T59" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="digoxin" precipitantCode="73K4184T59" effect="C54610"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="digoxin" precipitantCode="73K4184T59"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="lithium" precipitantCode="9FN79X2M3F" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="lithium" precipitantCode="9FN79X2M3F"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cox-2 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000008288" effect=" 39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cox-2 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000008288" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cox-2 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000008288" effect="236423003: Renal impairment (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agents" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect=" 39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agents" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agents" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="236423003: Renal impairment (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nsaids" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect=" 39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nsaids" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nsaids" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="236423003: Renal impairment (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nsaids" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="selective cox-2 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000008288" effect=" 39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="selective cox-2 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000008288" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="selective cox-2 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000008288" effect="236423003: Renal impairment (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="selective cox-2 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000008288" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="selective cyclooxygenase-2 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000008288" effect=" 39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="selective cyclooxygenase-2 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000008288" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="selective cyclooxygenase-2 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000008288" effect="236423003: Renal impairment (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nsaid" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="ace inhibitor" precipitantCode="N0000175562"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="diuretics" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="drugs that increase potassium levels" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="potassium supplements" precipitantCode="RWP5GA015D" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="potassium-containing salt substitutes" precipitantCode="N0000175600" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="potassium-sparing diuretics" precipitantCode="N0000175418" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ace inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175562" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ace inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175562" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ace inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175562" effect="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ace inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175562" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="dual blockade of the ras" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="dual blockade of the ras" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="dual blockade of the ras" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="dual blockade of the ras" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ramipril" precipitantCode="L35JN3I7SJ" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ramipril" precipitantCode="L35JN3I7SJ" effect="236423003: Renal impairment (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ramipril" precipitantCode="L35JN3I7SJ" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="ramipril" precipitantCode="L35JN3I7SJ" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="ramipril" precipitantCode="L35JN3I7SJ" effect="C54610"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="ramipril" precipitantCode="L35JN3I7SJ" effect="C54613"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="ras inhibitors" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="agents that affect the ras" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="166686006: Electrolytes abnormal (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="agents that affect the ras" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="38936003: Abnormal blood pressure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="agents that affect the ras" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="food" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="food" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54609"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="ramiprilat" precipitantCode="6N5U4QFC3G" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="ramiprilat" precipitantCode="6N5U4QFC3G" effect="C54610"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="ramiprilat" precipitantCode="6N5U4QFC3G" effect="C54613"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="drugs metabolized by cyp2c19" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54357"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>