<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Microzide" setid="afbefaff-97c4-4f84-b989-1595f882a885">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
Hydrochlorothiazide is contraindicated in patients with anuria. Hypersensitivity to this product or other sulfonamide derived drugs is also contraindicated.</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
For Control of Hypertension: The adult initial dose of MICROZIDE is one capsule given once daily whether given alone or in combination with other antihypertensives. Total daily doses greater than 50 mg are not recommended.</Section>
<Section name="PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="42232-9">
Electrolyte and Fluid Balance Status: In published studies, clinically significant hypokalemia has been consistently less common in patients who received 12.5 mg of hydrochlorothiazide than in patients who received higher doses. Nevertheless, periodic determination of serum electrolytes should be performed in patients who may be at risk for the development of hypokalemia. Patients should be observed for signs of fluid or electrolyte disturbances, i.e., hyponatremia, hypochloremic alkalosis, and hypokalemia and hypomagnesemia. Warning signs or symptoms of fluid and electrolyte imbalance include dryness of mouth, thirst, weakness, lethargy, drowsiness, restlessness, muscle pains or cramps, muscular fatigue, hypotension, oliguria, tachycardia, and gastrointestinal disturbances such as nausea and vomiting. Hypokalemia may develop, especially with brisk diuresis when severe cirrhosis is present, during concomitant use of corticosteroid or adrenocorticotropic hormone (ACTH) or after prolonged therapy. Interference with adequate oral electrolyte intake will also contribute to hypokalemia. Hypokalemia and hypomagnesemia can provoke ventricular arrhythmias or sensitize or exaggerate the response of the heart to the toxic effects of digitalis. Hypokalemia may be avoided or treated by potassium supplementation or increased intake of potassium rich foods. Dilutional hyponatremia is life-threatening and may occur in edematous patients in hot weather; appropriate therapy is water restriction rather than salt administration, except in rare instances when the hyponatremia is life-threatening. In actual salt depletion, appropriate replacement is the therapy of choice.  Hyperuricemia: Hyperuricemia or acute gout may be precipitated in certain patients receiving thiazide diuretics.  Impaired Hepatic Function: Thiazides should be used with caution in patients with impaired hepatic function. They can precipitate hepatic coma in patients with severe liver disease.  Parathyroid Disease: Calcium excretion is decreased by thiazides, and pathologic changes in the parathyroid glands, with hypercalcemia and hypophosphatemia, have been observed in a few patients on prolonged thiazide therapy.  Drug Interactions: When given concurrently the following drugs may interact with thiazide diuretics:  Alcohol, barbiturates, or narcotics - potentiation of orthostatic hypotension may occur.  Antidiabetic drugs - (oral agents and insulin) dosage adjustment of the antidiabetic drug may be required.  Other antihypertensive drugs - additive effect or potentiation.  Cholestyramine and colestipol resins - Cholestyramine and colestipol resins bind the hydrochlorothiazide and reduce its absorption from the gastrointestinal tract by up to 85 and 43 percent, respectively.  Corticosteroid, ACTH – intensified electrolyte depletion, particularly hypokalemia.  Pressor amines (e.g., norepinephrine) - possible decreased response to pressor amines but not sufficient to preclude their use.  Skeletal muscle relaxants, nondepolarizing (e.g., tubocurarine) - possible increased responsiveness to the muscle relaxant.  Lithium - generally should not be given with diuretics. Diuretic agents reduce the renal clearance of lithium and greatly increase the risk of lithium toxicity. Refer to the package insert for lithium preparations before use of such preparations with MICROZIDE.  Non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs - In some patients, the administration of a non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agent can reduce the diuretic, natriuretic, and antihypertensive effects of loop, potassium-sparing and thiazide diuretics. When MICROZIDE and non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agents are used concomitantly, the patients should be observed closely to determine if the desired effect of the diuretic is obtained.  Drug/Laboratory Test Interactions - Thiazides should be discontinued before carrying out tests for parathyroid function (see   PRECAUTIONS, General  ).  Carcinogenesis, Mutagenesis, Impairment of Fertility: Two-year feeding studies in mice and rats conducted under the auspices of the National Toxicology Program (NTP) uncovered no evidence of a carcinogenic potential of hydrochlorothiazide in female mice (at doses of up to approximately 600 mg/kg/day) or in male and female rats (at doses of approximately 100 mg/kg/day). The NTP, however, found equivocal evidence for hepatocarcinogenicity in male mice. Hydrochlorothiazide was not genotoxic in vitro in the Ames mutagenicity assay of Salmonella typhimurium strains TA 98, TA 100, TA 1535, TA 1537, and TA 1538 and in the Chinese Hamster Ovary (CHO) test for chromosomal aberrations, or in vivo in assays using mouse germinal cell chromosomes, Chinese hamster bone marrow chromosomes, and the Drosophila sex-linked recessive lethal trait gene. Positive test results were obtained only in the in vitro CHO Sister Chromatid Exchange (clastogenicity) and in the Mouse Lymphoma Cell (mutagenicity) assays, using concentrations of hydrochlorothiazide from 43 to 1300 mcg/mL, and in the Aspergillus nidulans non-disjunction assay at an unspecified concentration. Hydrochlorothiazide had no adverse effects on the fertility of mice and rats of either sex in studies wherein these species were exposed, via their diet, to doses of up to 100 and 4 mg/kg, respectively, prior to conception and throughout gestation.              Pregnancy Category B: Studies in which hydrochlorothiazide was orally administered to pregnant mice and rats during their respective periods of major organogenesis at doses up to 3000 and 1000 mg hydrochlorothiazide/kg, respectively, provided no evidence of harm to the fetus. There are, however, no adequate and well-controlled studies in pregnant women. Because animal reproduction studies are not always predictive of human response, this drug should be used during pregnancy only if clearly needed.          Thiazides cross the placental barrier and appear in cord blood. There is a risk of fetal or neonatal jaundice, thrombocytopenia, and possibly other adverse reactions that have occurred in adults.          Thiazides are excreted in breast milk. Because of the potential for serious adverse reactions in nursing infants, a decision should be made whether to discontinue nursing or to discontinue hydrochlorothiazide, taking into account the importance of the drug to the mother.            Safety and effectiveness in pediatric patients have not been established.          A greater blood pressure reduction and an increase in side effects may be observed in the elderly (i.e., &amp;gt; 65 years) with hydrochlorothiazide. Starting treatment with the lowest available dose of hydrochlorothiazide (12.5 mg) is therefore recommended. If further titration is required, 12.5 mg increments should be utilized.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS SECTION" id="34071-1">
Acute Myopia and Secondary Angle-Closure Glaucoma: Hydrochlorothiazide, a sulfonamide, can cause an idiosyncratic reaction, resulting in acute transient myopia and acute angle-closure glaucoma. Symptoms include acute onset of decreased visual acuity or ocular pain and typically occur within hours to weeks of drug initiation. Untreated acute angle-closure glaucoma can lead to permanent vision loss. The primary treatment is to discontinue hydrochlorothiazide as rapidly as possible. Prompt medical or surgical treatments may need to be considered if the intraocular pressure remains uncontrolled. Risk factors for developing acute angle-closure glaucoma may include a history of sulfonamide or penicillin allergy.  Diabetes and Hypoglycemia: Latent diabetes mellitus may become manifest and diabetic patients given thiazides may require adjustment of their insulin dose.  Renal Disease: Cumulative effects of the thiazides may develop in patients with impaired renal function. In such patients, thiazides may precipitate azotemia.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Hydrochlorothiazide blocks the reabsorption of sodium and chloride ions, and it thereby increases the quantity of sodium traversing the distal tubule and the volume of water excreted. A portion of the additional sodium presented to the distal tubule is exchanged there for potassium and hydrogen ions. With continued use of hydrochlorothiazide and depletion of sodium, compensatory mechanisms tend to increase this exchange and may produce excessive loss of potassium, hydrogen and chloride ions. Hydrochlorothiazide also decreases the excretion of calcium and uric acid, may increase the excretion of iodide and may reduce glomerular filtration rate. Metabolic toxicities associated with excessive electrolyte changes caused by hydrochlorothiazide have been shown to be dose-related.        Hydrochlorothiazide is well absorbed (65% to 75%) following oral administration. Absorption of hydrochlorothiazide is reduced in patients with congestive heart failure. Peak plasma concentrations are observed within 1 to 5 hours of dosing, and range from 70 to 490 ng/mL following oral doses of 12.5 to 100 mg. Plasma concentrations are linearly related to the administered dose. Concentrations of hydrochlorothiazide are 1.6 to 1.8 times higher in whole blood than in plasma. Binding to serum proteins has been reported to be approximately 40% to 68%. The plasma elimination half-life has been reported to be 6 to 15 hours. Hydrochlorothiazide is eliminated primarily by renal pathways. Following oral doses of 12.5 to 100 mg, 55% to 77% of the administered dose appears in urine and greater than 95% of the absorbed dose is excreted in urine as unchanged drug. In patients with renal disease, plasma concentrations of hydrochlorothiazide are increased and the elimination half-life is prolonged. When MICROZIDE is administered with food, its bioavailability is reduced by 10%, the maximum plasma concentration is reduced by 20%, and the time to maximum concentration increases from 1.6 to 2.9 hours.          Acute antihypertensive effects of thiazides are thought to result from a reduction in blood volume and cardiac output, secondary to a natriuretic effect, although a direct vasodilatory mechanism has also been proposed. With chronic administration, plasma volume returns toward normal, but peripheral vascular resistance is decreased. The exact mechanism of the antihypertensive effect of hydrochlorothiazide is not known. Thiazides do not affect normal blood pressure. Onset of action occurs within 2 hours of dosing, peak effect is observed at about 4 hours, and activity persists for up to 24 hours.          In an 87 patient 4-week double-blind, placebo controlled, parallel group trial, patients who received MICROZIDE had reductions in seated systolic and diastolic blood pressure that were significantly greater than those seen in patients who received placebo. In published placebo-controlled trials comparing 12.5 mg of hydrochlorothiazide to 25 mg, the 12.5 mg dose preserved most of the placebo-corrected blood pressure reduction seen with 25 mg.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="5231" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Hydrochlorothiazide is contraindicated in patients with anuria.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5232" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Hypersensitivity to this product or other sulfonamide derived drugs is also contraindicated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5233" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For Control of Hypertension: The adult initial dose of MICROZIDE is one capsule given once daily whether given alone or in combination with other antihypertensives.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5234" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Total daily doses greater than 50 mg are not recommended.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5235" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Electrolyte and Fluid Balance Status: In published studies, clinically significant hypokalemia has been consistently less common in patients who received 12.5 mg of hydrochlorothiazide than in patients who received higher doses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5236" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Nevertheless, periodic determination of serum electrolytes should be performed in patients who may be at risk for the development of hypokalemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5237" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Patients should be observed for signs of fluid or electrolyte disturbances, i.e., hyponatremia, hypochloremic alkalosis, and hypokalemia and hypomagnesemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5238" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Warning signs or symptoms of fluid and electrolyte imbalance include dryness of mouth, thirst, weakness, lethargy, drowsiness, restlessness, muscle pains or cramps, muscular fatigue, hypotension, oliguria, tachycardia, and gastrointestinal disturbances such as nausea and vomiting.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5239" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Hypokalemia may develop, especially with brisk diuresis when severe cirrhosis is present, during concomitant use of corticosteroid or adrenocorticotropic hormone (ACTH) or after prolonged therapy.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M12" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 11" str="Hypokalemia" code="43339004: Hypokalemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="163 4" str="ACTH" code="K0U68Q2TXA"/>
<Mention id="M5" type="Precipitant" span="134 27" str="adrenocorticotropic hormone" code="K0U68Q2TXA"/>
<Mention id="M8" type="Precipitant" span="41 14" str="brisk diuresis" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M11" type="Precipitant" span="116 14" str="corticosteroid" code="N0000175576"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M12" precipitant="M2" effect="M12"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M12" precipitant="M5" effect="M12"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M12" precipitant="M8" effect="M12"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M12" precipitant="M11" effect="M12"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5240" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Interference with adequate oral electrolyte intake will also contribute to hypokalemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5241" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Hypokalemia and hypomagnesemia can provoke ventricular arrhythmias or sensitize or exaggerate the response of the heart to the toxic effects of digitalis.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M13" type="Trigger" span="70 23" str="sensitize or exaggerate"/>
<Mention id="M14" type="Precipitant" span="144 9" str="digitalis" code="F1T8QT9U8B"/>
<Mention id="M15" type="SpecificInteraction" span="98 55" str="response of the heart to the toxic effects of digitalis" code="12876009: Poisoning caused by digitalis glycoside (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M13" precipitant="M14" effect="M15"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5242" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Hypokalemia may be avoided or treated by potassium supplementation or increased intake of potassium rich foods.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5243" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Dilutional hyponatremia is life-threatening and may occur in edematous patients in hot weather; appropriate therapy is water restriction rather than salt administration, except in rare instances when the hyponatremia is life-threatening.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5244" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In actual salt depletion, appropriate replacement is the therapy of choice.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5245" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Hyperuricemia: Hyperuricemia or acute gout may be precipitated in certain patients receiving thiazide diuretics.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5246" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Impaired Hepatic Function: Thiazides should be used with caution in patients with impaired hepatic function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5247" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>They can precipitate hepatic coma in patients with severe liver disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5248" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Parathyroid Disease: Calcium excretion is decreased by thiazides, and pathologic changes in the parathyroid glands, with hypercalcemia and hypophosphatemia, have been observed in a few patients on prolonged thiazide therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5249" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Drug Interactions: When given concurrently the following drugs may interact with thiazide diuretics: Alcohol, barbiturates, or narcotics - potentiation of orthostatic hypotension may occur.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M22" type="Trigger" span="139 12" str="potentiation"/>
<Mention id="M17" type="Precipitant" span="101 7" str="Alcohol" code="3K9958V90M"/>
<Mention id="M24" type="SpecificInteraction" span="155 23" str="orthostatic hypotension" code="28651003: Orthostatic hypotension (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M20" type="Precipitant" span="110 12" str="barbiturates" code="N0000175693"/>
<Mention id="M23" type="Precipitant" span="127 9" str="narcotics" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M22" precipitant="M17" effect="M24"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M22" precipitant="M20" effect="M24"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M22" precipitant="M23" effect="M24"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5250" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Antidiabetic drugs - (oral agents and insulin) dosage adjustment of the antidiabetic drug may be required.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M31" type="Trigger" span="47 17" str="dosage adjustment"/>
<Mention id="M26" type="Precipitant" span="0 12;22 11" str="Antidiabetic | oral agents" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M28" type="Precipitant" span="72 17" str="antidiabetic drug" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M30" type="Precipitant" span="0 18" str="Antidiabetic drugs" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M32" type="Precipitant" span="38 7" str="insulin" code="N0000175944"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M31" precipitant="M26"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M31" precipitant="M28"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M31" precipitant="M30"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M31" precipitant="M32"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5251" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Other antihypertensive drugs - additive effect or potentiation.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M33" type="Trigger" span="31 15" str="additive effect "/>
<Mention id="M34" type="Trigger" span="50 12" str=" potentiation"/>
<Mention id="M35" type="Precipitant" span="6 22" str="antihypertensive drugs" code="N0000178477"/>
<Mention id="M36" type="SpecificInteraction" span="6 16;40 6" str="antihypertensive | effect" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M33;M34" precipitant="M35" effect="M36"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5252" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Cholestyramine and colestipol resins - Cholestyramine and colestipol resins bind the hydrochlorothiazide and reduce its absorption from the gastrointestinal tract by up to 85 and 43 percent, respectively.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M39" type="Trigger" span="109 21" str="reduce its absorption"/>
<Mention id="M38" type="Precipitant" span="0 14" str="Cholestyramine" code="4B33BGI082"/>
<Mention id="M40" type="Precipitant" span="19 17" str="colestipol resins" code="K50N755924"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M39" precipitant="M38" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M39" precipitant="M40" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5253" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Corticosteroid, ACTH – intensified electrolyte depletion, particularly hypokalemia.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M53" type="Trigger" span="23 33" str="intensified electrolyte depletion "/>
<Mention id="M54" type="Trigger" span="71 11" str=" hypokalemia"/>
<Mention id="M47" type="Precipitant" span="16 4" str="ACTH" code="K0U68Q2TXA"/>
<Mention id="M52" type="SpecificInteraction" span="71 11" str="hypokalemia" code="43339004: Hypokalemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M56" type="SpecificInteraction" span="23 33" str="intensified electrolyte depletion" code="166686006: Electrolytes abnormal (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M55" type="Precipitant" span="0 14" str="Corticosteroid" code="N0000175576"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M53;M54" precipitant="M47" effect="M52"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M53;M54" precipitant="M47" effect="M56"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M53;M54" precipitant="M55" effect="M52"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M53;M54" precipitant="M55" effect="M56"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5254" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Pressor amines (e.g., norepinephrine) - possible decreased response to pressor amines but not sufficient to preclude their use.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M60" type="Trigger" span="49 18" str="decreased response"/>
<Mention id="M58" type="Precipitant" span="22 14" str="norepinephrine" code="X4W3ENH1CV"/>
<Mention id="M62" type="SpecificInteraction" span="49 36" str="decreased response to pressor amines" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M61" type="Precipitant" span="71 14" str="pressor amines" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M60" precipitant="M58" effect="M62"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M60" precipitant="M61" effect="M62"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5255" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Skeletal muscle relaxants, nondepolarizing (e.g., tubocurarine) - possible increased responsiveness to the muscle relaxant.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M69" type="Trigger" span="75 24" str="increased responsiveness"/>
<Mention id="M64" type="Precipitant" span="9 15" str="muscle relaxant" code="N0000175737"/>
<Mention id="M71" type="SpecificInteraction" span="75 47" str="increased responsiveness to the muscle relaxant" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M67" type="Precipitant" span="0 42" str="Skeletal muscle relaxants, nondepolarizing" code="N0000175738"/>
<Mention id="M70" type="Precipitant" span="50 12" str="tubocurarine" code="W9YXS298BM"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M69" precipitant="M64" effect="M71"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M69" precipitant="M67" effect="M71"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M69" precipitant="M70" effect="M71"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5256" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Lithium - generally should not be given with diuretics.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M72" type="Trigger" span="20 19" str="should not be given"/>
<Mention id="M73" type="Precipitant" span="0 7" str="Lithium" code="9FN79X2M3F"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M72" precipitant="M73"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5257" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Diuretic agents reduce the renal clearance of lithium and greatly increase the risk of lithium toxicity.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M74" type="Trigger" span="16 26" str="reduce the renal clearance "/>
<Mention id="M75" type="Trigger" span="95 8" str=" toxicity"/>
<Mention id="M76" type="Precipitant" span="46 7" str="lithium" code="9FN79X2M3F"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M74;M75" precipitant="M76" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5258" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Refer to the package insert for lithium preparations before use of such preparations with MICROZIDE.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M77" type="Trigger" span="0 27" str="Refer to the package insert"/>
<Mention id="M78" type="Precipitant" span="32 20" str="lithium preparations" code="9FN79X2M3F"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M77" precipitant="M78"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5259" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs - In some patients, the administration of a non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agent can reduce the diuretic, natriuretic, and antihypertensive effects of loop, potassium-sparing and thiazide diuretics.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M94" type="Trigger" span="124 6;179 7" str="reduce | effects"/>
<Mention id="M86" type="Precipitant" span="82 37" str="non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agent" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M93" type="SpecificInteraction" span="124 6;162 24" str="reduce | antihypertensive effects" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M90" type="SpecificInteraction" span="124 6;145 11;179 7" str="reduce | natriuretic | effects" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M96" type="SpecificInteraction" span="124 19;179 7" str="reduce the diuretic | effects" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M95" type="Precipitant" span="0 37" str="Non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs" code="N0000175722"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M94" precipitant="M86" effect="M93"/>
<Interaction id="I29" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M94" precipitant="M86" effect="M90"/>
<Interaction id="I30" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M94" precipitant="M86" effect="M96"/>
<Interaction id="I31" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M94" precipitant="M95" effect="M90"/>
<Interaction id="I32" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M94" precipitant="M95" effect="M93"/>
<Interaction id="I33" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M94" precipitant="M95" effect="M96"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5260" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>When MICROZIDE and non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agents are used concomitantly, the patients should be observed closely to determine if the desired effect of the diuretic is obtained.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M97" type="Trigger" span="95 26" str="should be observed closely"/>
<Mention id="M98" type="Precipitant" span="19 38" str="non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agents" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M99" type="SpecificInteraction" span="150 22" str="effect of the diuretic" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I34" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M97" precipitant="M98" effect="M99"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5261" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Drug/Laboratory Test Interactions - Thiazides should be discontinued before carrying out tests for parathyroid function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5262" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Carcinogenesis, Mutagenesis, Impairment of Fertility: Two-year feeding studies in mice and rats conducted under the auspices of the National Toxicology Program (NTP) uncovered no evidence of a carcinogenic potential of hydrochlorothiazide in female mice (at doses of up to approximately 600 mg/kg/day) or in male and female rats (at doses of approximately 100 mg/kg/day).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5263" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The NTP, however, found equivocal evidence for hepatocarcinogenicity in male mice.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5264" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Hydrochlorothiazide was not genotoxic in vitro in the Ames mutagenicity assay of Salmonella typhimurium strains TA 98, TA 100, TA 1535, TA 1537, and TA 1538 and in the Chinese Hamster Ovary (CHO) test for chromosomal aberrations, or in vivo in assays using mouse germinal cell chromosomes, Chinese hamster bone marrow chromosomes, and the Drosophila sex-linked recessive lethal trait gene.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5265" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Positive test results were obtained only in the in vitro CHO Sister Chromatid Exchange (clastogenicity) and in the Mouse Lymphoma Cell (mutagenicity) assays, using concentrations of hydrochlorothiazide from 43 to 1300 mcg/mL, and in the Aspergillus nidulans non-disjunction assay at an unspecified concentration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5266" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Hydrochlorothiazide had no adverse effects on the fertility of mice and rats of either sex in studies wherein these species were exposed, via their diet, to doses of up to 100 and 4 mg/kg, respectively, prior to conception and throughout gestation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5267" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Pregnancy Category B: Studies in which hydrochlorothiazide was orally administered to pregnant mice and rats during their respective periods of major organogenesis at doses up to 3000 and 1000 mg hydrochlorothiazide/kg, respectively, provided no evidence of harm to the fetus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5268" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>There are, however, no adequate and well-controlled studies in pregnant women.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5269" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because animal reproduction studies are not always predictive of human response, this drug should be used during pregnancy only if clearly needed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5270" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Thiazides cross the placental barrier and appear in cord blood.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5271" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>There is a risk of fetal or neonatal jaundice, thrombocytopenia, and possibly other adverse reactions that have occurred in adults.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5272" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because of the potential for serious adverse reactions in nursing infants, a decision should be made whether to discontinue nursing or to discontinue hydrochlorothiazide, taking into account the importance of the drug to the mother.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5273" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Safety and effectiveness in pediatric patients have not been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5274" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>A greater blood pressure reduction and an increase in side effects may be observed in the elderly (i.e., &gt; 65 years) with hydrochlorothiazide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5275" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Starting treatment with the lowest available dose of hydrochlorothiazide (12.5 mg) is therefore recommended.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5276" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>If further titration is required, 12.5 mg increments should be utilized.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5277" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Acute Myopia and Secondary Angle-Closure Glaucoma: Hydrochlorothiazide, a sulfonamide, can cause an idiosyncratic reaction, resulting in acute transient myopia and acute angle-closure glaucoma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5278" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Symptoms include acute onset of decreased visual acuity or ocular pain and typically occur within hours to weeks of drug initiation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5279" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Untreated acute angle-closure glaucoma can lead to permanent vision loss.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5280" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The primary treatment is to discontinue hydrochlorothiazide as rapidly as possible.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5281" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Prompt medical or surgical treatments may need to be considered if the intraocular pressure remains uncontrolled.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5282" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Risk factors for developing acute angle-closure glaucoma may include a history of sulfonamide or penicillin allergy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5283" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Diabetes and Hypoglycemia: Latent diabetes mellitus may become manifest and diabetic patients given thiazides may require adjustment of their insulin dose.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M100" type="Trigger" span="122 10;150 4" str="adjustment | dose"/>
<Mention id="M101" type="Precipitant" span="142 7" str="insulin" code="N0000175944"/>
<Interaction id="I35" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M100" precipitant="M101"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5284" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Renal Disease: Cumulative effects of the thiazides may develop in patients with impaired renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5285" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>In such patients, thiazides may precipitate azotemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5286" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Hydrochlorothiazide blocks the reabsorption of sodium and chloride ions, and it thereby increases the quantity of sodium traversing the distal tubule and the volume of water excreted.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5287" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A portion of the additional sodium presented to the distal tubule is exchanged there for potassium and hydrogen ions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5288" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>With continued use of hydrochlorothiazide and depletion of sodium, compensatory mechanisms tend to increase this exchange and may produce excessive loss of potassium, hydrogen and chloride ions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5289" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Hydrochlorothiazide also decreases the excretion of calcium and uric acid, may increase the excretion of iodide and may reduce glomerular filtration rate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5290" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Metabolic toxicities associated with excessive electrolyte changes caused by hydrochlorothiazide have been shown to be dose-related.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5291" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Hydrochlorothiazide is well absorbed (65% to 75%) following oral administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5292" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Absorption of hydrochlorothiazide is reduced in patients with congestive heart failure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5293" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Peak plasma concentrations are observed within 1 to 5 hours of dosing, and range from 70 to 490 ng/mL following oral doses of 12.5 to 100 mg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5294" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Plasma concentrations are linearly related to the administered dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5295" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Concentrations of hydrochlorothiazide are 1.6 to 1.8 times higher in whole blood than in plasma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5296" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Binding to serum proteins has been reported to be approximately 40% to 68%.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5297" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The plasma elimination half-life has been reported to be 6 to 15 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5298" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Hydrochlorothiazide is eliminated primarily by renal pathways.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5299" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following oral doses of 12.5 to 100 mg, 55% to 77% of the administered dose appears in urine and greater than 95% of the absorbed dose is excreted in urine as unchanged drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5300" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In patients with renal disease, plasma concentrations of hydrochlorothiazide are increased and the elimination half-life is prolonged.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5301" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>When MICROZIDE is administered with food, its bioavailability is reduced by 10%, the maximum plasma concentration is reduced by 20%, and the time to maximum concentration increases from 1.6 to 2.9 hours.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M102" type="Trigger" span="46 26" str="bioavailability is reduced"/>
<Mention id="M107" type="Precipitant" span="36 4" str="food" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M104" type="Trigger" span="141 39" str="time to maximum concentration increases"/>
<Mention id="M106" type="Trigger" span="85 39" str="maximum plasma concentration is reduced"/>
<Interaction id="I36" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M102" precipitant="M107" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I37" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M104" precipitant="M107" effect="C54604"/>
<Interaction id="I38" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M106" precipitant="M107" effect="C54606"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5302" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Acute antihypertensive effects of thiazides are thought to result from a reduction in blood volume and cardiac output, secondary to a natriuretic effect, although a direct vasodilatory mechanism has also been proposed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5303" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>With chronic administration, plasma volume returns toward normal, but peripheral vascular resistance is decreased.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5304" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The exact mechanism of the antihypertensive effect of hydrochlorothiazide is not known.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5305" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Thiazides do not affect normal blood pressure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5306" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Onset of action occurs within 2 hours of dosing, peak effect is observed at about 4 hours, and activity persists for up to 24 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5307" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In an 87 patient 4-week double-blind, placebo controlled, parallel group trial, patients who received MICROZIDE had reductions in seated systolic and diastolic blood pressure that were significantly greater than those seen in patients who received placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5308" LabelDrug="Microzide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In published placebo-controlled trials comparing 12.5 mg of hydrochlorothiazide to 25 mg, the 12.5 mg dose preserved most of the placebo-corrected blood pressure reduction seen with 25 mg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="acth" precipitantCode="K0U68Q2TXA" effect="166686006: Electrolytes abnormal (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="acth" precipitantCode="K0U68Q2TXA" effect="43339004: Hypokalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="adrenocorticotropic hormone" precipitantCode="K0U68Q2TXA" effect="43339004: Hypokalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="brisk diuresis" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="43339004: Hypokalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="corticosteroid" precipitantCode="N0000175576" effect="166686006: Electrolytes abnormal (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="corticosteroid" precipitantCode="N0000175576" effect="43339004: Hypokalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="digitalis" precipitantCode="F1T8QT9U8B" effect="12876009: Poisoning caused by digitalis glycoside (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="alcohol" precipitantCode="3K9958V90M" effect="28651003: Orthostatic hypotension (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="barbiturates" precipitantCode="N0000175693" effect="28651003: Orthostatic hypotension (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="narcotics" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="28651003: Orthostatic hypotension (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="antidiabetic | oral agents" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="antidiabetic drug" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="antidiabetic drugs" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="insulin" precipitantCode="N0000175944"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="antihypertensive drugs" precipitantCode="N0000178477" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cholestyramine" precipitantCode="4B33BGI082" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="colestipol resins" precipitantCode="K50N755924" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="norepinephrine" precipitantCode="X4W3ENH1CV" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="pressor amines" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="muscle relaxant" precipitantCode="N0000175737" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="skeletal muscle relaxants, nondepolarizing" precipitantCode="N0000175738" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="tubocurarine" precipitantCode="W9YXS298BM" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="lithium" precipitantCode="9FN79X2M3F" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="lithium" precipitantCode="9FN79X2M3F"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="lithium preparations" precipitantCode="9FN79X2M3F"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agent" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agents" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="food" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="food" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54604"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="food" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54606"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>