<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Minipress" setid="36c4da56-502e-4da1-acf7-8e81ee453dcc">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
MINIPRESS is contraindicated in patients with known sensitivity to quinazolines, prazosin, or any of the inert ingredients.</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
The dose of MINIPRESS should be adjusted according to the patient's individual blood pressure response. The following is a guide to its administration:        1 mg two or three times a day (see WARNINGS.)          Dosage may be slowly increased to a total daily dose of 20 mg given in divided doses. The therapeutic dosages most commonly employed have ranged from 6 mg to 15 mg daily given in divided doses. Doses higher than 20 mg usually do not increase efficacy, however a few patients may benefit from further increases up to a daily dose of 40 mg given in divided doses. After initial titration some patients can be maintained adequately on a twice daily dosage regimen.          When adding a diuretic or other antihypertensive agent, the dose of MINIPRESS should be reduced to 1 mg or 2 mg three times a day and retitration then carried out.  Concomitant administration of MINIPRESS with a PDE-5 inhibitor can result in additive blood pressure lowering effects and symptomatic hypotension; therefore, PDE-5 inhibitor therapy should be initiated at the lowest dose in patients taking MINIPRESS.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG &amp;amp; OR LABORATORY TEST INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34074-5">
In a study on five patients given from 12 to 24 mg of prazosin per day for 10 to 14 days, there was an average increase of 42% in the urinary metabolite of norepinephrine and an average increase in urinary VMA of 17%. Therefore, false positive results may occur in screening tests for pheochromocytoma in patients who are being treated with prazosin. If an elevated VMA is found, prazosin should be discontinued and the patient retested after a month.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
MINIPRESS has been administered without any adverse drug interaction in limited clinical experience to date with the following: (1) cardiac glycosides–digitalis and digoxin; (2) hypoglycemics–insulin, chlorpropamide, phenformin, tolazamide, and tolbutamide; (3) tranquilizers and sedatives–chlordiazepoxide, diazepam, and phenobarbital; (4) antigout–allopurinol, colchicine, and probenecid; (5) antiarrhythmics–procainamide, propranolol (see WARNINGS however), and quinidine; and (6) analgesics, antipyretics and anti-inflammatories–propoxyphene, aspirin, indomethacin, and phenylbutazone. Addition of a diuretic or other antihypertensive agent to MINIPRESS has been shown to cause an additive hypotensive effect. This effect can be minimized by reducing the MINIPRESS dose to 1 to 2 mg three times a day, by introducing additional antihypertensive drugs cautiously, and then by retitrating MINIPRESS based on clinical response. Concomitant administration of MINIPRESS with a phosphodiesterase-5 (PDE-5) inhibitor can result in additive blood pressure lowering effects and symptomatic hypotension (see DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION).</Section>
<Section name="PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="42232-9">
Intraoperative Floppy Iris Syndrome (IFIS) has been observed during cataract surgery in some patients treated with alpha-1 blockers. This variant of small pupil syndrome is characterized by the combination of a flaccid iris that billows in response to intraoperative irrigation currents, progressive intraoperative miosis despite preoperative dilation with standard mydriatic drugs, and potential prolapse of the iris toward the phacoemulsification incisions. The patient's ophthalmologist should be prepared for possible modifications to the surgical technique, such as the utilization of iris hooks, iris dilator rings, or viscoelastic substances. There does not appear to be a benefit of stopping alpha-1 blocker therapy prior to cataract surgery.           Dizziness or drowsiness may occur after the first dose of this medicine. Avoid driving or performing hazardous tasks for the first 24 hours after taking this medicine or when the dose is increased. Dizziness, lightheadedness, or fainting may occur, especially when rising from a lying or sitting position. Getting up slowly may help lessen the problem. These effects may also occur if you drink alcohol, stand for long periods of time, exercise, or if the weather is hot. While taking MINIPRESS, be careful in the amount of alcohol you drink. Also, use extra care during exercise or hot weather, or if standing for long periods. Check with your physician if you have any questions.          MINIPRESS has been administered without any adverse drug interaction in limited clinical experience to date with the following: (1) cardiac glycosides–digitalis and digoxin; (2) hypoglycemics–insulin, chlorpropamide, phenformin, tolazamide, and tolbutamide; (3) tranquilizers and sedatives–chlordiazepoxide, diazepam, and phenobarbital; (4) antigout–allopurinol, colchicine, and probenecid; (5) antiarrhythmics–procainamide, propranolol (see WARNINGS however), and quinidine; and (6) analgesics, antipyretics and anti-inflammatories–propoxyphene, aspirin, indomethacin, and phenylbutazone. Addition of a diuretic or other antihypertensive agent to MINIPRESS has been shown to cause an additive hypotensive effect. This effect can be minimized by reducing the MINIPRESS dose to 1 to 2 mg three times a day, by introducing additional antihypertensive drugs cautiously, and then by retitrating MINIPRESS based on clinical response. Concomitant administration of MINIPRESS with a phosphodiesterase-5 (PDE-5) inhibitor can result in additive blood pressure lowering effects and symptomatic hypotension (see DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION).          In a study on five patients given from 12 to 24 mg of prazosin per day for 10 to 14 days, there was an average increase of 42% in the urinary metabolite of norepinephrine and an average increase in urinary VMA of 17%. Therefore, false positive results may occur in screening tests for pheochromocytoma in patients who are being treated with prazosin. If an elevated VMA is found, prazosin should be discontinued and the patient retested after a month.          In clinical studies in which lipid profiles were followed, there were generally no adverse changes noted between pre- and post-treatment lipid levels.          No carcinogenic potential was demonstrated in an 18 month study in rats with MINIPRESS at dose levels more than 225 times the usual maximum recommended human dose of 20 mg per day. MINIPRESS was not mutagenic in in vivo genetic toxicology studies. In a fertility and general reproductive performance study in rats, both males and females, treated with 75 mg/kg (225 times the usual maximum recommended human dose), demonstrated decreased fertility, while those treated with 25 mg/kg (75 times the usual maximum recommended human dose) did not. In chronic studies (one year or more) of MINIPRESS in rats and dogs, testicular changes consisting of atrophy and necrosis occurred at 25 mg/kg/day (75 times the usual maximum recommended human dose). No testicular changes were seen in rats or dogs at 10 mg/kg/day (30 times the usual maximum recommended human dose). In view of the testicular changes observed in animals, 105 patients on long term MINIPRESS therapy were monitored for 17-ketosteroid excretion and no changes indicating a drug effect were observed. In addition, 27 males on MINIPRESS for up to 51 months did not have changes in sperm morphology suggestive of drug effect.          Pregnancy Category C. MINIPRESS has been shown to be associated with decreased litter size at birth, 1, 4, and 21 days of age in rats when given doses more than 225 times the usual maximum recommended human dose. No evidence of drug-related external, visceral, or skeletal fetal abnormalities were observed. No drug-related external, visceral, or skeletal abnormalities were observed in fetuses of pregnant rabbits and pregnant monkeys at doses more than 225 times and 12 times the usual maximum recommended human dose, respectively. The use of prazosin and a beta-blocker for the control of severe hypertension in 44 pregnant women revealed no drug-related fetal abnormalities or adverse effects. Therapy with prazosin was continued for as long as 14 weeks.1  Prazosin has also been used alone or in combination with other hypotensive agents in severe hypertension of pregnancy by other investigators. No fetal or neonatal abnormalities have been reported with the use of prazosin.2  There are no adequate and well controlled studies which establish the safety of MINIPRESS in pregnant women. MINIPRESS should be used during pregnancy only if the potential benefit justifies the potential risk to the mother and fetus.          MINIPRESS has been shown to be excreted in small amounts in human milk. Caution should be exercised when MINIPRESS is administered to a nursing woman.          Safety and effectiveness in children have not been established.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS SECTION" id="34071-1">
As with all alpha-blockers, MINIPRESS may cause syncope with sudden loss of consciousness. In most cases, this is believed to be due to an excessive postural hypotensive effect, although occasionally the syncopal episode has been preceded by a bout of severe tachycardia with heart rates of 120–160 beats per minute. Syncopal episodes have usually occurred within 30 to 90 minutes of the initial dose of the drug; occasionally, they have been reported in association with rapid dosage increases or the introduction of another antihypertensive drug into the regimen of a patient taking high doses of MINIPRESS. The incidence of syncopal episodes is approximately 1% in patients given an initial dose of 2 mg or greater. Clinical trials conducted during the investigational phase of this drug suggest that syncopal episodes can be minimized by limiting the initial dose of the drug to 1 mg, by subsequently increasing the dosage slowly, and by introducing any additional antihypertensive drugs into the patient's regimen with caution (see DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION). Hypotension may develop in patients given MINIPRESS who are also receiving a beta-blocker such as propranolol.  If syncope occurs, the patient should be placed in the recumbent position and treated supportively as necessary. This adverse effect is self-limiting and in most cases does not recur after the initial period of therapy or during subsequent dose titration. Patients should always be started on the 1 mg capsules of MINIPRESS. The 2 and 5 mg capsules are not indicated for initial therapy. More common than loss of consciousness are the symptoms often associated with lowering of the blood pressure, namely, dizziness and lightheadedness. The patient should be cautioned about these possible adverse effects and advised what measures to take should they develop. The patient should also be cautioned to avoid situations where injury could result should syncope occur during the initiation of MINIPRESS therapy.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
The exact mechanism of the hypotensive action of prazosin is unknown. Prazosin causes a decrease in total peripheral resistance and was originally thought to have a direct relaxant action on vascular smooth muscle. Recent animal studies, however, have suggested that the vasodilator effect of prazosin is also related to blockade of postsynaptic alpha-adrenoceptors. The results of dog forelimb experiments demonstrate that the peripheral vasodilator effect of prazosin is confined mainly to the level of the resistance vessels (arterioles). Unlike conventional alpha-blockers, the antihypertensive action of prazosin is usually not accompanied by a reflex tachycardia. Tolerance has not been observed to develop in long term therapy. Hemodynamic studies have been carried out in man following acute single dose administration and during the course of long term maintenance therapy. The results confirm that the therapeutic effect is a fall in blood pressure unaccompanied by a clinically significant change in cardiac output, heart rate, renal blood flow and glomerular filtration rate. There is no measurable negative chronotropic effect. In clinical studies to date, prazosin hydrochloride has not increased plasma renin activity. In man, blood pressure is lowered in both the supine and standing positions. This effect is most pronounced on the diastolic blood pressure. Following oral administration, human plasma concentrations reach a peak at about three hours with a plasma half-life of two to three hours. The drug is highly bound to plasma protein. Bioavailability studies have demonstrated that the total absorption relative to the drug in a 20% alcoholic solution is 90%, resulting in peak levels approximately 65% of that of the drug in solution. Animal studies indicate that prazosin hydrochloride is extensively metabolized, primarily by demethylation and conjugation, and excreted mainly via bile and feces. Less extensive human studies suggest similar metabolism and excretion in man. In clinical studies in which lipid profiles were followed, there were generally no adverse changes noted between pre- and post-treatment lipid levels.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="927" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>MINIPRESS is contraindicated in patients with known sensitivity to quinazolines, prazosin, or any of the inert ingredients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="928" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The dose of MINIPRESS should be adjusted according to the patient's individual blood pressure response.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="929" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The following is a guide to its administration: 1 mg two or three times a day</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="930" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dosage may be slowly increased to a total daily dose of 20 mg given in divided doses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="931" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The therapeutic dosages most commonly employed have ranged from 6 mg to 15 mg daily given in divided doses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="932" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Doses higher than 20 mg usually do not increase efficacy, however a few patients may benefit from further increases up to a daily dose of 40 mg given in divided doses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="933" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>After initial titration some patients can be maintained adequately on a twice daily dosage regimen.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="934" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>When adding a diuretic or other antihypertensive agent, the dose of MINIPRESS should be reduced to 1 mg or 2 mg three times a day and retitration then carried out.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M3" type="Trigger" span="60 4;78 17" str="dose | should be reduced"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="32 22" str="antihypertensive agent" code="N0000178477"/>
<Mention id="M4" type="Precipitant" span="14 8" str="diuretic" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M3" precipitant="M2" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M3" precipitant="M4" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="935" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant administration of MINIPRESS with a PDE-5 inhibitor can result in additive blood pressure lowering effects and symptomatic hypotension; therefore, PDE-5 inhibitor therapy should be initiated at the lowest dose in patients taking MINIPRESS.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M8" type="Trigger" span="77 8;110 7" str="additive | effects"/>
<Mention id="M9" type="Precipitant" span="47 15" str="PDE-5 inhibitor" code="N0000175599"/>
<Mention id="M7" type="SpecificInteraction" span="77 40" str="additive blood pressure lowering effects" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M10" type="SpecificInteraction" span="122 23" str="symptomatic hypotension" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M8" precipitant="M9" effect="M7"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M8" precipitant="M9" effect="M10"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="936" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34074-5">
<SentenceText>In a study on five patients given from 12 to 24 mg of prazosin per day for 10 to 14 days, there was an average increase of 42% in the urinary metabolite of norepinephrine and an average increase in urinary VMA of 17%.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="937" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34074-5">
<SentenceText>Therefore, false positive results may occur in screening tests for pheochromocytoma in patients who are being treated with prazosin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="938" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34074-5">
<SentenceText>If an elevated VMA is found, prazosin should be discontinued and the patient retested after a month.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="939" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>MINIPRESS has been administered without any adverse drug interaction in limited clinical experience to date with the following: (1) cardiac glycosides–digitalis and digoxin; (2) hypoglycemics–insulin, chlorpropamide, phenformin, tolazamide, and tolbutamide; (3) tranquilizers and sedatives–chlordiazepoxide, diazepam, and phenobarbital; (4) antigout–allopurinol, colchicine, and probenecid; (5) antiarrhythmics–procainamide, propranolol, and quinidine; and (6) analgesics, antipyretics and anti-inflammatories–propoxyphene, aspirin, indomethacin, and phenylbutazone.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="940" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Addition of a diuretic or other antihypertensive agent to MINIPRESS has been shown to cause an additive hypotensive effect.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M14" type="Trigger" span="95 8;116 6" str="additive | effect"/>
<Mention id="M12" type="Precipitant" span="32 22" str="antihypertensive agent" code="N0000178477"/>
<Mention id="M16" type="SpecificInteraction" span="95 27" str="additive hypotensive effect" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M15" type="Precipitant" span="14 8" str="diuretic" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M14" precipitant="M12" effect="M16"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M14" precipitant="M15" effect="M16"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="941" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>This effect can be minimized by reducing the MINIPRESS dose to 1 to 2 mg three times a day, by introducing additional antihypertensive drugs cautiously, and then by retitrating MINIPRESS based on clinical response.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="942" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant administration of MINIPRESS with a phosphodiesterase-5 (PDE-5) inhibitor can result in additive blood pressure lowering effects and symptomatic hypotension.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M26" type="Trigger" span="99 8;132 7" str="additive | effects"/>
<Mention id="M21" type="Precipitant" span="68 5;75 9" str="PDE-5 | inhibitor" code="N0000175599"/>
<Mention id="M25" type="SpecificInteraction" span="144 23" str="symptomatic hypotension" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M28" type="SpecificInteraction" span="99 40" str="additive blood pressure lowering effects" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M27" type="Precipitant" span="47 19;75 9" str="phosphodiesterase-5 | inhibitor" code="N0000175599"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M26" precipitant="M21" effect="M25"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M26" precipitant="M21" effect="M28"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M26" precipitant="M27" effect="M25"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M26" precipitant="M27" effect="M28"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="943" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Intraoperative Floppy Iris Syndrome (IFIS) has been observed during cataract surgery in some patients treated with alpha-1 blockers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="944" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>This variant of small pupil syndrome is characterized by the combination of a flaccid iris that billows in response to intraoperative irrigation currents, progressive intraoperative miosis despite preoperative dilation with standard mydriatic drugs, and potential prolapse of the iris toward the phacoemulsification incisions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="945" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The patient's ophthalmologist should be prepared for possible modifications to the surgical technique, such as the utilization of iris hooks, iris dilator rings, or viscoelastic substances.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="946" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>There does not appear to be a benefit of stopping alpha-1 blocker therapy prior to cataract surgery.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="947" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Dizziness or drowsiness may occur after the first dose of this medicine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="948" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Avoid driving or performing hazardous tasks for the first 24 hours after taking this medicine or when the dose is increased.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="949" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Dizziness, lightheadedness, or fainting may occur, especially when rising from a lying or sitting position.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="950" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Getting up slowly may help lessen the problem.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="951" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>These effects may also occur if you drink alcohol, stand for long periods of time, exercise, or if the weather is hot.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M29" type="Trigger" span="6 7" str="effects"/>
<Mention id="M30" type="Precipitant" span="42 7" str="alcohol" code="3K9958V90M"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M29" precipitant="M30"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="952" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>While taking MINIPRESS, be careful in the amount of alcohol you drink.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M31" type="Trigger" span="24 10" str="be careful"/>
<Mention id="M32" type="Precipitant" span="52 7" str="alcohol" code="3K9958V90M"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M31" precipitant="M32"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="953" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Also, use extra care during exercise or hot weather, or if standing for long periods.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="954" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Check with your physician if you have any questions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="955" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In clinical studies in which lipid profiles were followed, there were generally no adverse changes noted between pre- and post-treatment lipid levels.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="956" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>No carcinogenic potential was demonstrated in an 18 month study in rats with MINIPRESS at dose levels more than 225 times the usual maximum recommended human dose of 20 mg per day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="957" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>MINIPRESS was not mutagenic in in vivo genetic toxicology studies.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="958" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In a fertility and general reproductive performance study in rats, both males and females, treated with 75 mg/kg (225 times the usual maximum recommended human dose), demonstrated decreased fertility, while those treated with 25 mg/kg (75 times the usual maximum recommended human dose) did not.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="959" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In chronic studies (one year or more) of MINIPRESS in rats and dogs, testicular changes consisting of atrophy and necrosis occurred at 25 mg/kg/day (75 times the usual maximum recommended human dose).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="960" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>No testicular changes were seen in rats or dogs at 10 mg/kg/day (30 times the usual maximum recommended human dose).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="961" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In view of the testicular changes observed in animals, 105 patients on long term MINIPRESS therapy were monitored for 17-ketosteroid excretion and no changes indicating a drug effect were observed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="962" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In addition, 27 males on MINIPRESS for up to 51 months did not have changes in sperm morphology suggestive of drug effect.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="963" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>MINIPRESS has been shown to be associated with decreased litter size at birth, 1, 4, and 21 days of age in rats when given doses more than 225 times the usual maximum recommended human dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="964" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>No evidence of drug-related external, visceral, or skeletal fetal abnormalities were observed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="965" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>No drug-related external, visceral, or skeletal abnormalities were observed in fetuses of pregnant rabbits and pregnant monkeys at doses more than 225 times and 12 times the usual maximum recommended human dose, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="966" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The use of prazosin and a beta-blocker for the control of severe hypertension in 44 pregnant women revealed no drug-related fetal abnormalities or adverse effects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="967" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Therapy with prazosin was continued for as long as 14 weeks.1 Prazosin has also been used alone or in combination with other hypotensive agents in severe hypertension of pregnancy by other investigators.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="968" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>No fetal or neonatal abnormalities have been reported with the use of prazosin.2 There are no adequate and well controlled studies which establish the safety of MINIPRESS in pregnant women.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="969" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>MINIPRESS should be used during pregnancy only if the potential benefit justifies the potential risk to the mother and fetus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="970" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>MINIPRESS has been shown to be excreted in small amounts in human milk.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="971" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Caution should be exercised when MINIPRESS is administered to a nursing woman.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="972" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Safety and effectiveness in children have not been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="973" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>As with all alpha-blockers, MINIPRESS may cause syncope with sudden loss of consciousness.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="974" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>In most cases, this is believed to be due to an excessive postural hypotensive effect, although occasionally the syncopal episode has been preceded by a bout of severe tachycardia with heart rates of 120–160 beats per minute.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="975" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Syncopal episodes have usually occurred within 30 to 90 minutes of the initial dose of the drug; occasionally, they have been reported in association with rapid dosage increases or the introduction of another antihypertensive drug into the regimen of a patient taking high doses of MINIPRESS.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M33" type="Trigger" span="138 16" str="association with"/>
<Mention id="M34" type="Precipitant" span="209 21" str="antihypertensive drug" code="N0000178477"/>
<Mention id="M35" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 17" str="Syncopal episodes" code="271594007: Syncope (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M33" precipitant="M34" effect="M35"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="976" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The incidence of syncopal episodes is approximately 1% in patients given an initial dose of 2 mg or greater.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="977" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Clinical trials conducted during the investigational phase of this drug suggest that syncopal episodes can be minimized by limiting the initial dose of the drug to 1 mg, by subsequently increasing the dosage slowly, and by introducing any additional antihypertensive drugs into the patient's regimen with caution.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M36" type="Trigger" span="305 7" str="caution"/>
<Mention id="M37" type="Precipitant" span="250 22" str="antihypertensive drugs" code="N0000178477"/>
<Mention id="M38" type="SpecificInteraction" span="-1 17" str="Syncopal episodes" code="271594007: Syncope (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M36" precipitant="M37" effect="M38"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="978" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Hypotension may develop in patients given MINIPRESS who are also receiving a beta-blocker such as propranolol.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M42" type="Trigger" span="0 11" str="Hypotension"/>
<Mention id="M40" type="Precipitant" span="77 12" str="beta-blocker" code="N0000175556"/>
<Mention id="M44" type="SpecificInteraction" span="-1 11" str="hypotension" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M43" type="Precipitant" span="98 11" str="propranolol" code="9Y8NXQ24VQ"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M42" precipitant="M40" effect="M44"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M42" precipitant="M43" effect="M44"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="979" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>If syncope occurs, the patient should be placed in the recumbent position and treated supportively as necessary.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="980" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>This adverse effect is self-limiting and in most cases does not recur after the initial period of therapy or during subsequent dose titration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="981" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Patients should always be started on the 1 mg capsules of MINIPRESS.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="982" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The 2 and 5 mg capsules are not indicated for initial therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="983" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>More common than loss of consciousness are the symptoms often associated with lowering of the blood pressure, namely, dizziness and lightheadedness.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="984" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The patient should be cautioned about these possible adverse effects and advised what measures to take should they develop.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="985" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The patient should also be cautioned to avoid situations where injury could result should syncope occur during the initiation of MINIPRESS therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="986" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Prolonged erections and priapism have been reported with alpha-1 blockers including prazosin in post marketing experience.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="987" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>In the event of an erection that persists longer than 4 hours, seek immediate medical assistance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="988" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>If priapism is not treated immediately, penile tissue damage and permanent loss of potency could result.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="989" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The exact mechanism of the hypotensive action of prazosin is unknown.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="990" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Prazosin causes a decrease in total peripheral resistance and was originally thought to have a direct relaxant action on vascular smooth muscle.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="991" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Recent animal studies, however, have suggested that the vasodilator effect of prazosin is also related to blockade of postsynaptic alpha-adrenoceptors.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="992" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The results of dog forelimb experiments demonstrate that the peripheral vasodilator effect of prazosin is confined mainly to the level of the resistance vessels (arterioles).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="993" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Unlike conventional alpha-blockers, the antihypertensive action of prazosin is usually not accompanied by a reflex tachycardia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="994" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Tolerance has not been observed to develop in long term therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="995" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Hemodynamic studies have been carried out in man following acute single dose administration and during the course of long term maintenance therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="996" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The results confirm that the therapeutic effect is a fall in blood pressure unaccompanied by a clinically significant change in cardiac output, heart rate, renal blood flow and glomerular filtration rate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="997" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There is no measurable negative chronotropic effect.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="998" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In clinical studies to date, prazosin hydrochloride has not increased plasma renin activity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="999" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In man, blood pressure is lowered in both the supine and standing positions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1000" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This effect is most pronounced on the diastolic blood pressure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1001" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following oral administration, human plasma concentrations reach a peak at about three hours with a plasma half-life of two to three hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1002" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The drug is highly bound to plasma protein.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1003" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Bioavailability studies have demonstrated that the total absorption relative to the drug in a 20% alcoholic solution is 90%, resulting in peak levels approximately 65% of that of the drug in solution.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1004" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Animal studies indicate that prazosin hydrochloride is extensively metabolized, primarily by demethylation and conjugation, and excreted mainly via bile and feces.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1005" LabelDrug="Minipress" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Less extensive human studies suggest similar metabolism and excretion in man.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="antihypertensive agent" precipitantCode="N0000178477" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="antihypertensive agent" precipitantCode="N0000178477" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="diuretic" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="diuretic" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="pde-5 inhibitor" precipitantCode="N0000175599" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="pde-5 | inhibitor" precipitantCode="N0000175599" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="phosphodiesterase-5 | inhibitor" precipitantCode="N0000175599" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="alcohol" precipitantCode="3K9958V90M"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="antihypertensive drug" precipitantCode="N0000178477" effect="271594007: Syncope (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="antihypertensive drugs" precipitantCode="N0000178477" effect="271594007: Syncope (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="beta-blocker" precipitantCode="N0000175556" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="propranolol" precipitantCode="9Y8NXQ24VQ" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>