<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" setid="18fb1c2b-0c1e-436c-a5b6-d4840b5da228">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
Do not use in patients with advanced aortic stenosis (4.1).          Do not use nicardipine in patients with advanced aortic stenosis because of the afterload reduction effect of nicardipine. Reduction of diastolic pressure in these patients may worsen rather than improve myocardial oxygen balance.</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
For Intravenous Use.  DILUTE VIALS BEFORE INFUSION (2.2).  Individualize dosage based upon the severity of hypertension and response of the patient during dosing (2.1).  When substituting for oral nicardipine therapy, use the intravenous infusion rate from the table to produce an average plasma concentration equivalent to a given oral dose at steady state (2.3):       Oral Nicardipine Dose Equivalent Intravenous Infusion Rate      20 mg q8h  0.5 mg/hr    30 mg q8h  1.2 mg/hr    40 mg q8h  2.2 mg/hr     In a drug-free patient, initiate therapy at 50 mL/hr (5 mg/hr). For gradual reduction in blood pressure, increase the infusion rate by 25 mL/hr every 15 minutes up to a maximum of 150 mL/hr until desired blood pressure reduction is achieved. For rapid blood pressure reduction, increase the infusion rate by 25 mL/hr every 5 minutes up to a maximum of 150 mL/hr (2.4).  If unacceptable hypotension or tachycardia ensues, discontinue the infusion. When blood pressure and heart rate stabilize, restart the infusion at low doses such as 30 mL/hr to 50 mL/hr (2.5).          Nicardipine hydrochloride injection is intended for intravenous use. DOSAGE MUST BE INDIVIDUALIZED depending upon the severity of hypertension and the response of the patient during dosing. Blood pressure and heart rate should be monitored both during and after the infusion to avoid tachycardia or too rapid or excessive reduction in either systolic or diastolic blood pressure.            Warning: Dilute vials before infusion.          Nicardipine hydrochloride injection is administered by slow continuous infusion at a CONCENTRATION OF 0.1 MG/ML. Each vial (25 mg) should be diluted with 240 mL of compatible intravenous fluid (see below), resulting in 250 mL of solution at a concentration of 0.1 mg/mL.  Nicardipine hydrochloride injection has been found compatible and stable in polyvinyl chloride containers for 24 hours at controlled room temperature with:   Dextrose (5%) Injection, USP   Dextrose (5%) and Sodium Chloride (0.45%) Injection, USP   Dextrose (5%) and Sodium Chloride (0.9%) Injection, USP   Dextrose (5%) with 40 mEq Potassium, USP   Sodium Chloride (0.45%) Injection, USP   Sodium Chloride (0.9%) Injection, USP   Nicardipine hydrochloride injection is not compatible with Sodium Bicarbonate (5%) Injection, USP or Lactated Ringer's Injection, USP.   The diluted solution is stable for 24 hours at room temperature.           Visually inspect nicardipine hydrochloride injection for particulate matter and discoloration prior to administration, whenever solution and container permit. Nicardipine hydrochloride injection is normally light yellow in color.            The intravenous infusion rate required to produce an average plasma concentration equivalent to a given oral dose at steady state is shown in the following table:       Oral Nicardipine Dose Equivalent Intravenous Infusion Rate      20 mg q8h  0.5 mg/hr    30 mg q8h  1.2 mg/hr    40 mg q8h  2.2 mg/hr             The time course of blood pressure decrease is dependent on the initial rate of infusion and the frequency of dosage adjustment. Nicardipine hydrochloride injection is administered by slow continuous infusion at a concentration of 0.1 mg/mL. With constant infusion, blood pressure begins to fall within minutes. It reaches about 50% of its ultimate decrease in about 45 minutes.  When treating acute hypertensive episodes in patients with chronic hypertension, discontinuation of infusion is followed by a 50% offset of action in 30 minutes ± 7 minutes but plasma levels of drug and gradually decreasing antihypertensive effects exist for many hours.         For a gradual reduction in blood pressure, initiate therapy at a rate of 50 mL/hr (5 mg/hr). If desired blood pressure reduction is not achieved at this dose, increase the infusion rate by 25 mL/hr (2.5 mg/hr) every 15 minutes up to a maximum of 150 mL/hr (15 mg/hr), until desired blood pressure reduction is achieved. For more rapid blood pressure reduction, titrate every 5 minutes.           Adjust the rate of infusion as needed to maintain desired response.                 In case of hypotension or tachycardia, discontinue infusion. When blood pressure and heart rate stabilize, restart infusion at low doses such as 30 mL/hr to 50 mL/hr (3 mg/hr to 5 mg/hr) and titrate to maintain desired blood pressure.          Change infusion site every 12 hours if administered via peripheral vein.          Monitor closely when titrating nicardipine hydrochloride injection in patients with congestive heart failure or impaired hepatic or renal function [see Warnings and Precautions (5.4, 5.5 and 5.6)].             If treatment includes transfer to an oral antihypertensive agent other than nicardipine capsules, initiate oral therapy upon discontinuation of nicardipine hydrochloride injection.  When switching to a TID regimen of nicardipine capsules, administer the first dose 1 hour prior to discontinuation of the infusion.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
Cimetidine increases nicardipine plasma levels (7.3). Nicardipine increases cyclosporine plasma levels. Monitor cyclosporine levels when co-administering with nicardipine (7.5).          Since nicardipine hydrochloride injection may be administered to patients already being treated with other medications, including other antihypertensive agents, careful monitoring of these patients is necessary to detect and to treat promptly any undesired effects from concomitant administration.           In most patients, nicardipine hydrochloride injection can safely be used concomitantly with beta-blockers. However, monitor response carefully when combining nicardipine hydrochloride injection with a beta-blocker in the treatment of congestive heart failure patients [see Warnings and Precautions (5.4)].          Cimetidine has been shown to increase nicardipine plasma concentrations with oral nicardipine administration. Carefully monitor patients receiving the two drugs concomitantly. Data with other histamine-2 antagonists are not available.          Studies have shown that oral nicardipine usually does not alter digoxin plasma concentrations.           Concomitant administration of oral nicardipine and cyclosporine results in elevated plasma cyclosporine levels. Monitor closely plasma concentrations of cyclosporine during nicardipine hydrochloride injection administration, and adjust the dose of cyclosporine accordingly.           The plasma protein binding of nicardipine was not altered when therapeutic concentrations of furosemide, propranolol, dipyridamole, warfarin, quinidine, or naproxen were added to human plasma in vitro.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
To reduce the possibility of venous thrombosis, phlebitis, and vascular impairment, do not use small veins, such as those on the dorsum of the hand or wrist. Exercise extreme care to avoid intra-arterial administration or extravasation (5.7). To minimize the risk of peripheral venous irritation, change the site of infusion of nicardipine every 12 hours (5.7). Nicardipine is not a beta-blocker and therefore gives no protection against the dangers of abrupt beta-blocker withdrawal. Withdraw beta-blockers gradually (5.8). Closely monitor response in patients with angina (5.3), congestive heart failure (5.4), impaired hepatic function (5.5), portal hypertension (5.5), and renal impairment (5.6) and pheochromocytoma (5.9).          In administrating nicardipine, close monitoring of blood pressure and heart rate is required. Nicardipine may occasionally produce symptomatic hypotension or tachycardia. Avoid systemic hypotension when administering the drug to patients who have sustained an acute cerebral infarction or hemorrhage.           No clinical events have been reported suggestive of a too rapid decrease in blood pressure with nicardipine. However, as with any antihypertensive agent, blood pressure lowering should be accomplished over as long a time as is compatible with the patient's clinical status.          Increases in frequency, duration, or severity of angina have been seen in chronic oral therapy with nicardipine capsules. Induction or exacerbation of angina has been seen in less than 1% of coronary artery disease patients treated with nicardipine. The mechanism of this effect has not been established.           Nicardipine reduced afterload without impairing myocardial contractility in preliminary hemodynamic studies of CHF patients. However, in vitro and in some patients, a negative inotropic effect has been observed. Therefore, monitor vital signs carefully when using nicardipine, particularly in combination with a beta-blocker, in patients with CHF or significant left ventricular dysfunction.           Since nicardipine is metabolized in the liver, consider lower dosages and closely monitor response. Nicardipine administered intravenously increased hepatic venous pressure gradient by 4 mmHg in cirrhotic patients at high doses (5 mg/20 min) in one study. Use caution in patients with portal hypertension.           When nicardipine was given to mild-to-moderate hypertensive patients with moderate renal impairment, a significantly lower systemic clearance and higher AUC was observed. These results are consistent with those seen after oral administration of nicardipine. Careful dose titration is advised when treating patients with more than mild renal impairment.           To reduce the possibility of venous thrombosis, phlebitis, local irritation, swelling, extravasation, and the rare occurrence of vascular impairment, administer drug through large peripheral veins or central veins rather than arteries or small peripheral veins, such as those on the dorsum of the hand or wrist. To minimize the risk of peripheral venous irritation, consider changing the site of the drug infusion every 12 hours.           Nicardipine is not a beta-blocker and therefore gives no protection against the dangers of abrupt beta-blocker withdrawal. Withdraw beta-blockers gradually.          Only limited clinical experience exists in use of nicardipine for patients with hypertension from pheochromocytoma.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Nicardipine inhibits the transmembrane influx of calcium ions into cardiac muscle and smooth muscle without changing serum calcium concentrations. The contractile processes of cardiac muscle and vascular smooth muscle are dependent upon the movement of extracellular calcium ions into these cells through specific ion channels. The effects of nicardipine are more selective to vascular smooth muscle than cardiac muscle. In animal models, nicardipine produced relaxation of coronary vascular smooth muscle at drug levels which cause little or no negative inotropic effect.                Nicardipine produces significant decreases in systemic vascular resistance. In a study of intra-arterially administered nicardipine, the degree of vasodilation and the resultant decrease in blood pressure were more prominent in hypertensive patients than in normotensive volunteers. Administration of nicardipine to normotensive volunteers at dosages of 0.25 mg/hr to 3 mg/hr for eight hours produced changes of less than 5 mmHg in systolic blood pressure and less than 3 mmHg in diastolic blood pressure.  An increase in heart rate is a normal response to vasodilation and decrease in blood pressure; in some patients these increases in heart rate may be pronounced. In placebo-controlled trials, the mean increases in heart rate were 7 bpm ± 1 bpm in postoperative patients and 8 bpm ± 1 bpm in patients with severe hypertension at the end of the maintenance period.  Hemodynamic studies following intravenous dosing in patients with coronary artery disease and normal or moderately abnormal left ventricular function have shown significant increases in ejection fraction and cardiac output with no significant change, or a small decrease, in left ventricular end-diastolic pressure (LVEDP). There is evidence that nicardipine increases blood flow. Coronary dilatation induced by nicardipine improves perfusion and aerobic metabolism in areas with chronic ischemia, resulting in reduced lactate production and augmented oxygen consumption. In patients with coronary artery disease, nicardipine, administered after beta-blockade, significantly improved systolic and diastolic left ventricular function.  In congestive heart failure patients with impaired left ventricular function, nicardipine increased cardiac output both at rest and during exercise. Decreases in left ventricular end-diastolic pressure were also observed. However, in some patients with severe left ventricular dysfunction, it may have a negative inotropic effect and could lead to worsened failure.  "Coronary steal" has not been observed during treatment with nicardipine (Coronary steal is the detrimental redistribution of coronary blood flow in patients with coronary artery disease from under-perfused areas toward better perfused areas.) Nicardipine has been shown to improve systolic shortening in both normal and hypokinetic segments of myocardial muscle. Radionuclide angiography has confirmed that wall motion remained improved during increased oxygen demand. (Occasional patients have developed increased angina upon receiving nicardipine capsules. Whether this represents coronary steal in these patients, or is the result of increased heart rate and decreased diastolic pressure, is not clear.)  In patients with coronary artery disease, nicardipine improves left ventricular diastolic distensibility during the early filling phase, probably due to a faster rate of myocardial relaxation in previously underperfused areas. There is little or no effect on normal myocardium, suggesting the improvement is mainly by indirect mechanisms such as afterload reduction and reduced ischemia. Nicardipine has no negative effect on myocardial relaxation at therapeutic doses. The clinical benefits of these properties have not yet been demonstrated.           In general, no detrimental effects on the cardiac conduction system have been seen with nicardipine. During acute electrophysiologic studies, it increased heart rate and prolonged the corrected QT interval to a minor degree. It did not affect sinus node recovery or SA conduction times. The PA, AH, and HV intervals or the functional and effective refractory periods of the atrium were not prolonged. The relative and effective refractory periods of the His-Purkinje system were slightly shortened.  *PA = conduction time from high to low right atrium; AH = conduction time from low right atrium to His bundle deflection, or AV nodal conduction time; HV = conduction time through the His bundle and the bundle branch-Purkinje system.          Because nicardipine is extensively metabolized by the liver, plasma concentrations are influenced by changes in hepatic function. In a clinical study with nicardipine capsules in patients with severe liver disease, plasma concentrations were elevated and the half-life was prolonged [see Warnings and Precautions (5.5)]. Similar results were obtained in patients with hepatic disease when nicardipine hydrochloride was administered for 24 hours at 0.6 mg/hr.           When nicardipine was given to mild-to-moderate hypertensive patients with moderate degrees of renal impairment, significant reduction in glomerular filtration rate (GFR) and effective renal plasma flow (RPF) were observed. No significant differences in liver blood flow were observed in these patients. A significantly lower systemic clearance and higher area under the curve (AUC) were observed.  When nicardipine capsules (20 mg or 30 mg TID) were given to hypertensive patients with impaired renal function, mean plasma concentrations, AUC, and Cmax were approximately two-fold higher than in healthy controls. There was a transient increase in electrolyte excretion, including sodium [see Warnings and Precautions (5.6)].  Acute bolus administration of nicardipine hydrochloride injection (2.5 mg) in healthy volunteers decreased mean arterial pressure and renal vascular resistance; glomerular filtration rate (GFR), renal plasma flow (RPF), and the filtration fraction were unchanged. In healthy patients undergoing abdominal surgery, nicardipine hydrochloride injection (10 mg over 20 minutes) increased GFR with no change in RPF when compared with placebo. In hypertensive type ll diabetic patients with nephropathy, nicardipine capsules (20 mg TID) did not change RPF and GFR, but reduced renal vascular resistance.           In two well-controlled studies of patients with obstructive airway disease treated with nicardipine capsules, no evidence of increased bronchospasm was seen. In one of the studies, nicardipine capsules improved forced expiratory volume 1 second (FEV1) and forced vital capacity (FVC) in comparison with metoprolol. Adverse reactions reported in a limited number of patients with asthma, reactive airway disease, or obstructive airway disease were similar to reactions in other patients treated with nicardipine capsules.                  A rapid dose-related increase in nicardipine plasma concentrations is seen during the first two hours after the start of an infusion of nicardipine. Plasma concentrations increase at a much slower rate after the first few hours, and approach steady state at 24 hours to 48 hours. The steady-state pharmacokinetics of nicardipine are similar in elderly hypertensive patients (greater than 65 years) and young healthy adults. On termination of the infusion, nicardipine concentrations decrease rapidly, with at least a 50% decrease during the first two hours post-infusion. The effects of nicardipine on blood pressure significantly correlate with plasma concentrations. Nicardipine is highly protein bound (greater than 95%) in human plasma over a wide concentration range.  Following infusion, nicardipine plasma concentrations decline tri-exponentially, with a rapid early distribution phase (α-half-life of 3 minutes), an intermediate phase (β-half-life of 45 minutes), and a slow terminal phase (γ-half-life of 14 hours) that can only be detected after long-term infusions. Total plasma clearance (Cl) is 0.4 L/hr∙kg, and the apparent volume of distribution (Vd) using a non-compartment model is 8.3 L/kg. The pharmacokinetics of nicardipine is linear over the dosage range of 0.5 mg/hr to 40 mg/hr.           Nicardipine has been shown to be rapidly and extensively metabolized by the liver. Nicardipine does not induce or inhibit its own metabolism and does not induce or inhibit hepatic microsomal enzymes. After coadministration of a radioactive intravenous dose of nicardipine with an oral 30 mg dose given every 8 hours, 49% of the radioactivity was recovered in the urine and 43% in the feces within 96 hours. None of the dose was recovered as unchanged nicardipine.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="6663" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Do not use in patients with advanced aortic stenosis (4.1).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6664" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Do not use nicardipine in patients with advanced aortic stenosis because of the afterload reduction effect of nicardipine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6665" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Reduction of diastolic pressure in these patients may worsen rather than improve myocardial oxygen balance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6666" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Individualize dosage based upon the severity of hypertension and response of the patient during dosing (2.1).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6667" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Single dose vials must be diluted before use (2.2).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6668" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>When substituting for oral nicardipine therapy, use the intravenous infusion rate as follows (2.3): Oral Nicardipine Dose Equivalent IV Infusion Rate 20 mg q8h 0.5 mg/hr 30 mg q8h 1.2 mg/hr 40 mg q8h 2.2 mg/hr In a drug-free patient, initiate therapy at 5 mg/hr.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6669" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Increase the infusion rate by 2.5 mg/hr to a maximum of 15 mg/hr until desired blood pressure reduction is achieved.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6670" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For a gradual blood pressure reduction the rate can be increased every 15 minutes, for a rapid reduction, every 5 minutes (2.4).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6671" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If hypotension or tachycardia ensues, discontinue the infusion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6672" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>After stabilized, patient can be restarted at low doses such as 3 to 5 mg/hr (2.5).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6673" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Individualize dosing based on the severity of hypertension and the response of the patient during dosing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6674" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor blood pressure and heart rate both during and after the infusion to avoid tachycardia or too rapid or excessive reduction in either systolic or diastolic blood pressure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6675" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Administer Nicardipine Hydrochloride by slow continuous infusion by a central line or through a large peripheral vein.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6676" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Change the infusion site every 12 hours if administered via peripheral vein.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6677" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Parenteral drug products should be inspected visually for particulate matter and discoloration prior to administration, whenever solution and container permit.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6678" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not use the solution if particulate matter, precipitate, or crystallization is present, or if the container appears damaged.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6679" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Single Dose Vials Dilution Single dose vials must be diluted before infusion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6680" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Each vial (25 mg) must be diluted with 240 mL of compatible intravenous fluid, resulting in 250 mL of solution at a concentration of 0.1 mg/mL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6681" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Compatability Nicardipine hydrochloride injection has been found compatible and stable in polyvinyl chloride containers for 24 hours at controlled room temperature with: Dextrose (5%) Injection, USPDextrose (5%) and Sodium Chloride (0.45%) Injection, USPDextrose (5%) and Sodium Chloride (0.9%) Injection, USPDextrose (5%) with 40 mEq Potassium, USPSodium Chloride (0.45%) Injection, USPSodium Chloride (0.9%) Injection, USP Nicardipine hydrochloride is not compatible with Sodium Bicarbonate (5%) Injection, USP or Lactated Ringer’s Injection, USP.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M3" type="Trigger" span="454 14" str="not compatible"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="516 32" str="Lactated Ringer’s Injection, USP" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M4" type="Precipitant" span="474 38" str="Sodium Bicarbonate (5%) Injection, USP" code="8MDF5V39QO"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M3" precipitant="M2"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M3" precipitant="M4"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6682" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Flexible Containers Dilution is not required for Nicardipine Hydrochloride in 0.9% Sodium Chloride Injection.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6683" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Check the container for minute leaks prior to use by squeezing the bag firmly; ensure that the seal is intact.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6684" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If leaks are found, discard solution as sterility may be impaired.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6685" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not combine Nicardipine Hydrochloride in 0.9% Sodium Chloride Injection with any product in the same intravenous line or premixed container.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6686" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not add supplementary medication to the bag.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6687" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not use plastic containers in series connections.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6688" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Such use could result in air embolism due to residual air being drawn from the primary container before the administration of the fluid from the secondary container is complete.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6689" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Remove protector from outlet port at bottom of container.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6690" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Refer to complete directions accompanying set.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6691" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The intravenous infusion rate required to produce an average plasma concentration equivalent to a given oral dose at steady state is shown in the following table: Oral Nicardipine Dose Equivalent Intravenous Infusion Rate 20 mg q8h 0.5 mg/hr 30 mg q8h 1.2 mg/hr 40 mg q8h 2.2 mg/hr The time course of blood pressure decrease is dependent on the initial rate of infusion and the frequency of dosage adjustment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6692" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Nicardipine hydrochloride injection is administered by slow continuous infusion at a concentration of 0.1 mg/mL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6693" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>With constant infusion, blood pressure begins to fall within minutes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6694" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>It reaches about 50% of its ultimate decrease in about 45 minutes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6695" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>When treating acute hypertensive episodes in patients with chronic hypertension, discontinuation of infusion is followed by a 50% offset of action in 30 minutes± 7 minutes but plasma levels of drug and gradually decreasing antihypertensive effects exist for many hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6696" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For a gradual reduction in blood pressure, initiate therapy at a rate of 5 mg/hr.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6697" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If desired blood pressure reduction is not achieved at this dose, increase the infusion rate by 2.5 mg/hr every 15 minutes up to a maximum of15 mg/hr, until desired blood pressure reduction is achieved.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6698" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For more rapid blood pressure reduction, titrate every 5 minutes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6699" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Adjust the rate of infusion as needed to maintain desired response.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6700" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In case of hypotension or tachycardia, discontinue infusion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6701" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>When blood pressure and heart rate stabilize, restart infusion at low doses such as 30 mL/hr to 50 mL/hr (3 mg/hr to 5 mg/hr) and titrate to maintain desired blood pressure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6702" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Change infusion site every 12 hours if administered via peripheral vein.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6703" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor closely when titrating nicardipine hydrochloride injection in patients with congestive heart failure or impaired hepatic or renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6704" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If treatment includes transfer to an oral antihypertensive agent other than nicardipine capsules, initiate oral therapy upon discontinuation of nicardipine hydrochloride injection.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6705" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>When switching to a TID regimen of nicardipine capsules, administer the first dose 1 hour prior to discontinuation of the infusion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6706" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Cimetidine increases nicardipine plasma levels (7.3).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M5" type="Trigger" span="11 9;33 13" str="increases | plasma levels"/>
<Mention id="M6" type="Precipitant" span="0 10" str="Cimetidine" code="80061L1WGD"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M5" precipitant="M6" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6707" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Nicardipine may increase cyclosporine and tacrolimus plasma levels.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M9" type="Trigger" span="16 8;53 13" str="increase | plasma levels"/>
<Mention id="M8" type="Precipitant" span="25 12" str="cyclosporine" code="83HN0GTJ6D"/>
<Mention id="M10" type="Precipitant" span="42 10" str="tacrolimus" code="WM0HAQ4WNM"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M9" precipitant="M8" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M9" precipitant="M10" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6708" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Frequent monitoring of trough blood levels of cyclosporine and tacrolimus is recommended when co-administering nicardipine.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M13" type="Trigger" span="0 19" str="Frequent monitoring"/>
<Mention id="M12" type="Precipitant" span="46 12" str="cyclosporine" code="83HN0GTJ6D"/>
<Mention id="M14" type="Precipitant" span="63 10" str="tacrolimus" code="WM0HAQ4WNM"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M13" precipitant="M12"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M13" precipitant="M14"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6709" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Since nicardipine hydrochloride injection may be administered to patients already being treated with other medications, including other antihypertensive agents, careful monitoring of these patients is necessary to detect and to treat promptly any undesired effects from concomitant administration.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M15" type="Trigger" span="161 18" str="careful monitoring"/>
<Mention id="M16" type="Precipitant" span="136 23" str="antihypertensive agents" code="N0000178477"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M15" precipitant="M16"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6710" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>In most patients, nicardipine hydrochloride injection can safely be used concomitantly with beta-blockers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6711" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>However, monitor response carefully when combining nicardipine hydrochloride injection with a beta-blocker in the treatment of congestive heart failure patients.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M17" type="Trigger" span="9 7" str="monitor"/>
<Mention id="M18" type="Precipitant" span="94 12" str="beta-blocker" code="N0000175556"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M17" precipitant="M18"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6712" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Cimetidine has been shown to increase nicardipine plasma concentrations with oral nicardipine administration.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M19" type="Trigger" span="29 8;50 21" str="increase | plasma concentrations"/>
<Mention id="M20" type="Precipitant" span="0 10" str="Cimetidine" code="80061L1WGD"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M19" precipitant="M20" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6713" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Carefully monitor patients receiving the two drugs concomitantly.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6714" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Data with other histamine-2 antagonists are not available.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6715" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Studies have shown that oral nicardipine usually does not alter digoxin plasma concentrations.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6716" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant administration of oral or intravenous nicardipine and cyclosporine results in elevated plasma cyclosporine levels through nicardipine inhibition of hepatic microsomal enzymes, including CYP3A4.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M21" type="Trigger" span="90 15;119 6" str="elevated plasma | levels"/>
<Mention id="M22" type="Precipitant" span="66 12" str="cyclosporine" code="83HN0GTJ6D"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M21" precipitant="M22" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6717" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor closely plasma concentrations of cyclosporine during nicardipine hydrochloride injection administration, and adjust the dose of cyclosporine accordingly.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M23" type="Trigger" span="0 7" str="Monitor "/>
<Mention id="M24" type="Trigger" span="117 15" str=" adjust the dose"/>
<Mention id="M25" type="Precipitant" span="41 12" str="cyclosporine" code="83HN0GTJ6D"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M23;M24" precipitant="M25"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6718" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant administration of intravenous nicardipine and tacrolimus may result in elevated plasma tacrolimus levels through nicardipine inhibition of hepatic microsomal enzymes, including CYP3A4.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M26" type="Trigger" span="83 15;110 6" str="elevated plasma | levels"/>
<Mention id="M27" type="Precipitant" span="58 10" str="tacrolimus" code="WM0HAQ4WNM"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M26" precipitant="M27" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6719" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Closely monitor plasma concentrations of tacrolimus during nicardipine administration, and adjust the dose of tacrolimus accordingly.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M28" type="Trigger" span="0 15" str="Closely monitor "/>
<Mention id="M29" type="Trigger" span="91 15" str=" adjust the dose"/>
<Mention id="M30" type="Precipitant" span="41 10" str="tacrolimus" code="WM0HAQ4WNM"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M28;M29" precipitant="M30"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6720" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The plasma protein binding of nicardipine was not altered when therapeutic concentrations of furosemide, propranolol, dipyridamole, warfarin, quinidine, or naproxen were added to human plasma in vitro.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6721" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>To reduce the possibility of venous thrombosis, phlebitis, and vascular impairment, do not use small veins, such as those on the dorsum of the hand or wrist.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6722" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Avoid intraarterial administration or extravasation (5.7).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6723" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>To minimize the risk of peripheral venous irritation, change the site of infusion of nicardipine every 12 hours (5.7).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6724" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Nicardipine is not a beta-blocker and therefore gives no protection against the dangers of abrupt beta-blocker withdrawal.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6725" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Closely monitor response in patients with angina (5.3), congestive heart failure (5.4), impaired hepatic function (5.5), portal hypertension (5.5), and renal impairment (5.6) and pheochromocytoma (5.9).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6726" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In administrating nicardipine, close monitoring of blood pressure and heart rate is required.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6727" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Nicardipine may occasionally produce symptomatic hypotension or tachycardia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6728" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Avoid systemic hypotension when administering the drug to patients who have sustained an acute cerebral infarction or hemorrhage.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6729" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>No clinical events have been reported suggestive of a too rapid decrease in blood pressure with nicardipine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6730" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>However, as with any antihypertensive agent, blood pressure lowering should be accomplished over as long a time as is compatible with the patient's clinical status.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6731" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Increases in frequency, duration, or severity of angina have been seen in chronic oral therapy with nicardipine capsules.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6732" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Induction or exacerbation of angina has been seen in less than 1% of coronary artery disease patients treated with nicardipine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6733" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The mechanism of this effect has not been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6734" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Nicardipine reduced afterload without impairing myocardial contractility in preliminary hemodynamic studies of CHF patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6735" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>However, in vitro and in some patients, a negative inotropic effect has been observed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6736" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Therefore, monitor vital signs carefully when using nicardipine, particularly in combination with a beta-blocker, in patients with CHF or significant left ventricular dysfunction.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M31" type="Trigger" span="11 7" str="monitor"/>
<Mention id="M32" type="Precipitant" span="100 12" str="beta-blocker" code="N0000175556"/>
<Mention id="M33" type="SpecificInteraction" span="19 11" str="vital signs" code="41236000: Abnormal vital signs (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M31" precipitant="M32" effect="M33"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6737" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Since nicardipine is metabolized in the liver, consider lower dosages and closely monitor response.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6738" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Nicardipine administered intravenously increased hepatic venous pressure gradient by 4 mmHg in cirrhotic patients at high doses (5 mg/20 min) in one study.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6739" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Use caution in patients with portal hypertension.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6740" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>When nicardipine was given to mild-to-moderate hypertensive patients with moderate renal impairment, a significantly lower systemic clearance and higher AUC was observed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6741" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>These results are consistent with those seen after oral administration of nicardipine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6742" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Careful dose titration is advised when treating patients with more than mild renal impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6743" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>To reduce the possibility of venous thrombosis, phlebitis, local irritation, swelling, extravasation, and the rare occurrence of vascular impairment, administer drug through large peripheral veins or central veins rather than arteries or small peripheral veins, such as those on the dorsum of the hand or wrist.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6744" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>To minimize the risk of peripheral venous irritation, consider changing the site of the drug infusion every 12 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6745" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Only limited clinical experience exists in use of nicardipine for patients with hypertension from pheochromocytoma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6746" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Nicardipine inhibits the transmembrane influx of calcium ions into cardiac muscle and smooth muscle without changing serum calcium concentrations.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6747" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The contractile processes of cardiac muscle and vascular smooth muscle are dependent upon the movement of extracellular calcium ions into these cells through specific ion channels.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6748" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The effects of nicardipine are more selective to vascular smooth muscle than cardiac muscle.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6749" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In animal models, nicardipine produced relaxation of coronary vascular smooth muscle at drug levels which cause little or no negative inotropic effect.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6750" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Nicardipine produces significant decreases in systemic vascular resistance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6751" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In a study of intra-arterially administered nicardipine, the degree of vasodilation and the resultant decrease in blood pressure were more prominent in hypertensive patients than in normotensive volunteers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6752" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Administration of nicardipine to normotensive volunteers at dosages of 0.25 to 3 mg/hr for eight hours produced changes of less than 5 mmHg in systolic blood pressure and less than 3 mmHg in diastolic blood pressure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6753" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>An increase in heart rate is a normal response to vasodilation and decrease in blood pressure; in some patients these increases in heart rate may be pronounced.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6754" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In placebo-controlled trials, the mean increases in heart rate were 7± 1 bpm in postoperative patients and 8± 1 bpm in patients with severe hypertension at the end of the maintenance period.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6755" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Hemodynamic studies following intravenous dosing in patients with coronary artery disease and normal or moderately abnormal left ventricular function have shown significant increases in ejection fraction and cardiac output with no significant change, or a small decrease, in left ventricular end-diastolic pressure (LVEDP).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6756" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There is evidence that nicardipine increases blood flow.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6757" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Coronary dilatation induced by nicardipine improves perfusion and aerobic metabolism in areas with chronic ischemia, resulting in reduced lactate production and augmented oxygen consumption.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6758" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In patients with coronary artery disease, nicardipine, administered after beta-blockade, significantly improved systolic and diastolic left ventricular function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6759" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In congestive heart failure patients with impaired left ventricular function, nicardipine increased cardiac output both at rest and during exercise.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6760" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Decreases in left ventricular end-diastolic pressure were also observed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6761" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>However, in some patients with severe left ventricular dysfunction, it may have a negative inotropic effect and could lead to worsened failure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6762" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>“Coronary steal” has not been observed during treatment with nicardipine (Coronary steal is the detrimental redistribution of coronary blood flow in patients with coronary artery disease from underperfused areas toward better perfused areas.)</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6763" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Nicardipine has been shown to improve systolic shortening in both normal and hypokinetic segments of myocardial muscle.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6764" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Radionuclide angiography has confirmed that wall motion remained improved during increased oxygen demand.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6765" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>(Occasional patients have developed increased angina upon receiving nicardipine capsules.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6766" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Whether this represents coronary steal in these patients, or is the result of increased heart rate and decreased diastolic pressure, is not clear.)</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6767" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In patients with coronary artery disease, nicardipine improves left ventricular diastolic distensibility during the early filling phase, probably due to a faster rate of myocardial relaxation in previously underperfused areas.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6768" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There is little or no effect on normal myocardium, suggesting the improvement is mainly by indirect mechanisms such as afterload reduction and reduced ischemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6769" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Nicardipine has no negative effect on myocardial relaxation at therapeutic doses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6770" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The clinical benefits of these properties have not yet been demonstrated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6771" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In general, no detrimental effects on the cardiac conduction system have been seen with nicardipine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6772" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>During acute electrophysiologic studies, it increased heart rate and prolonged the corrected QT interval to a minor degree.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6773" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>It did not affect sinus node recovery or SA conduction times.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6774" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The PA, AH, and HV intervals* or the functional and effective refractory periods of the atrium were not prolonged.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6775" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The relative and effective refractory periods of the His-Purkinje system were slightly shortened.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6776" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>*PA = conduction time from high to low right atrium; AH = conduction time from low right atrium to His bundle deflection, or AV nodal conduction time; HV = conduction time through the His bundle and the bundle branch-Purkinje system.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6777" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Because nicardipine is extensively metabolized by the liver, plasma concentrations are influenced by changes in hepatic function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6778" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In a clinical study with nicardipine capsules in patients with severe liver disease, plasma concentrations were elevated and the half-life was prolonged.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6779" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Similar results were obtained in patients with hepatic disease when nicardipine hydrochloride was administered for 24 hours at 0.6 mg/hr.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6780" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>When nicardipine was given to mild-to-moderate hypertensive patients with moderate degrees of renal impairment, significant reduction in glomerular filtration rate (GFR) and effective renal plasma flow (RPF) were observed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6781" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No significant differences in liver blood flow were observed in these patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6782" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A significantly lower systemic clearance and higher area under the curve (AUC) were observed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6783" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>When nicardipine capsules (20or 30 mg TID) were given to hypertensive patients with impaired renal function, mean plasma concentrations, AUC, and Cmax were approximately two-fold higher than in healthy controls.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6784" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There was a transient increase in electrolyte excretion, including sodium.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6785" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Acute bolus administration of nicardipine hydrochloride injection (2.5 mg) in healthy volunteers decreased mean arterial pressure and renal vascular resistance; glomerular filtration rate (GFR), renal plasma flow (RPF), and the filtration fraction were unchanged.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6786" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In healthy patients undergoing abdominal surgery, nicardipine hydrochloride injection (10 mg over 20 minutes) increased GFR with no change in RPF when compared with placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6787" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In hypertensive type ll diabetic patients with nephropathy, nicardipine capsules (20 mg TID) did not change RPF and GFR, but reduced renal vascular resistance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6788" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In two well-controlled studies of patients with obstructive airway disease treated with nicardipine capsules, no evidence of increased bronchospasm was seen.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6789" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In one of the studies, nicardipine capsules improved forced expiratory volume 1 second (FEV1) and forced vital capacity (FVC) in comparison with metoprolol.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6790" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Adverse reactions reported in a limited number of patients with asthma, reactive airway disease, or obstructive airway disease were similar to reactions in other patients treated with nicardipine capsules.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6791" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A rapid dose-related increase in nicardipine plasma concentrations is seen during the first two hours after the start of an infusion of nicardipine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6792" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Plasma concentrations increase at a much slower rate after the first few hours, and approach steady state at 24to 48 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6793" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The steady-state pharmacokinetics of nicardipine are similar in elderly hypertensive patients (greater than 65 years) and young healthy adults.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6794" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>On termination of the infusion, nicardipine concentrations decrease rapidly, with at least a 50% decrease during the first two hours post-infusion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6795" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The effects of nicardipine on blood pressure significantly correlate with plasma concentrations.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6796" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Nicardipine is highly protein bound (greater than 95%) in human plasma over a wide concentration range.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6797" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following infusion, nicardipine plasma concentrations decline triexponentially, with a rapid early distribution phase (α-half-life of 3 minutes), an intermediate phase (ß-half-life of 45 minutes), and a slow terminal phase (ƴ-half-life of 14 hours) that can only be detected after long-term infusions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6798" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Total plasma clearance (Cl) is 0.4 L/hrkg, and the apparent volume of distribution (Vd) using a non-compartment model is 8.3 L/kg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6799" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacokinetics of nicardipine is linear over the dosage range of 0.5 mg/hr to 40 mg/hr.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6800" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Nicardipine has been shown to be rapidly and extensively metabolized by the hepatic cytochrome P450 enzymes, CYP2C8, 2D6, and 3A4.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6801" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Nicardipine does not induce or inhibit its own metabolism; however, nicardipine has been shown to inhibit certain cytochrome P450 enzymes (including CYP3A4, CYP2D6, CYP2C8, and CYP2C19).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6802" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Inhibition of these enzymes may result in increased plasma levels of certain drugs, including cyclosporine and tacrolimus.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M36" type="Trigger" span="42 23" str="increased plasma levels"/>
<Mention id="M35" type="Precipitant" span="94 12" str="cyclosporine" code="83HN0GTJ6D"/>
<Mention id="M37" type="Precipitant" span="111 10" str="tacrolimus" code="WM0HAQ4WNM"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M36" precipitant="M35" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M36" precipitant="M37" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6803" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The altered pharmacokinetics may necessitate dosage adjustment of the affected drug or discontinuation of treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6804" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>After coadministration of a radioactive intravenous dose of nicardipine with an oral 30 mg dose given every 8 hours, 49% of the radioactivity was recovered in the urine and 43% in the feces within 96 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6805" LabelDrug="Nicardipine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>None of the dose was recovered as unchanged nicardipine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="lactated ringer’s injection, usp" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="sodium bicarbonate (5%) injection, usp" precipitantCode="8MDF5V39QO"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cimetidine" precipitantCode="80061L1WGD" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cyclosporine" precipitantCode="83HN0GTJ6D" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="cyclosporine" precipitantCode="83HN0GTJ6D"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="tacrolimus" precipitantCode="WM0HAQ4WNM" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="tacrolimus" precipitantCode="WM0HAQ4WNM"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="antihypertensive agents" precipitantCode="N0000178477"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="beta-blocker" precipitantCode="N0000175556" effect="41236000: Abnormal vital signs (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="beta-blocker" precipitantCode="N0000175556"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>