<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Potassium Citrate" setid="2215dc1d-0b5a-469e-9b51-4d7480a51078">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
Potassium Citrate Extended-release Tablets are contraindicated:  In patients with hyperkalemia (or who have conditions pre-disposing them to hyperkalemia), as a further rise in serum potassium concentration may produce cardiac arrest. Such conditions include: chronic renal failure, uncontrolled diabetes mellitus, acute dehydration, strenuous physical exercise in unconditioned individuals, adrenal insufficiency, extensive tissue breakdown or the administration of a potassium-sparing agent (such as triamterene, spironolactone or amiloride). In patients in whom there is cause for arrest or delay in tablet passage through the gastrointestinal tract, such as those suffering from delayed gastric emptying, esophageal compression, intestinal obstruction or stricture, or those taking anticholinergic medication. In patients with peptic ulcer disease because of its ulcerogenic potential. In patients with active urinary tract infection (with either urea-splitting or other organisms, in association with either calcium or struvite stones). The ability of Potassium Citrate Extended-release Tablets to increase urinary citrate may be attenuated by bacterial enzymatic degradation of citrate. Moreover, the rise in urinary pH resulting from Potassium Citrate Extended-release Tablets therapy might promote further bacterial growth. In patients with renal insufficiency (glomerular filtration rate of less than 0.7 ml/kg/min), because of the danger of soft tissue calcification and increased risk for the development of hyperkalemia.        Patients with hyperkalemia (or who have conditions predisposing them to hyperkalemia). Such conditions include chronic renal failure, uncontrolled diabetes mellitus, acute dehydration, strenuous physical exercise in unconditioned individuals, adrenal insufficiency, extensive tissue breakdown (4) Patients for whom there is cause for arrest or delay in tablet passage through the gastrointestinal tract such as those suffering from delayed gastric emptying, esophageal compression, intestinal obstruction or stricture (4) Patients with peptic ulcer disease (4) Patients with active urinary tract infection (4) Patients with renal insufficiency (glomerular filtration rate of less than 0.7 ml/kg/min) (4)</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
Objective: To restore normal urinary citrate (greater than 320 mg/day and as close to the normal mean of 640 mg/day as possible), and to increase urinary pH to a level of 6.0 to 7.0.  Severe hypocitraturia (urinary citrate &amp;lt; 150 mg/day): therapy should be initiated at 60 mEq per day; a dose of 30 mEq two times per day or 20 mEq three times per day with meals or within 30 minutes after meals or bedtime snack (2.2) Mild to moderate hypocitraturia (urinary citrate &amp;gt;150 mg/day): therapy should be initiated at 30 mEq per day; a dose of 15 mEq two times per day or 10 mEq three times per day with meals or within 30 minutes after meals or bedtime snack (2.3)          Treatment with extended release potassium citrate should be added to a regimen that limits salt intake (avoidance of foods with high salt content and of added salt at the table) and encourages high fluid intake (urine volume should be at least two liters per day). The objective of treatment with Potassium Citrate Extended-release Tablets is to provide Potassium Citrate Extended-release Tablets in sufficient dosage to restore normal urinary citrate (greater than 320 mg/day and as close to the normal mean of 640 mg/day as possible), and to increase urinary pH to a level of 6.0 or 7.0. Monitor serum electrolytes (sodium, potassium, chloride and carbon dioxide), serum creatinine and complete blood counts every four months and more frequently in patients with cardiac disease, renal disease or acidosis. Perform electrocardiograms periodically. Treatment should be discontinued if there is hyperkalemia, a significant rise in serum creatinine or a significant fall in blood hemocrit or hemoglobin.          In patients with severe hypocitraturia (urinary citrate &amp;lt; 150 mg/day), therapy should be initiated at a dosage of 60 mEq/day (30 mEq two times/day or 20 mEq three times/day with meals or within 30 minutes after meals or bedtime snack). Twenty-four hour urinary citrate and/or urinary pH measurements should be used to determine the adequacy of the initial dosage and to evaluate the effectiveness of any dosage change. In addition, urinary citrate and/or pH should be measured every four months. Doses of Potassium Citrate Extended-release Tablets greater than 100 mEq/day have not been studied and should be avoided.          In patients with mild to moderate hypocitraturia (urinary citrate &amp;gt; 150 mg/day) therapy should be initiated at 30 mEq/day (15 mEq two times/day or 10 mEq three times/day within 30 minutes after meals or bedtime snack). Twenty-four hour urinary citrate and/or urinary pH measurements should be used to determine the adequacy of the initial dosage and to evaluate the effectiveness of any dosage change. Doses of Potassium Citrate Extended-release Tablets greater than 100 mEq/day have not been studied and should be avoided.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
The following drug interactions may occur with potassium citrate:  Potassium-sparing diuretics: concomitant administration should be avoided since the simultaneous administration of these agents can produce severe hyperkalemia (7.1) Drugs that slow gastrointestinal transit time: These agents (such as anticholinergics) can be expected to increase the gastrointestinal irritation produced by potassium salts (7.2)                Potassium-sparing Diuretics: Concomitant administration of Potassium Citrate Extended-release Tablets and a potassium-sparing diuretic (such as triamterene, spironolactone or amiloride) should be avoided since the simultaneous administration of these agents can produce severe hyperkalemia.                  Drugs that slow gastrointestinal transit time: These agents (such as anticholinergics) can be expected to increase the gastrointestinal irritation produced by potassium salts.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
Hyperkalemia: In patients with impaired mechanisms for excreting potassium, Potassium Citrate Extended-release Tablets administration can produce hyperkalemia and cardiac arrest. Potentially fatal hyperkalemia can develop rapidly and be asymptomatic. The use of Potassium Citrate Extended-release Tablets in patients with chronic renal failure, or any other condition which impairs potassium excretion such as severe myocardial damage or heart failure, should be avoided (5.1) Gastrointestinal lesions: if there is severe vomiting, abdominal pain or gastrointestinal bleeding, Potassium Citrate Extended-release Tablets should be discontinued immediately and the possibility of bowel perforation or obstruction investigated (5.2)          In patients with impaired mechanisms for excreting potassium, Potassium Citrate Extended-release Tablets administration can produce hyperkalemia and cardiac arrest. Potentially fatal hyperkalemia can develop rapidly and be asymptomatic. The use of Potassium Citrate Extended-release Tablets in patients with chronic renal failure, or any other condition which impairs potassium excretion such as severe myocardial damage or heart failure, should be avoided. Closely monitor for signs of hyperkalemia with periodic blood tests and ECGs.          Because of reports of upper gastrointestinal mucosal lesions following administration of potassium chloride (wax-matrix), an endoscopic examination of the upper gastrointestinal mucosa was performed in 30 normal volunteers after they had taken glycopyrrolate 2 mg p.o. t.i.d., Potassium Citrate Extended-release Tablets 95 mEq/day, wax-matrix potassium chloride 96 mEq/day or wax-matrix placebo, in thrice daily schedule in the fasting state for one week. Potassium Citrate Extended-release Tablets and the wax-matrix formulation of potassium chloride were indistinguishable but both were significantly more irritating than the wax-matrix placebo. In a subsequent, similar study, lesions were less severe when glycopyrrolate was omitted. Solid dosage forms of potassium chlorides have produced stenotic and/or ulcerative lesions of the small bowel and deaths. These lesions are caused by a high local concentration of potassium ions in the region of the dissolving tablets, which injured the bowel. In addition, perhaps because wax-matrix preparations are not enteric-coated and release some of their potassium content in the stomach, there have been reports of upper gastrointestinal bleeding associated with these products. The frequency of gastrointestinal lesions with wax-matrix potassium chloride products is estimated at one per 100,000 patient-years. Experience with Potassium Citrate Extended-release Tablets is limited, but a similar frequency of gastrointestinal lesions should be anticipated. If there is severe vomiting, abdominal pain or gastrointestinal bleeding, Potassium Citrate Extended-release Tablets should be discontinued immediately and the possibility of bowel perforation or obstruction investigated.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
When Potassium Citrate Extended-release Tablets are given orally, the metabolism of absorbed citrate produces an alkaline load. The induced alkaline load in turn increases urinary pH and raises urinary citrate by augmenting citrate clearance without measurably altering ultrafilterable serum citrate. Thus, Potassium Citrate Extended-release Tablets therapy appears to increase urinary citrate principally by modifying the renal handling of citrate, rather than by increasing the filtered load of citrate. The increased filtered load of citrate may play some role, however, as in small comparisons of oral citrate and oral bicarbonate, citrate had a greater effect on urinary citrate. In addition to raising urinary pH and citrate, Potassium Citrate Extended-release Tablets increase urinary potassium by approximately the amount contained in the medication. In some patients, Potassium Citrate Extended-release Tablets cause a transient reduction in urinary calcium. The changes induced by Potassium Citrate Extended-release Tablets produce urine that is less conducive to the crystallization of stone-forming salts (calcium oxalate, calcium phosphate and uric acid). Increased citrate in the urine, by complexing with calcium, decreases calcium ion activity and thus the saturation of calcium oxalate. Citrate also inhibits the spontaneous nucleation of calcium oxalate and calcium phosphate (brushite). The increase in urinary pH also decreases calcium ion activity by increasing calcium complexation to dissociated anions. The rise in urinary pH also increases the ionization of uric acid to the more soluble urate ion. Potassium Citrate Extended-release Tablets therapy does not alter the urinary saturation of calcium phosphate, since the effect of increased citrate complexation of calcium is opposed by the rise in pH-dependent dissociation of phosphate. Calcium phosphate stones are more stable in alkaline urine. In the setting of normal renal function, the rise in urinary citrate following a single dose begins by the first hour and lasts for 12 hours. With multiple doses the rise in citrate excretion reaches its peak by the third day and averts the normally wide circadian fluctuation in urinary citrate, thus maintaining urinary citrate at a higher, more constant level throughout the day. When the treatment is withdrawn, urinary citrate begins to decline toward the pre-treatment level on the first day. The rise in citrate excretion is directly dependent on the Potassium Citrate Extended-release Tablets dosage. Following long-term treatment, Potassium Citrate Extended-release Tablets at a dosage of 60 mEq/day raises urinary citrate by approximately 400 mg/day and increases urinary pH by approximately 0.7 units. In patients with severe renal tubular acidosis or chronic diarrheal syndrome where urinary citrate may be very low (&amp;lt;100 mg/day), Potassium Citrate Extended-release Tablets may be relatively ineffective in raising urinary citrate. A higher dose of Potassium Citrate Extended-release Tablets may therefore be required to produce a satisfactory citraturic response. In patients with renal tubular acidosis in whom urinary pH may be high, Potassium Citrate Extended-release Tablets produce a relatively small rise in urinary pH.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="6806" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Potassium citrate extended-release tablets are contraindicated: In patients with hyperkalemia (or who have conditions pre-disposing them to hyperkalemia), as a further rise in serum potassium concentration may produce cardiac arrest.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6807" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Such conditions include: chronic renal failure, uncontrolled diabetes mellitus, acute dehydration, strenuous physical exercise in unconditioned individuals, adrenal insufficiency, extensive tissue breakdown or the administration of a potassium-sparing agent (such as triamterene, spironolactone or amiloride).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6808" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>In patients in whom there is cause for arrest or delay in tablet passage through the gastrointestinal tract, such as those suffering from delayed gastric emptying, esophageal compression, intestinal obstruction or stricture, or those taking anticholinergic medication.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6809" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>In patients with peptic ulcer disease because of its ulcerogenic potential.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6810" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>In patients with active urinary tract infection (with either urea-splitting or other organisms, in association with either calcium or struvite stones).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6811" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>The ability of potassium citrate extended-release tablets to increase urinary citrate may be attenuated by bacterial enzymatic degradation of citrate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6812" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Moreover, the rise in urinary pH resulting from potassium citrate extended-release tablets therapy might promote further bacterial growth.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6813" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>In patients with renal insufficiency (glomerular filtration rate of less than 0.7 ml/kg/min), because of the danger of soft tissue calcification and increased risk for the development of hyperkalemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6814" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Patients with hyperkalemia (or who have conditions predisposing them to hyperkalemia).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6815" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Such conditions include chronic renal failure, uncontrolled diabetes mellitus, acute dehydration, strenuous physical exercise in unconditioned individuals, adrenal insufficiency, extensive tissue breakdown (4) Patients for whom there is cause for arrest or delay in tablet passage through the gastrointestinal tract such as those suffering from delayed gastric emptying, esophageal compression, intestinal obstruction or stricture (4) Patients with peptic ulcer disease (4) Patients with active urinary tract infection (4) Patients with renal insufficiency (glomerular filtration rate of less than 0.7 ml/kg/min) (4)</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6816" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Objective: To restore normal urinary citrate (greater than 320 mg/day and as close to the normal mean of 640 mg/day as possible), and to increase urinary pH to a level of 6.0 to 7.0.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6817" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Severe hypocitraturia (urinary citrate &lt; 150 mg/day): therapy should be initiated at 60 mEq per day; a dose of 30 mEq two times per day or 20 mEq three times per day with meals or within 30 minutes after meals or bedtime snack (2.2) Mild to moderate hypocitraturia (urinary citrate &gt;150 mg/day): therapy should be initiated at 30 mEq per day; a dose of 15 mEq two times per day or 10 mEq three times per day with meals or within 30 minutes after meals or bedtime snack (2.3) Treatment with extended release potassium citrate should be added to a regimen that limits salt intake (avoidance of foods with high salt content and of added salt at the table) and encourages high fluid intake (urine volume should be at least two liters per day).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M3" type="Trigger" span="579 9" str="avoidance"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="592 28" str="foods with high salt content" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M4" type="Precipitant" span="566 4" str="salt" code="451W47IQ8X"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M3" precipitant="M2"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M3" precipitant="M4"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6818" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The objective of treatment with potassium citrate extended-release tablets is to provide potassium citrate extended-release tablets in sufficient dosage to restore normal urinary citrate (greater than 320 mg/day and as close to the normal mean of 640 mg/day as possible), and to increase urinary pH to a level of 6.0 or 7.0.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6819" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor serum electrolytes (sodium, potassium, chloride and carbon dioxide), serum creatinine and complete blood counts every four months and more frequently in patients with cardiac disease, renal disease or acidosis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6820" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Treatment should be discontinued if there is hyperkalemia, a significant rise in serum creatinine or a significant fall in blood hemocrit or hemoglobin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6821" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In patients with severe hypocitraturia (urinary citrate &lt; 150 mg/day), therapy should be initiated at a dosage of 60 mEq/day (30 mEq two times/day or 20 mEq three times/day with meals or within 30 minutes after meals or bedtime snack).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6822" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Twenty-four hour urinary citrate and/or urinary pH measurements should be used to determine the adequacy of the initial dosage and to evaluate the effectiveness of any dosage change.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6823" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In addition, urinary citrate and/or pH should be measured every four months.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6824" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Doses of potassium citrate extended-release tablets greater than 100 mEq/day have not been studied and should be avoided.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6825" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In patients with mild to moderate hypocitraturia (urinary citrate &gt; 150 mg/day) therapy should be initiated at 30 mEq/day (15 mEq two times/day or 10 mEq three times/day within 30 minutes after meals or bedtime snack).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6826" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The following drug interactions may occur with potassium citrate: Potassium-sparing diuretics: concomitant administration should be avoided since the simultaneous administration of these agents can produce severe hyperkalemia (7.1) Drugs that slow gastrointestinal transit time: These agents (such as anticholinergics) can be expected to increase the gastrointestinal irritation produced by potassium salts (7.2) Potassium-sparing Diuretics: Concomitant administration of potassium citrate extended-release tablets and a potassium-sparing diuretic (such as triamterene, spironolactone or amiloride) should be avoided since the simultaneous administration of these agents can produce severe hyperkalemia.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M23" type="Trigger" span="198 7" str="produce"/>
<Mention id="M6" type="Precipitant" span="588 9" str="amiloride" code="7DZO8EB0Z3"/>
<Mention id="M25" type="SpecificInteraction" span="206 19" str="severe hyperkalemia" code="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M11" type="Trigger" span="338 8" str="increase"/>
<Mention id="M9" type="Precipitant" span="301 16" str="anticholinergics" code="N0000175574"/>
<Mention id="M13" type="SpecificInteraction" span="338 40" str="increase the gastrointestinal irritation" code="95516005: Gastrointestinal irritation (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M12" type="Precipitant" span="232 45" str="Drugs that slow gastrointestinal transit time" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M15" type="Precipitant" span="521 26" str="potassium-sparing diuretic" code="N0000175418"/>
<Mention id="M18" type="Precipitant" span="66 27" str="Potassium-sparing diuretics" code="N0000175418"/>
<Mention id="M21" type="Precipitant" span="570 14" str="spironolactone" code="27O7W4T232"/>
<Mention id="M24" type="Precipitant" span="557 11" str="triamterene" code="WS821Z52LQ"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M23" precipitant="M6" effect="M25"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M11" precipitant="M9" effect="M13"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M11" precipitant="M12" effect="M13"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M23" precipitant="M15" effect="M25"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M23" precipitant="M18" effect="M25"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M23" precipitant="M21" effect="M25"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M23" precipitant="M24" effect="M25"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6827" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Drugs that slow gastrointestinal transit time: These agents (such as anticholinergics) can be expected to increase the gastrointestinal irritation produced by potassium salts.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M29" type="Trigger" span="106 8" str="increase"/>
<Mention id="M27" type="Precipitant" span="69 16" str="anticholinergics" code="N0000175574"/>
<Mention id="M31" type="SpecificInteraction" span="106 40" str="increase the gastrointestinal irritation" code="95516005: Gastrointestinal irritation (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M30" type="Precipitant" span="0 45" str="Drugs that slow gastrointestinal transit time" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M29" precipitant="M27" effect="M31"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M29" precipitant="M30" effect="M31"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6828" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hyperkalemia: In patients with impaired mechanisms for excreting potassium, potassium citrate extended-release tablets administration can produce hyperkalemia and cardiac arrest.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6829" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Potentially fatal hyperkalemia can develop rapidly and be asymptomatic.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6830" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The use of potassium citrate extended-release tablets in patients with chronic renal failure, or any other condition which impairs potassium excretion such as severe myocardial damage or heart failure, should be avoided (5.1) Gastrointestinal lesions: if there is severe vomiting, abdominal pain or gastrointestinal bleeding, potassium citrate extended-release tablets should be discontinued immediately and the possibility of bowel perforation or obstruction investigated (5.2) In patients with impaired mechanisms for excreting potassium, potassium citrate extended-release tablets administration can produce hyperkalemia and cardiac arrest.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6831" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The use of potassium citrate extended-release tablets in patients with chronic renal failure, or any other condition which impairs potassium excretion such as severe myocardial damage or heart failure, should be avoided.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6832" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Closely monitor for signs of hyperkalemia with periodic blood tests and ECGs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6833" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Because of reports of upper gastrointestinal mucosal lesions following administration of potassium chloride (wax-matrix), an endoscopic examination of the upper gastrointestinal mucosa was performed in 30 normal volunteers after they had taken glycopyrrolate 2 mg p.o. t.i.d., potassium citrate extended-release tablets 95 mEq/day, wax-matrix potassium chloride 96 mEq/day or wax-matrix placebo, in thrice daily schedule in the fasting state for one week.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6834" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Potassium citrate extended-release tablets and the wax-matrix formulation of potassium chloride were indistinguishable but both were significantly more irritating than the wax-matrix placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6835" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In a subsequent, similar study, lesions were less severe when glycopyrrolate was omitted.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6836" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Solid dosage forms of potassium chlorides have produced stenotic and/or ulcerative lesions of the small bowel and deaths.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6837" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>These lesions are caused by a high local concentration of potassium ions in the region of the dissolving tablets, which injured the bowel.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6838" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In addition, perhaps because wax-matrix preparations are not enteric-coated and release some of their potassium content in the stomach, there have been reports of upper gastrointestinal bleeding associated with these products.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6839" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The frequency of gastrointestinal lesions with wax-matrix potassium chloride products is estimated at one per 100,000 patient-years.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6840" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Experience with potassium citrate extended-release tablets is limited, but a similar frequency of gastrointestinal lesions should be anticipated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6841" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If there is severe vomiting, abdominal pain or gastrointestinal bleeding, potassium citrate extended-release tablets should be discontinued immediately and the possibility of bowel perforation or obstruction investigated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6842" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>When potassium citrate extended-release tablets are given orally, the metabolism of absorbed citrate produces an alkaline load.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6843" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The induced alkaline load in turn increases urinary pH and raises urinary citrate by augmenting citrate clearance without measurably altering ultrafilterable serum citrate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6844" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Thus, potassium citrate extended-release tablets therapy appears to increase urinary citrate principally by modifying the renal handling of citrate, rather than by increasing the filtered load of citrate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6845" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The increased filtered load of citrate may play some role, however, as in small comparisons of oral citrate and oral bicarbonate, citrate had a greater effect on urinary citrate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6846" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In addition to raising urinary pH and citrate, potassium citrate extended-release tablets increase urinary potassium by approximately the amount contained in the medication.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6847" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In some patients, potassium citrate extended-release tablets cause a transient reduction in urinary calcium.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6848" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The changes induced by potassium citrate extended-release tablets produce urine that is less conducive to the crystallization of stone-forming salts (calcium oxalate, calcium phosphate and uric acid).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6849" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Increased citrate in the urine, by complexing with calcium, decreases calcium ion activity and thus the saturation of calcium oxalate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6850" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Citrate also inhibits the spontaneous nucleation of calcium oxalate and calcium phosphate (brushite).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6851" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The increase in urinary pH also decreases calcium ion activity by increasing calcium complexation to dissociated anions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6852" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The rise in urinary pH also increases the ionization of uric acid to the more soluble urate ion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6853" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Potassium citrate extended-release tablets therapy does not alter the urinary saturation of calcium phosphate, since the effect of increased citrate complexation of calcium is opposed by the rise in pH-dependent dissociation of phosphate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6854" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Calcium phosphate stones are more stable in alkaline urine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6855" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In the setting of normal renal function, the rise in urinary citrate following a single dose begins by the first hour and lasts for 12 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6856" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>With multiple doses the rise in citrate excretion reaches its peak by the third day and averts the normally wide circadian fluctuation in urinary citrate, thus maintaining urinary citrate at a higher, more constant level throughout the day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6857" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>When the treatment is withdrawn, urinary citrate begins to decline toward the pre-treatment level on the first day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6858" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The rise in citrate excretion is directly dependent on the potassium citrate extended-release tablets dosage.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6859" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following long-term treatment, potassium citrate extended-release tablets at a dosage of 60 mEq/day raises urinary citrate by approximately 400 mg/day and increases urinary pH by approximately 0.7 units.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6860" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In patients with severe renal tubular acidosis or chronic diarrheal syndrome where urinary citrate may be very low (&lt;100 mg/day), potassium citrate extended-release tablets may be relatively ineffective in raising urinary citrate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6861" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A higher dose of potassium citrate extended-release tablets may therefore be required to produce a satisfactory citraturic response.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6862" LabelDrug="Potassium Citrate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In patients with renal tubular acidosis in whom urinary pH may be high, potassium citrate extended-release tablets produce a relatively small rise in urinary pH.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="foods with high salt content" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="salt" precipitantCode="451W47IQ8X"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="amiloride" precipitantCode="7DZO8EB0Z3" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="anticholinergics" precipitantCode="N0000175574" effect="95516005: Gastrointestinal irritation (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="drugs that slow gastrointestinal transit time" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="95516005: Gastrointestinal irritation (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="potassium-sparing diuretic" precipitantCode="N0000175418" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="potassium-sparing diuretics" precipitantCode="N0000175418" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="spironolactone" precipitantCode="27O7W4T232" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="triamterene" precipitantCode="WS821Z52LQ" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>