<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Procardia" setid="e04aa152-b08d-47f7-b976-f8bee4c386db">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
Known hypersensitivity reaction to PROCARDIA.</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
The dosage of PROCARDIA needed to suppress angina and that can be tolerated by the patient must be established by titration. Excessive doses can result in hypotension.  Therapy should be initiated with the 10 mg capsule. The starting dose is one 10 mg capsule, swallowed whole, 3 times/day. The usual effective dose range is 10–20 mg three times daily. Some patients, especially those with evidence of coronary artery spasm, respond only to higher doses, more frequent administration, or both. In such patients, doses of 20–30 mg three or four times daily may be effective. Doses above 120 mg daily are rarely necessary. More than 180 mg per day is not recommended. In most cases, PROCARDIA titration should proceed over a 7–14 day period so that the physician can assess the response to each dose level and monitor the blood pressure before proceeding to higher doses. If symptoms so warrant, titration may proceed more rapidly provided that the patient is assessed frequently. Based on the patient's physical activity level, attack frequency, and sublingual nitroglycerin consumption, the dose of PROCARDIA may be increased from 10 mg t.i.d. to 20 mg t.i.d. and then to 30 mg t.i.d. over a three-day period. In hospitalized patients under close observation, the dose may be increased in 10 mg increments over four- to six-hour periods as required to control pain and arrhythmias due to ischemia. A single dose should rarely exceed 30 mg. Avoid co-administration of nifedipine with grapefruit juice (see CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY and PRECAUTIONS: Other Interactions). No "rebound effect" has been observed upon discontinuation of PROCARDIA. However, if discontinuation of PROCARDIA is necessary, sound clinical practice suggests that the dosage should be decreased gradually with close physician supervision.        Sublingual nitroglycerin may be taken as required for the control of acute manifestations of angina, particularly during PROCARDIA titration. See PRECAUTIONS, Drug Interactions, for information on co-administration of PROCARDIA with beta blockers or long-acting nitrates.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
(See INDICATIONS AND USAGE and WARNINGS.) Experience in over 1400 patients in a non-comparative clinical trial has shown that concomitant administration of PROCARDIA and beta-blocking agents is usually well tolerated, but there have been occasional literature reports suggesting that the combination may increase the likelihood of congestive heart failure, severe hypotension, or exacerbation of angina.          PROCARDIA may be safely co-administered with nitrates, but there have been no controlled studies to evaluate the antianginal effectiveness of this combination.          Since there have been isolated reports of patients with elevated digoxin levels, and since there is a possible interaction between digoxin and nifedipine, it is recommended that digoxin levels be monitored when initiating, adjusting, and discontinuing nifedipine to avoid possible over- or under-digitalization.          There have been rare reports of an interaction between quinidine and nifedipine (with a decreased plasma level of quinidine).          There have been rare reports of increased prothrombin time in patients taking coumarin anticoagulants to whom PROCARDIA was administered. However, the relationship to PROCARDIA therapy is uncertain.          A study in six healthy volunteers has shown a significant increase in peak nifedipine plasma levels (80%) and area-under-the-curve (74%) after a one week course of cimetidine at 1000 mg per day and nifedipine at 40 mg per day. Ranitidine produced smaller, non-significant increases. The effect may be mediated by the known inhibition of cimetidine on hepatic cytochrome P-450, the enzyme system probably responsible for the first-pass metabolism of nifedipine. If nifedipine therapy is initiated in a patient currently receiving cimetidine, cautious titration is advised. Nifedipine is metabolized by CYP3A4. Co-administration of nifedipine with phenytoin, an inducer of CYP3A4, lowers the systemic exposure to nifedipine by approximately 70%. Avoid co-administration of nifedipine with phenytoin or any known CYP3A4 inducer or consider an alternative antihypertensive therapy.</Section>
<Section name="PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="42232-9">
Because PROCARDIA decreases peripheral vascular resistance, careful monitoring of blood pressure during the initial administration and titration of PROCARDIA is suggested. Close observation is especially recommended for patients already taking medications that are known to lower blood pressure. (See WARNINGS.)          Mild to moderate peripheral edema, typically associated with arterial vasodilation and not due to left ventricular dysfunction, occurs in about one in ten patients treated with PROCARDIA (nifedipine). This edema occurs primarily in the lower extremities and usually responds to diuretic therapy. With patients whose angina is complicated by congestive heart failure, care should be taken to differentiate this peripheral edema from the effects of increasing left ventricular dysfunction.            Rare, usually transient, but occasionally significant elevations of enzymes such as alkaline phosphatase, CPK, LDH, SGOT, and SGPT have been noted. The relationship to PROCARDIA therapy is uncertain in most cases, but probable in some. These laboratory abnormalities have rarely been associated with clinical symptoms; however, cholestasis with or without jaundice has been reported. Rare instances of allergic hepatitis have been reported. PROCARDIA, like other calcium channel blockers, decreases platelet aggregation in vitro. Limited clinical studies have demonstrated a moderate but statistically significant decrease in platelet aggregation and an increase in bleeding time in some PROCARDIA patients. This is thought to be a function of inhibition of calcium transport across the platelet membrane. No clinical significance for these findings has been demonstrated. Positive direct Coombs Test with/without hemolytic anemia has been reported but a causal relationship between PROCARDIA administration and positivity of this laboratory test, including hemolysis, could not be determined. Although PROCARDIA has been used safely in patients with renal dysfunction and has been reported to exert a beneficial effect, in certain cases, rare, reversible elevations in BUN and serum creatinine have been reported in patients with pre-existing chronic renal insufficiency. The relationship to PROCARDIA therapy is uncertain in most cases but probable in some.               (See INDICATIONS AND USAGE and WARNINGS.) Experience in over 1400 patients in a non-comparative clinical trial has shown that concomitant administration of PROCARDIA and beta-blocking agents is usually well tolerated, but there have been occasional literature reports suggesting that the combination may increase the likelihood of congestive heart failure, severe hypotension, or exacerbation of angina.          PROCARDIA may be safely co-administered with nitrates, but there have been no controlled studies to evaluate the antianginal effectiveness of this combination.          Since there have been isolated reports of patients with elevated digoxin levels, and since there is a possible interaction between digoxin and nifedipine, it is recommended that digoxin levels be monitored when initiating, adjusting, and discontinuing nifedipine to avoid possible over- or under-digitalization.          There have been rare reports of an interaction between quinidine and nifedipine (with a decreased plasma level of quinidine).          There have been rare reports of increased prothrombin time in patients taking coumarin anticoagulants to whom PROCARDIA was administered. However, the relationship to PROCARDIA therapy is uncertain.          A study in six healthy volunteers has shown a significant increase in peak nifedipine plasma levels (80%) and area-under-the-curve (74%) after a one week course of cimetidine at 1000 mg per day and nifedipine at 40 mg per day. Ranitidine produced smaller, non-significant increases. The effect may be mediated by the known inhibition of cimetidine on hepatic cytochrome P-450, the enzyme system probably responsible for the first-pass metabolism of nifedipine. If nifedipine therapy is initiated in a patient currently receiving cimetidine, cautious titration is advised. Nifedipine is metabolized by CYP3A4. Co-administration of nifedipine with phenytoin, an inducer of CYP3A4, lowers the systemic exposure to nifedipine by approximately 70%. Avoid co-administration of nifedipine with phenytoin or any known CYP3A4 inducer or consider an alternative antihypertensive therapy.                 Co-administration of nifedipine with grapefruit juice resulted in approximately a doubling in nifedipine AUC and Cmax with no change in half-life. The increased plasma concentrations most likely result from inhibition of CYP 3A4 related first-pass metabolism. Avoid ingestion of grapefruit and grapefruit juice while taking nifedipine.            Nifedipine was administered orally to rats for two years and was not shown to be carcinogenic. When given to rats prior to mating, nifedipine caused reduced fertility at a dose approximately 5 times the maximum recommended human dose. There is a literature report of reversible reduction in the ability of human sperm obtained from a limited number of infertile men taking recommended doses of nifedipine to bind to and fertilize an ovum in vitro. In vivo mutagenicity studies were negative.               Nifedipine has been shown to produce teratogenic findings in rats and rabbits, including digital anomalies similar to those reported for phenytoin. Digital anomalies have been reported to occur with other members of the dihydropyridine class and are possibly a result of compromised uterine blood flow. Nifedipine administration was associated with a variety of embryotoxic, placentotoxic, and fetotoxic effects, including stunted fetuses (rats, mice, rabbits), rib deformities (mice), cleft palate (mice), small placentas and underdeveloped chorionic villi (monkeys), embryonic and fetal deaths (rats, mice, rabbits), and prolonged pregnancy/decreased neonatal survival (rats; not evaluated in other species). On a mg/kg basis, all of the doses associated with the teratogenic embryotoxic or fetotoxic effects in animals were higher (5 to 50 times) than the maximum recommended human dose of 120 mg/day. On a mg/m2 basis, some doses were higher and some were lower than the maximum recommended human dose but all were within an order of magnitude of it. The doses associated with placentotoxic effects in monkeys were equivalent to or lower than the maximum recommended human dose on a mg/m2 basis. There are no adequate and well-controlled studies in pregnant women. PROCARDIA should be used during pregnancy only if the potential benefit justifies the potential risk.            Nifedipine is transferred through breast milk. PROCARDIA should be used during breast-feeding only if the potential benefit justifies the potential risk.          Safety and effectiveness in pediatric patients have not been established. Use in pediatric population is not recommended.          Age appears to have a significant effect on the pharmacokinetics of nifedipine. The clearance is decreased resulting in a higher AUC in the elderly. These changes are not due to changes in renal function (see CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY, Pharmacokinetics).</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS SECTION" id="34071-1">
Although, in most patients, the hypotensive effect of PROCARDIA is modest and well tolerated, occasional patients have had excessive and poorly tolerated hypotension. These responses have usually occurred during initial titration or at the time of subsequent upward dosage adjustment. Although patients have rarely experienced excessive hypotension on PROCARDIA alone, this may be more common in patients on concomitant beta blocker therapy. Although not approved for this purpose, PROCARDIA and other immediate-release nifedipine capsules have been used (orally and sublingually) for acute reduction of blood pressure. Several well-documented reports describe cases of profound hypotension, myocardial infarction, and death when immediate-release nifedipine was used in this way. PROCARDIA capsules should not be used for the acute reduction of blood pressure.  Severe hypotension and/or increased fluid volume requirements have been reported in patients receiving PROCARDIA together with a beta-blocking agent who underwent coronary artery bypass surgery using high dose fentanyl anesthesia. The interaction with high dose fentanyl appears to be due to the combination of PROCARDIA and a beta blocker, but the possibility that it may occur with PROCARDIA alone, with low doses of fentanyl, in other surgical procedures, or with other narcotic analgesics cannot be ruled out. In PROCARDIA treated patients where surgery using high dose fentanyl anesthesia is contemplated, the physician should be aware of these potential problems and, if the patient's condition permits, sufficient time (at least 36 hours) should be allowed for PROCARDIA to be washed out of the body prior to surgery.          Rarely, patients, particularly those who have severe obstructive coronary artery disease, have developed well documented increased frequency, duration, and/or severity of angina or acute myocardial infarction on starting PROCARDIA or at the time of dosage increase. The mechanism of this effect is not established. Several well-controlled, randomized trials studied the use of immediate-release nifedipine in patients who had just sustained myocardial infarctions. In none of these trials did immediate-release nifedipine appear to provide any benefit. In some of the trials, patients who received immediate-release nifedipine had significantly worse outcomes than patients who received placebo. PROCARDIA capsules should not be administered within the first week or two after myocardial infarction, and they should also be avoided in the setting of acute coronary syndrome (when infarction may be imminent).           PROCARDIA and other immediate-release nifedipine capsules have also been used for the long-term control of essential hypertension, although PROCARDIA capsules have not been approved for this purpose and no properly controlled studies have been conducted to define an appropriate dose or dose interval for such treatment. PROCARDIA capsules should not be used for the control of essential hypertension.           Patients recently withdrawn from beta blockers may develop a withdrawal syndrome with increased angina, probably related to increased sensitivity to catecholamines. Initiation of PROCARDIA treatment will not prevent this occurrence and might be expected to exacerbate it by provoking reflex catecholamine release. There have been occasional reports of increased angina in a setting of beta blocker withdrawal and PROCARDIA initiation. It is important to taper beta blockers if possible, rather than stopping them abruptly before beginning PROCARDIA.          Rarely, patients, usually those receiving a beta blocker, have developed heart failure after beginning PROCARDIA. Patients with tight aortic stenosis may be at greater risk for such an event, as the unloading effect of PROCARDIA would be expected to be of less benefit to these patients, owing to their fixed impedance to flow across the aortic valve.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
PROCARDIA is a calcium ion influx inhibitor (slow-channel blocker or calcium ion antagonist) and inhibits the transmembrane influx of calcium ions into cardiac muscle and smooth muscle. The contractile processes of cardiac muscle and vascular smooth muscle are dependent upon the movement of extracellular calcium ions into these cells through specific ion channels. PROCARDIA selectively inhibits calcium ion influx across the cell membrane of cardiac muscle and vascular smooth muscle without changing serum calcium concentrations.        The precise means by which this inhibition relieves angina has not been fully determined, but includes at least the following two mechanisms:        PROCARDIA dilates the main coronary arteries and coronary arterioles, both in normal and ischemic regions, and is a potent inhibitor of coronary artery spasm, whether spontaneous or ergonovine-induced. This property increases myocardial oxygen delivery in patients with coronary artery spasm, and is responsible for the effectiveness of PROCARDIA in vasospastic (Prinzmetal's or variant) angina. Whether this effect plays any role in classical angina is not clear, but studies of exercise tolerance have not shown an increase in the maximum exercise rate-pressure product, a widely accepted measure of oxygen utilization. This suggests that, in general, relief of spasm or dilation of coronary arteries is not an important factor in classical angina.          PROCARDIA regularly reduces arterial pressure at rest and at a given level of exercise by dilating peripheral arterioles and reducing the total peripheral resistance (afterload) against which the heart works. This unloading of the heart reduces myocardial energy consumption and oxygen requirements and probably accounts for the effectiveness of PROCARDIA in chronic stable angina.            PROCARDIA is rapidly and fully absorbed after oral administration. The drug is detectable in serum 10 minutes after oral administration, and peak blood levels occur in approximately 30 minutes. Bioavailability is proportional to dose from 10 to 30 mg; half-life does not change significantly with dose. There is little difference in relative bioavailability when PROCARDIA capsules are given orally and either swallowed whole, bitten and swallowed, or bitten and held sublingually. However, biting through the capsule prior to swallowing does result in slightly earlier plasma concentrations (27 ng/mL 10 minutes after 10 mg) than if capsules are swallowed intact. PROCARDIA is highly bound by serum proteins. PROCARDIA is extensively converted to inactive metabolites and approximately 80 percent of PROCARDIA and metabolites are eliminated via the kidneys. The elimination half-life of nifedipine is approximately two hours. Since hepatic biotransformation is the predominant route for the disposition of nifedipine, the pharmacokinetics may be altered in patients with chronic liver disease. Patients with hepatic impairment (liver cirrhosis) have a longer disposition half-life and higher bioavailability of nifedipine than healthy volunteers. The degree of serum protein binding of nifedipine is high (92–98%). Protein binding may be greatly reduced in patients with renal or hepatic impairment. Following intravenous administration, clearance of nifedipine was decreased by 33% in elderly healthy subjects relative to young healthy subjects.          Like other slow-channel blockers, PROCARDIA exerts a negative inotropic effect on isolated myocardial tissue. This is rarely, if ever, seen in intact animals or man, probably because of reflex responses to its vasodilating effects. In man, PROCARDIA causes decreased peripheral vascular resistance and a fall in systolic and diastolic pressure, usually modest (5–10 mm Hg systolic), but sometimes larger. There is usually a small increase in heart rate, a reflex response to vasodilation. Measurements of cardiac function in patients with normal ventricular function have generally found a small increase in cardiac index without major effects on ejection fraction, left ventricular end diastolic pressure (LVEDP), or volume (LVEDV). In patients with impaired ventricular function, most acute studies have shown some increase in ejection fraction and reduction in left ventricular filling pressure.          Although, like other members of its class, PROCARDIA decreases sinoatrial node function and atrioventricular conduction in isolated myocardial preparations, such effects have not been seen in studies in intact animals or in man. In formal electrophysiologic studies, predominantly in patients with normal conduction systems, PROCARDIA has had no tendency to prolong atrioventricular conduction, prolong sinus node recovery time, or slow sinus rate.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="1" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Known hypersensitivity reaction to PROCARDIA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The dosage of PROCARDIA needed to suppress angina and that can be tolerated by the patient must be established by titration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Excessive doses can result in hypotension.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Therapy should be initiated with the 10 mg capsule.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The starting dose is one 10 mg capsule, swallowed whole, 3 times/day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The usual effective dose range is 10–20 mg three times daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Some patients, especially those with evidence of coronary artery spasm, respond only to higher doses, more frequent administration, or both.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In such patients, doses of 20–30 mg three or four times daily may be effective.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Doses above 120 mg daily are rarely necessary.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>More than 180 mg per day is not recommended.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="11" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In most cases, PROCARDIA titration should proceed over a 7–14 day period so that the physician can assess the response to each dose level and monitor the blood pressure before proceeding to higher doses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="12" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If symptoms so warrant, titration may proceed more rapidly provided that the patient is assessed frequently.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="13" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Based on the patient's physical activity level, attack frequency, and sublingual nitroglycerin consumption, the dose of PROCARDIA may be increased from 10 mg t.i.d. to 20 mg t.i.d. and then to 30 mg t.i.d. over a three-day period.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M1" type="Trigger" span="112 4;137 9" str="dose | increased"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="70 24" str="sublingual nitroglycerin" code="G59M7S0WS3"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M1" precipitant="M2"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="14" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In hospitalized patients under close observation, the dose may be increased in 10 mg increments over four- to six-hour periods as required to control pain and arrhythmias due to ischemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="15" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>A single dose should rarely exceed 30 mg. Avoid co-administration of nifedipine with grapefruit juice.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M3" type="Trigger" span="42 5" str="Avoid"/>
<Mention id="M4" type="Precipitant" span="85 16" str="grapefruit juice" code="JQ9EK2H6BG"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M3" precipitant="M4"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="16" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>No rebound effect has been observed upon discontinuation of PROCARDIA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="17" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>However, if discontinuation of PROCARDIA is necessary, sound clinical practice suggests that the dosage should be decreased gradually with close physician supervision.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="18" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Sublingual nitroglycerin may be taken as required for the control of acute manifestations of angina, particularly during PROCARDIA titration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="19" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>See PRECAUTIONS, Drug Interactions, for information on co-administration of PROCARDIA with beta blockers or long-acting nitrates.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M7" type="Trigger" span="17 17" str="Drug Interactions"/>
<Mention id="M6" type="Precipitant" span="91 13" str="beta blockers" code="N0000175556"/>
<Mention id="M8" type="Precipitant" span="108 20" str="long-acting nitrates" code="N0000175415"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M7" precipitant="M6"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M7" precipitant="M8"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="20" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Experience in over 1400 patients in a non-comparative clinical trial has shown that concomitant administration of PROCARDIA and beta-blocking agents is usually well tolerated, but there have been occasional literature reports suggesting that the combination may increase the likelihood of congestive heart failure, severe hypotension, or exacerbation of angina.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M15" type="Trigger" span="262 23" str="increase the likelihood"/>
<Mention id="M16" type="Precipitant" span="128 20" str="beta-blocking agents" code="N0000175556"/>
<Mention id="M11" type="SpecificInteraction" span="289 24" str="congestive heart failure" code="42343007: Congestive heart failure (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M14" type="SpecificInteraction" span="315 18" str="severe hypotension" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M17" type="SpecificInteraction" span="338 22" str="exacerbation of angina" code="194828000: Angina (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M15" precipitant="M16" effect="M11"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M15" precipitant="M16" effect="M14"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M15" precipitant="M16" effect="M17"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="21" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>PROCARDIA may be safely co-administered with nitrates, but there have been no controlled studies to evaluate the antianginal effectiveness of this combination.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="22" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Since there have been isolated reports of patients with elevated digoxin levels, and since there is a possible interaction between digoxin and nifedipine, it is recommended that digoxin levels be monitored when initiating, adjusting, and discontinuing nifedipine to avoid possible over- or under-digitalization.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M18" type="Trigger" span="102 20" str="possible interaction "/>
<Mention id="M19" type="Trigger" span="186 19" str=" levels be monitored"/>
<Mention id="M20" type="Precipitant" span="65 7" str="digoxin" code="73K4184T59"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M18;M19" precipitant="M20"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="23" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>There have been rare reports of an interaction between quinidine and nifedipine (with a decreased plasma level of quinidine).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M21" type="Trigger" span="88 22" str="decreased plasma level"/>
<Mention id="M22" type="Precipitant" span="55 9" str="quinidine" code="ITX08688JL"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M21" precipitant="M22" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="24" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>There have been rare reports of increased prothrombin time in patients taking coumarin anticoagulants to whom PROCARDIA was administered.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M25" type="SpecificInteraction" span="32 26" str="increased prothrombin time" code="409674002: Prothrombin time increased (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M24" type="Precipitant" span="78 23" str="coumarin anticoagulants" code="A4VZ22K1WT"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M25" precipitant="M24" effect="M25"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="25" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>However, the relationship to PROCARDIA therapy is uncertain.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="26" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>A study in six healthy volunteers has shown a significant increase in peak nifedipine plasma levels (80%) and area-under-the-curve (74%) after a one week course of cimetidine at 1000 mg per day and nifedipine at 40 mg per day.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M26" type="Trigger" span="58 16;86 13" str="increase in peak | plasma levels"/>
<Mention id="M29" type="Precipitant" span="164 10" str="cimetidine" code="80061L1WGD"/>
<Mention id="M28" type="Trigger" span="58 8;110 20" str="increase | area-under-the-curve"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M26" precipitant="M29" effect="C54602"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M28" precipitant="M29" effect="C54605"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="27" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Ranitidine produced smaller, non-significant increases.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="28" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The effect may be mediated by the known inhibition of cimetidine on hepatic cytochrome P-450, the enzyme system probably responsible for the first-pass metabolism of nifedipine.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M30" type="Trigger" span="40 10;152 10" str="inhibition | metabolism"/>
<Mention id="M31" type="Precipitant" span="54 10" str="cimetidine" code="80061L1WGD"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M30" precipitant="M31" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="29" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>If nifedipine therapy is initiated in a patient currently receiving cimetidine, cautious titration is advised.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M32" type="Trigger" span="80 18" str="cautious titration"/>
<Mention id="M33" type="Precipitant" span="68 10" str="cimetidine" code="80061L1WGD"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M32" precipitant="M33"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="30" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Co-administration of nifedipine with phenytoin, an inducer of CYP3A4, lowers the systemic exposure to nifedipine by approximately 70%.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M36" type="Trigger" span="70 28" str="lowers the systemic exposure"/>
<Mention id="M35" type="Precipitant" span="51 17" str="inducer of CYP3A4" code="N0000185506"/>
<Mention id="M37" type="Precipitant" span="37 9" str="phenytoin" code="6158TKW0C5"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M36" precipitant="M35" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M36" precipitant="M37" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="31" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Avoid co-administration of nifedipine with phenytoin or any known CYP3A4 inducer or consider an alternative antihypertensive therapy.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M41" type="Trigger" span="0 5" str="Avoid "/>
<Mention id="M42" type="Trigger" span="84 23" str=" consider an alternative"/>
<Mention id="M40" type="Precipitant" span="66 14" str="CYP3A4 inducer" code="N0000185506"/>
<Mention id="M43" type="Precipitant" span="43 9" str="phenytoin" code="6158TKW0C5"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M41;M42" precipitant="M40"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M41;M42" precipitant="M43"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="32" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>CYP3A inhibitors such as fluconazole, itraconazole, clarithromycin, erythromycin, nefazodone, fluoxetine, saquinavir, indinavir, and nelfinavir may result in increased exposure to nifedipine when co-administered.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M62" type="Trigger" span="158 18" str="increased exposure"/>
<Mention id="M45" type="Precipitant" span="52 14" str="clarithromycin" code="H1250JIK0A"/>
<Mention id="M47" type="Precipitant" span="0 16" str="CYP3A inhibitors" code="N0000191001"/>
<Mention id="M49" type="Precipitant" span="68 12" str="erythromycin" code="63937KV33D"/>
<Mention id="M51" type="Precipitant" span="25 11" str="fluconazole" code="8VZV102JFY"/>
<Mention id="M53" type="Precipitant" span="94 10" str="fluoxetine" code="01K63SUP8D"/>
<Mention id="M55" type="Precipitant" span="118 9" str="indinavir" code="5W6YA9PKKH"/>
<Mention id="M57" type="Precipitant" span="38 12" str="itraconazole" code="304NUG5GF4"/>
<Mention id="M59" type="Precipitant" span="82 10" str="nefazodone" code="59H4FCV1TF"/>
<Mention id="M61" type="Precipitant" span="133 10" str="nelfinavir" code="HO3OGH5D7I"/>
<Mention id="M63" type="Precipitant" span="106 10" str="saquinavir" code="L3JE09KZ2F"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M62" precipitant="M45" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M62" precipitant="M47" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M62" precipitant="M49" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M62" precipitant="M51" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M62" precipitant="M53" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M62" precipitant="M55" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M62" precipitant="M57" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M62" precipitant="M59" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M62" precipitant="M61" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M62" precipitant="M63" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="33" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Careful monitoring and dose adjustment may be necessary; consider initiating nifedipine at the lowest dose available if given concomitantly with these medications.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="34" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because PROCARDIA decreases peripheral vascular resistance, careful monitoring of blood pressure during the initial administration and titration of PROCARDIA is suggested.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="35" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Close observation is especially recommended for patients already taking medications that are known to lower blood pressure.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M64" type="Trigger" span="0 17" str="Close observation"/>
<Mention id="M65" type="Precipitant" span="72 50" str="medications that are known to lower blood pressure" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I29" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M64" precipitant="M65"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="36" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Mild to moderate peripheral edema, typically associated with arterial vasodilation and not due to left ventricular dysfunction, occurs in about one in ten patients treated with PROCARDIA (nifedipine).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="37" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>This edema occurs primarily in the lower extremities and usually responds to diuretic therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="38" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>With patients whose angina is complicated by congestive heart failure, care should be taken to differentiate this peripheral edema from the effects of increasing left ventricular dysfunction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="39" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Rare, usually transient, but occasionally significant elevations of enzymes such as alkaline phosphatase, CPK, LDH, SGOT, and SGPT have been noted.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="40" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The relationship to PROCARDIA therapy is uncertain in most cases, but probable in some.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="41" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>These laboratory abnormalities have rarely been associated with clinical symptoms; however, cholestasis with or without jaundice has been reported.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="42" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Rare instances of allergic hepatitis have been reported.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="43" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>PROCARDIA, like other calcium channel blockers, decreases platelet aggregation in vitro.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="44" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Limited clinical studies have demonstrated a moderate but statistically significant decrease in platelet aggregation and an increase in bleeding time in some PROCARDIA patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="45" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>This is thought to be a function of inhibition of calcium transport across the platelet membrane.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="46" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>No clinical significance for these findings has been demonstrated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="47" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Positive direct Coombs Test with/without hemolytic anemia has been reported but a causal relationship between PROCARDIA administration and positivity of this laboratory test, including hemolysis, could not be determined.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="48" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Although PROCARDIA has been used safely in patients with renal dysfunction and has been reported to exert a beneficial effect, in certain cases, rare, reversible elevations in BUN and serum creatinine have been reported in patients with pre-existing chronic renal insufficiency.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="49" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The relationship to PROCARDIA therapy is uncertain in most cases but probable in some.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="50" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Co-administration of nifedipine with grapefruit juice resulted in approximately a doubling in nifedipine AUC and Cmax with no change in half-life.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M66" type="Trigger" span="82 8;113 4" str="doubling | Cmax"/>
<Mention id="M69" type="Precipitant" span="37 16" str="grapefruit juice" code="JQ9EK2H6BG"/>
<Mention id="M68" type="Trigger" span="82 8;105 3" str="doubling | AUC"/>
<Interaction id="I30" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M66" precipitant="M69" effect="C54602"/>
<Interaction id="I31" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M68" precipitant="M69" effect="C54605"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="51" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The increased plasma concentrations most likely result from inhibition of CYP 3A4 related first-pass metabolism.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="52" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Avoid ingestion of grapefruit and grapefruit juice while taking nifedipine.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M72" type="Trigger" span="0 5" str="Avoid"/>
<Mention id="M71" type="Precipitant" span="19 10" str="grapefruit" code="O82C39RR8C"/>
<Mention id="M73" type="Precipitant" span="34 16" str="grapefruit juice" code="JQ9EK2H6BG"/>
<Interaction id="I32" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M72" precipitant="M71"/>
<Interaction id="I33" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M72" precipitant="M73"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="53" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Nifedipine was administered orally to rats for two years and was not shown to be carcinogenic.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="54" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>When given to rats prior to mating, nifedipine caused reduced fertility at a dose approximately 5 times the maximum recommended human dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="55" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>There is a literature report of reversible reduction in the ability of human sperm obtained from a limited number of infertile men taking recommended doses of nifedipine to bind to and fertilize an ovum in vitro.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="56" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In vivo mutagenicity studies were negative.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="57" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Nifedipine has been shown to produce teratogenic findings in rats and rabbits, including digital anomalies similar to those reported for phenytoin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="58" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Digital anomalies have been reported to occur with other members of the dihydropyridine class and are possibly a result of compromised uterine blood flow.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="59" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Nifedipine administration was associated with a variety of embryotoxic, placentotoxic, and fetotoxic effects, including stunted fetuses (rats, mice, rabbits), rib deformities (mice), cleft palate (mice), small placentas and underdeveloped chorionic villi (monkeys), embryonic and fetal deaths (rats, mice, rabbits), and prolonged pregnancy/decreased neonatal survival (rats; not evaluated in other species).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="60" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>On a mg/kg basis, all of the doses associated with the teratogenic embryotoxic or fetotoxic effects in animals were higher (5 to 50 times) than the maximum recommended human dose of 120 mg/day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="61" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>On a mg/m2 basis, some doses were higher and some were lower than the maximum recommended human dose but all were within an order of magnitude of it.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="62" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The doses associated with placentotoxic effects in monkeys were equivalent to or lower than the maximum recommended human dose on a mg/m2 basis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="63" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>There are no adequate and well-controlled studies in pregnant women.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="64" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>PROCARDIA should be used during pregnancy only if the potential benefit justifies the potential risk.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="65" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Nifedipine is transferred through breast milk.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="66" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>PROCARDIA should be used during breast-feeding only if the potential benefit justifies the potential risk.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="67" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Safety and effectiveness in pediatric patients have not been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="68" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Use in pediatric population is not recommended.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="69" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Age appears to have a significant effect on the pharmacokinetics of nifedipine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="70" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The clearance is decreased resulting in a higher AUC in the elderly.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="71" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>These changes are not due to changes in renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="72" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Although, in most patients, the hypotensive effect of PROCARDIA is modest and well tolerated, occasional patients have had excessive and poorly tolerated hypotension.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="73" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>These responses have usually occurred during initial titration or at the time of subsequent upward dosage adjustment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="74" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Although patients have rarely experienced excessive hypotension on PROCARDIA alone, this may be more common in patients on concomitant beta blocker therapy.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M76" type="SpecificInteraction" span="42 21" str="excessive hypotension" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M75" type="Precipitant" span="135 20" str="beta blocker therapy" code="N0000175556"/>
<Interaction id="I34" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M76" precipitant="M75" effect="M76"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="75" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Although not approved for this purpose, PROCARDIA and other immediate-release nifedipine capsules have been used (orally and sublingually) for acute reduction of blood pressure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="76" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Several well-documented reports describe cases of profound hypotension, myocardial infarction, and death when immediate-release nifedipine was used in this way.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="77" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>PROCARDIA capsules should not be used for the acute reduction of blood pressure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="78" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Severe hypotension and/or increased fluid volume requirements have been reported in patients receiving PROCARDIA together with a beta-blocking agent who underwent coronary artery bypass surgery using high dose fentanyl anesthesia.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M89" type="Trigger" span="0 18" str="Severe hypotension "/>
<Mention id="M90" type="Trigger" span="26 35" str=" increased fluid volume requirements"/>
<Mention id="M83" type="Precipitant" span="129 19" str="beta-blocking agent" code="N0000175556"/>
<Mention id="M92" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 18" str="Severe hypotension" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M88" type="SpecificInteraction" span="26 35" str="increased fluid volume requirements" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M91" type="Precipitant" span="200 29" str="high dose fentanyl anesthesia" code="UF599785JZ"/>
<Interaction id="I35" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M89;M90" precipitant="M83" effect="M92"/>
<Interaction id="I36" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M89;M90" precipitant="M83" effect="M88"/>
<Interaction id="I37" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M89;M90" precipitant="M91" effect="M88"/>
<Interaction id="I38" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M89;M90" precipitant="M91" effect="M92"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="79" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The interaction with high dose fentanyl appears to be due to the combination of PROCARDIA and a beta blocker, but the possibility that it may occur with PROCARDIA alone, with low doses of fentanyl, in other surgical procedures, or with other narcotic analgesics cannot be ruled out.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M97" type="Trigger" span="4 11" str="interaction"/>
<Mention id="M94" type="Precipitant" span="96 12" str="beta blocker" code="N0000175556"/>
<Mention id="M96" type="Precipitant" span="21 18" str="high dose fentanyl" code="UF599785JZ"/>
<Mention id="M98" type="Precipitant" span="242 19" str="narcotic analgesics" code="N0000175440"/>
<Interaction id="I39" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M97" precipitant="M94"/>
<Interaction id="I40" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M97" precipitant="M96"/>
<Interaction id="I41" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M97" precipitant="M98"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="80" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>In PROCARDIA treated patients where surgery using high dose fentanyl anesthesia is contemplated, the physician should be aware of these potential problems and, if the patient's condition permits, sufficient time (at least 36 hours) should be allowed for PROCARDIA to be washed out of the body prior to surgery.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M99" type="Trigger" span="136 18" str="potential problems "/>
<Mention id="M100" type="Trigger" span="196 15;264 16" str=" sufficient time | to be washed out"/>
<Mention id="M101" type="Precipitant" span="50 29" str="high dose fentanyl anesthesia" code="UF599785JZ"/>
<Interaction id="I42" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M99;M100" precipitant="M101"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="81" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Rarely, patients, particularly those who have severe obstructive coronary artery disease, have developed well documented increased frequency, duration, and/or severity of angina or acute myocardial infarction on starting PROCARDIA or at the time of dosage increase.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="82" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The mechanism of this effect is not established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="83" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Several well-controlled, randomized trials studied the use of immediate-release nifedipine in patients who had just sustained myocardial infarctions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="84" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>In none of these trials did immediate-release nifedipine appear to provide any benefit.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="85" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>In some of the trials, patients who received immediate-release nifedipine had significantly worse outcomes than patients who received placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="86" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>PROCARDIA capsules should not be administered within the first week or two after myocardial infarction, and they should also be avoided in the setting of acute coronary syndrome (when infarction may be imminent).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="87" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>PROCARDIA and other immediate-release nifedipine capsules have also been used for the long-term control of essential hypertension, although PROCARDIA capsules have not been approved for this purpose and no properly controlled studies have been conducted to define an appropriate dose or dose interval for such treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="88" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>PROCARDIA capsules should not be used for the control of essential hypertension.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="89" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Patients recently withdrawn from beta blockers may develop a withdrawal syndrome with increased angina, probably related to increased sensitivity to catecholamines.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M112" type="Trigger" span="61 19" str="withdrawal syndrome "/>
<Mention id="M113" type="Trigger" span="86 16" str=" increased angina "/>
<Mention id="M114" type="Trigger" span="124 39" str=" increased sensitivity to catecholamines"/>
<Mention id="M115" type="Precipitant" span="33 13" str="beta blockers" code="N0000175556"/>
<Mention id="M106" type="SpecificInteraction" span="124 39" str="increased sensitivity to catecholamines" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M111" type="SpecificInteraction" span="61 19" str="withdrawal syndrome" code="363101005: Drug withdrawal (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M116" type="SpecificInteraction" span="86 16" str="increased angina" code="194828000: Angina (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I43" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M112;M113;M114" precipitant="M115" effect="M106"/>
<Interaction id="I44" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M112;M113;M114" precipitant="M115" effect="M111"/>
<Interaction id="I45" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M112;M113;M114" precipitant="M115" effect="M116"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="90" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Initiation of PROCARDIA treatment will not prevent this occurrence and might be expected to exacerbate it by provoking reflex catecholamine release.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="91" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>There have been occasional reports of increased angina in a setting of beta blocker withdrawal and PROCARDIA initiation.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M119" type="SpecificInteraction" span="38 16" str="increased angina" code="194828000: Angina (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M118" type="Precipitant" span="71 23" str="beta blocker withdrawal" code="N0000175556"/>
<Interaction id="I46" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M119" precipitant="M118" effect="M119"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="92" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>It is important to taper beta blockers if possible, rather than stopping them abruptly before beginning PROCARDIA.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M120" type="Trigger" span="19 5" str="taper"/>
<Mention id="M121" type="Precipitant" span="25 13" str="beta blockers" code="N0000175556"/>
<Interaction id="I47" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M120" precipitant="M121"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="93" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Rarely, patients, usually those receiving a beta blocker, have developed heart failure after beginning PROCARDIA.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M124" type="SpecificInteraction" span="73 13" str="heart failure" code="42343007: Congestive heart failure (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M123" type="Precipitant" span="44 12" str="beta blocker" code="N0000175556"/>
<Interaction id="I48" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M124" precipitant="M123" effect="M124"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="94" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Patients with tight aortic stenosis may be at greater risk for such an event, as the unloading effect of PROCARDIA would be expected to be of less benefit to these patients, owing to their fixed impedance to flow across the aortic valve.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="95" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>PROCARDIA is a calcium ion influx inhibitor (slow-channel blocker or calcium ion antagonist) and inhibits the transmembrane influx of calcium ions into cardiac muscle and smooth muscle.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="96" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The contractile processes of cardiac muscle and vascular smooth muscle are dependent upon the movement of extracellular calcium ions into these cells through specific ion channels.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="97" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>PROCARDIA selectively inhibits calcium ion influx across the cell membrane of cardiac muscle and vascular smooth muscle without changing serum calcium concentrations.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="98" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The precise means by which this inhibition relieves angina has not been fully determined, but includes at least the following two mechanisms: PROCARDIA dilates the main coronary arteries and coronary arterioles, both in normal and ischemic regions, and is a potent inhibitor of coronary artery spasm, whether spontaneous or ergonovine-induced.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M125" type="Trigger" span="265 9" str="inhibitor"/>
<Mention id="M126" type="Precipitant" span="324 10" str="ergonovine" code="WH41D8433D"/>
<Mention id="M127" type="SpecificInteraction" span="265 34" str="inhibitor of coronary artery spasm" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I49" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M125" precipitant="M126" effect="M127"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="99" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This property increases myocardial oxygen delivery in patients with coronary artery spasm, and is responsible for the effectiveness of PROCARDIA in vasospastic (Prinzmetal's or variant) angina.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="100" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Whether this effect plays any role in classical angina is not clear, but studies of exercise tolerance have not shown an increase in the maximum exercise rate-pressure product, a widely accepted measure of oxygen utilization.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="101" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This suggests that, in general, relief of spasm or dilation of coronary arteries is not an important factor in classical angina.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="102" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>PROCARDIA regularly reduces arterial pressure at rest and at a given level of exercise by dilating peripheral arterioles and reducing the total peripheral resistance (afterload) against which the heart works.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="103" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This unloading of the heart reduces myocardial energy consumption and oxygen requirements and probably accounts for the effectiveness of PROCARDIA in chronic stable angina.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="104" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>PROCARDIA is rapidly and fully absorbed after oral administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="105" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The drug is detectable in serum 10 minutes after oral administration, and peak blood levels occur in approximately 30 minutes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="106" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Bioavailability is proportional to dose from 10 to 30 mg; half-life does not change significantly with dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="107" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There is little difference in relative bioavailability when PROCARDIA capsules are given orally and either swallowed whole, bitten and swallowed, or bitten and held sublingually.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="108" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>However, biting through the capsule prior to swallowing does result in slightly earlier plasma concentrations (27 ng/mL 10 minutes after 10 mg) than if capsules are swallowed intact.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="109" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>PROCARDIA is highly bound by serum proteins.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="110" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>PROCARDIA is extensively converted to inactive metabolites and approximately 80 percent of PROCARDIA and metabolites are eliminated via the kidneys.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="111" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The elimination half-life of nifedipine is approximately two hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="112" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Since hepatic biotransformation is the predominant route for the disposition of nifedipine, the pharmacokinetics may be altered in patients with chronic liver disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="113" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Patients with hepatic impairment (liver cirrhosis) have a longer disposition half-life and higher bioavailability of nifedipine than healthy volunteers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="114" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The degree of serum protein binding of nifedipine is high (92–98%).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="115" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Protein binding may be greatly reduced in patients with renal or hepatic impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="116" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following intravenous administration, clearance of nifedipine was decreased by 33% in elderly healthy subjects relative to young healthy subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="117" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Like other slow-channel blockers, PROCARDIA exerts a negative inotropic effect on isolated myocardial tissue.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="118" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This is rarely, if ever, seen in intact animals or man, probably because of reflex responses to its vasodilating effects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="119" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In man, PROCARDIA causes decreased peripheral vascular resistance and a fall in systolic and diastolic pressure, usually modest (5–10 mm Hg systolic), but sometimes larger.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="120" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There is usually a small increase in heart rate, a reflex response to vasodilation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="121" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Measurements of cardiac function in patients with normal ventricular function have generally found a small increase in cardiac index without major effects on ejection fraction, left ventricular end diastolic pressure (LVEDP), or volume (LVEDV).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="122" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In patients with impaired ventricular function, most acute studies have shown some increase in ejection fraction and reduction in left ventricular filling pressure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="123" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Although, like other members of its class, PROCARDIA decreases sinoatrial node function and atrioventricular conduction in isolated myocardial preparations, such effects have not been seen in studies in intact animals or in man.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="124" LabelDrug="Procardia" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In formal electrophysiologic studies, predominantly in patients with normal conduction systems, PROCARDIA has had no tendency to prolong atrioventricular conduction, prolong sinus node recovery time, or slow sinus rate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="sublingual nitroglycerin" precipitantCode="G59M7S0WS3"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="grapefruit juice" precipitantCode="JQ9EK2H6BG" effect="C54602"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="grapefruit juice" precipitantCode="JQ9EK2H6BG" effect="C54605"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="grapefruit juice" precipitantCode="JQ9EK2H6BG"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="beta blockers" precipitantCode="N0000175556" effect="194828000: Angina (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="beta blockers" precipitantCode="N0000175556" effect="363101005: Drug withdrawal (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="beta blockers" precipitantCode="N0000175556" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="beta blockers" precipitantCode="N0000175556"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="long-acting nitrates" precipitantCode="N0000175415"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="beta-blocking agents" precipitantCode="N0000175556" effect="194828000: Angina (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="beta-blocking agents" precipitantCode="N0000175556" effect="42343007: Congestive heart failure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="beta-blocking agents" precipitantCode="N0000175556" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="digoxin" precipitantCode="73K4184T59"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="quinidine" precipitantCode="ITX08688JL" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="coumarin anticoagulants" precipitantCode="A4VZ22K1WT" effect="409674002: Prothrombin time increased (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cimetidine" precipitantCode="80061L1WGD" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cimetidine" precipitantCode="80061L1WGD" effect="C54602"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cimetidine" precipitantCode="80061L1WGD" effect="C54605"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="cimetidine" precipitantCode="80061L1WGD"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="inducer of cyp3a4" precipitantCode="N0000185506" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="phenytoin" precipitantCode="6158TKW0C5" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="phenytoin" precipitantCode="6158TKW0C5"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="cyp3a4 inducer" precipitantCode="N0000185506"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="clarithromycin" precipitantCode="H1250JIK0A" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cyp3a inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000191001" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="erythromycin" precipitantCode="63937KV33D" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="fluconazole" precipitantCode="8VZV102JFY" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="fluoxetine" precipitantCode="01K63SUP8D" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="indinavir" precipitantCode="5W6YA9PKKH" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="itraconazole" precipitantCode="304NUG5GF4" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="nefazodone" precipitantCode="59H4FCV1TF" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="nelfinavir" precipitantCode="HO3OGH5D7I" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="saquinavir" precipitantCode="L3JE09KZ2F" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="medications that are known to lower blood pressure" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="grapefruit" precipitantCode="O82C39RR8C"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="beta blocker therapy" precipitantCode="N0000175556" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="beta-blocking agent" precipitantCode="N0000175556" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="beta-blocking agent" precipitantCode="N0000175556" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="high dose fentanyl anesthesia" precipitantCode="UF599785JZ" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="high dose fentanyl anesthesia" precipitantCode="UF599785JZ" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="high dose fentanyl anesthesia" precipitantCode="UF599785JZ"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="beta blocker" precipitantCode="N0000175556" effect="42343007: Congestive heart failure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="beta blocker" precipitantCode="N0000175556"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="high dose fentanyl" precipitantCode="UF599785JZ"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="narcotic analgesics" precipitantCode="N0000175440"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="beta blocker withdrawal" precipitantCode="N0000175556" effect="194828000: Angina (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ergonovine" precipitantCode="WH41D8433D" effect="NO MAP"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>