<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Renvela" setid="e6328460-a57b-450b-a48c-6dcd4b476360">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
Renvela is contraindicated in patients with bowel obstruction.       Bowel obstruction. (4)</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
Because of the rapid reaction with the hydrochloric acid in the stomach, the dosing of Renvela powder or tablet is anticipated to be similar to that of the sevelamer hydrochloride salt or tablet.         Starting dose of Renvela is 0.8 or 1.6 grams administered orally three times per day with meals. (2.1) Titrate by 0.8 g per meal in two week intervals as needed to obtain serum phosphorus target (3.5 to 5.5 mg/dL). (2.1) Switch gram-for-gram among sevelamer formulations. Further titration may be necessary to achieve desired phosphorus levels. (2.1)           Renvela should be given three times a day with meals.   Patients Not Taking a Phosphate Binder.  The recommended starting dose of Renvela is 0.8 to 1.6 g with meals based on serum phosphorus level. Table 1 provides recommended starting doses of Renvela for patients not taking a phosphate binder.       Table 1. Starting Dose for Dialysis Patients Not Taking a Phosphate Binder          Serum Phosphorus      Renvela® 800 mg Tablet      Renvela Powder        &amp;gt; 5.5 and &amp;lt; 7.5 mg/dL  1 tablet three times daily with meals  0.8 g three times daily with meals   ≥ 7.5 mg/dL 2 tablets three times daily with meals 1.6 g three times daily with meals      Switching from Sevelamer Hydrochloride Tablets.  For patients switching from sevelamer hydrochloride tablets to sevelamer carbonate tablets or powder, use the same dose in grams. Further titration may be necessary to achieve desired phosphorus levels. The highest daily dose of sevelamer carbonate studied was 14 grams in CKD patients on dialysis.    Switching between Sevelamer Carbonate Tablets and Powder.  Use the same dose in grams. Further titration may be necessary to achieve desired phosphorus levels.    Switching from Calcium Acetate.  In a study in 84 CKD patients on hemodialysis, a similar reduction in serum phosphorus was seen with equivalent doses (approximately mg for mg) of sevelamer hydrochloride and calcium acetate. Table 2 gives recommended starting doses of Renvela based on a patient’s current calcium acetate dose.   Table 2. Starting Dose for Dialysis Patients Switching From Calcium Acetate to Renvela         Calcium Acetate 667 mg(Tablets per meal) Renvela® 800 mg Tablet(Tablets per meal)  Renvela Powder      1 tablet 1 tablet 0.8 g   2 tablets 2 tablets 1.6 g   3 tablets 3 tablets  2.4 g      Dose Titration for All Patients Taking Renvela.  Titrate the Renvela dose by 0.8 g three times per day with meals at two-week intervals as necessary with the goal of controlling serum phosphorus within the target range.           The entire contents of each 0.8 or 2.4 g packet should be placed in a cup and mixed thoroughly with the amount of water described in Table 3.  Table 3. Sevelamer Carbonate Powder Preparation Instructions           Renvela PowderPacket Strength Minimum amount of water for dose preparation (either ounces, mL or teaspoon/Tablespoon)         ounces     mL     tsp/Tbsp     0.8 g 1 30 6 teaspoons/2 Tablespoons   2.4 g 2 60 4 Tablespoons    Multiple packets may be mixed together with the appropriate amount of water. Patients should be instructed to stir the mixture vigorously (it does not dissolve) and drink the entire preparation within 30 minutes and resuspend the preparation right before drinking.  Based on clinical studies, the average prescribed daily dose of sevelamer carbonate is approximately 7.2 g per day.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
Sevelamer carbonate has been studied in human drug-drug interaction studies with warfarin and digoxin. Sevelamer hydrochloride, which contains the same active moiety as sevelamer carbonate, has been studied in human drug-drug interaction studies with ciprofloxacin, digoxin, warfarin, enalapril, metoprolol and iron.       Sevelamer decreases the bioavailability of ciprofloxacin by approximately 50%. (7.1) Sevelamer did not alter the pharmacokinetics of single doses of digoxin, warfarin, enalapril, metoprolol, or iron. (7) When administering an oral medication where a reduction in the bioavailability of that medication would have a clinically significant effect on its safety or efficacy, administer the drug at least one hour before or three hours after Renvela, and monitor blood levels of the drug. (7.7)          In a study of 15 healthy subjects, a co-administered single dose of 2.8 grams of sevelamer hydrochloride decreased the bioavailability of ciprofloxacin by approximately 50%.          In 19 healthy subjects receiving 2.4 grams of sevelamer hydrochloride three times a day with meals for 2 days, sevelamer did not alter the pharmacokinetics of a single dose of digoxin. In 18 healthy subjects receiving 9.6 grams of sevelamer carbonate once daily with a meal, sevelamer did not alter the pharmacokinetics of a single dose of digoxin.           In 14 healthy subjects receiving 2.4 g of sevelamer hydrochloride three times a day with meals for two days sevelamer did not alter the pharmacokinetics of a single dose of warfarin.  In 14 healthy subjects receiving 9.6 grams of sevelamer carbonate once daily with a meal, sevelamer did not alter the pharmacokinetics of a single dose of warfarin.           In 28 healthy subjects a single 2.4 gram dose of sevelamer hydrochloride did not alter the pharmacokinetics of a single dose of enalapril.          In 31 healthy subjects a single 2.4 gram dose of sevelamer hydrochloride did not alter the pharmacokinetics of a single dose of metoprolol.          In 23 healthy subjects, a single 2.8 gram dose of sevelamer hydrochloride did not alter the absorption of a single oral dose of iron as 200 mg exsiccated ferrous sulfate tablet.          There are no empirical data on avoiding drug interactions between Renvela and most concomitant drugs. During postmarketing experience, very rare cases of increased thyroid stimulating hormone (TSH) levels have been reported in patients co-administered sevelamer hydrochloride and levothyroxine. Monitor TSH levels and signs of hypothyroidism in patients receiving both medications. When administering an oral medication where a reduction in the bioavailability of that medication would have a clinically significant effect on its safety or efficacy, there is no information that suggests a dosing regimen that would be universally appropriate for all drugs. One may, however, administer the drug one hour before or three hours after Renvela, and monitor blood levels of the drug. Patients taking anti-arrhythmic medications for the control of arrhythmias and anti-seizure medications for the control of seizure disorders were excluded from the clinical trials.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
Serious cases of dysphagia, bowel obstruction, and perforation have been associated with sevelamer use, some requiring hospitalization and surgery. (5.1)          Cases of dysphagia and esophageal tablet retention have been reported in association with use of the tablet formulation of sevelamer, some requiring hospitalization and intervention. Consider using sevelamer suspension in patients with a history of swallowing disorders.  Cases of bowel obstruction and perforation have also been reported with sevelamer use.  Patients with dysphagia, swallowing disorders, severe gastrointestinal (GI) motility disorders including severe constipation, or major GI tract surgery were not included in the Renvela clinical studies.           Bicarbonate and chloride levels should be monitored.          In preclinical studies in rats and dogs, sevelamer hydrochloride, which contains the same active moiety as sevelamer carbonate, reduced vitamins D, E, and K (coagulation parameters) and folic acid levels at doses of 6‑10 times the recommended human dose. In short-term clinical trials, there was no evidence of reduction in serum levels of vitamins. However, in a one-year clinical trial, 25-hydroxyvitamin D (normal range 10 to 55 ng/mL) fell from 39 ± 22 ng/mL to 34 ± 22 ng/mL (p&amp;lt;0.01) with sevelamer hydrochloride treatment. Most (approximately 75%) patients in sevelamer hydrochloride clinical trials received vitamin supplements, which is typical of patients on dialysis.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Patients with chronic kidney disease (CKD) retain phosphorus and can develop hyperphosphatemia. When the product of serum calcium and phosphorus concentrations (Ca x P) exceeds 55 mg2/dL2, there is an increased risk that ectopic calcification will occur. Hyperphosphatemia plays a role in the development of secondary hyperparathyroidism in renal insufficiency.  Treatment of hyperphosphatemia includes reduction in dietary intake of phosphate, inhibition of intestinal phosphate absorption with phosphate binders, and removal of phosphate with dialysis. Sevelamer carbonate taken with meals has been shown to control serum phosphorus concentrations in patients with CKD who are on dialysis.        Renvela contains sevelamer carbonate, a non-absorbed phosphate binding crosslinked polymer, free of metal and calcium. It contains multiple amines separated by one carbon from the polymer backbone. These amines exist in a protonated form in the intestine and interact with phosphate molecules through ionic and hydrogen bonding. By binding phosphate in the gastrointestinal tract and decreasing absorption, sevelamer carbonate lowers the phosphate concentration in the serum (serum phosphorus).          In addition to effects on serum phosphorus levels, sevelamer hydrochloride has been shown to bind bile acids  in vitro and  in vivo in experimental animal models. Bile acid binding by ion exchange resins is a well-established method of lowering blood cholesterol. Because sevelamer binds bile acids, it may interfere with normal fat absorption and thus may reduce absorption of fat soluble vitamins such as A, D and K. In clinical trials of sevelamer hydrochloride, both the mean total and LDL cholesterol declined by 15-31%. This effect is observed after 2 weeks. Triglycerides, HDL cholesterol and albumin did not change.          A mass balance study using 14C-sevelamer hydrochloride, in 16 healthy male and female volunteers showed that sevelamer hydrochloride is not systemically absorbed. No absorption studies have been performed in patients with renal disease.              Standard lifetime carcinogenicity bioassays were conducted in mice and rats. Rats were given sevelamer hydrochloride by diet at 0.3, 1, or 3 g/kg/day. There was an increased incidence of urinary bladder transitional cell papilloma in male rats of the high dose group (human equivalent dose twice the maximum clinical trial dose of 13 g). Mice received dietary administration of sevelamer hydrochloride at doses of up to 9 g/kg/day (human equivalent dose 3 times the maximum clinical trial dose). There was no increased incidence of tumors observed in mice. In an  in vitro mammalian cytogenetic test with metabolic activation, sevelamer hydrochloride caused a statistically significant increase in the number of structural chromosome aberrations. Sevelamer hydrochloride was not mutagenic in the Ames bacterial mutation assay. Sevelamer hydrochloride did not impair the fertility of male or female rats in a dietary administration study in which the females were treated from 14 days prior to mating through gestation and the males were treated for 28 days prior to mating. The highest dose in this study was 4.5 g/kg/day (human equivalent dose 3 times the maximum clinical trial dose of 13 g).          In pregnant rats given dietary doses of 0.5, 1.5 or 4.5 g/kg/day of sevelamer hydrochloride during organogenesis, reduced or irregular ossification of fetal bones, probably due to a reduced absorption of fat-soluble vitamin D, occurred in mid- and high-dose groups (human equivalent doses approximately equal to 3-4 times the maximum clinical trial dose of 13 g). In pregnant rabbits given oral doses of 100, 500 or 1000 mg/kg/day of sevelamer hydrochloride by gavage during organogenesis, an increase of early resorptions occurred in the high-dose group (human equivalent dose twice the maximum clinical trial dose).</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="125" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Renvela is contraindicated in patients with bowel obstruction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="126" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Renvela is contraindicated in patients with known hypersensitivity to sevelamer carbonate, sevelamer hydrochloride, or to any of the excipients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="127" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Known hypersensitivity to sevelamer carbonate, sevelamer hydrochloride, or to any of the excipients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="128" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Starting dose of Renvela is 0.8 or 1.6 grams administered orally three times per day with meals based on serum phosphorus levels for adult patients and based on body surface area (BSA) category for pediatric patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="129" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Titrate by 0.8 g per meal in two week intervals for adult patients as needed to obtain serum phosphorus target.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="130" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Titrate based on BSA category for pediatric patients in two week intervals for 6 weeks and then every 4 weeks as needed to obtain serum phosphorus target.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="131" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Starting Dose for Adult Patients Not Taking a Phosphate Binder.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M1" type="Trigger" span="33 10" str="Not Taking"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="46 16" str="Phosphate Binder" code="N0000175597"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M1" precipitant="M2"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="132" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommended starting dose of Renvela is 0.8 to 1.6 g taken orally with meals based on serum phosphorus level.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="133" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Table 1 provides recommended starting doses of Renvela for adult patients not taking a phosphate binder.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M3" type="Trigger" span="74 10" str="not taking"/>
<Mention id="M4" type="Precipitant" span="87 16" str="phosphate binder" code="N0000175597"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M3" precipitant="M4"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="134" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Table 1: Starting Dose for Adult Dialysis Patients Not Taking a Phosphate Binder Serum Phosphorus Renvela &gt;5.5 and &lt;7.5 mg/dL 0.8 g three times daily with meals ≥7.5 mg/dL 1.6 g three times daily with meals Dose Titration for Adult Patients Taking Renvela.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M5" type="Trigger" span="51 10" str="Not Taking"/>
<Mention id="M6" type="Precipitant" span="64 16" str="Phosphate Binder" code="N0000175597"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M5" precipitant="M6"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="135" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Titrate the Renvela dose by 0.8 g three times per day with meals at two-week intervals as necessary to achieve target serum phosphorus levels.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="136" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Based on clinical studies, the average prescribed adult daily dose of sevelamer carbonate is approximately 7.2 g per day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="137" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The highest daily adult dose of sevelamer carbonate studied was 14 grams in CKD patients on dialysis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="138" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Starting Dose for Pediatric Patients Not Taking a Phosphate Binder.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M7" type="Trigger" span="37 10" str="Not Taking"/>
<Mention id="M8" type="Precipitant" span="50 16" str="Phosphate Binder" code="N0000175597"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M7" precipitant="M8"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="139" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommended starting dose for pediatric patients 6 years of age and older is 0.8 g to 1.6 g taken three times per day with meals based on the patient's body surface area (BSA) category; see Table 2.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="140" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Table 2: Recommended Starting Dosage and Titration Increment Based on Pediatric Patient's Body Surface Area (m2) BSA (m2) Starting Dose Per Meal/Snack Titration Increases/Decreases Per Dose ≥0.75 to &lt;1.2 0.8 g Titrate by 0.4 g ≥1.2 1.6 g Titrate by 0.8 g Dose Titration for Pediatric Patients Taking Renvela.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="141" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Titrate the Renvela dose as needed to achieve target levels at two-week intervals based on BSA category, as shown in Table 2.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="142" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Switching from Sevelamer Hydrochloride Tablets.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="143" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For adult patients switching from sevelamer hydrochloride tablets to sevelamer carbonate tablets or powder, use the same dose in grams.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="144" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Switching between Sevelamer Carbonate Tablets and Powder.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="145" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Table 3 gives recommended starting doses of Renvela based on a patient's current calcium acetate dose.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M9" type="Trigger" span="35 5;52 8" str="doses | based on"/>
<Mention id="M10" type="Precipitant" span="81 15" str="calcium acetate" code="Y882YXF34X"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M9" precipitant="M10"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="146" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Table 3: Starting Dose for Dialysis Patients Switching from Calcium Acetate to Renvela Calcium Acetate 667 mg (Tablets per meal) Renvela 1 tablet 0.8 g 2 tablets 1.6 g 3 tablets 2.4 g Sevelamer carbonate powder is available in 0.8 or 2.4 g packets.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="147" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For dose increments of 0.4 g, use one half of a 0.8 g packet.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="148" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Place the sevelamer carbonate powder in a cup and suspend in the amount of water described in Table 4.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="149" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Table 4: Sevelamer Carbonate Powder Preparation Instructions Amount of Renvela Powder Minimum Amount of Water for Dose Preparation (either ounces, mL, or tablespoon) Ounces mL Tablespoons 0.4 g 1 30 2 0.8 g 1 30 2 2.4 g 2 60 4 Instruct patients to stir the mixture vigorously (it does not dissolve), resuspend, if necessary, right before administration, and drink the entire preparation within 30 minutes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="150" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>As an alternative to water, the entire contents of the sachet may be pre-mixed with a small amount of food or beverage and consumed immediately (within 30 minutes) as part of the meal.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="151" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not heat Renvela Powder (e.g., microwave) or add to heated foods or liquids.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="152" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>There are no empirical data on avoiding drug interactions between Renvela and most concomitant oral drugs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="153" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>For oral medication where a reduction in the bioavailability of that medication would have a clinically significant effect on its safety or efficacy (e.g., cyclosporine, tacrolimus, levothyroxine), consider separation of the timing of the administration of the two drugs.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M15" type="Trigger" span="28 32" str="reduction in the bioavailability"/>
<Mention id="M12" type="Precipitant" span="156 12" str="cyclosporine" code="83HN0GTJ6D"/>
<Mention id="M14" type="Precipitant" span="182 13" str="levothyroxine" code="Q51BO43MG4"/>
<Mention id="M16" type="Precipitant" span="170 10" str="tacrolimus" code="WM0HAQ4WNM"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M15" precipitant="M12" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M15" precipitant="M14" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M15" precipitant="M16" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="154" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The duration of separation depends upon the absorption characteristics of the medication concomitantly administered, such as the time to reach peak systemic levels and whether the drug is an immediate-release or an extended-release product.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="155" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Where possible consider monitoring clinical responses and/or blood levels of concomitant drugs that have a narrow therapeutic range.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M17" type="Trigger" span="24 10" str="monitoring"/>
<Mention id="M18" type="Precipitant" span="89 42" str="drugs that have a narrow therapeutic range" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M17" precipitant="M18"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="156" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Table 5: Sevelamer Drug Interactions Oral drugs for which sevelamer did not alter the pharmacokinetics when administered concomitantly Digoxin Enalapril Iron Metoprolol Warfarin Oral drugs that have demonstrated interaction with sevelamer and are to be dosed separately from Renvela Dosing Recommendations Ciprofloxacin Take at least 2 hours before or 6 hours after sevelamer Mycophenolate mofetil Take at least 2 hours before sevelamer For oral medication where a reduction in the bioavailability of that medication would have a clinically significant effect on its safety or efficacy, consider separation of the timing of administration and/or monitor clinical responses or blood levels of the concomitant medication.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M22" type="Trigger" span="212 11" str="interaction "/>
<Mention id="M23" type="Trigger" span="253 16" str=" dosed separately"/>
<Mention id="M21" type="Precipitant" span="306 13" str="Ciprofloxacin" code="5E8K9I0O4U"/>
<Mention id="M24" type="Precipitant" span="376 21" str="Mycophenolate mofetil" code="9242ECW6R0"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M22;M23" precipitant="M21"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M22;M23" precipitant="M24"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="157" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Sevelamer did not alter the pharmacokinetics of digoxin, enalapril, iron, metoprolol and warfarin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="158" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Sevelamer has demonstrated interaction with ciprofloxacin, mycophenolate mofetil, and therefore, these drugs should be dosed separately from Renvela.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M28" type="Trigger" span="27 11" str="interaction "/>
<Mention id="M29" type="Trigger" span="119 16" str=" dosed separately"/>
<Mention id="M27" type="Precipitant" span="44 13" str="ciprofloxacin" code="5E8K9I0O4U"/>
<Mention id="M30" type="Precipitant" span="59 21" str="mycophenolate mofetil" code="9242ECW6R0"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M28;M29" precipitant="M27"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M28;M29" precipitant="M30"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="159" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Serious cases of dysphagia, bowel obstruction, and perforation have been associated with sevelamer use, some requiring hospitalization and surgery.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="160" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Cases of dysphagia and esophageal tablet retention have been reported in association with use of the tablet formulation of sevelamer, some requiring hospitalization and intervention.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="161" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Consider using sevelamer suspension in patients with a history of swallowing disorders.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="162" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Cases of bowel obstruction and perforation have also been reported with sevelamer use.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="163" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients with dysphagia, swallowing disorders, severe gastrointestinal (GI) motility disorders, including severe constipation, or major GI tract surgery were not included in the Renvela clinical studies.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="164" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In preclinical studies in rats and dogs, sevelamer hydrochloride, which contains the same active moiety as sevelamer carbonate, reduced vitamins D, E, and K (coagulation parameters) and folic acid levels at doses of 6–10 times the recommended human dose.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M37" type="Trigger" span="128 7" str="reduced"/>
<Mention id="M32" type="Precipitant" span="186 10" str="folic acid" code="935E97BOY8"/>
<Mention id="M34" type="Precipitant" span="136 8;148 1" str="vitamins | E" code="H4N855PNZ1"/>
<Mention id="M36" type="Precipitant" span="136 8;155 1" str="vitamins | K" code="N0000180191"/>
<Mention id="M38" type="Precipitant" span="136 10" str="vitamins D" code="N0000175952"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M37" precipitant="M32" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M37" precipitant="M34" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M37" precipitant="M36" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M37" precipitant="M38" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="165" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In short-term clinical trials, there was no evidence of reduction in serum levels of vitamins.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="166" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>However, in a one-year clinical trial, 25-hydroxyvitamin D (normal range 10 to 55 ng/mL) fell from 39 ± 22 ng/mL to 34 ± 22 ng/mL (p&lt;0.01) with sevelamer hydrochloride treatment.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M39" type="Trigger" span="89 4" str="fell"/>
<Mention id="M40" type="Precipitant" span="39 19" str="25-hydroxyvitamin D" code="A288AR3C9H"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M39" precipitant="M40" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="167" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Most (approximately 75%) patients in sevelamer hydrochloride clinical trials were receiving vitamin supplements.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="168" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Renvela contains sevelamer carbonate, a non-absorbed phosphate binding cross-linked polymer, free of metal and calcium.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="169" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>It contains multiple amines separated by one carbon from the polymer backbone.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="170" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>These amines exist in a protonated form in the intestine and interact with phosphate molecules through ionic and hydrogen bonding.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="171" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>By binding phosphate in the gastrointestinal tract and decreasing absorption, sevelamer carbonate lowers the phosphate concentration in the serum (serum phosphorus).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="172" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In addition to effects on serum phosphorus levels, sevelamer hydrochloride has been shown to bind bile acids in vitro and in vivo in experimental animal models.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="173" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Because sevelamer binds bile acids, it may interfere with normal fat absorption and thus may reduce absorption of fat soluble vitamins such as A, D and K. In clinical trials of sevelamer hydrochloride, both the mean total and LDL cholesterol declined by 15%–31%; the clinical significance of this finding, which was observed after 2 weeks, is unclear.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M47" type="Trigger" span="93 17" str="reduce absorption"/>
<Mention id="M42" type="Precipitant" span="114 20" str="fat soluble vitamins" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M44" type="Precipitant" span="126 8;143 1" str="vitamins | A" code="N0000175950"/>
<Mention id="M46" type="Precipitant" span="126 8;146 1" str="vitamins | D" code="N0000175952"/>
<Mention id="M48" type="Precipitant" span="126 8;152 1" str="vitamins | K" code="N0000180191"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M47" precipitant="M42" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M47" precipitant="M44" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M47" precipitant="M46" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M47" precipitant="M48" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="174" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Triglycerides, HDL cholesterol, and albumin did not change.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="175" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A mass balance study using 14C-sevelamer hydrochloride, in 16 healthy male and female volunteers showed that sevelamer hydrochloride is not systemically absorbed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="176" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No absorption studies have been performed in patients with renal disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="177" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Drug Interactions In vivo Sevelamer carbonate has been studied in human drug-drug interaction studies (9.6 grams once daily with a meal) with warfarin and digoxin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="178" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Sevelamer hydrochloride, which contains the same active moiety as sevelamer carbonate, has been studied in human drug-drug interaction studies (2.4–2.8 grams single dose or three times daily with meals or two times daily without meals) with ciprofloxacin, digoxin, enalapril, iron, metoprolol, mycophenolate mofetil, and warfarin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="179" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Coadministered single dose of 2.8 grams of sevelamer hydrochloride in fasted state decreased the bioavailability of ciprofloxacin by approximately 50% in healthy subjects.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M49" type="Trigger" span="83 29" str="decreased the bioavailability"/>
<Mention id="M50" type="Precipitant" span="116 13" str="ciprofloxacin" code="5E8K9I0O4U"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M49" precipitant="M50" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="180" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Concomitant administration of sevelamer and mycophenolate mofetil in adult and pediatric patients decreased the mean MPA Cmax and AUC0–12h by 36% and 26%, respectively.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M51" type="Trigger" span="98 9;130 3" str="decreased | AUC"/>
<Mention id="M54" type="Precipitant" span="44 21" str="mycophenolate mofetil" code="9242ECW6R0"/>
<Mention id="M53" type="Trigger" span="98 9;121 4" str="decreased | Cmax"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M51" precipitant="M54" effect="C54614"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M53" precipitant="M54" effect="C54615"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="181" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Sevelamer carbonate or sevelamer hydrochloride did not alter the pharmacokinetics of enalapril, digoxin, iron, metoprolol, and warfarin when coadministered.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="182" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>During postmarketing experience, cases of increased thyroid stimulating hormone (TSH) levels have been reported in patients coadministered sevelamer hydrochloride and levothyroxine.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M57" type="SpecificInteraction" span="42 50" str="increased thyroid stimulating hormone (TSH) levels" code="309080005: Raised thyroid stimulating hormone level (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M56" type="Precipitant" span="167 13" str="levothyroxine" code="Q51BO43MG4"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M57" precipitant="M56" effect="M57"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="183" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Reduction in concentrations of cyclosporine and tacrolimus leading to dose increases has also been reported in transplant patients when coadministered with sevelamer hydrochloride without any clinical consequences (for example, graft rejection).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M61" type="Trigger" span="0 27" str="Reduction in concentrations "/>
<Mention id="M62" type="Trigger" span="70 14" str=" dose increases"/>
<Mention id="M60" type="Precipitant" span="31 12" str="cyclosporine" code="83HN0GTJ6D"/>
<Mention id="M63" type="Precipitant" span="48 10" str="tacrolimus" code="WM0HAQ4WNM"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M61;M62" precipitant="M60" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M61;M62" precipitant="M63" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="184" LabelDrug="Renvela" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The possibility of an interaction cannot be excluded with these drugs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="phosphate binder" precipitantCode="N0000175597"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="calcium acetate" precipitantCode="Y882YXF34X"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cyclosporine" precipitantCode="83HN0GTJ6D" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="levothyroxine" precipitantCode="Q51BO43MG4" effect="309080005: Raised thyroid stimulating hormone level (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="levothyroxine" precipitantCode="Q51BO43MG4" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="tacrolimus" precipitantCode="WM0HAQ4WNM" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="drugs that have a narrow therapeutic range" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="ciprofloxacin" precipitantCode="5E8K9I0O4U" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="ciprofloxacin" precipitantCode="5E8K9I0O4U"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="mycophenolate mofetil" precipitantCode="9242ECW6R0" effect="C54614"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="mycophenolate mofetil" precipitantCode="9242ECW6R0" effect="C54615"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="mycophenolate mofetil" precipitantCode="9242ECW6R0"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="folic acid" precipitantCode="935E97BOY8" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="vitamins | e" precipitantCode="H4N855PNZ1" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="vitamins | k" precipitantCode="N0000180191" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="vitamins d" precipitantCode="N0000175952" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="25-hydroxyvitamin d" precipitantCode="A288AR3C9H" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="fat soluble vitamins" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="vitamins | a" precipitantCode="N0000175950" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="vitamins | d" precipitantCode="N0000175952" effect="C54358"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>