<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Revatio" setid="f158fe10-d5dc-4432-b2c9-fc665401291b">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
REVATIO is contraindicated in patients with:  Concomitant use of organic nitrates in any form, either regularly or intermittently, because of the greater risk of hypotension [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]. Known hypersensitivity to sildenafil or any component of the tablet, injection, or oral suspension. Hypersensitivity, including anaphylactic reaction, anaphylactic shock and anaphylactoid reaction, has been reported in association with the use of sildenafil.        Use with organic nitrates (4) History of hypersensitivity reaction to sildenafil or any component of the tablet, injection, or oral suspension (4)</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
Tablet and oral suspension: 5 mg or 20 mg three times a day, 4–6 hours apart (2.1) Injection: 2.5 mg or 10 mg three times a day administered as an intravenous bolus injection (2.2)           The recommended dose of REVATIO is 5 mg or 20 mg three times a day. Administer REVATIO doses 4–6 hours apart.  In the clinical trial no greater efficacy was achieved with the use of higher doses. Treatment with doses higher than 20 mg three times a day is not recommended.          REVATIO injection is for the continued treatment of patients with PAH who are currently prescribed oral REVATIO and who are temporarily unable to take oral medication.  The recommended dose is 2.5 mg or 10 mg administered as an intravenous bolus injection three times a day. The dose of REVATIO injection does not need to be adjusted for body weight.  A 10 mg dose of REVATIO injection is predicted to provide pharmacological effect of sildenafil and its N-desmethyl metabolite equivalent to that of a 20 mg oral dose.           Tap the bottle to release the powder. Remove the cap. Accurately measure out 60 mL of water and pour the water into the bottle. (Figure 1)  Figure 1   Replace the cap and shake the bottle vigorously for a minimum of 30 seconds. (Figure 2)  Figure 2   Remove the cap. Accurately measure out another 30 mL of water and add this to the bottle. You should always add a total of 90 mL of water irrespective of the dose prescribed. (Figure 3)  Figure 3   Replace the cap and shake the bottle vigorously for a minimum of 30 seconds. (Figure 4)  Figure 4   Remove the cap. Press the bottle adaptor into the neck of the bottle (as shown on Figure 5, below). The adaptor is provided so that you can fill the oral syringe with medicine from the bottle. Replace the cap on the bottle.  Figure 5    Write the expiration date of the constituted oral suspension on the bottle label (the expiration date of the constituted oral suspension is 60 days from the date of constitution).       Figure 1        Figure 2        Figure 3        Figure 4        Figure 5            Incompatibilities  Do not mix with any other medication or additional flavoring agent.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
Concomitant alpha-blockers or amlodipine: Note additive blood pressure lowering effects. (7) Use with ritonavir and other potent CYP3A inhibitors: Not recommended. (7, 12.3) Concomitant PDE-5 inhibitors: Avoid use with Viagra or other PDE-5 inhibitors. (5.7)           Nitrates  Concomitant use of REVATIO with nitrates in any form is contraindicated [see Contraindications (4)].           Ritonavir and other Potent CYP3A Inhibitors  Concomitant use of REVATIO with ritonavir and other potent CYP3A inhibitors is not recommended [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)].           Other drugs that reduce blood pressure          Alpha blockers. In drug-drug interaction studies, sildenafil (25 mg, 50 mg, or 100 mg) and the alpha-blocker doxazosin (4 mg or 8 mg) were administered simultaneously to patients with benign prostatic hyperplasia (BPH) stabilized on doxazosin therapy. In these study populations, mean additional reductions of supine systolic and diastolic blood pressure of 7/7 mmHg, 9/5 mmHg, and 8/4 mmHg, respectively, were observed. Mean additional reductions of standing blood pressure of 6/6 mmHg, 11/4 mmHg, and 4/5 mmHg, respectively, were also observed. There were infrequent reports of patients who experienced symptomatic postural hypotension. These reports included dizziness and light-headedness, but not syncope.           Amlodipine. When sildenafil 100 mg oral was co-administered with amlodipine, 5 mg or 10 mg oral, to hypertensive patients, the mean additional reduction on supine blood pressure was 8 mmHg systolic and 7 mmHg diastolic. Monitor blood pressure when co-administering blood pressure lowering drugs with REVATIO [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)].</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
Increased mortality with increasing doses in pediatric patients. Not recommended for use in pediatric patients. (5.1) Vasodilation effects may be more common in patients with hypotension or on antihypertensive therapy. (5.2) Use in pulmonary veno-occlusive disease may cause pulmonary edema and is not recommended. (5.3) Hearing or visual impairment: Seek medical attention if sudden decrease or loss of vision or hearing occurs. (5.5, 5.6) Pulmonary hypertension secondary to sickle cell disease: REVATIO may cause serious vaso-occlusive crises. (5.9)          In a long-term trial in pediatric patients with PAH, an increase in mortality with increasing REVATIO dose was observed. Deaths were first observed after about 1 year and causes of death were typical of patients with PAH. Use of REVATIO, particularly chronic use, is not recommended in children [see Use in Specific Populations (8.4)].           REVATIO has vasodilatory properties, resulting in mild and transient decreases in blood pressure. Before prescribing REVATIO, carefully consider whether patients with certain underlying conditions could be adversely affected by such vasodilatory effects (e.g., patients on antihypertensive therapy or with resting hypotension [BP less than 90/50], fluid depletion, severe left ventricular outflow obstruction, or autonomic dysfunction). Monitor blood pressure when co-administering blood pressure lowering drugs with REVATIO.          Pulmonary vasodilators may significantly worsen the cardiovascular status of patients with pulmonary veno-occlusive disease (PVOD). Since there are no clinical data on administration of REVATIO to patients with veno-occlusive disease, administration of REVATIO to such patients is not recommended. Should signs of pulmonary edema occur when REVATIO is administered, consider the possibility of associated PVOD.          The incidence of epistaxis was 13% in patients taking REVATIO with PAH secondary to CTD. This effect was not seen in idiopathic PAH (REVATIO 3%, placebo 2%) patients. The incidence of epistaxis was also higher in REVATIO-treated patients with a concomitant oral vitamin K antagonist (9% versus 2% in those not treated with concomitant vitamin K antagonist). The safety of REVATIO is unknown in patients with bleeding disorders or active peptic ulceration.          When used to treat erectile dysfunction, non-arteritic anterior ischemic optic neuropathy (NAION), a cause of decreased vision including permanent loss of vision, has been reported postmarketing in temporal association with the use of phosphodiesterase type 5 (PDE-5) inhibitors, including sildenafil. Most, but not all, of these patients had underlying anatomic or vascular risk factors for developing NAION, including but not necessarily limited to: low cup to disc ratio ("crowded disc"), age over 50, diabetes, hypertension, coronary artery disease, hyperlipidemia and smoking. It is not possible to determine whether these events are related directly to the use of PDE-5 inhibitors, to the patient's underlying vascular risk factors or anatomical defects, to a combination of these factors, or to other factors. Advise patients to seek immediate medical attention in the event of a sudden loss of vision in one or both eyes while taking PDE-5 inhibitors, including REVATIO. Physicians should also discuss the increased risk of NAION with patients who have already experienced NAION in one eye, including whether such individuals could be adversely affected by use of vasodilators, such as PDE-5 inhibitors. There are no controlled clinical data on the safety or efficacy of REVATIO in patients with retinitis pigmentosa, a minority whom have genetic disorders of retinal phosphodiesterases. Prescribe REVATIO with caution in these patients.          Cases of sudden decrease or loss of hearing, which may be accompanied by tinnitus and dizziness, have been reported in temporal association with the use of PDE-5 inhibitors, including REVATIO. In some of the cases, medical conditions and other factors were reported that may have played a role. In many cases, medical follow-up information was limited. It is not possible to determine whether these reported events are related directly to the use of REVATIO, to the patient's underlying risk factors for hearing loss, a combination of these factors, or to other factors. Advise patients to seek prompt medical attention in the event of sudden decrease or loss of hearing while taking PDE-5 inhibitors, including REVATIO.          Sildenafil is also marketed as VIAGRA®. The safety and efficacy of combinations of REVATIO with VIAGRA or other PDE-5 inhibitors have not been studied. Inform patients taking REVATIO not to take VIAGRA or other PDE-5 inhibitors.          Use REVATIO with caution in patients with anatomical deformation of the penis (e.g., angulation, cavernosal fibrosis, or Peyronie's disease) or in patients who have conditions, which may predispose them to priapism (e.g., sickle cell anemia, multiple myeloma, or leukemia). In the event of an erection that persists longer than 4 hours, the patient should seek immediate medical assistance. If priapism (painful erection greater than 6 hours in duration) is not treated immediately, penile tissue damage and permanent loss of potency could result.          In a small, prematurely terminated study of patients with pulmonary hypertension (PH) secondary to sickle cell disease, vaso-occlusive crises requiring hospitalization were more commonly reported by patients who received REVATIO than by those randomized to placebo. The effectiveness and safety of REVATIO in the treatment of PAH secondary to sickle cell anemia has not been established.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Sildenafil is an inhibitor of cGMP specific phosphodiesterase type-5 (PDE-5) in the smooth muscle of the pulmonary vasculature, where PDE-5 is responsible for degradation of cGMP. Sildenafil, therefore, increases cGMP within pulmonary vascular smooth muscle cells resulting in relaxation. In patients with PAH, this can lead to vasodilation of the pulmonary vascular bed and, to a lesser degree, vasodilatation in the systemic circulation. Studies in vitro have shown that sildenafil is selective for PDE-5. Its effect is more potent on PDE-5 than on other known phosphodiesterases (10-fold for PDE6, greater than 80-fold for PDE1, greater than 700-fold for PDE2, PDE3, PDE4, PDE7, PDE8, PDE9, PDE10, and PDE11). The approximately 4,000-fold selectivity for PDE-5 versus PDE3 is important because PDE3 is involved in control of cardiac contractility. Sildenafil is only about 10-fold as potent for PDE-5 compared to PDE6, an enzyme found in the retina and involved in the phototransduction pathway of the retina. This lower selectivity is thought to be the basis for abnormalities related to color vision observed with higher doses or plasma levels [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)]. In addition to pulmonary vascular smooth muscle and the corpus cavernosum, PDE-5 is also found in other tissues including vascular and visceral smooth muscle and in platelets. The inhibition of PDE-5 in these tissues by sildenafil may be the basis for the enhanced platelet anti-aggregatory activity of nitric oxide observed in vitro, and the mild peripheral arterial-venous dilatation in vivo.                Effects of REVATIO on Hemodynamic Measures  Patients on all REVATIO doses achieved a statistically significant reduction in mean pulmonary arterial pressure (mPAP) compared to those on placebo in a study with no background vasodilators [Study 1 in Clinical Studies (14)]. Data on other hemodynamic measures for the REVATIO 20 mg three times a day and placebo dosing regimens is displayed in Table 3. The relationship between these effects and improvements in 6-minute walk distance is unknown.  Table 3. Changes from Baseline in Hemodynamic Parameters at Week 12 [mean (95% CI)] for the REVATIO 20 mg Three Times a Day and Placebo Group       Placebo(n = 65)The number of patients per treatment group varied slightly for each parameter due to missing assessments.  REVATIO 20 mgthree times a day(n = 65)      mPAP = mean pulmonary arterial pressure; PVR= pulmonary vascular resistance; SVR = systemic vascular resistance; RAP = right atrial pressure; CO = cardiac output; HR = heart rate      mPAP (mmHg)  0.6 (-0.8, 2.0) -2.1 (-4.3, 0.0)    PVR (dyn∙s/cm5)  49 (-54, 153) -122 (-217, -27)    SVR (dyn∙s/cm5)  -78 (-197, 41) -167 (-307, -26)    RAP (mmHg)  0.3 (-0.9, 1.5) -0.8 (-1.9, 0.3)    CO (L/min)  -0.1 (-0.4, 0.2) 0.4 (0.1, 0.7)    HR (beats/min)  -1.3 (-4.1, 1.4) -3.7 (-5.9, -1.4)    In another study evaluating lower doses of sildenafil 1 mg, 5 mg and 20 mg [Study 3 in Clinical Studies (14)], there were no significant differences in the effects on hemodynamic variables between doses.           Effects of REVATIO on Blood Pressure  Single oral doses of sildenafil 100 mg administered to healthy volunteers produced decreases in supine blood pressure (mean maximum decrease in systolic/diastolic blood pressure of 8/5 mmHg). The decrease in blood pressure was most notable approximately 1–2 hours after dosing, and was not different from placebo at 8 hours. Similar effects on blood pressure were noted with 25 mg, 50 mg and 100 mg doses of sildenafil, therefore the effects are not related to dose or plasma levels within this dosage range. Larger effects were recorded among patients receiving concomitant nitrates [see Contraindications (4)]. Single oral doses of sildenafil up to 100 mg in healthy volunteers produced no clinically relevant effects on ECG. After chronic dosing of 80 mg three times a day to patients with PAH, no clinically relevant effects on ECG were reported. After chronic dosing of 80 mg three times a day sildenafil to healthy volunteers, the largest mean change from baseline in supine systolic and supine diastolic blood pressures was a decrease of 9.0 mmHg and 8.4 mmHg, respectively. After chronic dosing of 80 mg three times a day sildenafil to patients with systemic hypertension, the mean change from baseline in systolic and diastolic blood pressures was a decrease of 9.4 mmHg and 9.1 mmHg, respectively. After chronic dosing of 80 mg three times a day sildenafil to patients with PAH, lesser reductions than above in systolic and diastolic blood pressures were observed (a decrease in both of 2 mmHg).           Effects of REVATIO on Vision  At single oral doses of 100 mg and 200 mg, transient dose-related impairment of color discrimination (blue/green) was detected using the Farnsworth-Munsell 100-hue test, with peak effects near the time of peak plasma levels. This finding is consistent with the inhibition of PDE6, which is involved in phototransduction in the retina. An evaluation of visual function at doses up to 200 mg revealed no effects of REVATIO on visual acuity, intraocular pressure, or pupillometry.                  Absorption and Distribution  REVATIO is rapidly absorbed after oral administration, with a mean absolute bioavailability of 41% (25–63%). Maximum observed plasma concentrations are reached within 30 to 120 minutes (median 60 minutes) of oral dosing in the fasted state. When REVATIO is taken with a high-fat meal, the rate of absorption is reduced, with a mean delay in Tmax of 60 minutes and a mean reduction in Cmax of 29%. The mean steady state volume of distribution (Vss) for sildenafil is 105 L, indicating distribution into the tissues. Sildenafil and its major circulating N-desmethyl metabolite are both approximately 96% bound to plasma proteins. Protein binding is independent of total drug concentrations. Bioequivalence was established between the 20 mg tablet and the 10 mg/mL oral suspension when administered as a 20 mg single oral dose of sildenafil (as citrate).           Metabolism and Excretion  Sildenafil is cleared predominantly by the CYP3A (major route) and cytochrome P450 2C9 (CYP2C9, minor route) hepatic microsomal isoenzymes. The major circulating metabolite results from N-desmethylation of sildenafil, and is, itself, further metabolized. This metabolite has a phosphodiesterase selectivity profile similar to sildenafil and an in vitro potency for PDE-5 approximately 50% of the parent drug. In healthy volunteers, plasma concentrations of this metabolite are approximately 40% of those seen for sildenafil, so that the metabolite accounts for about 20% of sildenafil's pharmacologic effects. In patients with PAH, however, the ratio of the metabolite to sildenafil is higher. Both sildenafil and the active metabolite have terminal half-lives of about 4 hours. After either oral or intravenous administration, sildenafil is excreted as metabolites predominantly in the feces (approximately 80% of the administered oral dose) and to a lesser extent in the urine (approximately 13% of the administered oral dose). REVATIO Injection: The pharmacokinetic profile of REVATIO has been characterized following intravenous administration. A 10 mg dose of REVATIO Injection is predicted to provide a pharmacological effect of sildenafil and its N-desmethyl metabolite equivalent to that of a 20 mg oral dose.           Population Pharmacokinetics  Age, gender, race, and renal and hepatic function were included as factors assessed in the population pharmacokinetic model to evaluate sildenafil pharmacokinetics in patients with PAH. The dataset available for the population pharmacokinetic evaluation contained a wide range of demographic data and laboratory parameters associated with hepatic and renal function. None of these factors had a significant impact on sildenafil pharmacokinetics in patients with PAH. In patients with PAH, the average steady-state concentrations were 20–50% higher when compared to those of healthy volunteers. There was also a doubling of Cmin levels compared to healthy volunteers. Both findings suggest a lower clearance and/or a higher oral bioavailability of sildenafil in patients with PAH compared to healthy volunteers.         Geriatric Patients  Healthy elderly volunteers (65 years or over) had a reduced clearance of sildenafil, resulting in approximately 84% and 107% higher plasma concentrations of sildenafil and its active N-desmethyl metabolite, respectively, compared to those seen in healthy younger volunteers (18–45 years). Due to age-differences in plasma protein binding, the corresponding increase in the AUC of free (unbound) sildenafil and its active N-desmethyl metabolite were 45% and 57%, respectively.           Renal Impairment  In volunteers with mild (CLcr = 50–80 mL/min) and moderate (CLcr = 30–49 mL/min) renal impairment, the pharmacokinetics of a single oral dose of sildenafil (50 mg) was not altered. In volunteers with severe (CLcr less than 30 mL/min) renal impairment, sildenafil clearance was reduced, resulting in approximately doubling of AUC and Cmax compared to age-matched volunteers with no renal impairment. In addition, N-desmethyl metabolite AUC and Cmax values were significantly increased 200 % and 79 %, respectively, in subjects with severe renal impairment compared to subjects with normal renal function.           Hepatic Impairment  In volunteers with mild to moderate hepatic cirrhosis (Child-Pugh class A and B), sildenafil clearance was reduced, resulting in increases in AUC (84%) and Cmax (47%) compared to age-matched volunteers with no hepatic impairment. Patients with severe hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh class C) have not been studied.             Drug Interaction Studies           In vitro studies  Sildenafil metabolism is principally mediated by the CYP3A (major route) and CYP2C9 (minor route) cytochrome P450 isoforms. Therefore, inhibitors of these isoenzymes may reduce sildenafil clearance and inducers of these isoenzymes may increase sildenafil clearance. Sildenafil is a weak inhibitor of the cytochrome P450 isoforms 1A2, 2C9, 2C19, 2D6, 2E1 and 3A (IC50 greater than150 µM). Sildenafil is not expected to affect the pharmacokinetics of compounds which are substrates of these CYP enzymes at clinically relevant concentrations.            In vivo studies  The effects of other drugs on sildenafil pharmacokinetics and the effects of sildenafil on the exposure to other drugs are shown in Figure 7 and Figure 8, respectively.      Figure 7. Effects of Other Drugs on Sildenafil Pharmacokinetics            Figure 8 Effects of Sildenafil on Other Drugs                Figure 7        Figure 8            CYP3A Inhibitors and Beta Blockers  Population pharmacokinetic analysis of data from patients in clinical trials indicated an approximately 30% reduction in sildenafil clearance when it was co-administered with mild/moderate CYP3A inhibitors and an approximately 34% reductions in sildenafil clearance when co-administered with beta-blockers. Sildenafil exposure at a dose of 80 mg three times a day without concomitant medication is shown to be 5-fold the exposure at a dose of 20 mg three times a day. This concentration range covers the same increased sildenafil exposure observed in specifically-designed drug interaction studies with CYP3A inhibitors (except for potent inhibitors such as ketoconazole, itraconazole, and ritonavir). REVATIO Injection: Predictions based on a pharmacokinetic model suggest that drug-drug interactions with CYP3A inhibitors will be less than those observed after oral sildenafil administration.           CYP3A4 inducers including bosentan  Concomitant administration of potent CYP3A inducers is expected to cause substantial decreases in plasma levels of sildenafil. Population pharmacokinetic analysis of data from patients in clinical trials indicated approximately 3-fold the sildenafil clearance when it was co-administered with mild CYP3A inducers.           Epoprostenol  The mean reduction of sildenafil (80 mg three times a day) bioavailability when co-administered with epoprostenol was 28%, resulting in about 22% lower mean average steady state concentrations. Therefore, the slight decrease of sildenafil exposure in the presence of epoprostenol is not considered clinically relevant. The effect of sildenafil on epoprostenol pharmacokinetics is not known. No significant interactions were shown with tolbutamide (250 mg) or warfarin (40 mg), both of which are metabolized by CYP2C9.           Alcohol  Sildenafil (50 mg) did not potentiate the hypotensive effect of alcohol in healthy volunteers with mean maximum blood alcohol levels of 0.08%.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="2646" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>REVATIO is contraindicated in patients with: Concomitant use of organic nitrates in any form, either regularly or intermittently, because of the greater risk of hypotension.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M1" type="Trigger" span="145 12" str="greater risk"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="64 16" str="organic nitrates" code="N0000175415"/>
<Mention id="M3" type="SpecificInteraction" span="161 11" str="hypotension" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M1" precipitant="M2" effect="M3"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2647" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Concomitant use of riociguat, a guanylate cyclase stimulator.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2648" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>PDE-5 inhibitors, including sildenafil, may potentiate the hypotensive effects of riociguat.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M4" type="Trigger" span="44 10;71 7" str="potentiate | effects"/>
<Mention id="M5" type="Precipitant" span="82 9" str="riociguat" code="RU3FE2Y4XI"/>
<Mention id="M6" type="SpecificInteraction" span="44 34" str="potentiate the hypotensive effects" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M4" precipitant="M5" effect="M6"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2649" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Known hypersensitivity to sildenafil or any component of the tablet, injection, or oral suspension.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2650" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Hypersensitivity, including anaphylactic reaction, anaphylactic shock and anaphylactoid reaction, has been reported in association with the use of sildenafil.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2651" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Use with organic nitrates or riociguat (4) History of hypersensitivity reaction to sildenafil or any component of the tablet, injection, or oral suspension (4)</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2652" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Tablet and oral suspension: 5 mg or 20 mg three times a day, 4–6 hours apart (2.1) Injection: 2.5 mg or 10 mg three times a day administered as an intravenous bolus injection (2.2) The recommended dose of REVATIO is 5 mg or 20 mg three times a day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2653" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Administer REVATIO doses 4–6 hours apart.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2654" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In the clinical trial no greater efficacy was achieved with the use of higher doses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2655" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Treatment with doses higher than 20 mg three times a day is not recommended.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2656" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>REVATIO injection is for the continued treatment of patients with PAH who are currently prescribed oral REVATIO and who are temporarily unable to take oral medication.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2657" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommended dose is 2.5 mg or 10 mg administered as an intravenous bolus injection three times a day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2658" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The dose of REVATIO injection does not need to be adjusted for body weight.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2659" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>A 10 mg dose of REVATIO injection is predicted to provide pharmacological effect of sildenafil and its N-desmethyl metabolite equivalent to that of a 20 mg oral dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2660" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Accurately measure out 60 mL of water and pour the water into the bottle.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2661" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>(Figure 1) Figure 1 Replace the cap and shake the bottle vigorously for a minimum of 30 seconds.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2662" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>(Figure 2) Figure 2 Remove the cap.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2663" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Accurately measure out another 30 mL of water and add this to the bottle.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2664" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>You should always add a total of 90 mL of water irrespective of the dose prescribed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2665" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>(Figure 3) Figure 3 Replace the cap and shake the bottle vigorously for a minimum of 30 seconds.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2666" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>(Figure 4) Figure 4 Remove the cap.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2667" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Press the bottle adaptor into the neck of the bottle (as shown on Figure 5, below).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2668" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The adaptor is provided so that you can fill the oral syringe with medicine from the bottle.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2669" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Figure 5 Write the expiration date of the constituted oral suspension on the bottle label (the expiration date of the constituted oral suspension is 60 days from the date of constitution).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2670" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Figure 1 Figure 2 Figure 3 Figure 4 Figure 5 Incompatibilities Do not mix with any other medication or additional flavoring agent.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2671" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant alpha-blockers or amlodipine: Note additive blood pressure lowering effects.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M10" type="Trigger" span="47 8;80 7" str="additive | effects"/>
<Mention id="M8" type="Precipitant" span="12 14" str="alpha-blockers" code="N0000175553"/>
<Mention id="M12" type="SpecificInteraction" span="47 40" str="additive blood pressure lowering effects" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M11" type="Precipitant" span="30 10" str="amlodipine" code="1J444QC288"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M10" precipitant="M8" effect="M12"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M10" precipitant="M11" effect="M12"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2672" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Use with ritonavir and other potent CYP3A inhibitors: Not recommended.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M15" type="Trigger" span="54 15" str="Not recommended"/>
<Mention id="M14" type="Precipitant" span="29 23" str="potent CYP3A inhibitors" code="N0000191001"/>
<Mention id="M16" type="Precipitant" span="9 9" str="ritonavir" code="O3J8G9O825"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M15" precipitant="M14"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M15" precipitant="M16"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2673" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant PDE-5 inhibitors: Avoid use with Viagra or other PDE-5 inhibitors.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M19" type="Trigger" span="30 5" str="Avoid"/>
<Mention id="M18" type="Precipitant" span="12 16" str="PDE-5 inhibitors" code="N0000175599"/>
<Mention id="M20" type="Precipitant" span="45 6" str="Viagra" code="BW9B0ZE037"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M19" precipitant="M18"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M19" precipitant="M20"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2674" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Nitrates Concomitant use of REVATIO with nitrates in any form is contraindicated.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M21" type="Trigger" span="65 15" str="contraindicated"/>
<Mention id="M22" type="Precipitant" span="41 8" str="nitrates" code="N0000175415"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M21" precipitant="M22"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2675" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Ritonavir and other Potent CYP3A Inhibitors Concomitant use of REVATIO with ritonavir and other potent CYP3A inhibitors is not recommended.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M25" type="Trigger" span="123 15" str="not recommended"/>
<Mention id="M24" type="Precipitant" span="96 23" str="potent CYP3A inhibitors" code="N0000191001"/>
<Mention id="M26" type="Precipitant" span="76 9" str="ritonavir" code="O3J8G9O825"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M25" precipitant="M24"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M25" precipitant="M26"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2676" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Other drugs that reduce blood pressure Alpha blockers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2677" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>In drug-drug interaction studies, sildenafil (25 mg, 50 mg, or 100 mg) and the alpha-blocker doxazosin (4 mg or 8 mg) were administered simultaneously to patients with benign prostatic hyperplasia (BPH) stabilized on doxazosin therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2678" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>In these study populations, mean additional reductions of supine systolic and diastolic blood pressure of 7/7 mmHg, 9/5 mmHg, and 8/4 mmHg, respectively, were observed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2679" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Mean additional reductions of standing blood pressure of 6/6 mmHg, 11/4 mmHg, and 4/5 mmHg, respectively, were also observed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2680" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>There were infrequent reports of patients who experienced symptomatic postural hypotension.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2681" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>These reports included dizziness and light-headedness, but not syncope.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2682" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>When sildenafil 100 mg oral was co-administered with amlodipine, 5 mg or 10 mg oral, to hypertensive patients, the mean additional reduction on supine blood pressure was 8 mmHg systolic and 7 mmHg diastolic.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M27" type="Trigger" span="120 20" str="additional reduction"/>
<Mention id="M28" type="Precipitant" span="53 10" str="amlodipine" code="1J444QC288"/>
<Mention id="M29" type="SpecificInteraction" span="120 45" str="additional reduction on supine blood pressure" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M27" precipitant="M28" effect="M29"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2683" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor blood pressure when co-administering blood pressure lowering drugs with REVATIO.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M30" type="Trigger" span="0 7" str="Monitor"/>
<Mention id="M31" type="Precipitant" span="45 29" str="blood pressure lowering drugs" code="N0000178477"/>
<Mention id="M32" type="SpecificInteraction" span="-1 14" str="Blood pressure" code="38936003: Abnormal blood pressure (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M30" precipitant="M31" effect="M32"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2684" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Increased mortality with increasing doses in pediatric patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2685" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Not recommended for use in pediatric patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2686" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Vasodilation effects may be more common in patients with hypotension or on antihypertensive therapy.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M33" type="Trigger" span="13 26" str="effects may be more common"/>
<Mention id="M34" type="Precipitant" span="75 24" str="antihypertensive therapy" code="N0000178477"/>
<Mention id="M35" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 20" str="Vasodilation effects" code="91081006: Vasodilatation (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M33" precipitant="M34" effect="M35"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2687" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Use in pulmonary veno-occlusive disease may cause pulmonary edema and is not recommended.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2688" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hearing or visual impairment: Seek medical attention if sudden decrease or loss of vision or hearing occurs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2689" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Pulmonary hypertension secondary to sickle cell disease: REVATIO may cause serious vaso-occlusive crises.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2690" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In a long-term trial in pediatric patients with PAH, an increase in mortality with increasing REVATIO dose was observed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2691" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Deaths were first observed after about 1 year and causes of death were typical of patients with PAH.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2692" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Use of REVATIO, particularly chronic use, is not recommended in children.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2693" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>REVATIO has vasodilatory properties, resulting in mild and transient decreases in blood pressure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2694" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Before prescribing REVATIO, carefully consider whether patients with certain underlying conditions could be adversely affected by such vasodilatory effects (e.g., patients on antihypertensive therapy or with resting hypotension [BP less than 90/50], fluid depletion, severe left ventricular outflow obstruction, or autonomic dysfunction).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M36" type="Trigger" span="99 27" str="could be adversely affected"/>
<Mention id="M37" type="Precipitant" span="175 24" str="antihypertensive therapy" code="N0000178477"/>
<Mention id="M38" type="SpecificInteraction" span="135 20" str="vasodilatory effects" code="91081006: Vasodilatation (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M36" precipitant="M37" effect="M38"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2695" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Pulmonary vasodilators may significantly worsen the cardiovascular status of patients with pulmonary veno-occlusive disease (PVOD).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2696" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Since there are no clinical data on administration of REVATIO to patients with veno-occlusive disease, administration of REVATIO to such patients is not recommended.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2697" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Should signs of pulmonary edema occur when REVATIO is administered, consider the possibility of associated PVOD.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2698" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The incidence of epistaxis was 13% in patients taking REVATIO with PAH secondary to CTD.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2699" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>This effect was not seen in idiopathic PAH (REVATIO 3%, placebo 2%) patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2700" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The incidence of epistaxis was also higher in REVATIO-treated patients with a concomitant oral vitamin K antagonist (9% versus 2% in those not treated with concomitant vitamin K antagonist).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M39" type="Trigger" span="4 9;36 6" str="incidence | higher"/>
<Mention id="M40" type="Precipitant" span="90 25" str="oral vitamin K antagonist" code="N0000175476"/>
<Mention id="M41" type="SpecificInteraction" span="17 9" str="epistaxis" code="249366005: Bleeding from nose (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M39" precipitant="M40" effect="M41"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2701" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The safety of REVATIO is unknown in patients with bleeding disorders or active peptic ulceration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2702" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>When used to treat erectile dysfunction, non-arteritic anterior ischemic optic neuropathy (NAION), a cause of decreased vision including permanent loss of vision, has been reported postmarketing in temporal association with the use of phosphodiesterase type 5 (PDE-5) inhibitors, including sildenafil.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2703" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Most, but not all, of these patients had underlying anatomic or vascular risk factors for developing NAION, including but not necessarily limited to: low cup to disc ratio (crowded disc), age over 50, diabetes, hypertension, coronary artery disease, hyperlipidemia and smoking.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2704" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Based on published literature, the annual incidence of NAION is 2.5–11.8 cases per 100,000 males aged ≥ 50 per year in the general population.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2705" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>An observational case-crossover study evaluated the risk of NAION when PDE-5 inhibitor use, as a class, occurred immediately before NAION onset (within 5 half-lives), compared to PDE-5 inhibitor use in a prior time period.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2706" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The results suggest an approximate 2-fold increase in the risk of NAION, with a risk estimate of 2.15 (95% CI 1.06, 4.34).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2707" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>A similar study reported a consistent result, with a risk estimate of 2.27 (95% CI 0.99, 5.20).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2708" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Other risk factors for NAION, such as the presence of crowded optic disc, may have contributed to the occurrence of NAION in these studies.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2709" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Neither the rare postmarketing reports, nor the association of PDE-5 inhibitor use and NAION in the observational studies, substantiate a causal relationship between PDE-5 inhibitor use and NAION.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2710" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Advise patients to seek immediate medical attention in the event of a sudden loss of vision in one or both eyes while taking PDE-5 inhibitors, including REVATIO.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2711" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Physicians should also discuss the increased risk of NAION with patients who have already experienced NAION in one eye, including whether such individuals could be adversely affected by use of vasodilators, such as PDE-5 inhibitors.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2712" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There are no controlled clinical data on the safety or efficacy of REVATIO in patients with retinitis pigmentosa, a minority whom have genetic disorders of retinal phosphodiesterases.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2713" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Prescribe REVATIO with caution in these patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2714" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Cases of sudden decrease or loss of hearing, which may be accompanied by tinnitus and dizziness, have been reported in temporal association with the use of PDE-5 inhibitors, including REVATIO.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2715" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In some of the cases, medical conditions and other factors were reported that may have played a role.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2716" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In many cases, medical follow-up information was limited.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2717" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>It is not possible to determine whether these reported events are related directly to the use of REVATIO, to the patient's underlying risk factors for hearing loss, a combination of these factors, or to other factors.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2718" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Advise patients to seek prompt medical attention in the event of sudden decrease or loss of hearing while taking PDE-5 inhibitors, including REVATIO.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2719" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The safety and efficacy of combinations of REVATIO with VIAGRA or other PDE-5 inhibitors have not been studied.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2720" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Inform patients taking REVATIO not to take VIAGRA or other PDE-5 inhibitors.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M44" type="Trigger" span="0 15;31 11" str="Inform patients | not to take"/>
<Mention id="M43" type="Precipitant" span="59 16" str="PDE-5 inhibitors" code="N0000175599"/>
<Mention id="M45" type="Precipitant" span="43 6" str="VIAGRA" code="BW9B0ZE037"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M44" precipitant="M43"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M44" precipitant="M45"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2721" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Use REVATIO with caution in patients with anatomical deformation of the penis (e.g., angulation, cavernosal fibrosis, or Peyronie's disease) or in patients who have conditions, which may predispose them to priapism (e.g., sickle cell anemia, multiple myeloma, or leukemia).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2722" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In the event of an erection that persists longer than 4 hours, the patient should seek immediate medical assistance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2723" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If priapism (painful erection greater than 6 hours in duration) is not treated immediately, penile tissue damage and permanent loss of potency could result.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2724" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In a small, prematurely terminated study of patients with pulmonary hypertension (PH) secondary to sickle cell disease, vaso-occlusive crises requiring hospitalization were more commonly reported by patients who received REVATIO than by those randomized to placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2725" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The effectiveness and safety of REVATIO in the treatment of PAH secondary to sickle cell anemia has not been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2726" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Sildenafil is an inhibitor of cGMP specific phosphodiesterase type-5 (PDE-5) in the smooth muscle of the pulmonary vasculature, where PDE-5 is responsible for degradation of cGMP.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2727" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Sildenafil, therefore, increases cGMP within pulmonary vascular smooth muscle cells resulting in relaxation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2728" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In patients with PAH, this can lead to vasodilation of the pulmonary vascular bed and, to a lesser degree, vasodilatation in the systemic circulation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2729" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Studies in vitro have shown that sildenafil is selective for PDE-5.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2730" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Its effect is more potent on PDE-5 than on other known phosphodiesterases (10-fold for PDE6, greater than 80-fold for PDE1, greater than 700-fold for PDE2, PDE3, PDE4, PDE7, PDE8, PDE9, PDE10, and PDE11).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2731" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The approximately 4,000-fold selectivity for PDE-5 versus PDE3 is important because PDE3 is involved in control of cardiac contractility.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2732" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Sildenafil is only about 10-fold as potent for PDE-5 compared to PDE6, an enzyme found in the retina and involved in the phototransduction pathway of the retina.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2733" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This lower selectivity is thought to be the basis for abnormalities related to color vision observed with higher doses or plasma levels.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2734" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In addition to pulmonary vascular smooth muscle and the corpus cavernosum, PDE-5 is also found in other tissues including vascular and visceral smooth muscle and in platelets.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2735" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The inhibition of PDE-5 in these tissues by sildenafil may be the basis for the enhanced platelet anti-aggregatory activity of nitric oxide observed in vitro, and the mild peripheral arterial-venous dilatation in vivo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2736" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Effects of REVATIO on Hemodynamic Measures Patients on all REVATIO doses achieved a statistically significant reduction in mean pulmonary arterial pressure (mPAP) compared to those on placebo in a study with no background vasodilators [Study 1 in Clinical Studies (14)].</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2737" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Data on other hemodynamic measures for the REVATIO 20 mg three times a day and placebo dosing regimens is displayed in Table 3.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2738" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The relationship between these effects and improvements in 6-minute walk distance is unknown.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2739" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Changes from Baseline in Hemodynamic Parameters at Week 12 [mean (95% CI)] for the REVATIO 20 mg Three Times a Day and Placebo Group Placebo(n = 65)The number of patients per treatment group varied slightly for each parameter due to missing assessments.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2740" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>REVATIO 20 mgthree times a day(n = 65) mPAP = mean pulmonary arterial pressure; PVR= pulmonary vascular resistance; SVR = systemic vascular resistance; RAP = right atrial pressure; CO = cardiac output; HR = heart rate mPAP (mmHg) 0.6 (-0.8, 2.0) -2.1 (-4.3, 0.0) PVR (dyn∙s/cm5) 49 (-54, 153) -122 (-217, -27) SVR (dyn∙s/cm5) -78 (-197, 41) -167 (-307, -26) RAP (mmHg) 0.3 (-0.9, 1.5) -0.8 (-1.9, 0.3) CO (L/min) -0.1 (-0.4, 0.2) 0.4 (0.1, 0.7) HR (beats/min) -1.3 (-4.1, 1.4) -3.7 (-5.9, -1.4) In another study evaluating lower doses of sildenafil 1 mg, 5 mg and 20 mg [Study 3 in Clinical Studies (14)], there were no significant differences in the effects on hemodynamic variables between doses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2741" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Effects of REVATIO on Blood Pressure Single oral doses of sildenafil 100 mg administered to healthy volunteers produced decreases in supine blood pressure (mean maximum decrease in systolic/diastolic blood pressure of 8/5 mmHg).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2742" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The decrease in blood pressure was most notable approximately 1–2 hours after dosing, and was not different from placebo at 8 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2743" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Similar effects on blood pressure were noted with 25 mg, 50 mg and 100 mg doses of sildenafil, therefore the effects are not related to dose or plasma levels within this dosage range.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2744" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Larger effects were recorded among patients receiving concomitant nitrates.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M46" type="Trigger" span="0 14" str="Larger effects"/>
<Mention id="M47" type="Precipitant" span="66 8" str="nitrates" code="N0000175415"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M46" precipitant="M47"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2745" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Single oral doses of sildenafil up to 100 mg in healthy volunteers produced no clinically relevant effects on ECG.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2746" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>After chronic dosing of 80 mg three times a day to patients with PAH, no clinically relevant effects on ECG were reported.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2747" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>After chronic dosing of 80 mg three times a day sildenafil to healthy volunteers, the largest mean change from baseline in supine systolic and supine diastolic blood pressures was a decrease of 9.0 mmHg and 8.4 mmHg, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2748" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>After chronic dosing of 80 mg three times a day sildenafil to patients with systemic hypertension, the mean change from baseline in systolic and diastolic blood pressures was a decrease of 9.4 mmHg and 9.1 mmHg, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2749" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>After chronic dosing of 80 mg three times a day sildenafil to patients with PAH, lesser reductions than above in systolic and diastolic blood pressures were observed (a decrease in both of 2 mmHg).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2750" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Effects of REVATIO on Vision At single oral doses of 100 mg and 200 mg, transient dose-related impairment of color discrimination (blue/green) was detected using the Farnsworth-Munsell 100-hue test, with peak effects near the time of peak plasma levels.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2751" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This finding is consistent with the inhibition of PDE6, which is involved in phototransduction in the retina.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2752" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>An evaluation of visual function at doses up to 200 mg revealed no effects of REVATIO on visual acuity, intraocular pressure, or pupillometry.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2753" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Absorption and Distribution REVATIO is rapidly absorbed after oral administration, with a mean absolute bioavailability of 41% (25–63%).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2754" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Maximum observed plasma concentrations are reached within 30 to 120 minutes (median 60 minutes) of oral dosing in the fasted state.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2755" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>When REVATIO is taken with a high-fat meal, the rate of absorption is reduced, with a mean delay in Tmax of 60 minutes and a mean reduction in Cmax of 29%.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M48" type="Trigger" span="48 29" str="rate of absorption is reduced"/>
<Mention id="M53" type="Precipitant" span="29 13" str="high-fat meal" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M50" type="Trigger" span="91 13" str="delay in Tmax"/>
<Mention id="M52" type="Trigger" span="130 17" str="reduction in Cmax"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M48" precipitant="M53" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M50" precipitant="M53" effect="C54604"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M52" precipitant="M53" effect="C54606"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2756" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mean steady state volume of distribution (Vss) for sildenafil is 105 L, indicating distribution into the tissues.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2757" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Sildenafil and its major circulating N-desmethyl metabolite are both approximately 96% bound to plasma proteins.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2758" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Protein binding is independent of total drug concentrations.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2759" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Bioequivalence was established between the 20 mg tablet and the 10 mg/mL oral suspension when administered as a 20 mg single oral dose of sildenafil (as citrate).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2760" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Metabolism and Excretion Sildenafil is cleared predominantly by the CYP3A (major route) and cytochrome P450 2C9 (CYP2C9, minor route) hepatic microsomal isoenzymes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2761" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The major circulating metabolite results from N-desmethylation of sildenafil, and is, itself, further metabolized.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2762" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This metabolite has a phosphodiesterase selectivity profile similar to sildenafil and an in vitro potency for PDE-5 approximately 50% of the parent drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2763" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In healthy volunteers, plasma concentrations of this metabolite are approximately 40% of those seen for sildenafil, so that the metabolite accounts for about 20% of sildenafil's pharmacologic effects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2764" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In patients with PAH, however, the ratio of the metabolite to sildenafil is higher.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2765" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Both sildenafil and the active metabolite have terminal half-lives of about 4 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2766" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>After either oral or intravenous administration, sildenafil is excreted as metabolites predominantly in the feces (approximately 80% of the administered oral dose) and to a lesser extent in the urine (approximately 13% of the administered oral dose).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2767" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>REVATIO Injection: The pharmacokinetic profile of REVATIO has been characterized following intravenous administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2768" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A 10 mg dose of REVATIO Injection is predicted to provide a pharmacological effect of sildenafil and its N-desmethyl metabolite equivalent to that of a 20 mg oral dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2769" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Population Pharmacokinetics Age, gender, race, and renal and hepatic function were included as factors assessed in the population pharmacokinetic model to evaluate sildenafil pharmacokinetics in patients with PAH.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2770" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The dataset available for the population pharmacokinetic evaluation contained a wide range of demographic data and laboratory parameters associated with hepatic and renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2771" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>None of these factors had a significant impact on sildenafil pharmacokinetics in patients with PAH.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2772" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In patients with PAH, the average steady-state concentrations were 20–50% higher when compared to those of healthy volunteers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2773" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There was also a doubling of Cmin levels compared to healthy volunteers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2774" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Both findings suggest a lower clearance and/or a higher oral bioavailability of sildenafil in patients with PAH compared to healthy volunteers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2775" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Geriatric Patients Healthy elderly volunteers (65 years or over) had a reduced clearance of sildenafil, resulting in approximately 84% and 107% higher plasma concentrations of sildenafil and its active N-desmethyl metabolite, respectively, compared to those seen in healthy younger volunteers (18–45 years).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2776" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Due to age-differences in plasma protein binding, the corresponding increase in the AUC of free (unbound) sildenafil and its active N-desmethyl metabolite were 45% and 57%, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2777" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Renal Impairment In volunteers with mild (CLcr = 50–80 mL/min) and moderate (CLcr = 30–49 mL/min) renal impairment, the pharmacokinetics of a single oral dose of sildenafil (50 mg) was not altered.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2778" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In volunteers with severe (CLcr less than 30 mL/min) renal impairment, sildenafil clearance was reduced, resulting in approximately doubling of AUC and Cmax compared to age-matched volunteers with no renal impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2779" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In addition, N-desmethyl metabolite AUC and Cmax values were significantly increased 200 % and 79 %, respectively, in subjects with severe renal impairment compared to subjects with normal renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2780" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Hepatic Impairment In volunteers with mild to moderate hepatic cirrhosis (Child-Pugh class A and B), sildenafil clearance was reduced, resulting in increases in AUC (84%) and Cmax (47%) compared to age-matched volunteers with no hepatic impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2781" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Patients with severe hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh class C) have not been studied.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2782" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Drug Interaction Studies In vitro studies Sildenafil metabolism is principally mediated by the CYP3A (major route) and CYP2C9 (minor route) cytochrome P450 isoforms.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2783" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Therefore, inhibitors of these isoenzymes may reduce sildenafil clearance and inducers of these isoenzymes may increase sildenafil clearance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2784" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Sildenafil is a weak inhibitor of the cytochrome P450 isoforms 1A2, 2C9, 2C19, 2D6, 2E1 and 3A (IC50 greater than150 µM).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2785" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Sildenafil is not expected to affect the pharmacokinetics of compounds which are substrates of these CYP enzymes at clinically relevant concentrations.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2786" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In vivo studies The effects of other drugs on sildenafil pharmacokinetics and the effects of sildenafil on the exposure to other drugs are shown in Figure 7 and Figure 8, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2787" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Effects of Other Drugs on Sildenafil Pharmacokinetics Figure 8 Effects of Sildenafil on Other Drugs Figure 7 Figure 8 CYP3A Inhibitors and Beta Blockers Population pharmacokinetic analysis of data from patients in clinical trials indicated an approximately 30% reduction in sildenafil clearance when it was co-administered with mild/moderate CYP3A inhibitors and an approximately 34% reductions in sildenafil clearance when co-administered with beta-blockers.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M54" type="Trigger" span="384 10;285 9" str="reductions | clearance"/>
<Mention id="M55" type="Precipitant" span="445 13" str="beta-blockers" code="N0000175556"/>
<Mention id="M56" type="Trigger" span="261 9;285 9" str="reduction | clearance"/>
<Mention id="M57" type="Precipitant" span="328 30" str="mild/moderate CYP3A inhibitors" code="N0000191001"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M54" precipitant="M55" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M56" precipitant="M57" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2788" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Sildenafil exposure at a dose of 80 mg three times a day without concomitant medication is shown to be 5-fold the exposure at a dose of 20 mg three times a day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2789" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This concentration range covers the same increased sildenafil exposure observed in specifically-designed drug interaction studies with CYP3A inhibitors (except for potent inhibitors such as ketoconazole, itraconazole, and ritonavir).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M58" type="Trigger" span="41 9;62 8" str="increased | exposure"/>
<Mention id="M59" type="Precipitant" span="135 16" str="CYP3A inhibitors" code="N0000191001"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M58" precipitant="M59" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2790" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>REVATIO Injection: Predictions based on a pharmacokinetic model suggest that drug-drug interactions with CYP3A inhibitors will be less than those observed after oral sildenafil administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2791" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>CYP3A4 inducers including bosentan Concomitant administration of potent CYP3A inducers is expected to cause substantial decreases in plasma levels of sildenafil.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M64" type="Trigger" span="120 26" str="decreases in plasma levels"/>
<Mention id="M61" type="Precipitant" span="26 8" str="bosentan" code="Q326023R30"/>
<Mention id="M63" type="Precipitant" span="0 15" str="CYP3A4 inducers" code="N0000185506"/>
<Mention id="M65" type="Precipitant" span="65 21" str="potent CYP3A inducers" code="N0000190118"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M64" precipitant="M61" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M64" precipitant="M63" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M64" precipitant="M65" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2792" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Population pharmacokinetic analysis of data from patients in clinical trials indicated approximately 3-fold the sildenafil clearance when it was co-administered with mild CYP3A inducers.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M66" type="Trigger" span="101 6;123 9" str="3-fold | clearance"/>
<Mention id="M67" type="Precipitant" span="166 19" str="mild CYP3A inducers" code="N0000190118"/>
<Interaction id="I29" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M66" precipitant="M67" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2793" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Epoprostenol The mean reduction of sildenafil (80 mg three times a day) bioavailability when co-administered with epoprostenol was 28%, resulting in about 22% lower mean average steady state concentrations.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M68" type="Trigger" span="22 9;72 15" str="reduction | bioavailability"/>
<Mention id="M71" type="Precipitant" span="114 12" str="epoprostenol" code="DCR9Z582X0"/>
<Mention id="M70" type="Trigger" span="159 5;191 14" str="lower | concentrations"/>
<Interaction id="I30" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M68" precipitant="M71" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I31" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M70" precipitant="M71" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2794" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Therefore, the slight decrease of sildenafil exposure in the presence of epoprostenol is not considered clinically relevant.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M72" type="Trigger" span="22 8;45 8" str="decrease | exposure"/>
<Mention id="M73" type="Precipitant" span="73 12" str="epoprostenol" code="DCR9Z582X0"/>
<Interaction id="I32" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M72" precipitant="M73" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2795" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The effect of sildenafil on epoprostenol pharmacokinetics is not known.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2796" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No significant interactions were shown with tolbutamide (250 mg) or warfarin (40 mg), both of which are metabolized by CYP2C9.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2797" LabelDrug="Revatio" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Alcohol Sildenafil (50 mg) did not potentiate the hypotensive effect of alcohol in healthy volunteers with mean maximum blood alcohol levels of 0.08%.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="organic nitrates" precipitantCode="N0000175415" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="riociguat" precipitantCode="RU3FE2Y4XI" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="alpha-blockers" precipitantCode="N0000175553" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="amlodipine" precipitantCode="1J444QC288" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="potent cyp3a inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000191001"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="ritonavir" precipitantCode="O3J8G9O825"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="pde-5 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175599"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="viagra" precipitantCode="BW9B0ZE037"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="nitrates" precipitantCode="N0000175415"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="blood pressure lowering drugs" precipitantCode="N0000178477" effect="38936003: Abnormal blood pressure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="antihypertensive therapy" precipitantCode="N0000178477" effect="91081006: Vasodilatation (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="oral vitamin k antagonist" precipitantCode="N0000175476" effect="249366005: Bleeding from nose (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="high-fat meal" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="high-fat meal" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54604"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="high-fat meal" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54606"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="beta-blockers" precipitantCode="N0000175556" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="mild/moderate cyp3a inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000191001" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cyp3a inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000191001" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="bosentan" precipitantCode="Q326023R30" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cyp3a4 inducers" precipitantCode="N0000185506" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="potent cyp3a inducers" precipitantCode="N0000190118" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="mild cyp3a inducers" precipitantCode="N0000190118" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="epoprostenol" precipitantCode="DCR9Z582X0" effect="C54356"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>