<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="SULAR" setid="bcdeafac-f4ef-4dda-bdb7-1f819c33bb76">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
SULAR is contraindicated in patients with known hypersensitivity to dihydropyridine calcium channel blockers.</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
The dosage of SULAR must be adjusted to each patient's needs. Therapy usually should be initiated with 17 mg orally once daily, then increased by 8.5 mg per week or longer intervals, to attain adequate control of blood pressure. Usual maintenance dosage is 17 to 34 mg once daily. Blood pressure response increases over the 8.5 - 34 mg daily dose range but adverse event rates also increase. Doses beyond 34 mg once daily are not recommended. SULAR has been used safely with diuretics, ACE inhibitors, and beta-blocking agents. Patients over age 65, or patients with impaired liver function are expected to develop higher plasma concentrations of nisoldipine. Their blood pressure should be monitored closely during any dosage adjustment. A starting dose not exceeding 8.5 mg daily is recommended in these patient groups. SULAR tablets should be administered orally once daily. SULAR should be taken on an empty stomach (1 hour before or 2 hours after a meal). Grapefruit products should be avoided before and after dosing. SULAR is an extended release dosage form and tablets should be swallowed whole, not bitten, divided or crushed.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
A 30 to 45% increase in AUC and Cmax of nisoldipine was observed with concomitant administration of cimetidine 400 mg twice daily. Ranitidine 150 mg twice daily did not interact significantly with nisoldipine (AUC was decreased by 15 - 20%). No pharmacodynamic effects of either histamine H2 receptor antagonist were observed.  CYP3A4 inhibitors and inducers  SULAR is substrate of CYP3A4 and coadministration of SULAR with any known inducer or inhibitor of CYP3A4 should be avoided in general. Coadministration of phenytoin with a dose bioequivalent to 34 mg SULAR tablets in epileptic patients lowered the nisoldipine plasma concentrations to undetectable levels. Coadministration of SULAR with phenytoin should be avoided and alternative antihypertensive therapy should be considered. Pharmacokinetic interactions between nisoldipine and beta-blockers (atenolol, propranolol) were variable and not significant. Propranolol attenuated the heart rate increase following administration of immediate release nisoldipine. The blood pressure effect of SULAR tended to be greater in patients on atenolol than in patients on no other antihypertensive therapy. Quinidine at 648 mg bid decreased the bioavailability (AUC) of nisoldipine by 26%, but not the peak concentration. Immediate release nisoldipine increased plasma quinidine concentrations by about 20%. This interaction was not accompanied by ECG changes and its clinical significance is not known. No significant interactions were found between nisoldipine and warfarin of digoxin.</Section>
<Section name="PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="42232-9">
Hypotension  Because nisoldipine, like other vasodilators, decreases peripheral vascular resistance, careful monitoring of blood pressure during the initial administration and titration of SULAR is recommended. Close observation is especially important for patients already taking medications that are known to lower blood pressure. Although in most patients the hypotensive effect of SULAR is modest and well tolerated, occasional patients have had excessive and poorly tolerated hypotension. These responses have usually occurred during initial titration or at the time of subsequent upward dosage adjustment.  Congestive Heart Failure  Although acute hemodynamic studies of nisoldipine in patients with NYHA Class II-IV heart failure have not demonstrated negative inotropic effects, safety of SULAR in patients with heart failure has not been established. Caution therefore should be exercised when using SULAR in patients with heart failure or compromised ventricular function, particularly in combination with a beta-blocker.  Patients with Hepatic Impairment  Because nisoldipine is extensively metabolized by the liver and, in patients with cirrhosis, it reaches blood concentrations about 5 times those in normals, SULAR should be administered cautiously in patients with severe hepatic dysfunction (See  DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION ).           SULAR is an extended release tablet and should be swallowed whole. Tablets should not be chewed, divided or crushed. SULAR should be taken on an empty stomach (1 hour before or 2 hours after a meal). Grapefruit juice, which has been shown to increase significantly the bioavailability of nisoldipine and other dihydropyridine type calcium channel blockers, should not be taken with SULAR. This product contains FD&amp;amp;C Yellow No. 5 (tartrazine) which may cause allergic-type reactions (including bronchial asthma) in certain susceptible persons. Although the overall incidence of FD&amp;amp;C Yellow No. 5 (tartrazine) sensitivity in the general population is low, it is frequently seen in patients who also have aspirin hypersensitivity.          SULAR is not known to interfere with the interpretation of laboratory tests.          A 30 to 45% increase in AUC and Cmax of nisoldipine was observed with concomitant administration of cimetidine 400 mg twice daily. Ranitidine 150 mg twice daily did not interact significantly with nisoldipine (AUC was decreased by 15 - 20%). No pharmacodynamic effects of either histamine H2 receptor antagonist were observed.  CYP3A4 inhibitors and inducers  SULAR is substrate of CYP3A4 and coadministration of SULAR with any known inducer or inhibitor of CYP3A4 should be avoided in general. Coadministration of phenytoin with a dose bioequivalent to 34 mg SULAR tablets in epileptic patients lowered the nisoldipine plasma concentrations to undetectable levels. Coadministration of SULAR with phenytoin should be avoided and alternative antihypertensive therapy should be considered. Pharmacokinetic interactions between nisoldipine and beta-blockers (atenolol, propranolol) were variable and not significant. Propranolol attenuated the heart rate increase following administration of immediate release nisoldipine. The blood pressure effect of SULAR tended to be greater in patients on atenolol than in patients on no other antihypertensive therapy. Quinidine at 648 mg bid decreased the bioavailability (AUC) of nisoldipine by 26%, but not the peak concentration. Immediate release nisoldipine increased plasma quinidine concentrations by about 20%. This interaction was not accompanied by ECG changes and its clinical significance is not known. No significant interactions were found between nisoldipine and warfarin of digoxin.          Dietary administration of nisoldipine to male and female rats for up to 24 months (mean doses up to 82 and 111 mg/kg/day, 16 and 19 times the maximum recommended human dose [MRHD] on a mg/m2 basis, respectively and female mice for up to 21 months (mean doses of up to 217 mg/kg/day, 20 times the MRHD on a mg/m2 basis) revealed no evidence of tumorigenic effect of nisoldipine. In male mice receiving a mean dose of 163 mg nisoldipine/kg/day (16 times the MRHD of 60 mg/day on a mg/m2 basis), an increased frequency of stomach papilloma, but still within the historical range, was observed. No evidence of stomach neoplasia was observed at lower doses (up to 58 mg/kg/day). Nisoldipine was negative when tested in a battery of genotoxicity assays including the Ames test and the CHO/HGRPT assay for mutagenicity and the in vivo mouse micronucleus test and in vitro CHO cell test for clastogenicity. When administered to male and female rats at doses of up to 30 mg/kg/day (about 5 times the MRHD on a mg/m2 basis) nisoldipine had no effect on fertility.          Nisoldipine was neither teratogenic nor fetotoxic at doses that were not maternally toxic. Nisoldipine was fetotoxic but not teratogenic in rats and rabbits at doses resulting in maternal toxicity (reduced maternal body weight gain). In pregnant rats, increased fetal resorption (postimplantation loss) was observed at 100 mg/kg/day and decreased fetal weight was observed at both 30 and 100 mg/kg/day. These doses are, respectively, about 5 and 16 times the MRHD when compared on a mg/m2 basis. In pregnant rabbits, decreased fetal and placental weights were observed at a dose of 30 mg/kg/day, about 10 times the MRHD when compared on a mg/m2 basis. In a study in which pregnant monkeys (both treated and control) had high rates of abortion and mortality, the only surviving fetus from a group exposed to a maternal dose of 100 mg nisoldipine/kg/day (about 30 times the MRHD when compared on a mg/m2 basis) presented with forelimb and vertebral abnormalities not previously seen in control monkeys of the same strain. There are no adequate and well controlled studies in pregnant women. SULAR should be used in pregnancy only if the potential benefit justifies the potential risk to the fetus.          It is not known whether nisoldipine is excreted in human milk. Because many drugs are excreted in human milk, a decision should be made to discontinue nursing, or to discontinue SULAR, taking into account the importance of the drug to the mother.          Safety and effectiveness in pediatric patients have not been established.          Clinical studies of nisoldipine did not include sufficient numbers of subjects aged 65 and over to determine whether they respond differently from younger subjects. Other reported clinical experience has not identified differences in responses between the elderly and younger patients. Patients over 65 are expected to develop higher plasma concentrations of nisoldipine. In general, dose selection for an elderly patient should be cautious, usually starting at the low end of the dosing range, reflecting the greater frequency of decreased hepatic, renal or cardiac function, and of concomitant disease or other drug therapy.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS SECTION" id="34071-1">
Rarely, patients, particularly those with severe obstructive coronary artery disease, have developed increased frequency, duration and/or severity of angina, or acute myocardial infarction on starting calcium channel blocker therapy or at the time of dosage increase. The mechanism of this effect has not been established. In controlled studies of SULAR in patients with angina this was seen about 1.5% of the time in patients given nisoldipine, compared with 0.9% in patients given placebo.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Nisoldipine is a member of the dihydropyridine class of calcium channel antagonists (calcium ion antagonists or slow channel blockers) that inhibit the transmembrane influx of calcium into vascular smooth muscle and cardiac muscle. It reversibly competes with other dihydropyridines for binding to the calcium channel. Because the contractile process of vascular smooth muscle is dependent upon the movement of extracellular calcium into the muscle through specific ion channels, inhibition of the calcium channel results in dilation of the arterioles. In vitro studies show that the effects of nisoldipine on contractile processes are selective, with greater potency on vascular smooth muscle than on cardiac muscle. Although, like other dihydropyridine calcium channel blockers, nisoldipine has negative inotropic effects in vitro, studies conducted in intact anesthetized animals have shown that the vasodilating effect occurs at doses lower than those that affect cardiac contractility. The effect of nisoldipine on blood pressure is principally a consequence of a dose-related decrease of peripheral vascular resistance. While nisoldipine, like other dihydropyridines, exhibits a mild diuretic effect, most of the antihypertensive activity is attributed to its effect on peripheral vascular resistance.          Nisoldipine pharmacokinetics are independent of the dose across the clicinal dosage range of 17 to 51 mg, with plasma concentrations proportional to dose. Nisoldipine accumulation, during multiple dosing, is predictable from a single dose. Nisoldipine is relatively well absorbed into the systemic circulation with 87% of the radiolabeled drug recovered in urine and feces. The absolute bioavailability of nisoldipine is about 5%. Nisoldipine's low bioavailability is due, in part, to pre-systemic metabolism in the gut wall, and this metabolism decreases from the proximal to the distal parts of the intestine. A pronounced food-effect is observed when SULAR is administered with a high-fat meal resulting in an increased peak concentration (Cmax) of up to 245%. Total exposure (AUC) is decreased by 25%. As a result, SULAR should be taken on an empty stomach (1 hour before or 2 hours after a meal). Maximal plasma concentrations of nisoldipine are reached at 9.2 ± 5.1 hours. The terminal elimination half-life (reflecting post absorption clearance of nisoldipine) ranges from 13.7 ± 4.3 hours. After oral administration, the concentration of (+)-nisoldipine, the active enantiomer, is about 6 times higher than the inactive (-) -nisoldipine enantiomer. The plasma protein binding of nisoldipine is very high, with less than 1% unbound over the plasma concentration range of 100 ng/mL to 10 mcg/mL. Nisoldipine is highly metabolized; 5 major urinary metabolites have been identified. Although 60 - 80% of an oral dose undergoes urinary excretion, only traces of unchanged nisoldipine are found in urine. The major biotransformation pathway appears to be the hydroxylation of the isobutyl ester. A hydroxylated derivative of the side chain, present in plasma at concentrations approximately equal to the parent compound, appears to be the only active metabolite, and has about 10% of the activity of the parent compound. Cytochrome P450 enzymes are believed to play a major role in the metabolism of nisoldipine. The particular isoenzyme system responsible for its metabolism has not been identified, but other dihydropyridines are metabolized by cytochrome P450 IIIA4. Nisoldipine should not be administered with grapefruit juice, as this has been shown, in a study of 12 subjects, to interfere with nisoldipine metabolism, resulting in a mean increase in Cmax of about 3-fold (ranging up to about 7-fold) and AUC of almost 2-fold (ranging up to about 5-fold). A similar phenomenon has been seen with several other dihydropyridine calcium channel blockers.           Renal Dysfunction  Because renal elimination is not an important pathway, bioavailability and pharmacokinetics of SULAR were not significantly different in patients with various degrees of renal impairment. Dosing adjustments in patients with mild to moderate renal impairment are not necessary.  Geriatric  Elderly patients have been found to have 2 to 3 fold higher plasma concentrations (Cmax and AUC) than young subjects. This should be reflected in more cautious dosing (See  DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION ).  Hepatic Insufficiency  In patients with liver cirrhosis given a dose bioequivalent to 8.5 mg SULAR, plasma concentrations of the parent compound were 4 to 5 times higher than those in healthy young subjects. Lower starting and maintenance doses should be used in cirrhotic patients (See  DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION ).  Gender and Race  The effect of gender or race on the pharmacokinetics of nisoldipine has not been investigated.  Disease States  Hypertension does not significantly alter the pharmacokinetics of nisoldipine.           Hemodynamic Effects  Administration of a single dose of nisoldipine leads to decreased systemic vascular resistance and blood pressure with a transient increase in heart rate. The change in heart rate is greater with immediate release nisoldipine preparations. The effect on blood pressure is directly related to the initial degree of elevation above normal. Chronic administration of nisoldipine results in a sustained decrease in vascular resistance and small increases in stroke index and left ventricular ejection fraction. A study of the immediate release formulation showed no effect of nisoldipine on the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system or on plasma norepinephrine concentration in normals. Changes in blood pressure in hypertensive patients given SULAR were dose related over the clinical dosage range. Nisoldipine does not appear to have significant negative inotropic activity in intact animals or humans, and did not lead to worsening of clinical heart failure in three small studies of patients with asymptomatic and symptomatic left ventricular dysfunction. There is little information, however, in patients with severe congestive heart failure, and all calcium channel blockers should be used with caution in any patient with heart failure.  Electrophysiologic Effects  Nisoldipine has no clinically important chronotropic effects. Except for mild shortening of sinus cycle, SA conduction time and AH intervals, single oral doses up to 20 mg of immediate release nisoldipine did not significantly change other conduction parameters. Similar electrophysiologic effects were seen with single IV doses, which could be blunted in patients pre-treated with beta-blockers. Dose and plasma level related flattening or inversion of T-waves have been observed in a few small studies. Such reports were concentrated in patients receiving rapidly increased high doses in one study; the phenomenon has not been a cause of safety concern in large clinical trials.          The antihypertensive efficacy of SULAR was studied in 5 double-blind, placebo-controlled, randomized studies, in which over 600 patients were treated with SULAR as monotherapy and about 300 with placebo; 4 of the five studies compared 2 or 3 fixed doses while the fifth allowed titration from doses bioequivalent to 8.5 - 34 mg. Once daily administration of SULAR produced sustained reductions in systolic and diastolic blood pressures over the 24 hour dosing interval in both supine and standing positions. The mean placebo-subtracted reductions in supine systolic and diastolic blood pressure at trough, 24 hours post-dose, in these studies, are shown below. Changes in standing blood pressure were similar: MEAN SUPINE TROUGH SYSTOLIC AND DIASTOLIC BLOOD PRESSURE CHANGES (mm Hg)           SULAR     Doses bioequivalent to:   (mg/day)   8.5 mg   17   mg   25.5 mg   34   mg   8.5-34   mg   titrated     Systolic  8  11  11  14 15    Diastolic  3  5  7  7 8    In patients receiving atenolol, supine blood pressure reductions with SULAR doses bioequivalent to 17 and 34 mg once daily were 12/6 and 19/8 mm Hg, respectively. The sustained antihypertensive effect of SULAR was demonstrated by 24 hour blood pressure monitoring and examination of peak and trough effects. The trough/peak ratios ranged from 70 to 100% for diastolic and systolic blood pressure. The mean change in heart rate in these studies was less than one beat per minute. In 4 of the 5 studies, patients received intial doses bioequivalent to 17-25.5 mg SULAR without incident (excessive effects on blood pressure or heart rate). The fifth study started patients on lower doses of SULAR. Patient race and gender did not influence the blood pressure lowering effect of SULAR. Despite the higher plasma concentration of nisoldipine in the elderly, there was no consistent difference in their blood pressure response except that the lowest clinical dose was somewhat more effective than in non-elderly patients. No postural effect on blood pressure was apparent and there was no evidence of tolerance to the antihypertensive effect of SULAR in patients treated for up to one year.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="7439" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>SULAR is contraindicated in patients with known hypersensitivity to dihydropyridine calcium channel blockers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7440" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The dosage of SULAR must be adjusted to each patient's needs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7441" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Therapy usually should be initiated with 17 mg orally once daily, then increased by 8.5 mg per week or longer intervals, to attain adequate control of blood pressure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7442" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Usual maintenance dosage is 17 to 34 mg once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7443" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Blood pressure response increases over the 8.5 - 34 mg daily dose range but adverse event rates also increase.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7444" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Doses beyond 34 mg once daily are not recommended.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7445" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>SULAR has been used safely with diuretics, ACE inhibitors, and beta-blocking agents.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7446" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Patients over age 65, or patients with impaired liver function are expected to develop higher plasma concentrations of nisoldipine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7447" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Their blood pressure should be monitored closely during any dosage adjustment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7448" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>A starting dose not exceeding 8.5 mg daily is recommended in these patient groups.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7449" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>SULAR tablets should be administered orally once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7450" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>SULAR should be taken on an empty stomach (1 hour before or 2 hours after a meal).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7451" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Grapefruit products should be avoided before and after dosing.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M1" type="Trigger" span="20 17" str="should be avoided"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="0 19" str="Grapefruit products" code="O82C39RR8C"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M1" precipitant="M2"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7452" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>SULAR is an extended release dosage form and tablets should be swallowed whole, not bitten, divided or crushed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7453" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>A 30 to 45% increase in AUC and Cmax of nisoldipine was observed with concomitant administration of cimetidine 400 mg twice daily.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M3" type="Trigger" span="12 8;32 4" str="increase | Cmax"/>
<Mention id="M6" type="Precipitant" span="100 10" str="cimetidine" code="80061L1WGD"/>
<Mention id="M5" type="Trigger" span="12 15" str="increase in AUC"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M3" precipitant="M6" effect="C54602"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M5" precipitant="M6" effect="C54605"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7454" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Ranitidine 150 mg twice daily did not interact significantly with nisoldipine (AUC was decreased by 15 - 20%).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M7" type="Trigger" span="79 17" str="AUC was decreased"/>
<Mention id="M8" type="Precipitant" span="0 10" str="Ranitidine" code="884KT10YB7"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M7" precipitant="M8" effect="C54609"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7455" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>No pharmacodynamic effects of either histamine H2 receptor antagonist were observed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7456" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>SULAR is substrate of CYP3A4 and coadministration of SULAR with any known inducer or inhibitor of CYP3A4 should be avoided in general.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M13" type="Trigger" span="105 17" str="should be avoided"/>
<Mention id="M10" type="Precipitant" span="74 7;19 9" str="inducer | of CYP3A4" code="N0000185506"/>
<Mention id="M12" type="Precipitant" span="74 30" str="inducer or inhibitor of CYP3A4" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M14" type="Precipitant" span="85 19" str="inhibitor of CYP3A4" code="N0000182141"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M13" precipitant="M10"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M13" precipitant="M12"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M13" precipitant="M14"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7457" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Coadministration of phenytoin with a dose bioequivalent to 34 mg SULAR tablets in epileptic patients lowered the nisoldipine plasma concentrations to undetectable levels.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M15" type="Trigger" span="101 7;125 21" str="lowered | plasma concentrations"/>
<Mention id="M16" type="Precipitant" span="20 9" str="phenytoin" code="6158TKW0C5"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M15" precipitant="M16" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7458" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Coadministration of SULAR with phenytoin should be avoided and alternative antihypertensive therapy should be considered.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M17" type="Trigger" span="41 17" str="should be avoided "/>
<Mention id="M18" type="Trigger" span="63 11;100 20" str=" alternative | should be considered"/>
<Mention id="M19" type="Precipitant" span="31 9" str="phenytoin" code="6158TKW0C5"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M17;M18" precipitant="M19"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7459" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Pharmacokinetic interactions between nisoldipine and beta-blockers (atenolol, propranolol) were variable and not significant.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7460" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Propranolol attenuated the heart rate increase following administration of immediate release nisoldipine.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M20" type="Trigger" span="12 10" str="attenuated"/>
<Mention id="M21" type="Precipitant" span="0 11" str="Propranolol" code="9Y8NXQ24VQ"/>
<Mention id="M22" type="SpecificInteraction" span="12 34" str="attenuated the heart rate increase" code="3424008: Tachycardia (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M20" precipitant="M21" effect="M22"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7461" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The blood pressure effect of SULAR tended to be greater in patients on atenolol than in patients on no other antihypertensive therapy.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M23" type="Trigger" span="19 6;48 7" str="effect | greater"/>
<Mention id="M24" type="Precipitant" span="71 8" str="atenolol" code="50VV3VW0TI"/>
<Mention id="M25" type="SpecificInteraction" span="4 21;48 7" str="blood pressure effect | greater" code="38936003: Abnormal blood pressure (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M23" precipitant="M24" effect="M25"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7462" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Quinidine at 648 mg bid decreased the bioavailability (AUC) of nisoldipine by 26%, but not the peak concentration.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M26" type="Trigger" span="24 29" str="decreased the bioavailability"/>
<Mention id="M29" type="Precipitant" span="0 9" str="Quinidine" code="ITX08688JL"/>
<Mention id="M28" type="Trigger" span="24 9;55 3" str="decreased | AUC"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M26" precipitant="M29" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M28" precipitant="M29" effect="C54609"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7463" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Immediate release nisoldipine increased plasma quinidine concentrations by about 20%.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M30" type="Trigger" span="30 16;57 14" str="increased plasma | concentrations"/>
<Mention id="M31" type="Precipitant" span="47 9" str="quinidine" code="ITX08688JL"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M30" precipitant="M31" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7464" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>This interaction was not accompanied by ECG changes and its clinical significance is not known.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7465" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>No significant interactions were found between nisoldipine and warfarin of digoxin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7466" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because nisoldipine, like other vasodilators, decreases peripheral vascular resistance, careful monitoring of blood pressure during the initial administration and titration of SULAR is recommended.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7467" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Close observation is especially important for patients already taking medications that are known to lower blood pressure.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M32" type="Trigger" span="0 17" str="Close observation"/>
<Mention id="M33" type="Precipitant" span="70 50" str="medications that are known to lower blood pressure" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M32" precipitant="M33"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7468" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Although in most patients the hypotensive effect of SULAR is modest and well tolerated, occasional patients have had excessive and poorly tolerated hypotension.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7469" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>These responses have usually occurred during initial titration or at the time of subsequent upward dosage adjustment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7470" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Although acute hemodynamic studies of nisoldipine in patients with NYHA Class II-IV heart failure have not demonstrated negative inotropic effects, safety of SULAR in patients with heart failure has not been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7471" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Caution therefore should be exercised when using SULAR in patients with heart failure or compromised ventricular function, particularly in combination with a beta-blocker.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M34" type="Trigger" span="0 7" str="Caution"/>
<Mention id="M35" type="Precipitant" span="158 12" str="beta-blocker" code="N0000175556"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M34" precipitant="M35"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7472" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because nisoldipine is extensively metabolized by the liver and, in patients with cirrhosis, it reaches blood concentrations about 5 times those in normals, SULAR should be administered cautiously in patients with severe hepatic dysfunction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7473" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>SULAR is an extended release tablet and should be swallowed whole.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7474" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Tablets should not be chewed, divided or crushed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7475" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Grapefruit juice, which has been shown to increase significantly the bioavailability of nisoldipine and other dihydropyridine type calcium channel blockers, should not be taken with SULAR.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M36" type="Trigger" span="42 8;69 15" str="increase | bioavailability"/>
<Mention id="M37" type="Precipitant" span="0 16" str="Grapefruit juice" code="JQ9EK2H6BG"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M36" precipitant="M37" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7476" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>5 (tartrazine) which may cause allergic-type reactions (including bronchial asthma) in certain susceptible persons.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7477" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Although the overall incidence of FD&amp;C Yellow No.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7478" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>5 (tartrazine) sensitivity in the general population is low, it is frequently seen in patients who also have aspirin hypersensitivity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7479" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>SULAR is not known to interfere with the interpretation of laboratory tests.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7480" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Dietary administration of nisoldipine to male and female rats for up to 24 months (mean doses up to 82 and 111 mg/kg/day, 16 and 19 times the maximum recommended human dose [MRHD] on a mg/m2 basis, respectively and female mice for up to 21 months (mean doses of up to 217 mg/kg/day, 20 times the MRHD on a mg/m2 basis) revealed no evidence of tumorigenic effect of nisoldipine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7481" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In male mice receiving a mean dose of 163 mg nisoldipine/kg/day (16 times the MRHD of 60 mg/day on a mg/m2 basis), an increased frequency of stomach papilloma, but still within the historical range, was observed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7482" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>No evidence of stomach neoplasia was observed at lower doses (up to 58 mg/kg/day).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7483" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Nisoldipine was negative when tested in a battery of genotoxicity assays including the Ames test and the CHO/HGRPT assay for mutagenicity and the in vivo mouse micronucleus test and in vitro CHO cell test for clastogenicity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7484" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>When administered to male and female rats at doses of up to 30 mg/kg/day (about 5 times the MRHD on a mg/m2 basis) nisoldipine had no effect on fertility.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7485" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Nisoldipine was neither teratogenic nor fetotoxic at doses that were not maternally toxic.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7486" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Nisoldipine was fetotoxic but not teratogenic in rats and rabbits at doses resulting in maternal toxicity (reduced maternal body weight gain).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7487" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In pregnant rats, increased fetal resorption (postimplantation loss) was observed at 100 mg/kg/day and decreased fetal weight was observed at both 30 and 100 mg/kg/day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7488" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>These doses are, respectively, about 5 and 16 times the MRHD when compared on a mg/m2 basis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7489" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In pregnant rabbits, decreased fetal and placental weights were observed at a dose of 30 mg/kg/day, about 10 times the MRHD when compared on a mg/m2 basis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7490" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In a study in which pregnant monkeys (both treated and control) had high rates of abortion and mortality, the only surviving fetus from a group exposed to a maternal dose of 100 mg nisoldipine/kg/day (about 30 times the MRHD when compared on a mg/m2 basis) presented with forelimb and vertebral abnormalities not previously seen in control monkeys of the same strain.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7491" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>There are no adequate and well controlled studies in pregnant women.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7492" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>SULAR should be used in pregnancy only if the potential benefit justifies the potential risk to the fetus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7493" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>It is not known whether nisoldipine is excreted in human milk.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7494" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because many drugs are excreted in human milk, a decision should be made to discontinue nursing, or to discontinue SULAR, taking into account the importance of the drug to the mother.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7495" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Safety and effectiveness in pediatric patients have not been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7496" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Clinical studies of nisoldipine did not include sufficient numbers of subjects aged 65 and over to determine whether they respond differently from younger subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7497" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Other reported clinical experience has not identified differences in responses between the elderly and younger patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7498" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Patients over 65 are expected to develop higher plasma concentrations of nisoldipine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7499" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In general, dose selection for an elderly patient should be cautious, usually starting at the low end of the dosing range, reflecting the greater frequency of decreased hepatic, renal or cardiac function, and of concomitant disease or other drug therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7500" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Increased angina and/or myocardial infarction in patients with coronary artery disease: Rarely, patients, particularly those with severe obstructive coronary artery disease, have developed increased frequency, duration and/or severity of angina, or acute myocardial infarction on starting calcium channel blocker therapy or at the time of dosage increase.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7501" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The mechanism of this effect has not been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7502" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>In controlled studies of SULAR in patients with angina this was seen about 1.5% of the time in patients given nisoldipine, compared with 0.9% in patients given placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7503" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Nisoldipine is a member of the dihydropyridine class of calcium channel antagonists (calcium ion antagonists or slow channel blockers) that inhibit the transmembrane influx of calcium into vascular smooth muscle and cardiac muscle.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7504" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>It reversibly competes with other dihydropyridines for binding to the calcium channel.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7505" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Because the contractile process of vascular smooth muscle is dependent upon the movement of extracellular calcium into the muscle through specific ion channels, inhibition of the calcium channel results in dilation of the arterioles.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7506" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In vitro studies show that the effects of nisoldipine on contractile processes are selective, with greater potency on vascular smooth muscle than on cardiac muscle.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7507" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Although, like other dihydropyridine calcium channel blockers, nisoldipine has negative inotropic effects in vitro, studies conducted in intact anesthetized animals have shown that the vasodilating effect occurs at doses lower than those that affect cardiac contractility.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7508" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The effect of nisoldipine on blood pressure is principally a consequence of a dose-related decrease of peripheral vascular resistance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7509" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>While nisoldipine, like other dihydropyridines, exhibits a mild diuretic effect, most of the antihypertensive activity is attributed to its effect on peripheral vascular resistance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7510" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Nisoldipine pharmacokinetics are independent of the dose across the clinical dosage range of 17 to 51 mg, with plasma concentrations proportional to dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7511" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Nisoldipine accumulation, during multiple dosing, is predictable from a single dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7512" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Nisoldipine is relatively well absorbed into the systemic circulation with 87% of the radiolabeled drug recovered in urine and feces.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7513" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The absolute bioavailability of nisoldipine is about 5%.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7514" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Nisoldipine's low bioavailability is due, in part, to pre-systemic metabolism in the gut wall, and this metabolism decreases from the proximal to the distal parts of the intestine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7515" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A pronounced food-effect is observed when SULAR is administered with a high-fat meal resulting in an increased peak concentration (Cmax) of up to 245%.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M38" type="Trigger" span="101 28" str="increased peak concentration "/>
<Mention id="M39" type="Trigger" span="101 9;131 4" str=" increased | Cmax"/>
<Mention id="M40" type="Precipitant" span="71 13" str="high-fat meal" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M38;M39" precipitant="M40" effect="C54602"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7516" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Total exposure (AUC) is decreased by 25%.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7517" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>As a result, SULAR should be taken on an empty stomach (1 hour before or 2 hours after a meal).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M41" type="Trigger" span="19 15;56 30" str="should be taken | 1 hour before or 2 hours after"/>
<Mention id="M42" type="Precipitant" span="89 4" str="meal" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M41" precipitant="M42"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7518" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Maximal plasma concentrations of nisoldipine are reached at 9.2 ± 5.1 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7519" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The terminal elimination half-life (reflecting post absorption clearance of nisoldipine) ranges from 13.7 ± 4.3 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7520" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>After oral administration, the concentration of (+)-nisoldipine, the active enantiomer, is about 6 times higher than the inactive (-) -nisoldipine enantiomer.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7521" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The plasma protein binding of nisoldipine is very high, with less than 1% unbound over the plasma concentration range of 100 ng/mL to 10 mcg/mL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7522" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Nisoldipine is highly metabolized; 5 major urinary metabolites have been identified.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7523" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Although 60 - 80% of an oral dose undergoes urinary excretion, only traces of unchanged nisoldipine are found in urine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7524" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The major biotransformation pathway appears to be the hydroxylation of the isobutyl ester.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7525" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A hydroxylated derivative of the side chain, present in plasma at concentrations approximately equal to the parent compound, appears to be the only active metabolite, and has about 10% of the activity of the parent compound.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7526" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Cytochrome P450 enzymes are believed to play a major role in the metabolism of nisoldipine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7527" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The particular isoenzyme system responsible for its metabolism has not been identified, but other dihydropyridines are metabolized by cytochrome P450 IIIA4.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7528" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Nisoldipine should not be administered with grapefruit juice, as this has been shown, in a study of 12 subjects, to interfere with nisoldipine metabolism, resulting in a mean increase in Cmax of about 3-fold (ranging up to about 7-fold) and AUC of almost 2-fold (ranging up to about 5-fold).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M43" type="Trigger" span="175 16" str="increase in Cmax"/>
<Mention id="M46" type="Precipitant" span="44 16" str="grapefruit juice" code="JQ9EK2H6BG"/>
<Mention id="M45" type="Trigger" span="175 8;241 3" str="increase | AUC"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M43" precipitant="M46" effect="C54602"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M45" precipitant="M46" effect="C54605"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7529" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A similar phenomenon has been seen with several other dihydropyridine calcium channel blockers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7530" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Because renal elimination is not an important pathway, bioavailability and pharmacokinetics of SULAR were not significantly different in patients with various degrees of renal impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7531" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Dosing adjustments in patients with mild to moderate renal impairment are not necessary.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7532" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Elderly patients have been found to have 2 to 3 fold higher plasma concentrations (Cmax and AUC) than young subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7533" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This should be reflected in more cautious dosing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7534" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In patients with liver cirrhosis given a dose bioequivalent to 8.5 mg SULAR, plasma concentrations of the parent compound were 4 to 5 times higher than those in healthy young subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7535" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Lower starting and maintenance doses should be used in cirrhotic patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7536" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The effect of gender or race on the pharmacokinetics of nisoldipine has not been investigated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7537" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Hypertension does not significantly alter the pharmacokinetics of nisoldipine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7538" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Administration of a single dose of nisoldipine leads to decreased systemic vascular resistance and blood pressure with a transient increase in heart rate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7539" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The change in heart rate is greater with immediate release nisoldipine preparations.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7540" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The effect on blood pressure is directly related to the initial degree of elevation above normal.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7541" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Chronic administration of nisoldipine results in a sustained decrease in vascular resistance and small increases in stroke index and left ventricular ejection fraction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7542" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A study of the immediate release formulation showed no effect of nisoldipine on the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system or on plasma norepinephrine concentration in normals.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7543" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Changes in blood pressure in hypertensive patients given SULAR were dose related over the clinical dosage range.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7544" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Nisoldipine does not appear to have significant negative inotropic activity in intact animals or humans, and did not lead to worsening of clinical heart failure in three small studies of patients with asymptomatic and symptomatic left ventricular dysfunction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7545" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There is little information, however, in patients with severe congestive heart failure, and all calcium channel blockers should be used with caution in any patient with heart failure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7546" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Nisoldipine has no clinically important chronotropic effects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7547" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Except for mild shortening of sinus cycle, SA conduction time and AH intervals, single oral doses up to 20 mg of immediate release nisoldipine did not significantly change other conduction parameters.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7548" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Similar electrophysiologic effects were seen with single IV doses, which could be blunted in patients pre-treated with beta-blockers.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M47" type="Trigger" span="27 7;82 7" str="effects | blunted"/>
<Mention id="M48" type="Precipitant" span="119 13" str="beta-blockers" code="N0000175556"/>
<Mention id="M49" type="SpecificInteraction" span="8 26;82 7" str="electrophysiologic effects | blunted" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M47" precipitant="M48" effect="M49"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7549" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Dose and plasma level related flattening or inversion of T-waves have been observed in a few small studies.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7550" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Such reports were concentrated in patients receiving rapidly increased high doses in one study; the phenomenon has not been a cause of safety concern in large clinical trials.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7551" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The antihypertensive efficacy of SULAR was studied in 5 double-blind, placebo-controlled, randomized studies, in which over 600 patients were treated with SULAR as monotherapy and about 300 with placebo; 4 of the five studies compared 2 or 3 fixed doses while the fifth allowed titration from doses bioequivalent to 8.5 - 34 mg. Once daily administration of SULAR produced sustained reductions in systolic and diastolic blood pressures over the 24 hour dosing interval in both supine and standing positions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7552" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mean placebo-subtracted reductions in supine systolic and diastolic blood pressure at trough, 24 hours post-dose, in these studies, are shown below.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7553" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Changes in standing blood pressure were similar: MEAN SUPINE TROUGH SYSTOLIC AND DIASTOLIC BLOOD PRESSURE CHANGES (mm Hg) SULAR Doses bioequivalent to: (mg/day) 8.5 mg 17 mg 25.5 mg 34 mg 8.5-34 mg titrated Systolic 8 11 11 14 15 Diastolic 3 5 7 7 8 In patients receiving atenolol, supine blood pressure reductions with SULAR doses bioequivalent to 17 and 34 mg once daily were 12/6 and 19/8 mm Hg, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7554" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The sustained antihypertensive effect of SULAR was demonstrated by 24 hour blood pressure monitoring and examination of peak and trough effects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7555" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The trough/peak ratios ranged from 70 to 100% for diastolic and systolic blood pressure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7556" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mean change in heart rate in these studies was less than one beat per minute.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7557" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In 4 of the 5 studies, patients received initial doses bioequivalent to 17-25.5 mg SULAR without incident (excessive effects on blood pressure or heart rate).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7558" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The fifth study started patients on lower doses of SULAR.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7559" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Patient race and gender did not influence the blood pressure lowering effect of SULAR.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7560" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Despite the higher plasma concentration of nisoldipine in the elderly, there was no consistent difference in their blood pressure response except that the lowest clinical dose was somewhat more effective than in non-elderly patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7561" LabelDrug="SULAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No postural effect on blood pressure was apparent and there was no evidence of tolerance to the antihypertensive effect of SULAR in patients treated for up to one year.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="grapefruit products" precipitantCode="O82C39RR8C"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cimetidine" precipitantCode="80061L1WGD" effect="C54602"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cimetidine" precipitantCode="80061L1WGD" effect="C54605"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="ranitidine" precipitantCode="884KT10YB7" effect="C54609"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="inducer | of cyp3a4" precipitantCode="N0000185506"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="inducer or inhibitor of cyp3a4" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="inhibitor of cyp3a4" precipitantCode="N0000182141"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="phenytoin" precipitantCode="6158TKW0C5" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="phenytoin" precipitantCode="6158TKW0C5"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="propranolol" precipitantCode="9Y8NXQ24VQ" effect="3424008: Tachycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="atenolol" precipitantCode="50VV3VW0TI" effect="38936003: Abnormal blood pressure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="quinidine" precipitantCode="ITX08688JL" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="quinidine" precipitantCode="ITX08688JL" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="quinidine" precipitantCode="ITX08688JL" effect="C54609"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="medications that are known to lower blood pressure" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="beta-blocker" precipitantCode="N0000175556"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="grapefruit juice" precipitantCode="JQ9EK2H6BG" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="grapefruit juice" precipitantCode="JQ9EK2H6BG" effect="C54602"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="grapefruit juice" precipitantCode="JQ9EK2H6BG" effect="C54605"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="high-fat meal" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54602"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="meal" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="beta-blockers" precipitantCode="N0000175556" effect="NO MAP"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>