<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="TENORMIN" setid="fcfc9676-4edc-460e-6199-8161b824908f">
<Text><Section name="Boxed Warning section" id="34066-1">
Cessation of Therapy with TENORMIN  Patients with coronary artery disease, who are being treated with TENORMIN, should be advised against abrupt discontinuation of therapy. Severe exacerbation of angina and the occurrence of myocardial infarction and ventricular arrhythmias have been reported in angina patients following the abrupt discontinuation of therapy with beta blockers. The last two complications may occur with or without preceding exacerbation of the angina pectoris. As with other beta blockers, when discontinuation of TENORMIN is planned, the patients should be carefully observed and advised to limit physical activity to a minimum. If the angina worsens or acute coronary insufficiency develops, it is recommended that TENORMIN be promptly reinstituted, at least temporarily. Because coronary artery disease is common and may be unrecognized, it may be prudent not to discontinue TENORMIN therapy abruptly even in patients treated only for hypertension. (See DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION.)</Section>
<Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
TENORMIN is contraindicated in sinus bradycardia, heart block greater than first degree, cardiogenic shock, and overt cardiac failure. (See WARNINGS.) TENORMIN is contraindicated in those patients with a history of hypersensitivity to the atenolol or any of the drug product’s components.</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
The initial dose of TENORMIN is 50 mg given as one tablet a day either alone or added to diuretic therapy. The full effect of this dose will usually be seen within one to two weeks. If an optimal response is not achieved, the dosage should be increased to TENORMIN 100 mg given as one tablet a day. Increasing the dosage beyond 100 mg a day is unlikely to produce any further benefit.  TENORMIN may be used alone or concomitantly with other antihypertensive agents including thiazide-type diuretics, hydralazine, prazosin, and alpha-methyldopa.          The initial dose of TENORMIN is 50 mg given as one tablet a day. If an optimal response is not achieved within one week, the dosage should be increased to TENORMIN 100 mg given as one tablet a day. Some patients may require a dosage of 200 mg once a day for optimal effect.  Twenty-four hour control with once daily dosing is achieved by giving doses larger than necessary to achieve an immediate maximum effect. The maximum early effect on exercise tolerance occurs with doses of 50 to 100 mg, but at these doses the effect at 24 hours is attenuated, averaging about 50% to 75% of that observed with once a day oral doses of 200 mg.          In patients with definite or suspected acute myocardial infarction, treatment with TENORMIN I.V. Injection should be initiated as soon as possible after the patient's arrival in the hospital and after eligibility is established. Such treatment should be initiated in a coronary care or similar unit immediately after the patient's hemodynamic condition has stabilized. Treatment should begin with the intravenous administration of 5 mg TENORMIN over 5 minutes followed by another 5 mg intravenous injection 10 minutes later. TENORMIN I.V. Injection should be administered under carefully controlled conditions including monitoring of blood pressure, heart rate, and electrocardiogram. Dilutions of TENORMIN I.V. Injection in Dextrose Injection USP, Sodium Chloride Injection USP, or Sodium Chloride and Dextrose Injection may be used. These admixtures are stable for 48 hours if they are not used immediately. In patients who tolerate the full intravenous dose (10 mg), TENORMIN Tablets 50 mg should be initiated 10 minutes after the last intravenous dose followed by another 50 mg oral dose 12 hours later. Thereafter, TENORMIN can be given orally either 100 mg once daily or 50 mg twice a day for a further 6-9 days or until discharge from the hospital. If bradycardia or hypotension requiring treatment or any other untoward effects occur, TENORMIN should be discontinued. (See full prescribing information prior to initiating therapy with TENORMIN Tablets.) Data from other beta blocker trials suggest that if there is any question concerning the use of IV beta blocker or clinical estimate that there is a contraindication, the IV beta blocker may be eliminated and patients fulfilling the safety criteria may be given TENORMIN Tablets 50 mg twice daily or 100 mg once a day for at least seven days (if the IV dosing is excluded).  Although the demonstration of efficacy of TENORMIN is based entirely on data from the first seven postinfarction days, data from other beta blocker trials suggest that treatment with beta blockers that are effective in the postinfarction setting may be continued for one to three years if there are no contraindications. TENORMIN is an additional treatment to standard coronary care unit therapy.          TENORMIN is excreted by the kidneys; consequently dosage should be adjusted in cases of severe impairment of renal function. In general, dose selection for an elderly patient should be cautious, usually starting at the low end of the dosing range, reflecting greater frequency of decreased hepatic, renal, or cardiac function, and of concomitant disease or other drug therapy. Evaluation of patients with hypertension or myocardial infarction should always include assessment of renal function. Atenolol excretion would be expected to decrease with advancing age. No significant accumulation of TENORMIN occurs until creatinine clearance falls below 35 mL/min/1.73m2. Accumulation of atenolol and prolongation of its half-life were studied in subjects with creatinine clearance between 5 and 105 mL/min. Peak plasma levels were significantly increased in subjects with creatinine clearances below 30 mL/min. The following maximum oral dosages are recommended for elderly, renally-impaired patients and for patients with renal impairment due to other causes:        Creatinine Clearance (mL/min/1.73m2)   Atenolol Elimination Half-Life (h)   Maximum Dosage     15-35   16-27   50 mg daily     &amp;lt;15   &amp;gt;27   25 mg daily     Some renally-impaired or elderly patients being treated for hypertension may require a lower starting dose of TENORMIN: 25 mg given as one tablet a day. If this 25 mg dose is used, assessment of efficacy must be made carefully. This should include measurement of blood pressure just prior to the next dose ("trough" blood pressure) to ensure that the treatment effect is present for a full 24 hours. Although a similar dosage reduction may be considered for elderly and/or renally-impaired patients being treated for indications other than hypertension, data are not available for these patient populations. Patients on hemodialysis should be given 25 mg or 50 mg after each dialysis; this should be done under hospital supervision as marked falls in blood pressure can occur.          If withdrawal of TENORMIN therapy is planned, it should be achieved gradually and patients should be carefully observed and advised to limit physical activity to a minimum.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
Catecholamine-depleting drugs (eg, reserpine) may have an additive effect when given with beta-blocking agents. Patients treated with TENORMIN plus a catecholamine depletor should therefore be closely observed for evidence of hypotension and/or marked bradycardia which may produce vertigo, syncope, or postural hypotension. Calcium channel blockers may also have an additive effect when given with TENORMIN (See WARNINGS). Disopyramide is a Type I antiarrhythmic drug with potent negative inotropic and chronotropic effects. Disopyramide has been associated with severe bradycardia, asystole and heart failure when administered with beta blockers. Amiodarone is an antiarrhythmic agent with negative chronotropic properties that may be additive to those seen with beta blockers. Beta blockers may exacerbate the rebound hypertension which can follow the withdrawal of clonidine. If the two drugs are coadministered, the beta blocker should be withdrawn several days before the gradual withdrawal of clonidine. If replacing clonidine by beta-blocker therapy, the introduction of beta blockers should be delayed for several days after clonidine administration has stopped. Concomitant use of prostaglandin synthase inhibiting drugs, eg, indomethacin, may decrease the hypotensive effects of beta blockers. Information on concurrent usage of atenolol and aspirin is limited. Data from several studies, ie, TIMI-II, ISIS-2, currently do not suggest any clinical interaction between aspirin and beta blockers in the acute myocardial infarction setting. While taking beta blockers, patients with a history of anaphylactic reaction to a variety of allergens may have a more severe reaction on repeated challenge, either accidental, diagnostic or therapeutic. Such patients may be unresponsive to the usual doses of epinephrine used to treat the allergic reaction. Both digitalis glycosides and beta-blockers slow atrioventricular conduction and decrease heart rate. Concomitant use can increase the risk of bradycardia.</Section>
<Section name="PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="42232-9">
Patients already on a beta blocker must be evaluated carefully before TENORMIN is administered. Initial and subsequent TENORMIN dosages can be adjusted downward depending on clinical observations including pulse and blood pressure. TENORMIN may aggravate peripheral arterial circulatory disorders.          The drug should be used with caution in patients with impaired renal function. (See DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION.)          Catecholamine-depleting drugs (eg, reserpine) may have an additive effect when given with beta-blocking agents. Patients treated with TENORMIN plus a catecholamine depletor should therefore be closely observed for evidence of hypotension and/or marked bradycardia which may produce vertigo, syncope, or postural hypotension. Calcium channel blockers may also have an additive effect when given with TENORMIN (See WARNINGS). Disopyramide is a Type I antiarrhythmic drug with potent negative inotropic and chronotropic effects. Disopyramide has been associated with severe bradycardia, asystole and heart failure when administered with beta blockers. Amiodarone is an antiarrhythmic agent with negative chronotropic properties that may be additive to those seen with beta blockers. Beta blockers may exacerbate the rebound hypertension which can follow the withdrawal of clonidine. If the two drugs are coadministered, the beta blocker should be withdrawn several days before the gradual withdrawal of clonidine. If replacing clonidine by beta-blocker therapy, the introduction of beta blockers should be delayed for several days after clonidine administration has stopped. Concomitant use of prostaglandin synthase inhibiting drugs, eg, indomethacin, may decrease the hypotensive effects of beta blockers. Information on concurrent usage of atenolol and aspirin is limited. Data from several studies, ie, TIMI-II, ISIS-2, currently do not suggest any clinical interaction between aspirin and beta blockers in the acute myocardial infarction setting. While taking beta blockers, patients with a history of anaphylactic reaction to a variety of allergens may have a more severe reaction on repeated challenge, either accidental, diagnostic or therapeutic. Such patients may be unresponsive to the usual doses of epinephrine used to treat the allergic reaction. Both digitalis glycosides and beta-blockers slow atrioventricular conduction and decrease heart rate. Concomitant use can increase the risk of bradycardia.          Two long-term (maximum dosing duration of 18 or 24 months) rat studies and one long-term (maximum dosing duration of 18 months) mouse study, each employing dose levels as high as 300 mg/kg/day or 150 times the maximum recommended human antihypertensive dose1 1) resulted in increased incidences of benign adrenal medullary tumors in males and females, mammary fibroadenomas in females, and anterior pituitary adenomas and thyroid parafollicular cell carcinomas in males. No evidence of a mutagenic potential of atenolol was uncovered in the dominant lethal test (mouse), in vivo cytogenetics test (Chinese hamster) or Ames test (S typhimurium). Fertility of male or female rats (evaluated at dose levels as high as 200 mg/kg/day or 100 times the maximum recommended human dose1) was unaffected by atenolol administration.          Chronic studies employing oral atenolol performed in animals have revealed the occurrence of vacuolation of epithelial cells of Brunner's glands in the duodenum of both male and female dogs at all tested dose levels of atenolol (starting at 15 mg/kg/day or 7.5 times the maximum recommended human antihypertensive dose1 1, respectively).               See WARNINGS - Pregnancy and Fetal Injury.            Atenolol is excreted in human breast milk at a ratio of 1.5 to 6.8 when compared to the concentration in plasma. Caution should be exercised when TENORMIN is administered to a nursing woman. Clinically significant bradycardia has been reported in breast-fed infants. Premature infants, or infants with impaired renal function, may be more likely to develop adverse effects. Neonates born to mothers who are receiving TENORMIN at parturition or breast-feeding may be at risk for hypoglycemia and bradycardia. Caution should be exercised when TENORMIN is administered during pregnancy or to a woman who is breast-feeding (See WARNINGS, Pregnancy and Fetal Injury).          Safety and effectiveness in pediatric patients have not been established.               Clinical studies of TENORMIN did not include sufficient number of patients aged 65 and over to determine whether they respond differently from younger subjects. Other reported clinical experience has not identified differences in responses between the elderly and younger patients. In general, dose selection for an elderly patient should be cautious, usually starting at the low end of the dosing range, reflecting the greater frequency of decreased hepatic, renal, or cardiac function, and of concomitant disease or other drug therapy.          Of the 8,037 patients with suspected acute myocardial infarction randomized to TENORMIN in the ISIS-1 trial (See CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY), 33% (2,644) were 65 years of age and older. It was not possible to identify significant differences in efficacy and safety between older and younger patients; however, elderly patients with systolic blood pressure &amp;lt; 120 mmHg seemed less likely to benefit (See INDICATIONS AND USAGE). In general, dose selection for an elderly patient should be cautious, usually starting at the low end of the dosing range, reflecting greater frequency of decreased hepatic, renal, or cardiac function, and of concomitant disease or other drug therapy. Evaluation of patients with hypertension or myocardial infarction should always include assessment of renal function.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS SECTION" id="34071-1">
Sympathetic stimulation is necessary in supporting circulatory function in congestive heart failure, and beta blockade carries the potential hazard of further depressing myocardial contractility and precipitating more severe failure.  In patients with acute myocardial infarction, cardiac failure which is not promptly and effectively controlled by 80 mg of intravenous furosemide or equivalent therapy is a contraindication to beta-blocker treatment.           Continued depression of the myocardium with beta-blocking agents over a period of time can, in some cases, lead to cardiac failure. At the first sign or symptom of impending cardiac failure, patients should be treated appropriately according to currently recommended guidelines, and the response observed closely. If cardiac failure continues despite adequate treatment, TENORMIN should be withdrawn. (See DOSAGE AND ADMNISTRATION)           Cessation of Therapy with TENORMIN  Patients with coronary artery disease, who are being treated with TENORMIN, should be advised against abrupt discontinuation of therapy. Severe exacerbation of angina and the occurrence of myocardial infarction and ventricular arrhythmias have been reported in angina patients following the abrupt discontinuation of therapy with beta blockers. The last two complications may occur with or without preceding exacerbation of the angina pectoris. As with other beta blockers, when discontinuation of TENORMIN is planned, the patients should be carefully observed and advised to limit physical activity to a minimum. If the angina worsens or acute coronary insufficiency develops, it is recommended that TENORMIN be promptly reinstituted, at least temporarily. Because coronary artery disease is common and may be unrecognized, it may be prudent not to discontinue TENORMIN therapy abruptly even in patients treated only for hypertension. (See DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION.)          Bradycardia and heart block can occur and the left ventricular end diastolic pressure can rise when beta-blockers are administered with verapamil or diltiazem. Patients with pre-existing conduction abnormalities or left ventricular dysfunction are particularly susceptible. (See  PRECAUTIONS .)           PATIENTS WITH BRONCHOSPASTIC DISEASE SHOULD, IN GENERAL, NOT RECEIVE BETA BLOCKERS. Because of its relative beta1 selectivity, however, TENORMIN may be used with caution in patients with bronchospastic disease who do not respond to, or cannot tolerate, other antihypertensive treatment. Since beta1 selectivity is not absolute, the lowest possible dose of TENORMIN should be used with therapy initiated at 50 mg and a beta2-stimulating agent (bronchodilator) should be made available. If dosage must be increased, dividing the dose should be considered in order to achieve lower peak blood levels.           Chronically administered beta-blocking therapy should not be routinely withdrawn prior to major surgery, however the impaired ability of the heart to respond to reflex adrenergic stimuli may augment the risks of general anesthesia and surgical procedures.          TENORMIN should be used with caution in diabetic patients if a beta-blocking agent is required. Beta blockers may mask tachycardia occurring with hypoglycemia, but other manifestations such as dizziness and sweating may not be significantly affected. At recommended doses TENORMIN does not potentiate insulin-induced hypoglycemia and, unlike nonselective beta blockers, does not delay recovery of blood glucose to normal levels.          Beta-adrenergic blockade may mask certain clinical signs (eg, tachycardia) of hyperthyroidism. Abrupt withdrawal of beta blockade might precipitate a thyroid storm; therefore, patients suspected of developing thyrotoxicosis from whom TENORMIN therapy is to be withdrawn should be monitored closely. (See DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION.)          TENORMIN should not be given to patients with untreated pheochromocytoma.          Atenolol can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. Atenolol crosses the placental barrier and appears in cord blood. Administration of atenolol, starting in the second trimester of pregnancy, has been associated with the birth of infants that are small for gestational age. No studies have been performed on the use of atenolol in the first trimester and the possibility of fetal injury cannot be excluded. If this drug is used during pregnancy, or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking this drug, the patient should be apprised of the potential hazard to the fetus. Neonates born to mothers who are receiving TENORMIN at parturition or breast-feeding may be at risk for hypoglycemia and bradycardia. Caution should be exercised when TENORMIN is administered during pregnancy or to a woman who is breast-feeding. (See PRECAUTIONS, Nursing Mothers.) Atenolol has been shown to produce a dose-related increase in embryo/fetal resorptions in rats at doses equal to or greater than 50 mg/kg/day or 25 or more times the maximum recommended human antihypertensive dose Based on the maximum dose of 100 mg/day in a 50 kg patient.. Although similar effects were not seen in rabbits, the compound was not evaluated in rabbits at doses above 25 mg/kg/day or 12.5 times the maximum recommended human antihypertensive dose1.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
TENORMIN is a beta1-selective (cardioselective) beta-adrenergic receptor blocking agent without membrane stabilizing or intrinsic sympathomimetic (partial agonist) activities. This preferential effect is not absolute, however, and at higher doses, TENORMIN inhibits beta2-adrenoreceptors, chiefly located in the bronchial and vascular musculature.        In man, absorption of an oral dose is rapid and consistent but incomplete. Approximately 50% of an oral dose is absorbed from the gastrointestinal tract, the remainder being excreted unchanged in the feces. Peak blood levels are reached between two (2) and four (4) hours after ingestion. Unlike propranolol or metoprolol, but like nadolol, TENORMIN undergoes little or no metabolism by the liver, and the absorbed portion is eliminated primarily by renal excretion. Over 85% of an intravenous dose is excreted in urine within 24 hours compared with approximately 50% for an oral dose. TENORMIN also differs from propranolol in that only a small amount (6%-16%) is bound to proteins in the plasma. This kinetic profile results in relatively consistent plasma drug levels with about a fourfold interpatient variation.  The elimination half-life of oral TENORMIN is approximately 6 to 7 hours, and there is no alteration of the kinetic profile of the drug by chronic administration. Following intravenous administration, peak plasma levels are reached within 5 minutes. Declines from peak levels are rapid (5- to 10-fold) during the first 7 hours; thereafter, plasma levels decay with a half-life similar to that of orally administered drug. Following oral doses of 50 mg or 100 mg, both beta-blocking and antihypertensive effects persist for at least 24 hours. When renal function is impaired, elimination of TENORMIN is closely related to the glomerular filtration rate; significant accumulation occurs when the creatinine clearance falls below 35 mL/min/1.73m2. (See DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION.)          In standard animal or human pharmacological tests, beta-adrenoreceptor blocking activity of TENORMIN has been demonstrated by: (1) reduction in resting and exercise heart rate and cardiac output, (2) reduction of systolic and diastolic blood pressure at rest and on exercise, (3) inhibition of isoproterenol induced tachycardia, and (4) reduction in reflex orthostatic tachycardia.  A significant beta-blocking effect of TENORMIN, as measured by reduction of exercise tachycardia, is apparent within one hour following oral administration of a single dose. This effect is maximal at about 2 to 4 hours, and persists for at least 24 hours. Maximum reduction in exercise tachycardia occurs within 5 minutes of an intravenous dose. For both orally and intravenously administered drug, the duration of action is dose related and also bears a linear relationship to the logarithm of plasma TENORMIN concentration. The effect on exercise tachycardia of a single 10 mg intravenous dose is largely dissipated by 12 hours, whereas beta-blocking activity of single oral doses of 50 mg and 100 mg is still evident beyond 24 hours following administration. However, as has been shown for all beta-blocking agents, the antihypertensive effect does not appear to be related to plasma level.  In normal subjects, the beta1 selectivity of TENORMIN has been shown by its reduced ability to reverse the beta2-mediated vasodilating effect of isoproterenol as compared to equivalent beta-blocking doses of propranolol. In asthmatic patients, a dose of TENORMIN producing a greater effect on resting heart rate than propranolol resulted in much less increase in airway resistance. In a placebo controlled comparison of approximately equipotent oral doses of several beta blockers, TENORMIN produced a significantly smaller decrease of FEV1 than nonselective beta blockers such as propranolol and, unlike those agents, did not inhibit bronchodilation in response to isoproterenol.  Consistent with its negative chronotropic effect due to beta blockade of the SA node, TENORMIN increases sinus cycle length and sinus node recovery time. Conduction in the AV node is also prolonged. TENORMIN is devoid of membrane stabilizing activity, and increasing the dose well beyond that producing beta blockade does not further depress myocardial contractility. Several studies have demonstrated a moderate (approximately 10%) increase in stroke volume at rest and during exercise.  In controlled clinical trials, TENORMIN, given as a single daily oral dose, was an effective antihypertensive agent providing 24-hour reduction of blood pressure. TENORMIN has been studied in combination with thiazide-type diuretics, and the blood pressure effects of the combination are approximately additive. TENORMIN is also compatible with methyldopa, hydralazine, and prazosin, each combination resulting in a larger fall in blood pressure than with the single agents. The dose range of TENORMIN is narrow and increasing the dose beyond 100 mg once daily is not associated with increased antihypertensive effect. The mechanisms of the antihypertensive effects of beta-blocking agents have not been established. Several possible mechanisms have been proposed and include: (1) competitive antagonism of catecholamines at peripheral (especially cardiac) adrenergic neuron sites, leading to decreased cardiac output, (2) a central effect leading to reduced sympathetic outflow to the periphery, and (3) suppression of renin activity. The results from long-term studies have not shown any diminution of the antihypertensive efficacy of TENORMIN with prolonged use. By blocking the positive chronotropic and inotropic effects of catecholamines and by decreasing blood pressure, atenolol generally reduces the oxygen requirements of the heart at any given level of effort, making it useful for many patients in the long-term management of angina pectoris. On the other hand, atenolol can increase oxygen requirements by increasing left ventricular fiber length and end diastolic pressure, particularly in patients with heart failure. In a multicenter clinical trial (ISIS-1) conducted in 16,027 patients with suspected myocardial infarction, patients presenting within 12 hours (mean = 5 hours) after the onset of pain were randomized to either conventional therapy plus TENORMIN (n = 8,037), or conventional therapy alone (n = 7,990). Patients with a heart rate of &amp;lt; 50 bpm or systolic blood pressure &amp;lt; 100 mm Hg, or with other contraindications to beta blockade were excluded. Thirty-eight percent of each group were treated within 4 hours of onset of pain. The mean time from onset of pain to entry was 5.0 ± 2.7 hours in both groups. Patients in the TENORMIN group were to receive TENORMIN I.V. Injection 5-10 mg given over 5 minutes plus TENORMIN Tablets 50 mg every 12 hours orally on the first study day (the first oral dose administered about 15 minutes after the IV dose) followed by either TENORMIN Tablets 100 mg once daily or TENORMIN Tablets 50 mg twice daily on days 2-7. The groups were similar in demographic and medical history characteristics and in electrocardiographic evidence of myocardial infarction, bundle branch block, and first degree atrioventricular block at entry. During the treatment period (days 0-7), the vascular mortality rates were 3.89% in the TENORMIN group (313 deaths) and 4.57% in the control group (365 deaths). This absolute difference in rates, 0.68%, is statistically significant at the P &amp;lt; 0.05 level. The absolute difference translates into a proportional reduction of 15% (3.89-4.57/4.57 = -0.15). The 95% confidence limits are 1%-27%. Most of the difference was attributed to mortality in days 0-1 (TENORMIN - 121 deaths; control - 171 deaths). Despite the large size of the ISIS-1 trial, it is not possible to identify clearly subgroups of patients most likely or least likely to benefit from early treatment with atenolol. Good clinical judgment suggests, however, that patients who are dependent on sympathetic stimulation for maintenance of adequate cardiac output and blood pressure are not good candidates for beta blockade. Indeed, the trial protocol reflected that judgment by excluding patients with blood pressure consistently below 100 mm Hg systolic. The overall results of the study are compatible with the possibility that patients with borderline blood pressure (less than 120 mm Hg systolic), especially if over 60 years of age, are less likely to benefit. The mechanism through which atenolol improves survival in patients with definite or suspected acute myocardial infarction is unknown, as is the case for other beta blockers in the postinfarction setting. Atenolol, in addition to its effects on survival, has shown other clinical benefits including reduced frequency of ventricular premature beats, reduced chest pain, and reduced enzyme elevation.        In general, elderly patients present higher atenolol plasma levels with total clearance values about 50% lower than younger subjects. The half-life is markedly longer in the elderly compared to younger subjects. The reduction in atenolol clearance follows the general trend that the elimination of renally excreted drugs is decreased with increasing age.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="2242" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Cessation of Therapy with TENORMIN Patients with coronary artery disease, who are being treated with TENORMIN, should be advised against abrupt discontinuation of therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2243" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Severe exacerbation of angina and the occurrence of myocardial infarction and ventricular arrhythmias have been reported in angina patients following the abrupt discontinuation of therapy with beta blockers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2244" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>The last two complications may occur with or without preceding exacerbation of the angina pectoris.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2245" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>As with other beta blockers, when discontinuation of TENORMIN is planned, the patients should be carefully observed and advised to limit physical activity to a minimum.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2246" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>If the angina worsens or acute coronary insufficiency develops, it is recommended that TENORMIN be promptly reinstituted, at least temporarily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2247" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Because coronary artery disease is common and may be unrecognized, it may be prudent not to discontinue TENORMIN therapy abruptly even in patients treated only for hypertension.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2248" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>TENORMIN is contraindicated in sinus bradycardia, heart block greater than first degree, cardiogenic shock, and overt cardiac failure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2249" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>TENORMIN is contraindicated in those patients with a history of hypersensitivity to the atenolol or any of the drug product’s components.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2250" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The initial dose of TENORMIN is 50 mg given as one tablet a day either alone or added to diuretic therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2251" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The full effect of this dose will usually be seen within one to two weeks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2252" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If an optimal response is not achieved, the dosage should be increased to TENORMIN 100 mg given as one tablet a day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2253" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Increasing the dosage beyond 100 mg a day is unlikely to produce any further benefit.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2254" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>TENORMIN may be used alone or concomitantly with other antihypertensive agents including thiazide-type diuretics, hydralazine, prazosin, and alpha-methyldopa.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2255" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The initial dose of TENORMIN is 50 mg given as one tablet a day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2256" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If an optimal response is not achieved within one week, the dosage should be increased to TENORMIN 100 mg given as one tablet a day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2257" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Some patients may require a dosage of 200 mg once a day for optimal effect.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2258" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Twenty-four hour control with once daily dosing is achieved by giving doses larger than necessary to achieve an immediate maximum effect.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2259" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The maximum early effect on exercise tolerance occurs with doses of 50 to 100 mg, but at these doses the effect at 24 hours is attenuated, averaging about 50% to 75% of that observed with once a day oral doses of 200 mg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2260" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In patients with definite or suspected acute myocardial infarction, treatment with TENORMIN I.V.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2261" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Injection should be initiated as soon as possible after the patient's arrival in the hospital and after eligibility is established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2262" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Such treatment should be initiated in a coronary care or similar unit immediately after the patient's hemodynamic condition has stabilized.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2263" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Treatment should begin with the intravenous administration of 5 mg TENORMIN over 5minutes followed by another 5 mg intravenous injection 10 minutes later.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2264" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Injection should be administered under carefully controlled conditions including monitoring of blood pressure, heart rate, and electrocardiogram.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2265" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Injection in Dextrose Injection USP, Sodium Chloride Injection USP, or Sodium Chloride and Dextrose Injection may be used.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2266" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>These admixtures are stable for 48 hours if they are not used immediately.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2267" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In patients who tolerate the full intravenous dose (10 mg), TENORMIN Tablets 50 mg should be initiated 10 minutes after the last intravenous dose followed by another 50 mg oral dose 12 hours later.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2268" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Thereafter, TENORMIN can be given orally either 100 mg once daily or 50 mg twice a day for a further 6-9 days or until discharge from the hospital.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2269" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If bradycardia or hypotension requiring treatment or any other untoward effects occur, TENORMIN should be discontinued.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2270" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Data from other beta blocker trials suggest that if there is any question concerning the use of IV beta blocker or clinical estimate that there is a contraindication, the IV beta blocker may be eliminated and patients fulfilling the safety criteria may be given TENORMIN Tablets 50 mg twice daily or 100 mg once a day for at least seven days (if the IV dosing is excluded).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2271" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Although the demonstration of efficacy of TENORMIN is based entirely on data from the first seven postinfarction days, data from other beta blocker trials suggest that treatment with beta blockers that are effective in the postinfarction setting may be continued for one to three years if there are no contraindications.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2272" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>TENORMIN is an additional treatment to standard coronary care unit therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2273" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>TENORMIN is excreted by the kidneys; consequently dosage should be adjusted in cases of severe impairment of renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2274" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In general, dose selection for an elderly patient should be cautious, usually starting at the low end of the dosing range, reflecting greater frequency of decreased hepatic, renal, or cardiac function, and of concomitant disease or other drug therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2275" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Evaluation of patients with hypertension or myocardial infarction should always include assessment of renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2276" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Atenolol excretion would be expected to decrease with advancing age.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2277" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>No significant accumulation of TENORMIN occurs until creatinine clearance falls below 35mL/min/1.73m2.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2278" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Accumulation of atenolol and prolongation of its half-life were studied in subjects with creatinine clearance between 5 and 105 mL/min.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2279" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Peak plasma levels were significantly increased in subjects with creatinine clearances below 30mL/min.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2280" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The following maximum oral dosages are recommended for elderly, renally-impaired patients and for patients with renal impairment due to other causes: Creatinine Clearance (mL/min/1.73m2) Atenolol Elimination Half-Life (h) Maximum Dosage 15-35 16-27 50 mg daily &lt;15 &gt;27 25 mg daily Some renally-impaired or elderly patients being treated for hypertension may require a lower starting dose of TENORMIN: 25 mg given as one tablet a day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2281" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If this 25mg dose is used, assessment of efficacy must be made carefully.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2282" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>This should include measurement of blood pressure just prior to the next dose (trough blood pressure) to ensure that the treatment effect is present for a full 24 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2283" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Although a similar dosage reduction may be considered for elderly and/or renally-impaired patients being treated for indications other than hypertension, data are not available for these patient populations.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2284" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Patients on hemodialysis should be given 25 mg or 50 mg after each dialysis; this should be done under hospital supervision as marked falls in blood pressure can occur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2285" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If withdrawal of TENORMIN therapy is planned, it should be achieved gradually and patients should be carefully observed and advised to limit physical activity to a minimum.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2286" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Catecholamine-depleting drugs (eg, reserpine) may have an additive effect when given with beta-blocking agents.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M6" type="SpecificInteraction" span="58 15" str="additive effect" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="0 29" str="Catecholamine-depleting drugs" code="N0000175640"/>
<Mention id="M5" type="Precipitant" span="35 9" str="reserpine" code="8B1QWR724A"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M6" precipitant="M2" effect="M6"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M6" precipitant="M5" effect="M6"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2287" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Patients treated with TENORMIN plus a catecholamine depletor should therefore be closely observed for evidence of hypotension and/or marked bradycardia which may produce vertigo, syncope, or postural hypotension.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M19" type="Trigger" span="61 6;78 19" str="should | be closely observed"/>
<Mention id="M20" type="Precipitant" span="38 22" str="catecholamine depletor" code="N0000175640"/>
<Mention id="M9" type="SpecificInteraction" span="191 20" str="postural hypotension" code="28651003: Orthostatic hypotension (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M12" type="SpecificInteraction" span="170 7" str="vertigo" code="399153001: Vertigo (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M15" type="SpecificInteraction" span="179 7" str="syncope" code="271594007: Syncope (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M18" type="SpecificInteraction" span="114 11" str="hypotension" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M21" type="SpecificInteraction" span="133 18" str="marked bradycardia" code="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M19" precipitant="M20" effect="M9"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M19" precipitant="M20" effect="M12"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M19" precipitant="M20" effect="M15"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M19" precipitant="M20" effect="M18"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M19" precipitant="M20" effect="M21"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2288" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Calcium channel blockers may also have an additive effect when given with TENORMIN.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M24" type="SpecificInteraction" span="42 15" str="additive effect" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M23" type="Precipitant" span="0 24" str="Calcium channel blockers" code="N0000175566"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M24" precipitant="M23" effect="M24"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2289" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Disopyramide is a Type I antiarrhythmic drug with potent negative inotropic and chronotropic effects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2290" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Disopyramide has been associated with severe bradycardia, asystole and heart failure when administered with beta blockers.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M31" type="Trigger" span="22 15" str="associated with"/>
<Mention id="M32" type="Precipitant" span="0 12" str="Disopyramide" code="GFO928U8MQ"/>
<Mention id="M27" type="SpecificInteraction" span="71 13" str="heart failure" code="42343007: Congestive heart failure (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M30" type="SpecificInteraction" span="38 18" str="severe bradycardia" code="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M33" type="SpecificInteraction" span="58 8" str="asystole" code="397829000: Asystole (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M31" precipitant="M32" effect="M27"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M31" precipitant="M32" effect="M30"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M31" precipitant="M32" effect="M33"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2291" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Amiodarone is an antiarrhythmic agent with negative chronotropic properties that may be additive to those seen with beta blockers.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M34" type="Trigger" span="65 31" str="properties that may be additive"/>
<Mention id="M35" type="Precipitant" span="0 10" str="Amiodarone" code="N3RQ532IUT"/>
<Mention id="M36" type="SpecificInteraction" span="43 53" str="negative chronotropic properties that may be additive" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M34" precipitant="M35" effect="M36"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2292" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Beta blockers may exacerbate the rebound hypertension which can follow the withdrawal of clonidine.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M37" type="Trigger" span="18 10" str="exacerbate"/>
<Mention id="M38" type="Precipitant" span="89 9" str="clonidine" code="MN3L5RMN02"/>
<Mention id="M39" type="SpecificInteraction" span="33 20" str="rebound hypertension" code="84094009: Rebound hypertension (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M37" precipitant="M38" effect="M39"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2293" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>If the two drugs are coadministered, the beta blocker should be withdrawn several days before the gradual withdrawal of clonidine.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M40" type="Trigger" span="54 62" str="should be withdrawn several days before the gradual withdrawal"/>
<Mention id="M41" type="Precipitant" span="120 9" str="clonidine" code="MN3L5RMN02"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M40" precipitant="M41"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2294" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>If replacing clonidine by beta-blocker therapy, the introduction of beta blockers should be delayed for several days after clonidine administration has stopped.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M42" type="Trigger" span="82 40;133 26" str="should be delayed for several days after | administration has stopped"/>
<Mention id="M43" type="Precipitant" span="13 9" str="clonidine" code="MN3L5RMN02"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M42" precipitant="M43"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2295" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant use of prostaglandin synthase inhibiting drugs, eg, indomethacin, may decrease the hypotensive effects of beta blockers.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M47" type="Trigger" span="82 8;107 7" str="decrease | effects"/>
<Mention id="M45" type="Precipitant" span="64 12" str="indomethacin" code="XXE1CET956"/>
<Mention id="M49" type="SpecificInteraction" span="82 49" str="decrease the hypotensive effects of beta blockers" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M48" type="Precipitant" span="19 39" str="prostaglandin synthase inhibiting drugs" code="N0000175939"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M47" precipitant="M45" effect="M49"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M47" precipitant="M48" effect="M49"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2296" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Information on concurrent usage of atenolol and aspirin is limited.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2297" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Data from several studies, ie, TIMI-II, ISIS-2, currently do not suggest any clinical interaction between aspirin and beta blockers in the acute myocardial infarction setting.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2298" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>While taking beta blockers, patients with a history of anaphylactic reaction to a variety of allergens may have a more severe reaction on repeated challenge, either accidental, diagnostic or therapeutic.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M52" type="SpecificInteraction" span="114 20" str="more severe reaction" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M51" type="Precipitant" span="93 9" str="allergens" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M52" precipitant="M51" effect="M52"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2299" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Such patients may be unresponsive to the usual doses of epinephrine used to treat the allergic reaction.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M53" type="Trigger" span="21 31" str="unresponsive to the usual doses"/>
<Mention id="M54" type="Precipitant" span="56 11" str="epinephrine" code="YKH834O4BH"/>
<Mention id="M55" type="SpecificInteraction" span="86 17" str="allergic reaction" code="419076005: Allergic reaction (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M53" precipitant="M54" effect="M55"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2300" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Both digitalis glycosides and beta-blockers slow atrioventricular conduction and decrease heart rate.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M59" type="Trigger" span="0 4" str="Both"/>
<Mention id="M60" type="Precipitant" span="5 20" str="digitalis glycosides" code="F1T8QT9U8B"/>
<Mention id="M58" type="SpecificInteraction" span="44 32" str="slow atrioventricular conduction" code="233917008: Atrioventricular block (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M61" type="SpecificInteraction" span="81 19" str="decrease heart rate" code="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M59" precipitant="M60" effect="M58"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M59" precipitant="M60" effect="M61"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2301" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant use can increase the risk of bradycardia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2302" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Patients already on a beta blocker must be evaluated carefully before TENORMIN is administered.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M62" type="Trigger" span="0 19;35 27" str="Patients already on | must be evaluated carefully"/>
<Mention id="M63" type="Precipitant" span="22 12" str="beta blocker" code="N0000175556"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M62" precipitant="M63"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2303" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Initial and subsequent TENORMIN dosages can be adjusted downward depending on clinical observations including pulse and blood pressure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2304" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>TENORMIN may aggravate peripheral arterial circulatory disorders.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2305" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The drug should be used with caution in patients with impaired renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2306" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Two long-term (maximum dosing duration of 18 or 24months) rat studies and one long-term (maximum dosing duration of 18 months) mouse study, each employing dose levels as high as 300 mg/kg/day or 150 times the maximum recommended human antihypertensive dose, did not indicate a carcinogenic potential of atenolol.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2307" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>A third (24month) rat study, employing doses of 500 and 1,500mg/kg/day (250 and 750 times the maximum recommended human antihypertensive dose) resulted in increased incidences of benign adrenal medullary tumors in males and females, mammary fibroadenomas in females, and anterior pituitary adenomas and thyroid parafollicular cell carcinomas in males.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2308" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>No evidence of a mutagenic potential of atenolol was uncovered in the dominant lethal test (mouse), in vivo cytogenetics test (Chinese hamster) or Ames test (S typhimurium).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2309" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Fertility of male or female rats (evaluated at dose levels as high as 200 mg/kg/day or 100 times the maximum recommended human dose) was unaffected by atenolol administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2310" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Chronic studies employing oral atenolol performed in animals have revealed the occurrence of vacuolation of epithelial cells of Brunner's glands in the duodenum of both male and female dogs at all tested dose levels of atenolol (starting at 15 mg/kg/day or 7.5 times the maximum recommended human antihypertensive dose) and increased incidence of atrial degeneration of hearts of male rats at 300 but not 150 mg atenolol/kg/day (150 and 75times the maximum recommended human antihypertensive dose, respectively).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2311" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>See WARNINGS - Pregnancy and Fetal Injury.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2312" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Atenolol is excreted in human breast milk at a ratio of 1.5 to 6.8 when compared to the concentration in plasma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2313" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Caution should be exercised when TENORMIN is administered to a nursing woman.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2314" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Clinically significant bradycardia has been reported in breast-fed infants.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2315" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Premature infants, or infants with impaired renal function, may be more likely to develop adverse effects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2316" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Neonates born to mothers who are receiving TENORMIN at parturition or breast-feeding may be at risk for hypoglycemia and bradycardia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2317" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Caution should be exercised when TENORMIN is administered during pregnancy or to a woman who is breast-feeding.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2318" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Safety and effectiveness in pediatric patients have not been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2319" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Clinical studies of TENORMIN did not include sufficient number of patients aged 65 and over to determine whether they respond differently from younger subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2320" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Other reported clinical experience has not identified differences in responses between the elderly and younger patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2321" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In general, dose selection for an elderly patient should be cautious, usually starting at the low end of the dosing range, reflecting the greater frequency of decreased hepatic, renal, or cardiac function, and of concomitant disease or other drug therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2322" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Of the 8,037 patients with suspected acute myocardial infarction randomized to TENORMIN in the ISIS-1 trial, 33% (2,644) were 65 years of age and older.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2323" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>It was not possible to identify significant differences in efficacy and safety between older and younger patients; however, elderly patients with systolic blood pressure &lt; 120 mmHg seemed less likely to benefit.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2324" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Sympathetic stimulation is necessary in supporting circulatory function in congestive heart failure, and beta blockade carries the potential hazard of further depressing myocardial contractility and precipitating more severe failure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2325" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>In patients with acute myocardial infarction, cardiac failure which is not promptly and effectively controlled by 80 mg of intravenous furosemide or equivalent therapy is a contraindication to beta-blocker treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2326" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Continued depression of the myocardium with beta-blocking agents over a period of time can, in some cases, lead to cardiac failure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2327" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>At the first sign or symptom of impending cardiac failure, patients should be treated appropriately according to currently recommended guidelines, and the response observed closely.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2328" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>If cardiac failure continues despite adequate treatment, TENORMIN should be withdrawn.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2329" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Bradycardia and heart block can occur and the left ventricular end diastolic pressure can rise when beta-blockers are administered with verapamil or diltiazem.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M89" type="Trigger" span="0 11" str="Bradycardia "/>
<Mention id="M90" type="Trigger" span="16 11" str=" heart block "/>
<Mention id="M91" type="Trigger" span="46 48" str=" left ventricular end diastolic pressure can rise"/>
<Mention id="M77" type="Precipitant" span="149 9" str="diltiazem" code="EE92BBP03H"/>
<Mention id="M93" type="SpecificInteraction" span="16 11" str="heart block" code="233916004: Heart block (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M88" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 11" str="Bradycardia" code="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M83" type="SpecificInteraction" span="46 48" str="left ventricular end diastolic pressure can rise" code="23154005: Increased diastolic arterial pressure (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M92" type="Precipitant" span="136 9" str="verapamil" code="CJ0O37KU29"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M89;M90;M91" precipitant="M77" effect="M93"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M89;M90;M91" precipitant="M77" effect="M88"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M89;M90;M91" precipitant="M77" effect="M83"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M89;M90;M91" precipitant="M92" effect="M83"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M89;M90;M91" precipitant="M92" effect="M88"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M89;M90;M91" precipitant="M92" effect="M93"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2330" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Patients with pre-existing conduction abnormalities or left ventricular dysfunction are particularly susceptible.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2331" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>PATIENTS WITH BRONCHOSPASTIC DISEASE SHOULD, IN GENERAL, NOT RECEIVE BETA BLOCKERS.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2332" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Because of its relative beta1 selectivity, however, TENORMIN may be used with caution in patients with bronchospastic disease who do not respond to, or cannot tolerate, other antihypertensive treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2333" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Since beta1 selectivity is not absolute, the lowest possible dose of TENORMIN should be used with therapy initiated at 50 mg and a beta2-stimulating agent (bronchodilator) should be made available.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2334" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>If dosage must be increased, dividing the dose should be considered in order to achieve lower peak blood levels.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2335" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Chronically administered beta-blocking therapy should not be routinely withdrawn prior to major surgery, however the impaired ability of the heart to respond to reflex adrenergic stimuli may augment the risks of general anesthesia and surgical procedures.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M94" type="Trigger" span="191 17" str="augment the risks"/>
<Mention id="M95" type="Precipitant" span="212 18" str="general anesthesia" code="N0000175681"/>
<Mention id="M96" type="SpecificInteraction" span="191 39" str="augment the risks of general anesthesia" code="736523005: At risk of complication of anesthesia (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I29" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M94" precipitant="M95" effect="M96"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2336" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>TENORMIN should be used with caution in diabetic patients if a beta-blocking agent is required.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2337" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Beta blockers may mask tachycardia occurring with hypoglycemia, but other manifestations such as dizziness and sweating may not be significantly affected.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2338" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>At recommended doses TENORMIN does not potentiate insulin-induced hypoglycemia and, unlike nonselective beta blockers, does not delay recovery of blood glucose to normal levels.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2339" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Beta-adrenergic blockade may mask certain clinical signs (eg, tachycardia) of hyperthyroidism.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2340" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Abrupt withdrawal of beta blockade might precipitate a thyroid storm; therefore, patients suspected of developing thyrotoxicosis from whom TENORMIN therapy is to be withdrawn should be monitored closely.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2341" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>TENORMIN should not be given to patients with untreated pheochromocytoma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2342" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Atenolol can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2343" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Atenolol crosses the placental barrier and appears in cord blood.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2344" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Administration of atenolol, starting in the second trimester of pregnancy, has been associated with the birth of infants that are small for gestational age.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2345" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>No studies have been performed on the use of atenolol in the first trimester and the possibility of fetal injury cannot be excluded.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2346" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>If this drug is used during pregnancy, or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking this drug, the patient should be apprised of the potential hazard to the fetus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2347" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Atenolol has been shown to produce a dose-related increase in embryo/fetal resorptions in rats at doses equal to or greater than 50 mg/kg/day or 25 or more times the maximum recommended human antihypertensive dose Based on the maximum dose of 100 mg/day in a 50 kg patient..</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2348" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Although similar effects were not seen in rabbits, the compound was not evaluated in rabbits at doses above 25mg/kg/day or 12.5 times the maximum recommended human antihypertensive dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2349" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>TENORMIN is a beta1-selective (cardioselective) beta-adrenergic receptor blocking agent without membrane stabilizing or intrinsic sympathomimetic (partial agonist) activities.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2350" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This preferential effect is not absolute, however, and at higher doses, TENORMIN inhibits beta2-adrenoreceptors, chiefly located in the bronchial and vascular musculature.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2351" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In man, absorption of an oral dose is rapid and consistent but incomplete.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2352" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Approximately 50% of an oral dose is absorbed from the gastrointestinal tract, the remainder being excreted unchanged in the feces.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2353" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Peak blood levels are reached between two (2) and four (4) hours after ingestion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2354" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Unlike propranolol or metoprolol, but like nadolol, TENORMIN undergoes little or no metabolism by the liver, and the absorbed portion is eliminated primarily by renal excretion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2355" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Over 85% of an intravenous dose is excreted in urine within 24 hours compared with approximately 50% for an oral dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2356" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>TENORMIN also differs from propranolol in that only a small amount (6%-16%) is bound to proteins in the plasma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2357" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This kinetic profile results in relatively consistent plasma drug levels with about a fourfold interpatient variation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2358" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The elimination half-life of oral TENORMIN is approximately 6 to 7 hours, and there is no alteration of the kinetic profile of the drug by chronic administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2359" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following intravenous administration, peak plasma levels are reached within 5 minutes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2360" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Declines from peak levels are rapid (5- to 10-fold) during the first 7 hours; thereafter, plasma levels decay with a half-life similar to that of orally administered drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2361" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following oral doses of 50 mg or 100 mg, both beta-blocking and antihypertensive effects persist for at least 24 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2362" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>When renal function is impaired, elimination of TENORMIN is closely related to the glomerular filtration rate; significant accumulation occurs when the creatinine clearance falls below 35mL/min/1.73m2.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2363" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In standard animal or human pharmacological tests, beta-adrenoreceptor blocking activity of TENORMIN has been demonstrated by: (1) reduction in resting and exercise heart rate and cardiac output, (2) reduction of systolic and diastolic blood pressure at rest and on exercise, (3) inhibition of isoproterenol induced tachycardia, and (4) reduction in reflex orthostatic tachycardia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2364" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A significant beta-blocking effect of TENORMIN, as measured by reduction of exercise tachycardia, is apparent within one hour following oral administration of a single dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2365" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This effect is maximal at about 2 to 4 hours, and persists for at least 24 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2366" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Maximum reduction in exercise tachycardia occurs within 5 minutes of an intravenous dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2367" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>For both orally and intravenously administered drug, the duration of action is dose related and also bears a linear relationship to the logarithm of plasma TENORMIN concentration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2368" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The effect on exercise tachycardia of a single 10 mg intravenous dose is largely dissipated by 12 hours, whereas beta-blocking activity of single oral doses of 50 mg and 100 mg is still evident beyond 24 hours following administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2369" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>However, as has been shown for all beta-blocking agents, the antihypertensive effect does not appear to be related to plasma level.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2370" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In normal subjects, the beta1 selectivity of TENORMIN has been shown by its reduced ability to reverse the beta2-mediated vasodilating effect of isoproterenol as compared to equivalent beta-blocking doses of propranolol.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2371" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In asthmatic patients, a dose of TENORMIN producing a greater effect on resting heart rate than propranolol resulted in much less increase in airway resistance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2372" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In a placebo controlled comparison of approximately equipotent oral doses of several beta blockers, TENORMIN produced a significantly smaller decrease of FEV1 than nonselective beta blockers such as propranolol and, unlike those agents, did not inhibit bronchodilation in response to isoproterenol.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2373" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Consistent with its negative chronotropic effect due to beta blockade of the SA node, TENORMIN increases sinus cycle length and sinus node recovery time.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2374" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Conduction in the AV node is also prolonged.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2375" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>TENORMIN is devoid of membrane stabilizing activity, and increasing the dose well beyond that producing beta blockade does not further depress myocardial contractility.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2376" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Several studies have demonstrated a moderate (approximately 10%) increase in stroke volume at rest and during exercise.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2377" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In controlled clinical trials, TENORMIN, given as a single daily oral dose, was an effective antihypertensive agent providing 24-hour reduction of blood pressure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2378" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>TENORMIN has been studied in combination with thiazide-type diuretics, and the blood pressure effects of the combination are approximately additive.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M97" type="Trigger" span="94 7;139 8" str="effects | additive"/>
<Mention id="M98" type="Precipitant" span="46 23" str="thiazide-type diuretics" code="N0000175419"/>
<Mention id="M99" type="SpecificInteraction" span="79 22;139 8" str="blood pressure effects | additive" code="38936003: Abnormal blood pressure (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I30" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M97" precipitant="M98" effect="M99"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2379" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>TENORMIN is also compatible with methyldopa, hydralazine, and prazosin, each combination resulting in a larger fall in blood pressure than with the single agents.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M106" type="Trigger" span="104 11" str="larger fall"/>
<Mention id="M101" type="Precipitant" span="45 11" str="hydralazine" code="26NAK24LS8"/>
<Mention id="M108" type="SpecificInteraction" span="104 29" str="larger fall in blood pressure" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M104" type="Precipitant" span="33 10" str="methyldopa" code="56LH93261Y"/>
<Mention id="M107" type="Precipitant" span="62 8" str="prazosin" code="XM03YJ541D"/>
<Interaction id="I31" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M106" precipitant="M101" effect="M108"/>
<Interaction id="I32" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M106" precipitant="M104" effect="M108"/>
<Interaction id="I33" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M106" precipitant="M107" effect="M108"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2380" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The dose range of TENORMIN is narrow and increasing the dose beyond 100 mg once daily is not associated with increased antihypertensive effect.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2381" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mechanisms of the antihypertensive effects of beta-blocking agents have not been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2382" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Several possible mechanisms have been proposed and include: (1) competitive antagonism of catecholamines at peripheral (especially cardiac) adrenergic neuron sites, leading to decreased cardiac output, (2) a central effect leading to reduced sympathetic outflow to the periphery, and (3) suppression of renin activity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2383" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The results from long-term studies have not shown any diminution of the antihypertensive efficacy of TENORMIN with prolonged use.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2384" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>By blocking the positive chronotropic and inotropic effects of catecholamines and by decreasing blood pressure, atenolol generally reduces the oxygen requirements of the heart at any given level of effort, making it useful for many patients in the long-term management of angina pectoris.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2385" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>On the other hand, atenolol can increase oxygen requirements by increasing left ventricular fiber length and end diastolic pressure, particularly in patients with heart failure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2386" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In a multicenter clinical trial (ISIS-1) conducted in 16,027 patients with suspected myocardial infarction, patients presenting within 12 hours (mean = 5 hours) after the onset of pain were randomized to either conventional therapy plus TENORMIN (n = 8,037), or conventional therapy alone (n = 7,990).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2387" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Patients with a heart rate of &lt; 50 bpm or systolic blood pressure &lt;100mmHg, or with other contraindications to beta blockade were excluded.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2388" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Thirty-eight percent of each group were treated within 4 hours of onset of pain.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2389" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mean time from onset of pain to entry was 5.0 ± 2.7 hours in both groups.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2390" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Patients in the TENORMIN group were to receive TENORMIN I.V.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2391" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Injection 5-10 mg given over 5 minutes plus TENORMIN Tablets 50 mg every 12 hours orally on the first study day (the first oral dose administered about 15 minutes after the IV dose) followed by either TENORMIN Tablets 100 mg once daily or TENORMIN Tablets 50 mg twice daily on days 2-7.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2392" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The groups were similar in demographic and medical history characteristics and in electrocardiographic evidence of myocardial infarction, bundle branch block, and first degree atrioventricular block at entry.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2393" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>During the treatment period (days 0-7), the vascular mortality rates were 3.89% in the TENORMIN group (313deaths) and 4.57% in the control group (365 deaths).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2394" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This absolute difference in rates, 0.68%, is statistically significant at the P &lt; 0.05 level.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2395" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The absolute difference translates into a proportional reduction of 15% (3.89-4.57/4.57 = -0.15).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2396" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Most of the difference was attributed to mortality in days 0-1 (TENORMIN - 121 deaths; control - 171 deaths).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2397" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Despite the large size of the ISIS-1 trial, it is not possible to identify clearly subgroups of patients most likely or least likely to benefit from early treatment with atenolol.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2398" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Good clinical judgment suggests, however, that patients who are dependent on sympathetic stimulation for maintenance of adequate cardiac output and blood pressure are not good candidates for beta blockade.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2399" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Indeed, the trial protocol reflected that judgment by excluding patients with blood pressure consistently below 100 mm Hg systolic.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2400" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The overall results of the study are compatible with the possibility that patients with borderline blood pressure (less than 120 mm Hg systolic), especially if over 60 years of age, are less likely to benefit.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2401" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mechanism through which atenolol improves survival in patients with definite or suspected acute myocardial infarction is unknown, as is the case for other beta blockers in the postinfarction setting.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2402" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Atenolol, in addition to its effects on survival, has shown other clinical benefits including reduced frequency of ventricular premature beats, reduced chest pain, and reduced enzyme elevation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2403" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In general, elderly patients present higher atenolol plasma levels with total clearance values about 50% lower than younger subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2404" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The half-life is markedly longer in the elderly compared to younger subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2405" LabelDrug="TENORMIN" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The reduction in atenolol clearance follows the general trend that the elimination of renally excreted drugs is decreased with increasing age.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="catecholamine-depleting drugs" precipitantCode="N0000175640" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="reserpine" precipitantCode="8B1QWR724A" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="catecholamine depletor" precipitantCode="N0000175640" effect="271594007: Syncope (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="catecholamine depletor" precipitantCode="N0000175640" effect="28651003: Orthostatic hypotension (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="catecholamine depletor" precipitantCode="N0000175640" effect="399153001: Vertigo (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="catecholamine depletor" precipitantCode="N0000175640" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="catecholamine depletor" precipitantCode="N0000175640" effect="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="calcium channel blockers" precipitantCode="N0000175566" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="disopyramide" precipitantCode="GFO928U8MQ" effect="397829000: Asystole (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="disopyramide" precipitantCode="GFO928U8MQ" effect="42343007: Congestive heart failure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="disopyramide" precipitantCode="GFO928U8MQ" effect="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="amiodarone" precipitantCode="N3RQ532IUT" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="clonidine" precipitantCode="MN3L5RMN02" effect="84094009: Rebound hypertension (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="clonidine" precipitantCode="MN3L5RMN02"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="indomethacin" precipitantCode="XXE1CET956" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="prostaglandin synthase inhibiting drugs" precipitantCode="N0000175939" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="allergens" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="epinephrine" precipitantCode="YKH834O4BH" effect="419076005: Allergic reaction (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="digitalis glycosides" precipitantCode="F1T8QT9U8B" effect="233917008: Atrioventricular block (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="digitalis glycosides" precipitantCode="F1T8QT9U8B" effect="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="beta blocker" precipitantCode="N0000175556"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="diltiazem" precipitantCode="EE92BBP03H" effect="23154005: Increased diastolic arterial pressure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="diltiazem" precipitantCode="EE92BBP03H" effect="233916004: Heart block (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="diltiazem" precipitantCode="EE92BBP03H" effect="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="verapamil" precipitantCode="CJ0O37KU29" effect="23154005: Increased diastolic arterial pressure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="verapamil" precipitantCode="CJ0O37KU29" effect="233916004: Heart block (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="verapamil" precipitantCode="CJ0O37KU29" effect="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="general anesthesia" precipitantCode="N0000175681" effect="736523005: At risk of complication of anesthesia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="thiazide-type diuretics" precipitantCode="N0000175419" effect="38936003: Abnormal blood pressure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="hydralazine" precipitantCode="26NAK24LS8" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="methyldopa" precipitantCode="56LH93261Y" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="prazosin" precipitantCode="XM03YJ541D" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>