<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="TENORETIC" setid="0ebcca1e-ca16-4483-429a-aec5dcacd1dc">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
TENORETIC is contraindicated in patients with: sinus bradycardia; heart block greater than first degree; cardiogenic shock; overt cardiac failure (see WARNINGS); anuria; hypersensitivity to this product or to sulfonamide-derived drugs.</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
DOSAGE MUST BE INDIVIDUALIZED. (See INDICATIONS AND USAGE.)  Chlorthalidone is usually given at a dose of 25 mg daily; the usual initial dose of atenolol is 50 mg daily. Therefore, the initial dose should be one TENORETIC 50 tablet given once a day. If an optimal response is not achieved, the dosage should be increased to one TENORETIC 100 tablet given once a day.  When necessary, another antihypertensive agent may be added gradually beginning with 50 percent of the usual recommended starting dose to avoid an excessive fall in blood pressure.  Since atenolol is excreted via the kidneys, dosage should be adjusted in cases of severe impairment of renal function. No significant accumulation of atenolol occurs until creatinine clearance falls below 35 mL/min/1.73m2 (normal range is 100-150 mL/min/1.73m2); therefore, the following maximum dosages are recommended for patients with renal impairment.        Creatinine Clearance (mL/min/1.73m2)   Atenolol Elimination Half-Life (hrs)   Maximum Dosage     15-35   16-27   50 mg daily     &amp;lt;15   &amp;gt;27   50 mg every other day</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
TENORETIC may potentiate the action of other antihypertensive agents used concomitantly. Patients treated with TENORETIC plus a catecholamine depletor (eg, reserpine) should be closely observed for evidence of hypotension and/or marked bradycardia which may produce vertigo, syncope or postural hypotension.  Calcium channel blockers may also have an additive effect when given with TENORETIC. (See WARNINGS.) Disopyramide is a Type I antiarrhythmic drug with potent negative inotropic and chronotropic effects. Disopyramide has been associated with severe bradycardia, asystole and heart failure when administered with beta blockers.  Amiodarone is an antiarrhythmic agent with negative chronotropic properties that may be additive to those seen with beta blockers. Thiazides may decrease arterial responsiveness to norepinephrine. This diminution is not sufficient to preclude the therapeutic effectiveness of norepinephrine. Thiazides may increase the responsiveness to tubocurarine. Concomitant use of prostaglandin synthase inhibiting drugs, eg, indomethacin, may decrease the hypotensive effects of beta blockers. Lithium generally should not be given with diuretics because they reduce its renal clearance and add a high risk of lithium toxicity. Read prescribing information for lithium preparations before use of such preparations with TENORETIC. Beta blockers may exacerbate the rebound hypertension which can follow the withdrawal of clonidine. If the two drugs are coadministered, the beta blocker should be withdrawn several days before the gradual withdrawal of clonidine. If replacing clonidine by beta-blocker therapy, the introduction of beta blockers should be delayed for several days after clonidine administration has stopped. While taking beta blockers, patients with a history of anaphylactic reaction to a variety of allergens may have a more severe reaction on repeated challenge, either accidental, diagnostic or therapeutic. Such patients may be unresponsive to the usual doses of epinephrine used to treat the allergic reaction. Both digitalis glycosides and beta-blockers slow atrioventricular conduction and decrease heart rate. Concomitant use can increase the risk of bradycardia.</Section>
<Section name="PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="42232-9">
TENORETIC may aggravate peripheral arterial circulatory disorders.          Periodic determination of serum electrolytes to detect possible electrolyte imbalance should be performed at appropriate intervals. Patients should be observed for clinical signs of fluid or electrolyte imbalance; i.e., hyponatremia, hypochloremic alkalosis, and hypokalemia. Serum and urine electrolyte determinations are particularly important when the patient is vomiting excessively or receiving parenteral fluids. Warning signs or symptoms of fluid and electrolyte imbalance include dryness of the mouth, thirst, weakness, lethargy, drowsiness, restlessness, muscle pains or cramps, muscular fatigue, hypotension, oliguria, tachycardia, and gastrointestinal disturbances such as nausea and vomiting. Measurement of potassium levels is appropriate especially in elderly patients, those receiving digitalis preparations for cardiac failure, patients whose dietary intake of potassium is abnormally low, or those suffering from gastrointestinal complaints.  Hypokalemia may develop especially with brisk diuresis, when severe cirrhosis is present, or during concomitant use of corticosteroids or ACTH.  Interference with adequate oral electrolyte intake will also contribute to hypokalemia. Hypokalemia can sensitize or exaggerate the response of the heart to the toxic effects of digitalis (eg, increased ventricular irritability). Hypokalemia may be avoided or treated by use of potassium supplements or foods with a high potassium content. Any chloride deficit during thiazide therapy is generally mild and usually does not require specific treatment except under extraordinary circumstances (as in liver disease or renal disease). Dilutional hyponatremia may occur in edematous patients in hot weather; appropriate therapy is water restriction rather than administration of salt except in rare instances when the hyponatremia is life-threatening. In actual salt depletion, appropriate replacement is the therapy of choice.          TENORETIC may potentiate the action of other antihypertensive agents used concomitantly. Patients treated with TENORETIC plus a catecholamine depletor (eg, reserpine) should be closely observed for evidence of hypotension and/or marked bradycardia which may produce vertigo, syncope or postural hypotension.  Calcium channel blockers may also have an additive effect when given with TENORETIC. (See WARNINGS.) Disopyramide is a Type I antiarrhythmic drug with potent negative inotropic and chronotropic effects. Disopyramide has been associated with severe bradycardia, asystole and heart failure when administered with beta blockers.  Amiodarone is an antiarrhythmic agent with negative chronotropic properties that may be additive to those seen with beta blockers. Thiazides may decrease arterial responsiveness to norepinephrine. This diminution is not sufficient to preclude the therapeutic effectiveness of norepinephrine. Thiazides may increase the responsiveness to tubocurarine. Concomitant use of prostaglandin synthase inhibiting drugs, eg, indomethacin, may decrease the hypotensive effects of beta blockers. Lithium generally should not be given with diuretics because they reduce its renal clearance and add a high risk of lithium toxicity. Read prescribing information for lithium preparations before use of such preparations with TENORETIC. Beta blockers may exacerbate the rebound hypertension which can follow the withdrawal of clonidine. If the two drugs are coadministered, the beta blocker should be withdrawn several days before the gradual withdrawal of clonidine. If replacing clonidine by beta-blocker therapy, the introduction of beta blockers should be delayed for several days after clonidine administration has stopped. While taking beta blockers, patients with a history of anaphylactic reaction to a variety of allergens may have a more severe reaction on repeated challenge, either accidental, diagnostic or therapeutic. Such patients may be unresponsive to the usual doses of epinephrine used to treat the allergic reaction. Both digitalis glycosides and beta-blockers slow atrioventricular conduction and decrease heart rate. Concomitant use can increase the risk of bradycardia.          In patients receiving thiazides, sensitivity reactions may occur with or without a history of allergy or bronchial asthma. The possible exacerbation or activation of systemic lupus erythematosus has been reported. The antihypertensive effects of thiazides may be enhanced in the postsympathectomy patient.          Two long-term (maximum dosing duration of 18 or 24 months) rat studies and one long-term (maximum dosing duration of 18 months) mouse study, each employing dose levels as high as 300 mg/kg/day or 150 times the maximum recommended human antihypertensive dose1, did not indicate a carcinogenic potential of atenolol. A third (24 month) rat study, employing doses of 500 and 1,500 mg/kg/day (250 and 750 times the maximum recommended human antihypertensive dose1) resulted in increased incidences of benign adrenal medullary tumors in males and females, mammary fibroadenomas in females, and anterior pituitary adenomas and thyroid parafollicular cell carcinomas in males. No evidence of a mutagenic potential of atenolol was uncovered in the dominant lethal test (mouse), in vivo cytogenetics test (Chinese hamster) or Ames test (S typhimurium).  Fertility of male or female rats (evaluated at dose levels as high as 200 mg/kg/day or 100 times the maximum recommended human dose1) was unaffected by atenolol administration.           Six month oral administration studies were conducted in rats and dogs using TENORETIC doses up to 12.5 mg/kg/day (atenolol/chlorthalidone 10/2.5 mg/kg/day -- approximately five times the maximum recommended human antihypertensive dose1). There were no functional or morphological abnormalities resulting from dosing either compound alone or together other than minor changes in heart rate, blood pressure and urine chemistry which were attributed to the known pharmacologic properties of atenolol and/or chlorthalidone. Chronic studies of atenolol performed in animals have revealed the occurrence of vacuolation of epithelial cells of Brunner's glands in the duodenum of both male and female dogs at all tested dose levels (starting at 15 mg/kg/day or 7.5 times the maximum recommended human antihypertensive dose1) and increased incidence of atrial degeneration of hearts of male rats at 300 but not 150 mg atenolol/kg/day (150 and 75 times the maximum recommended human antihypertensive dose,1 respectively).          Pregnancy Category D: See WARNINGS - Pregnancy and Fetal Injury           Atenolol is excreted in human breast milk at a ratio of 1.5 to 6.8 when compared to the concentration in plasma. Caution should be exercised when atenolol is administered to a nursing woman. Clinically significant bradycardia has been reported in breast-fed infants. Premature infants, or infants with impaired renal function, may be more likely to develop adverse effects. Neonates born to mothers who are receiving atenolol at parturition or breast-feeding may be at risk for hypoglycemia and bradycardia. Caution should be exercised when TENORETIC is administered during pregnancy or to a woman who is breast-feeding. (See WARNINGS, Pregnancy and Fetal Injury.)</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS SECTION" id="34071-1">
Sympathetic stimulation is necessary in supporting circulatory function in congestive heart failure, and beta blockade carries the potential hazard of further depressing myocardial contractility and precipitating more severe failure. IN PATIENTS WITHOUT A HISTORY OF CARDIAC FAILURE, continued depression of the myocardium with beta-blocking agents over a period of time can, in some cases, lead to cardiac failure. At the first sign or symptom of impending cardiac failure, patients should be treated appropriately according to currently recommended guidelines, and the response observed closely. If cardiac failure continues despite adequate treatment, TENORETIC should be withdrawn. (See DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION.)          Since atenolol is excreted via the kidneys, TENORETIC should be used with caution in patients with impaired renal function. In patients with renal disease, thiazides may precipitate azotemia. Since cumulative effects may develop in the presence of impaired renal function, if progressive renal impairment becomes evident, TENORETIC should be discontinued.  In patients with impaired hepatic function or progressive liver disease, minor alterations in fluid and electrolyte balance may precipitate hepatic coma. TENORETIC should be used with caution in these patients.           Following abrupt cessation of therapy with certain beta-blocking agents in patients with coronary artery disease, exacerbations of angina pectoris and, in some cases, myocardial infarction have been reported. Therefore, such patients should be cautioned against interruption of therapy without the physician's advice. Even in the absence of overt angina pectoris, when discontinuation of TENORETIC is planned, the patient should be carefully observed and should be advised to limit physical activity to a minimum. TENORETIC should be reinstated if withdrawal symptoms occur. Because coronary artery disease is common and may be unrecognized, it may be prudent not to discontinue TENORETIC therapy abruptly even in patients treated only for hypertension.           Bradycardia and heart block can occur and the left ventricular end diastolic pressure can rise when beta-blockers are administered with verapamil or diltiazem. Patients with pre-existing conduction abnormalities or left ventricular dysfunction are particularly susceptible. (See  PRECAUTIONS .)           PATIENTS WITH BRONCHOSPASTIC DISEASE SHOULD, IN GENERAL, NOT RECEIVE BETA BLOCKERS. Because of its relative beta1-selectivity, however, TENORETIC may be used with caution in patients with bronchospastic disease who do not respond to or cannot tolerate, other antihypertensive treatment. Since beta1-selectivity is not absolute, the lowest possible dose of TENORETIC should be used and a beta2-stimulating agent (bronchodilator) should be made available. If dosage must be increased, dividing the dose should be considered in order to achieve lower peak blood levels.            Chronically administered beta-blocking therapy should not be routinely withdrawn prior to major surgery, however the impaired ability of the heart to respond to reflex adrenergic stimuli may augment the risks of general anesthesia and surgical procedures.          TENORETIC may be used with caution in diabetic patients. Beta blockers may mask tachycardia occurring with hypoglycemia, but other manifestations such as dizziness and sweating may not be significantly affected. At recommended doses atenolol does not potentiate insulin-induced hypoglycemia and, unlike nonselective beta blockers, does not delay recovery of blood glucose to normal levels.  Insulin requirements in diabetic patients may be increased, decreased or unchanged; latent diabetes mellitus may become manifest during chlorthalidone administration.  Beta-adrenergic blockade may mask certain clinical signs (eg, tachycardia) of hyperthyroidism. Abrupt withdrawal of beta blockade might precipitate a thyroid storm; therefore, patients suspected of developing thyrotoxicosis from whom TENORETIC therapy is to be withdrawn should be monitored closely.  Because calcium excretion is decreased by thiazides, TENORETIC should be discontinued before carrying out tests for parathyroid function. Pathologic changes in the parathyroid glands, with hypercalcemia and hypophosphatemia, have been observed in a few patients on prolonged thiazide therapy; however, the common complications of hyperparathyroidism such as renal lithiasis, bone resorption, and peptic ulceration have not been seen.  Hyperuricemia may occur, or acute gout may be precipitated in certain patients receiving thiazide therapy.           TENORETIC should not be given to patients with untreated pheochromocytoma.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Atenolol and chlorthalidone have been used singly and concomitantly for the treatment of hypertension. The antihypertensive effects of these agents are additive, and studies have shown that there is no interference with bioavailability when these agents are given together in the single combination tablet. Therefore, this combination provides a convenient formulation for the concomitant administration of these two entities. In patients with more severe hypertension, TENORETIC may be administered with other antihypertensives such as vasodilators.          Atenolol is a beta1-selective (cardioselective) beta-adrenergic receptor blocking agent without membrane stabilizing or intrinsic sympathomimetic (partial agonist) activities. This preferential effect is not absolute, however, and at higher doses, atenolol inhibits beta2-adrenoreceptors, chiefly located in the bronchial and vascular musculature.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="2553" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>TENORETIC is contraindicated in patients with: sinus bradycardia; heart block greater than first degree; cardiogenic shock; overt cardiac failure ; anuria; hypersensitivity to this product or to sulfonamide-derived drugs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2554" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Chlorthalidone is usually given at a dose of 25 mg daily; the usual initial dose of atenolol is 50 mg daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2555" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Therefore, the initial dose should be one TENORETIC 50 tablet given once a day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2556" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If an optimal response is not achieved, the dosage should be increased to one TENORETIC 100 tablet given once a day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2557" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>When necessary, another antihypertensive agent may be added gradually beginning with 50 percent of the usual recommended starting dose to avoid an excessive fall in blood pressure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2558" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Since atenolol is excreted via the kidneys, dosage should be adjusted in cases of severe impairment of renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2559" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>No significant accumulation of atenolol occurs until creatinine clearance falls below 35 mL/min/1.73m2 (normal range is 100-150 mL/min/1.73m2); therefore, the following maximum dosages are recommended for patients with renal impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2560" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Creatinine Clearance (mL/min/1.73m2) Atenolol Elimination Half-Life (hrs) Maximum Dosage 15-35 16-27 50 mg daily &lt;15 &gt;27 50 mg every other day</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2561" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>TENORETIC may potentiate the action of other antihypertensive agents used concomitantly.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M1" type="Trigger" span="14 21" str="potentiate the action"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="45 23" str="antihypertensive agents" code="N0000178477"/>
<Mention id="M3" type="SpecificInteraction" span="14 54" str="potentiate the action of other antihypertensive agents" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M1" precipitant="M2" effect="M3"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2562" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Patients treated with TENORETIC plus a catecholamine depletor (eg, reserpine) should be closely observed for evidence of hypotension and/or marked bradycardia which may produce vertigo, syncope or postural hypotension.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M31" type="Trigger" span="78 26" str="should be closely observed"/>
<Mention id="M17" type="Precipitant" span="39 22" str="catecholamine depletor" code="N0000175640"/>
<Mention id="M33" type="SpecificInteraction" span="197 20" str="postural hypotension" code="28651003: Orthostatic hypotension (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M24" type="SpecificInteraction" span="140 18" str="marked bradycardia" code="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M30" type="SpecificInteraction" span="186 7" str="syncope" code="271594007: Syncope (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M27" type="SpecificInteraction" span="121 11" str="hypotension" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M21" type="SpecificInteraction" span="177 7" str="vertigo" code="399153001: Vertigo (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M32" type="Precipitant" span="67 9" str="reserpine" code="8B1QWR724A"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M31" precipitant="M17" effect="M33"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M31" precipitant="M17" effect="M24"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M31" precipitant="M17" effect="M30"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M31" precipitant="M17" effect="M27"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M31" precipitant="M17" effect="M21"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M31" precipitant="M32" effect="M21"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M31" precipitant="M32" effect="M24"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M31" precipitant="M32" effect="M27"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M31" precipitant="M32" effect="M30"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M31" precipitant="M32" effect="M33"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2563" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Calcium channel blockers may also have an additive effect when given with TENORETIC.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M36" type="SpecificInteraction" span="42 15" str="additive effect" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M35" type="Precipitant" span="0 24" str="Calcium channel blockers" code="N0000175566"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M36" precipitant="M35" effect="M36"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2564" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Disopyramide is a Type I antiarrhythmic drug with potent negative inotropic and chronotropic effects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2565" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Disopyramide has been associated with severe bradycardia, asystole and heart failure when administered with beta blockers.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M43" type="Trigger" span="22 15" str="associated with"/>
<Mention id="M44" type="Precipitant" span="0 12" str="Disopyramide" code="GFO928U8MQ"/>
<Mention id="M39" type="SpecificInteraction" span="38 18" str="severe bradycardia" code="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M42" type="SpecificInteraction" span="58 8" str="asystole" code="397829000: Asystole (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M45" type="SpecificInteraction" span="71 13" str="heart failure" code="42343007: Congestive heart failure (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M43" precipitant="M44" effect="M39"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M43" precipitant="M44" effect="M42"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M43" precipitant="M44" effect="M45"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2566" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Amiodarone is an antiarrhythmic agent with negative chronotropic properties that may be additive to those seen with beta blockers.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M46" type="Trigger" span="88 8" str="additive"/>
<Mention id="M47" type="Precipitant" span="0 10" str="Amiodarone" code="N3RQ532IUT"/>
<Mention id="M48" type="SpecificInteraction" span="43 32" str="negative chronotropic properties" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M46" precipitant="M47" effect="M48"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2567" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Thiazides may decrease arterial responsiveness to norepinephrine.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M49" type="Trigger" span="14 8;32 14" str="decrease | responsiveness"/>
<Mention id="M50" type="Precipitant" span="50 14" str="norepinephrine" code="X4W3ENH1CV"/>
<Mention id="M51" type="SpecificInteraction" span="14 50" str="decrease arterial responsiveness to norepinephrine" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M49" precipitant="M50" effect="M51"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2568" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>This diminution is not sufficient to preclude the therapeutic effectiveness of norepinephrine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2569" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Thiazides may increase the responsiveness to tubocurarine.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M52" type="Trigger" span="14 27" str="increase the responsiveness"/>
<Mention id="M53" type="Precipitant" span="45 12" str="tubocurarine" code="W9YXS298BM"/>
<Mention id="M54" type="SpecificInteraction" span="14 43" str="increase the responsiveness to tubocurarine" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M52" precipitant="M53" effect="M54"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2570" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant use of prostaglandin synthase inhibiting drugs, eg, indomethacin, may decrease the hypotensive effects of beta blockers.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M58" type="Trigger" span="82 8;107 7" str="decrease | effects"/>
<Mention id="M56" type="Precipitant" span="64 12" str="indomethacin" code="XXE1CET956"/>
<Mention id="M60" type="SpecificInteraction" span="82 49" str="decrease the hypotensive effects of beta blockers" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M59" type="Precipitant" span="19 39" str="prostaglandin synthase inhibiting drugs" code="N0000175939"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M58" precipitant="M56" effect="M60"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M58" precipitant="M59" effect="M60"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2571" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Lithium generally should not be given with diuretics because they reduce its renal clearance and add a high risk of lithium toxicity.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M61" type="Trigger" span="66 6;77 15" str="reduce | renal clearance "/>
<Mention id="M62" type="Trigger" span="103 9;124 8" str=" high risk | toxicity"/>
<Mention id="M63" type="Precipitant" span="0 7" str="Lithium" code="9FN79X2M3F"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M61;M62" precipitant="M63" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2572" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Read prescribing information for lithium preparations before use of such preparations with TENORETIC.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M64" type="Trigger" span="0 28" str="Read prescribing information"/>
<Mention id="M65" type="Precipitant" span="33 20" str="lithium preparations" code="9FN79X2M3F"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M64" precipitant="M65"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2573" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Beta blockers may exacerbate the rebound hypertension which can follow the withdrawal of clonidine.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M66" type="Trigger" span="18 10" str="exacerbate"/>
<Mention id="M67" type="Precipitant" span="89 9" str="clonidine" code="MN3L5RMN02"/>
<Mention id="M68" type="SpecificInteraction" span="33 20" str="rebound hypertension" code="84094009: Rebound hypertension (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M66" precipitant="M67" effect="M68"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2574" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>If the two drugs are coadministered, the beta blocker should be withdrawn several days before the gradual withdrawal of clonidine.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M69" type="Trigger" span="54 19;87 29" str="should be withdrawn | before the gradual withdrawal"/>
<Mention id="M70" type="Precipitant" span="120 9" str="clonidine" code="MN3L5RMN02"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M69" precipitant="M70"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2575" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>If replacing clonidine by beta-blocker therapy, the introduction of beta blockers should be delayed for several days after clonidine administration has stopped.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M71" type="Trigger" span="82 17;117 5;152 7" str="should be delayed | after | stopped"/>
<Mention id="M72" type="Precipitant" span="13 9" str="clonidine" code="MN3L5RMN02"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M71" precipitant="M72"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2576" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>While taking beta blockers, patients with a history of anaphylactic reaction to a variety of allergens may have a more severe reaction on repeated challenge, either accidental, diagnostic or therapeutic.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M73" type="Trigger" span="114 20" str="more severe reaction"/>
<Mention id="M74" type="Precipitant" span="93 9" str="allergens" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M75" type="SpecificInteraction" span="93 9;114 20" str="allergens | more severe reaction" code="419076005: Allergic reaction (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M73" precipitant="M74" effect="M75"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2577" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Such patients may be unresponsive to the usual doses of epinephrine used to treat the allergic reaction.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M76" type="Trigger" span="21 31" str="unresponsive to the usual doses"/>
<Mention id="M77" type="Precipitant" span="56 11" str="epinephrine" code="YKH834O4BH"/>
<Mention id="M78" type="SpecificInteraction" span="21 46" str="unresponsive to the usual doses of epinephrine" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M76" precipitant="M77" effect="M78"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2578" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Both digitalis glycosides and beta-blockers slow atrioventricular conduction and decrease heart rate.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M82" type="Trigger" span="0 4" str="Both"/>
<Mention id="M83" type="Precipitant" span="5 20" str="digitalis glycosides" code="F1T8QT9U8B"/>
<Mention id="M81" type="SpecificInteraction" span="44 32" str="slow atrioventricular conduction" code="233917008: Atrioventricular block (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M84" type="SpecificInteraction" span="81 19" str="decrease heart rate" code="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M82" precipitant="M83" effect="M81"/>
<Interaction id="I29" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M82" precipitant="M83" effect="M84"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2579" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant use can increase the risk of bradycardia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2580" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>TENORETIC may aggravate peripheral arterial circulatory disorders.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2581" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Periodic determination of serum electrolytes to detect possible electrolyte imbalance should be performed at appropriate intervals.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2582" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Patients should be observed for clinical signs of fluid or electrolyte imbalance; i.e., hyponatremia, hypochloremic alkalosis, and hypokalemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2583" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Serum and urine electrolyte determinations are particularly important when the patient is vomiting excessively or receiving parenteral fluids.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2584" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Warning signs or symptoms of fluid and electrolyte imbalance include dryness of the mouth, thirst, weakness, lethargy, drowsiness, restlessness, muscle pains or cramps, muscular fatigue, hypotension, oliguria, tachycardia, and gastrointestinal disturbances such as nausea and vomiting.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2585" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Measurement of potassium levels is appropriate especially in elderly patients, those receiving digitalis preparations for cardiac failure, patients whose dietary intake of potassium is abnormally low, or those suffering from gastrointestinal complaints.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2586" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Hypokalemia may develop especially with brisk diuresis, when severe cirrhosis is present, or during concomitant use of corticosteroids or ACTH.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M90" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 11" str="Hypokalemia" code="43339004: Hypokalemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M86" type="Precipitant" span="138 4" str="ACTH" code="K0U68Q2TXA"/>
<Mention id="M89" type="Precipitant" span="119 15" str="corticosteroids" code="N0000175576"/>
<Interaction id="I30" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M90" precipitant="M86" effect="M90"/>
<Interaction id="I31" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M90" precipitant="M89" effect="M90"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2587" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Interference with adequate oral electrolyte intake will also contribute to hypokalemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2588" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Hypokalemia can sensitize or exaggerate the response of the heart to the toxic effects of digitalis (eg, increased ventricular irritability).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2589" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Hypokalemia may be avoided or treated by use of potassium supplements or foods with a high potassium content.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2590" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Any chloride deficit during thiazide therapy is generally mild and usually does not require specific treatment except under extraordinary circumstances (as in liver disease or renal disease).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2591" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Dilutional hyponatremia may occur in edematous patients in hot weather; appropriate therapy is water restriction rather than administration of salt except in rare instances when the hyponatremia is life-threatening.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2592" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In actual salt depletion, appropriate replacement is the therapy of choice.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2593" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In patients receiving thiazides, sensitivity reactions may occur with or without a history of allergy or bronchial asthma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2594" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The possible exacerbation or activation of systemic lupus erythematosus has been reported.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2595" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The antihypertensive effects of thiazides may be enhanced in the postsympathectomy patient.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2596" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Two long-term (maximum dosing duration of 18 or 24 months) rat studies and one long-term (maximum dosing duration of 18 months) mouse study, each employing dose levels as high as 300 mg/kg/day or 150 times the maximum recommended human antihypertensive dose1, did not indicate a carcinogenic potential of atenolol.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2597" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>A third (24 month) rat study, employing doses of 500 and 1,500 mg/kg/day (250 and 750 times the maximum recommended human antihypertensive dose1) resulted in increased incidences of benign adrenal medullary tumors in males and females, mammary fibroadenomas in females, and anterior pituitary adenomas and thyroid parafollicular cell carcinomas in males.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2598" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>No evidence of a mutagenic potential of atenolol was uncovered in the dominant lethal test (mouse), in vivo cytogenetics test (Chinese hamster) or Ames test (S typhimurium).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2599" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Fertility of male or female rats (evaluated at dose levels as high as 200 mg/kg/day or 100 times the maximum recommended human dose1) was unaffected by atenolol administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2600" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Six month oral administration studies were conducted in rats and dogs using TENORETIC doses up to 12.5 mg/kg/day (atenolol/chlorthalidone 10/2.5 mg/kg/day -- approximately five times the maximum recommended human antihypertensive dose1).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2601" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>There were no functional or morphological abnormalities resulting from dosing either compound alone or together other than minor changes in heart rate, blood pressure and urine chemistry which were attributed to the known pharmacologic properties of atenolol and/or chlorthalidone.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2602" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Chronic studies of atenolol performed in animals have revealed the occurrence of vacuolation of epithelial cells of Brunner's glands in the duodenum of both male and female dogs at all tested dose levels (starting at 15 mg/kg/day or 7.5 times the maximum recommended human antihypertensive dose) and increased incidence of atrial degeneration of hearts of male rats at 300 but not 150 mg atenolol/kg/day (150 and 75 times the maximum recommended human antihypertensive dose, respectively).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2603" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Pregnancy Category D: See WARNINGS - Pregnancy and Fetal Injury Atenolol is excreted in human breast milk at a ratio of 1.5 to 6.8 when compared to the concentration in plasma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2604" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Caution should be exercised when atenolol is administered to a nursing woman.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2605" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Clinically significant bradycardia has been reported in breast-fed infants.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2606" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Premature infants, or infants with impaired renal function, may be more likely to develop adverse effects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2607" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Neonates born to mothers who are receiving atenolol at parturition or breast-feeding may be at risk for hypoglycemia and bradycardia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2608" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Caution should be exercised when TENORETIC is administered during pregnancy or to a woman who is breast-feeding.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2609" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Sympathetic stimulation is necessary in supporting circulatory function in congestive heart failure, and beta blockade carries the potential hazard of further depressing myocardial contractility and precipitating more severe failure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2610" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>IN PATIENTS WITHOUT A HISTORY OF CARDIAC FAILURE, continued depression of the myocardium with beta-blocking agents over a period of time can, in some cases, lead to cardiac failure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2611" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>At the first sign or symptom of impending cardiac failure, patients should be treated appropriately according to currently recommended guidelines, and the response observed closely.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2612" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>If cardiac failure continues despite adequate treatment, TENORETIC should be withdrawn.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2613" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Since atenolol is excreted via the kidneys, TENORETIC should be used with caution in patients with impaired renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2614" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>In patients with renal disease, thiazides may precipitate azotemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2615" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Since cumulative effects may develop in the presence of impaired renal function, if progressive renal impairment becomes evident, TENORETIC should be discontinued.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2616" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>In patients with impaired hepatic function or progressive liver disease, minor alterations in fluid and electrolyte balance may precipitate hepatic coma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2617" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>TENORETIC should be used with caution in these patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2618" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Following abrupt cessation of therapy with certain beta-blocking agents in patients with coronary artery disease, exacerbations of angina pectoris and, in some cases, myocardial infarction have been reported.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2619" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Therefore, such patients should be cautioned against interruption of therapy without the physician's advice.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2620" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Even in the absence of overt angina pectoris, when discontinuation of TENORETIC is planned, the patient should be carefully observed and should be advised to limit physical activity to a minimum.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2621" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>TENORETIC should be reinstated if withdrawal symptoms occur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2622" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Because coronary artery disease is common and may be unrecognized, it may be prudent not to discontinue TENORETIC therapy abruptly even in patients treated only for hypertension.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2623" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Bradycardia and heart block can occur and the left ventricular end diastolic pressure can rise when beta-blockers are administered with verapamil or diltiazem.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M116" type="Trigger" span="0 11" str="Bradycardia "/>
<Mention id="M117" type="Trigger" span="16 11" str=" heart block "/>
<Mention id="M118" type="Trigger" span="46 48" str=" left ventricular end diastolic pressure can rise"/>
<Mention id="M104" type="Precipitant" span="149 9" str="diltiazem" code="EE92BBP03H"/>
<Mention id="M120" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 11" str="Bradycardia" code="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M110" type="SpecificInteraction" span="46 48" str="left ventricular end diastolic pressure can rise" code="23154005: Increased diastolic arterial pressure (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M115" type="SpecificInteraction" span="16 11" str="heart block" code="233916004: Heart block (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M119" type="Precipitant" span="136 9" str="verapamil" code="CJ0O37KU29"/>
<Interaction id="I32" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M116;M117;M118" precipitant="M104" effect="M120"/>
<Interaction id="I33" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M116;M117;M118" precipitant="M104" effect="M110"/>
<Interaction id="I34" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M116;M117;M118" precipitant="M104" effect="M115"/>
<Interaction id="I35" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M116;M117;M118" precipitant="M119" effect="M110"/>
<Interaction id="I36" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M116;M117;M118" precipitant="M119" effect="M115"/>
<Interaction id="I37" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M116;M117;M118" precipitant="M119" effect="M120"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2624" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Patients with pre-existing conduction abnormalities or left ventricular dysfunction are particularly susceptible.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2625" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>PATIENTS WITH BRONCHOSPASTIC DISEASE SHOULD, IN GENERAL, NOT RECEIVE BETA BLOCKERS.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2626" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Because of its relative beta1-selectivity, however, TENORETIC may be used with caution in patients with bronchospastic disease who do not respond to or cannot tolerate, other antihypertensive treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2627" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Since beta1-selectivity is not absolute, the lowest possible dose of TENORETIC should be used and a beta2-stimulating agent (bronchodilator) should be made available.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2628" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>If dosage must be increased, dividing the dose should be considered in order to achieve lower peak blood levels.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2629" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Chronically administered beta-blocking therapy should not be routinely withdrawn prior to major surgery, however the impaired ability of the heart to respond to reflex adrenergic stimuli may augment the risks of general anesthesia and surgical procedures.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M121" type="Trigger" span="191 17" str="augment the risks"/>
<Mention id="M122" type="Precipitant" span="212 18" str="general anesthesia" code="N0000175681"/>
<Mention id="M123" type="SpecificInteraction" span="191 39" str="augment the risks of general anesthesia" code="736523005: At risk of complication of anesthesia (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I38" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M121" precipitant="M122" effect="M123"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2630" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>TENORETIC may be used with caution in diabetic patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2631" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Beta blockers may mask tachycardia occurring with hypoglycemia, but other manifestations such as dizziness and sweating may not be significantly affected.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2632" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>At recommended doses atenolol does not potentiate insulin-induced hypoglycemia and, unlike nonselective beta blockers, does not delay recovery of blood glucose to normal levels.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2633" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Insulin requirements in diabetic patients may be increased, decreased or unchanged; latent diabetes mellitus may become manifest during chlorthalidone administration.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M126" type="SpecificInteraction" span="84 44" str="latent diabetes mellitus may become manifest" code="73211009: Diabetes mellitus (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M125" type="Precipitant" span="136 14" str="chlorthalidone" code="Q0MQD1073Q"/>
<Mention id="M127" type="Trigger" span="8 12;49 33" str="requirements | increased, decreased or unchanged"/>
<Mention id="M128" type="Precipitant" span="0 7" str="Insulin" code="N0000175944"/>
<Interaction id="I39" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M126" precipitant="M125" effect="M126"/>
<Interaction id="I40" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M127" precipitant="M128"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2634" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Beta-adrenergic blockade may mask certain clinical signs (eg, tachycardia) of hyperthyroidism.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2635" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Abrupt withdrawal of beta blockade might precipitate a thyroid storm; therefore, patients suspected of developing thyrotoxicosis from whom TENORETIC therapy is to be withdrawn should be monitored closely.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2636" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Because calcium excretion is decreased by thiazides, TENORETIC should be discontinued before carrying out tests for parathyroid function.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M129" type="Trigger" span="63 29" str="should be discontinued before"/>
<Mention id="M130" type="Precipitant" span="106 30" str="tests for parathyroid function" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I41" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M129" precipitant="M130"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2637" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Pathologic changes in the parathyroid glands, with hypercalcemia and hypophosphatemia, have been observed in a few patients on prolonged thiazide therapy; however, the common complications of hyperparathyroidism such as renal lithiasis, bone resorption, and peptic ulceration have not been seen.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2638" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Hyperuricemia may occur, or acute gout may be precipitated in certain patients receiving thiazide therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2639" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>TENORETIC should not be given to patients with untreated pheochromocytoma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2640" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Atenolol and chlorthalidone have been used singly and concomitantly for the treatment of hypertension.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2641" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The antihypertensive effects of these agents are additive, and studies have shown that there is no interference with bioavailability when these agents are given together in the single combination tablet.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2642" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Therefore, this combination provides a convenient formulation for the concomitant administration of these two entities.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2643" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In patients with more severe hypertension, TENORETIC may be administered with other antihypertensives such as vasodilators.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2644" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Atenolol is a beta1-selective (cardioselective) beta-adrenergic receptor blocking agent without membrane stabilizing or intrinsic sympathomimetic (partial agonist) activities.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2645" LabelDrug="TENORETIC" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This preferential effect is not absolute, however, and at higher doses, atenolol inhibits beta2-adrenoreceptors, chiefly located in the bronchial and vascular musculature.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="antihypertensive agents" precipitantCode="N0000178477" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="catecholamine depletor" precipitantCode="N0000175640" effect="271594007: Syncope (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="catecholamine depletor" precipitantCode="N0000175640" effect="28651003: Orthostatic hypotension (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="catecholamine depletor" precipitantCode="N0000175640" effect="399153001: Vertigo (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="catecholamine depletor" precipitantCode="N0000175640" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="catecholamine depletor" precipitantCode="N0000175640" effect="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="reserpine" precipitantCode="8B1QWR724A" effect="271594007: Syncope (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="reserpine" precipitantCode="8B1QWR724A" effect="28651003: Orthostatic hypotension (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="reserpine" precipitantCode="8B1QWR724A" effect="399153001: Vertigo (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="reserpine" precipitantCode="8B1QWR724A" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="reserpine" precipitantCode="8B1QWR724A" effect="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="calcium channel blockers" precipitantCode="N0000175566" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="disopyramide" precipitantCode="GFO928U8MQ" effect="397829000: Asystole (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="disopyramide" precipitantCode="GFO928U8MQ" effect="42343007: Congestive heart failure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="disopyramide" precipitantCode="GFO928U8MQ" effect="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="amiodarone" precipitantCode="N3RQ532IUT" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="norepinephrine" precipitantCode="X4W3ENH1CV" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="tubocurarine" precipitantCode="W9YXS298BM" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="indomethacin" precipitantCode="XXE1CET956" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="prostaglandin synthase inhibiting drugs" precipitantCode="N0000175939" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="lithium" precipitantCode="9FN79X2M3F" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="lithium preparations" precipitantCode="9FN79X2M3F"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="clonidine" precipitantCode="MN3L5RMN02" effect="84094009: Rebound hypertension (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="clonidine" precipitantCode="MN3L5RMN02"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="allergens" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="419076005: Allergic reaction (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="epinephrine" precipitantCode="YKH834O4BH" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="digitalis glycosides" precipitantCode="F1T8QT9U8B" effect="233917008: Atrioventricular block (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="digitalis glycosides" precipitantCode="F1T8QT9U8B" effect="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="acth" precipitantCode="K0U68Q2TXA" effect="43339004: Hypokalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="corticosteroids" precipitantCode="N0000175576" effect="43339004: Hypokalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="diltiazem" precipitantCode="EE92BBP03H" effect="23154005: Increased diastolic arterial pressure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="diltiazem" precipitantCode="EE92BBP03H" effect="233916004: Heart block (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="diltiazem" precipitantCode="EE92BBP03H" effect="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="verapamil" precipitantCode="CJ0O37KU29" effect="23154005: Increased diastolic arterial pressure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="verapamil" precipitantCode="CJ0O37KU29" effect="233916004: Heart block (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="verapamil" precipitantCode="CJ0O37KU29" effect="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="general anesthesia" precipitantCode="N0000175681" effect="736523005: At risk of complication of anesthesia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="chlorthalidone" precipitantCode="Q0MQD1073Q" effect="73211009: Diabetes mellitus (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="insulin" precipitantCode="N0000175944"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="tests for parathyroid function" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>