<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="THALITONE" setid="e2eb7dad-3ea3-439c-dcbb-d1d61aa49dfc">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
Anuria. Known hypersensitivity to chlorthalidone or other sulfonamide-derived drugs.</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
Therapy should be initiated with the lowest possible dose, then titrated according to individual patient response. A single dose given in the morning with food is recommended; divided doses are unnecessary.  Hypertension  Therapy in most patients should be initiated with a single daily dose of 15 mg. If the response is insufficient after a suitable trial, the dosage may be increased to 30 mg and then to a single daily dose of 45-50 mg. If additional control is required, the addition of a second antihypertensive drug is recommended. Increases in serum uric acid and decreases in serum potassium are dose-related over the 15-50 mg/day range and beyond.  Edema  INITIATION: Adults, initially 30 to 60 mg daily or 60 mg on alternate days. Some patients may require 90 to 120 mg at these intervals or up to 120 mg daily. Dosages above this level, however, do not usually produce a greater response. MAINTENANCE: Maintenance doses may often be lower than initial doses and should be adjusted according to the individual patient. Effectiveness is well sustained during continued use.</Section>
<Section name="PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="42232-9">
General Hypokalemia and other electrolyte abnormalities, including hyponatremia and hypochloremic alkalosis, are common in patients receiving chlorthalidone. These abnormalities are dose-related but may occur even at the lowest marketed doses of chlorthalidone. Serum electrolytes should be determined before initiating therapy and at periodic intervals during therapy. Serum and urine electrolyte determinations are particularly important when the patient is vomiting excessively or receiving parenteral fluids. All patients taking chlorthalidone should be observed for clinical signs of electrolyte imbalance, including dryness of mouth, thirst, weakness, lethargy, drowsiness, restlessness, muscle pains or cramps, muscular fatigue, hypotension, oliguria, tachycardia, palpitations and gastrointestinal disturbances, such as nausea and vomiting. Digitalis therapy may exaggerate metabolic effects of hypokalemia especially with reference to myocardial activity. Any chloride deficit is generally mild and usually does not require specific treatment except under extraordinary circumstances (as in liver disease or renal disease). Dilutional hyponatremia may occur in edematous patients in hot weather; appropriate therapy is water restriction, rather than administration of salt, except in rare instances when the hyponatremia is life-threatening. In cases of actual salt depletion, appropriate replacement is the therapy of choice. Thiazide-like diuretics have been shown to increase the urinary excretion of magnesium; this may result in hypomagnesemia.  Calcium excretion is decreased by thiazide-like drugs. Pathological changes in the parathyroid gland with hypercalcemia and hypophosphatemia have been observed in a few patients on thiazide therapy. The common complications of hyperparathyroidism such as renal lithiasis, bone resorption and peptic ulceration have not been seen.   Uric Acid  Hyperuricemia may occur or frank gout may be precipitated in certain patients receiving chlorthalidone.   Other Increases in serum glucose may occur and latent diabetes mellitus may become manifest during chlorthalidone therapy (see  PRECAUTIONS Drug Interactions ). Chlorthalidone and related drugs may decrease serum PBI levels without signs of thyroid disturbance.  Information For Patients Patients should inform their doctor if they have: 1) had an allergic reaction to chlorthalidone or other diuretics or have asthma 2) kidney disease 3) liver disease 4) gout 5) systemic lupus erythematosus, or 6) been taking other drugs such as cortisone, digitalis, lithium carbonate, or drugs for diabetes. Patients should be cautioned to contact their physician if they experience any of the following symptoms of potassium loss: excess thirst, tiredness, drowsiness, restlessness, muscle pains or cramps, nausea, vomiting or increased heart rate or pulse.  Patients should also be cautioned that taking alcohol can increase the chance of dizziness occurring.   Laboratory Tests Periodic determination of serum electrolytes to detect possible electrolyte imbalance should be performed at appropriate intervals.  All patients receiving chlorthalidone should be observed for clinical signs of fluid or electrolyte imbalance: namely, hyponatremia, hypochloremic alkalosis and hypokalemia. Serum and urine electrolyte determinations are particularly important when the patient is vomiting excessively or receiving parenteral fluids.  Drug Interactions Chlorthalidone may add to or potentiate the action of other antihypertensive drugs.  Insulin requirements in diabetic patients may be increased, decreased or unchanged. Higher dosage of oral hypoglycemic agents may be required.  Chlorthalidone and related drugs may increase the responsiveness to tubocurarine.  Chlorthalidone and related drugs may decrease arterial responsiveness to norepinephrine. This diminution is not sufficient to preclude effectiveness of the pressor agent for therapeutic use.  Lithium renal clearance is reduced by chlorthalidone, increasing the risk of lithium toxicity.  Drug/Laboratory Test Interactions Chlorthalidone and related drugs may decrease serum PBI levels without signs of thyroid disturbance.  Carcinogenesis, Mutagenesis, Impairment of Fertility No information is available.   Pregnancy/Teratogenic Effects  PREGNANCY CATEGORY B: Reproduction studies have been performed in the rat and the rabbit at doses up to 420 times the human dose and have revealed no evidence of harm to the fetus due to chlorthalidone. There are, however, no adequate and well-controlled studies in pregnant women. Because animal reproduction studies are not always predictive of human response, this drug should be used during pregnancy only if clearly needed.  Pregnancy/Non-Teratogenic Effects Thiazides cross the placental barrier and appear in cord blood. The use of chlorthalidone and related drugs in pregnant women requires that the anticipated benefits of the drug be weighed against possible hazards to the fetus. These hazards include fetal or neonatal jaundice, thrombocytopenia, and possibly other adverse reactions that have occurred in the adult.   Nursing Mothers  Thiazides are excreted in human milk. Because of the potential for serious adverse reactions in nursing infants from chlorthalidone, a decision should be made whether to discontinue nursing or to discontinue the drug, taking into account the importance of the drug to the mother.  Pediatric Use  Safety and effectiveness in children have not been established.   Geriatric Use Clinical studies of Thalitone® did not include sufficient numbers of subjects aged 65 and over to determine whether they respond differently from younger subjects. Other reported clinical experience has not identified differences in responses between the elderly and younger patients. In general, dose selection for an elderly patient should be cautious, usually starting at the low end of the dosing range, reflecting the greater frequency of decreased hepatic, renal or cardiac function, and of concomitant disease or other drug therapy. This drug is known to be substantially excreted by the kidney, and the risk of toxic reactions to this drug may be greater in patients with impaired renal function. Because elderly patients are more likely to have decreased renal function, care should be taken in dose selection, and it may be useful to monitor renal function.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS SECTION" id="34071-1">
Thalitone® (chlorthalidone USP) should be used with caution in severe renal disease. In patients with renal disease, chlorthalidone or related drugs may precipitate azotemia. Cumulative effects of the drug may develop in patients with impaired renal function. Chlorthalidone should be used with caution in patients with impaired hepatic function or progressive liver disease, because minor alterations of fluid and electrolyte balance may precipitate hepatic coma.  Sensitivity reactions may occur in patients with a history of allergy or bronchial asthma.  The possibility of exacerbation or activation of systemic lupus erythematosus has been reported with thiazide diuretics which are structurally related to chlorthalidone. However, systemic lupus erythematosus has not been reported following chlorthalidone administration.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Chlorthalidone is a long-acting oral diuretic with antihypertensive activity. Its diuretic action commences a mean of 2.6 hours after dosing and continues for up to 72 hours. The drug produces diuresis with increased excretion of sodium and chloride. The diuretic effects of chlorthalidone and the benzothiadiazine (thiazide) diuretics appear to arise from similar mechanisms and the maximal effect of chlorthalidone and the thiazides appear to be similar. The site of the action appears to be the distal convoluted tubule of the nephron. The diuretic effects of chlorthalidone lead to decreased extracellular fluid volume, plasma volume, cardiac output, total exchangeable sodium, glomerular filtration rate, and renal plasma flow. Although the mechanism of action of chlorthalidone and related drugs is not wholly clear, sodium and water depletion appear to provide a basis for its antihypertensive effect. Like the thiazide diuretics, chlorthalidone produces dose-related reductions in serum potassium levels, elevations in serum uric acid and blood glucose, and it can lead to decreased sodium and chloride levels. The mean plasma half-life of chlorthalidone is about 40 to 60 hours. It is eliminated primarily as unchanged drug in the urine. Non-renal routes of elimination have yet to be clarified. In the blood, approximately 75% of the drug is bound to plasma proteins. Thalitone® (chlorthalidone USP) has been formulated with PVP (povidone polyvinylpyrrolidone), a bioavailability enhancer that provides 104% to 116% bioavailability relative to an oral solution of chlorthalidone. Thalitone® cannot be substituted for other formulations of chlorthalidone and likewise, other formulations of chlorthalidone cannot be substituted for Thalitone®.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="5908" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Known hypersensitivity to chlorthalidone or other sulfonamide-derived drugs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5909" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Therapy should be initiated with the lowest possible dose, then titrated according to individual patient response.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5910" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>A single dose given in the morning with food is recommended; divided doses are unnecessary.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5911" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Hypertension Therapy in most patients should be initiated with a single daily dose of 15 mg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5912" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If the response is insufficient after a suitable trial, the dosage may be increased to 30 mg and then to a single daily dose of 45-50 mg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5913" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If additional control is required, the addition of a second antihypertensive drug is recommended.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5914" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Increases in serum uric acid and decreases in serum potassium are dose-related over the 15-50 mg/day range and beyond.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5915" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Edema INITIATION: Adults, initially 30 to 60 mg daily or 60 mg on alternate days.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5916" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Some patients may require 90 to 120 mg at these intervals or up to 120 mg daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5917" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dosages above this level, however, do not usually produce a greater response.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5918" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>MAINTENANCE: Maintenance doses may often be lower than initial doses and should be adjusted according to the individual patient.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5919" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Effectiveness is well sustained during continued use.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5920" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>GeneralHypokalemia and other electrolyte abnormalities, including hyponatremia and hypochloremic alkalosis, are common in patients receiving chlorthalidone.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5921" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>These abnormalities are dose-related but may occur even at the lowest marketed doses of chlorthalidone.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5922" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Serum electrolytes should be determined before initiating therapy and at periodic intervals during therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5923" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Serum and urine electrolyte determinations are particularly important when the patient is vomiting excessively or receiving parenteral fluids.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M1" type="Trigger" span="28 41" str="determinations are particularly important"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="124 17" str="parenteral fluids" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M3" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 42" str="Serum and urine electrolyte determinations" code="166686006: Electrolytes abnormal (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M1" precipitant="M2" effect="M3"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5924" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>All patients taking chlorthalidone should be observed for clinical signs of electrolyte imbalance, including dryness of mouth, thirst, weakness, lethargy, drowsiness, restlessness, muscle pains or cramps, muscular fatigue, hypotension, oliguria, tachycardia, palpitations and gastrointestinal disturbances, such as nausea and vomiting.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5925" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Digitalis therapy may exaggerate metabolic effects of hypokalemia especially with reference to myocardial activity.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M7" type="Trigger" span="22 10;43 7" str="exaggerate | effects"/>
<Mention id="M8" type="Precipitant" span="0 9" str="Digitalis" code="F1T8QT9U8B"/>
<Mention id="M6" type="SpecificInteraction" span="33 32" str="metabolic effects of hypokalemia" code="43339004: Hypokalemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M9" type="SpecificInteraction" span="95 19" str="myocardial activity" code="57809008: Myocardial disease (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M7" precipitant="M8" effect="M6"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M7" precipitant="M8" effect="M9"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5926" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Any chloride deficit is generally mild and usually does not require specific treatment except under extraordinary circumstances (as in liver disease or renal disease).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5927" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Dilutional hyponatremia may occur in edematous patients in hot weather; appropriate therapy is water restriction, rather than administration of salt, except in rare instances when the hyponatremia is life-threatening.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5928" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In cases of actual salt depletion, appropriate replacement is the therapy of choice.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5929" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Thiazide-like diuretics have been shown to increase the urinary excretion of magnesium; this may result in hypomagnesemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5930" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Calcium excretion is decreased by thiazide-like drugs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5931" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Pathological changes in the parathyroid gland with hypercalcemia and hypophosphatemia have been observed in a few patients on thiazide therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5932" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The common complications of hyperparathyroidism such as renal lithiasis, bone resorption and peptic ulceration have not been seen.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5933" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Uric Acid Hyperuricemia may occur or frank gout may be precipitated in certain patients receiving chlorthalidone.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5934" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Other Increases in serum glucose may occur and latent diabetes mellitus may become manifest during chlorthalidone therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5935" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Chlorthalidone and related drugs may decrease serum PBI levels without signs of thyroid disturbance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5936" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Information For Patients Patients should inform their doctor if they have: 1) had an allergic reaction to chlorthalidone or other diuretics or have asthma 2) kidney disease 3) liver disease 4) gout 5) systemic lupus erythematosus, or 6) been taking other drugs such as cortisone, digitalis, lithium carbonate, or drugs for diabetes.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M16" type="Trigger" span="25 48;237 11" str="Patients should inform their doctor if they have | been taking"/>
<Mention id="M11" type="Precipitant" span="269 9" str="cortisone" code="V27W9254FZ"/>
<Mention id="M13" type="Precipitant" span="280 9" str="digitalis" code="F1T8QT9U8B"/>
<Mention id="M15" type="Precipitant" span="313 18" str="drugs for diabetes" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M17" type="Precipitant" span="291 17" str="lithium carbonate" code="2BMD2GNA4V"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M16" precipitant="M11"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M16" precipitant="M13"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M16" precipitant="M15"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M16" precipitant="M17"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5937" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Patients should be cautioned to contact their physician if they experience any of the following symptoms of potassium loss: excess thirst, tiredness, drowsiness, restlessness, muscle pains or cramps, nausea, vomiting or increased heart rate or pulse.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5938" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Patients should also be cautioned that taking alcohol can increase the chance of dizziness occurring.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M18" type="Trigger" span="58 19" str="increase the chance"/>
<Mention id="M19" type="Precipitant" span="46 7" str="alcohol" code="3K9958V90M"/>
<Mention id="M20" type="SpecificInteraction" span="81 9" str="dizziness" code="404640003: Dizziness (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M18" precipitant="M19" effect="M20"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5939" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Laboratory Tests Periodic determination of serum electrolytes to detect possible electrolyte imbalance should be performed at appropriate intervals.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5940" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>All patients receiving chlorthalidone should be observed for clinical signs of fluid or electrolyte imbalance: namely, hyponatremia, hypochloremic alkalosis and hypokalemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5941" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Drug Interactions Chlorthalidone may add to or potentiate the action of other antihypertensive drugs.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M21" type="Trigger" span="37 20" str="add to or potentiate"/>
<Mention id="M22" type="Precipitant" span="78 22" str="antihypertensive drugs" code="N0000178477"/>
<Mention id="M23" type="SpecificInteraction" span="37 20;78 16" str="add to or potentiate | antihypertensive" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M21" precipitant="M22" effect="M23"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5942" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Insulin requirements in diabetic patients may be increased, decreased or unchanged.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M24" type="Trigger" span="8 12;49 33" str="requirements | increased, decreased or unchanged"/>
<Mention id="M25" type="Precipitant" span="0 7" str="Insulin" code="N0000175944"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M24" precipitant="M25"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5943" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Higher dosage of oral hypoglycemic agents may be required.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M26" type="Trigger" span="0 13" str="Higher dosage"/>
<Mention id="M27" type="Precipitant" span="17 24" str="oral hypoglycemic agents" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M26" precipitant="M27" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5944" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Chlorthalidone and related drugs may increase the responsiveness to tubocurarine.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M28" type="Trigger" span="37 27" str="increase the responsiveness"/>
<Mention id="M29" type="Precipitant" span="68 12" str="tubocurarine" code="W9YXS298BM"/>
<Mention id="M30" type="SpecificInteraction" span="37 43" str="increase the responsiveness to tubocurarine" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M28" precipitant="M29" effect="M30"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5945" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Chlorthalidone and related drugs may decrease arterial responsiveness to norepinephrine.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M31" type="Trigger" span="37 8;55 14" str="decrease | responsiveness"/>
<Mention id="M32" type="Precipitant" span="73 14" str="norepinephrine" code="X4W3ENH1CV"/>
<Mention id="M33" type="SpecificInteraction" span="37 32" str="decrease arterial responsiveness" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M31" precipitant="M32" effect="M33"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5946" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>This diminution is not sufficient to preclude effectiveness of the pressor agent for therapeutic use.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5947" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Lithium renal clearance is reduced by chlorthalidone, increasing the risk of lithium toxicity.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M34" type="Trigger" span="8 26" str="renal clearance is reduced "/>
<Mention id="M35" type="Trigger" span="85 8" str=" toxicity"/>
<Mention id="M36" type="Precipitant" span="77 7" str="lithium" code="9FN79X2M3F"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M34;M35" precipitant="M36" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5948" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Drug/Laboratory Test Interactions Chlorthalidone and related drugs may decrease serum PBI levels without signs of thyroid disturbance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5949" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Carcinogenesis, Mutagenesis, Impairment of Fertility No information is available.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5950" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Pregnancy/Teratogenic Effects PREGNANCY CATEGORY B: Reproduction studies have been performed in the rat and the rabbit at doses up to 420 times the human dose and have revealed no evidence of harm to the fetus due to chlorthalidone.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5951" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>There are, however, no adequate and well-controlled studies in pregnant women.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5952" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because animal reproduction studies are not always predictive of human response, this drug should be used during pregnancy only if clearly needed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5953" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Pregnancy/Non-Teratogenic Effects Thiazides cross the placental barrier and appear in cord blood.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5954" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The use of chlorthalidone and related drugs in pregnant women requires that the anticipated benefits of the drug be weighed against possible hazards to the fetus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5955" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>These hazards include fetal or neonatal jaundice, thrombocytopenia, and possibly other adverse reactions that have occurred in the adult.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5956" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Nursing Mothers Thiazides are excreted in human milk.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5957" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because of the potential for serious adverse reactions in nursing infants from chlorthalidone, a decision should be made whether to discontinue nursing or to discontinue the drug, taking into account the importance of the drug to the mother.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5958" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Pediatric Use Safety and effectiveness in children have not been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5959" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Geriatric Use Clinical studies of Thalitone® did not include sufficient numbers of subjects aged 65 and over to determine whether they respond differently from younger subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5960" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Other reported clinical experience has not identified differences in responses between the elderly and younger patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5961" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In general, dose selection for an elderly patient should be cautious, usually starting at the low end of the dosing range, reflecting the greater frequency of decreased hepatic, renal or cardiac function, and of concomitant disease or other drug therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5962" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>This drug is known to be substantially excreted by the kidney, and the risk of toxic reactions to this drug may be greater in patients with impaired renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5963" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because elderly patients are more likely to have decreased renal function, care should be taken in dose selection, and it may be useful to monitor renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5964" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Thalitone® (chlorthalidone USP) should be used with caution in severe renal disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5965" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>In patients with renal disease, chlorthalidone or related drugs may precipitate azotemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5966" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Cumulative effects of the drug may develop in patients with impaired renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5967" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Chlorthalidone should be used with caution in patients with impaired hepatic function or progressive liver disease, because minor alterations of fluid and electrolyte balance may precipitate hepatic coma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5968" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Sensitivity reactions may occur in patients with a history of allergy or bronchial asthma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5969" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The possibility of exacerbation or activation of systemic lupus erythematosus has been reported with thiazide diuretics which are structurally related to chlorthalidone.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5970" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>However, systemic lupus erythematosus has not been reported following chlorthalidone administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5971" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Chlorthalidone is a long-acting oral diuretic with antihypertensive activity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5972" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Its diuretic action commences a mean of 2.6 hours after dosing and continues for up to 72 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5973" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The drug produces diuresis with increased excretion of sodium and chloride.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5974" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The diuretic effects of chlorthalidone and the benzothiadiazine (thiazide) diuretics appear to arise from similar mechanisms and the maximal effect of chlorthalidone and the thiazides appear to be similar.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5975" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The site of the action appears to be the distal convoluted tubule of the nephron.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5976" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The diuretic effects of chlorthalidone lead to decreased extracellular fluid volume, plasma volume, cardiac output, total exchangeable sodium, glomerular filtration rate, and renal plasma flow.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5977" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Although the mechanism of action of chlorthalidone and related drugs is not wholly clear, sodium and water depletion appear to provide a basis for its antihypertensive effect.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5978" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Like the thiazide diuretics, chlorthalidone produces dose-related reductions in serum potassium levels, elevations in serum uric acid and blood glucose, and it can lead to decreased sodium and chloride levels.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5979" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mean plasma half-life of chlorthalidone is about 40 to 60 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5980" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>It is eliminated primarily as unchanged drug in the urine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5981" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Non-renal routes of elimination have yet to be clarified.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5982" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In the blood, approximately 75% of the drug is bound to plasma proteins.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5983" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Thalitone® (chlorthalidone USP) has been formulated with PVP (povidone polyvinylpyrrolidone), a bioavailability enhancer that provides 104% to 116% bioavailability relative to an oral solution of chlorthalidone.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5984" LabelDrug="THALITONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Thalitone® cannot be substituted for other formulations of chlorthalidone and likewise, other formulations of chlorthalidone cannot be substituted for Thalitone®.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="parenteral fluids" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="166686006: Electrolytes abnormal (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="digitalis" precipitantCode="F1T8QT9U8B" effect="43339004: Hypokalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="digitalis" precipitantCode="F1T8QT9U8B" effect="57809008: Myocardial disease (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="digitalis" precipitantCode="F1T8QT9U8B"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="cortisone" precipitantCode="V27W9254FZ"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="drugs for diabetes" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="lithium carbonate" precipitantCode="2BMD2GNA4V"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="alcohol" precipitantCode="3K9958V90M" effect="404640003: Dizziness (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="antihypertensive drugs" precipitantCode="N0000178477" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="insulin" precipitantCode="N0000175944"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="oral hypoglycemic agents" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="tubocurarine" precipitantCode="W9YXS298BM" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="norepinephrine" precipitantCode="X4W3ENH1CV" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="lithium" precipitantCode="9FN79X2M3F" effect="C54357"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>