<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Thiola" setid="494a714e-923c-cd57-df6c-12886afb265a">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
The use of THIOLA® during pregnancy is contraindicated, except in those with severe cystinuria where the anticipated benefit of inhibited stone formation clearly outweighs possible hazards of treatment (see PRECAUTIONS). THIOLA® should not be begun again in patients with a prior history of developing agranulocytosis, aplastic anemia or thrombocytopenia on this medication. Mothers maintained on THIOLA® treatment should not nurse their infants.</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
It is recommended that a conservative treatment program should be attempted first. At least 3 liters of fluid (10-10 oz. glassfuls) should be provided, including two glasses with each meal and at bedtime. The patients should be expected to awake at night to urinate; they should drink two more glasses of fluids before returning to bed. Additional fluids should be consumed if there is excessive sweating or intestinal fluid loss. A minimum urine output of 2 liters/day on a consistent basis should be sought. A modest amount of alkali should be provided in order to maintain urinary pH at a high normal range (6.5-7.0). Potassium alkali are advantageous over sodium alkali, because they do not cause hypercalciuria and are less likely to cause the complication of calcium stones. Excessive alkali therapy is not advisable. When urinary pH increases above 7.0 with alkali therapy, the complication of calcium phosphate nephrolithiasis may ensue because of the enhanced urinary supersaturation of hydroxyapatite in an alkaline environment. In patients who continue to form cystine stones on the above conservative program, THIOLA® may be added to the treatment program. THIOLA® may also be substituted for d-penicillamine in patients who have developed toxicity to the latter drug. In both situations, the conservative treatment program should be continued. The dose of THIOLA® should not be arbitrary but should be based on that amount required to reduce urinary cystine concentration to below its solubility limit (generally &amp;lt;250 mg/liter). The extent of the decline in cystine excretion is generally dependent on the THIOLA® dosage. THIOLA® may be begun at a dosage of 800 mg/day in adult patients with cystine stones. In a multiclinic trial, average dose of THIOLA® was about 1000 mg/day. However, some patients require a smaller dose. In children, initial dosage may be based on 15 mg/kg/day. Urinary cystine should be measured at 1 month after THIOLA® treatment, and every 3 months thereafter. THIOLA® dosage should be readjusted depending on the urinary cystine value. Whenever possible, THIOLA® should be given in divided doses 3 times/day at least one hour before or 2 hours after meals. In patients who had shown severe toxicity to d-penicillamine, THIOLA® might be begun at a lower dosage.</Section>
<Section name="PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="42232-9">
Patients should be advised of the potential development of complications and to report promptly the occurrence of any symptom or sign of them. To help monitor potential complications, the following tests are recommended: peripheral blood counts, direct platelet count, hemoglobin, serum albumin, liver function tests, 24-hour urinary protein and routine urinalysis at 3- 6 month intervals during treatment. In order to assess effect on stone disease, urinary cystine analysis should be monitored frequently during the first 6 months when the optimum dose schedule is being determined, and at 6-month intervals thereafter. Abdominal roentogenogram (KUB) is advised on a yearly basis to monitor the size and appearance/disappearance of stone(s).   CARCINOGENESIS, MUTAGENESIS, IMPAIRMENT OF FERTILITY: Long-term carcino-genicity studies in animals have not been performed. High doses of THIOLA® in experimental animals have been shown to interfere with maintenance of pregnancy and viability of the fetus.  USE IN PREGNANCY: Pregnancy category C. D-penicillamine has been shown to cause skeletal defects and cleft palates in the fetus when given to pregnant rats at 10 times the dose recommended for human use. A similar teratogenicity might be expected for THIOLA® although no such findings could be related to the drug in studies in mice and rats at doses up to 10 times the highest recommended human dose.There are no adequate and well-controlled studies in pregnant women. THIOLA® should be used during pregnancy only if the potential benefit justifies potential risk to the fetus.  NURSING MOTHERS: Because THIOLA® may be excreted in milk and because of the potential serious adverse reactions of nursing infants from THIOLA®, mothers taking THIOLA® should not nurse their infants.  PEDIATRIC USE: Safety and effectiveness below the age of 9 have not been established.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS SECTION" id="34071-1">
Despite apparent lower toxicity of THIOLA™, THIOLA® may potentially cause all the serious adverse reactions reported for d-penicillamine. Thus, although no death has been reported to result directly from THIOLA® treatment, a fatal outcome from THIOLA® is possible, as has been reported with d-penicillamine therapy from such complications as aplastic anemia, agranulocytosis, thrombocytopenia, Goodpasture’s syndrome or myasthenia gravis. Leukopenia of the granulocytic series may develop without eosinophilia. Thrombocytopenia may be immunologic in origin or occur on an idiosyncratic basis. The reduction in peripheral blood white count to less than 3500/cubic mm or in platelet count to below 100,000 cubic mm mandates cessation of therapy. Patients should be instructed to report promptly the occurrence of any symptom or sign of these hematological abnormalities, such as fever, sore throat, chills, bleeding or easy bruisability. Proteinuria, sometimes sufficiently severe to cause nephrotic syndrome, may develop from membranous glomerulopathy. A close observation of affected patients is mandatory. The following complications, though rare, have been reported during d-penicillamine therapy and could occur during THIOLA® treatment. When there are abnormal urinary findings associated with hemoptysis and pulmonary infiltrates suggestive of Goodpasture’s syndrome, THIOLA® treatment should be stopped. Appearance of myasthenic syndrome or myasthenia gravis requires cessation of treatment. When pemphigus-type reactions develop, THIOLA® therapy should be stopped. Steroid treatment may be necessary.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
THIOLA® is an active reducing agent which undergoes thiol-disulfide exchange with cystine to form a mixed disulfide of Thiola-cysteine.  From this reaction, a water-soluble mixed disulfide is formed and the amount of sparingly soluble cystine is reduced. When THIOLA® is given orally, up to 48% of dose appears in urine during the first 4 hours and up to 78% by 72 hours. Thus, in patients with cystinuria, sufficient amount of THIOLA® or its active metabolites could appear in urine to react with cystine, lowering cystine excretion. The decrement in urinary cystine produced by THIOLA® is generally proportional to the dose. A reduction in urinary cystine of 250-350 mg/day at a THIOLA® dosage of 1 g/day, and a decline of approximately 500 mg/day at a dosage of 2 g/day, might be expected. THIOLA® causes a sustained reduction in cystine excretion without apparent loss of effectiveness. THIOLA® has a rapid onset and offset of action, showing a fall in cystine excretion on the first day of administration and a rise on the first day of drug withdrawal.     thiola-formula</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="4881" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>The use of THIOLA® during pregnancy is contraindicated, except in those with severe cystinuria where the anticipated benefit of inhibited stone formation clearly outweighs possible hazards of treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4882" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>THIOLA® should not be begun again in patients with a prior history of developing agranulocytosis, aplastic anemia or thrombocytopenia on this medication.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4883" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Mothers maintained on THIOLA® treatment should not nurse their infants.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4884" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>It is recommended that a conservative treatment program should be attempted first.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4885" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>At least 3 liters of fluid (10-10 oz. glassfuls) should be provided, including two glasses with each meal and at bedtime.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4886" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The patients should be expected to awake at night to urinate; they should drink two more glasses of fluids before returning to bed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4887" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Additional fluids should be consumed if there is excessive sweating or intestinal fluid loss.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4888" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>A minimum urine output of 2 liters/day on a consistent basis should be sought.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4889" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>A modest amount of alkali should be provided in order to maintain urinary pH at a high normal range (6.5-7.0).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4890" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Potassium alkali are advantageous over sodium alkali, because they do not cause hypercalciuria and are less likely to cause the complication of calcium stones.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4891" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Excessive alkali therapy is not advisable.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4892" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>When urinary pH increases above 7.0 with alkali therapy, the complication of calcium phosphate nephrolithiasis may ensue because of the enhanced urinary supersaturation of hydroxyapatite in an alkaline environment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4893" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In patients who continue to form cystine stones on the above conservative program, THIOLA® may be added to the treatment program.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4894" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>THIOLA® may also be substituted for d-penicillamine in patients who have developed toxicity to the latter drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4895" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In both situations, the conservative treatment program should be continued.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4896" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The dose of THIOLA® should not be arbitrary but should be based on that amount required to reduce urinary cystine concentration to below its solubility limit (generally &lt;250 mg/liter).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4897" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The extent of the decline in cystine excretion is generally dependent on the THIOLA® dosage.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4898" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>THIOLA® may be begun at a dosage of 800 mg/day in adult patients with cystine stones.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4899" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In a multiclinic trial, average dose of THIOLA® was about 1000 mg/day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4900" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>However, some patients require a smaller dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4901" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In children, initial dosage may be based on 15 mg/kg/day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4902" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Urinary cystine should be measured at 1 month after THIOLA® treatment, and every 3 months thereafter.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4903" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>THIOLA® dosage should be readjusted depending on the urinary cystine value.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4904" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Whenever possible, THIOLA® should be given in divided doses 3 times/day at least one hour before or 2 hours after meals.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4905" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In patients who had shown severe toxicity to d-penicillamine, THIOLA® might be begun at a lower dosage.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4906" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Patients should be advised of the potential development of complications and to report promptly the occurrence of any symptom or sign of them.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4907" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>To help monitor potential complications, the following tests are recommended: peripheral blood counts, direct platelet count, hemoglobin, serum albumin, liver function tests, 24-hour urinary protein and routine urinalysis at 3- 6 month intervals during treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4908" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In order to assess effect on stone disease, urinary cystine analysis should be monitored frequently during the first 6 months when the optimum dose schedule is being determined, and at 6-month intervals thereafter.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4909" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Abdominal roentogenogram (KUB) is advised on a yearly basis to monitor the size and appearance/disappearance of stone(s).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4910" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>CARCINOGENESIS, MUTAGENESIS, IMPAIRMENT OF FERTILITY: Long-term carcino-genicity studies in animals have not been performed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4911" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>High doses of THIOLA® in experimental animals have been shown to interfere with maintenance of pregnancy and viability of the fetus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4912" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>USE IN PREGNANCY: Pregnancy category C. D-penicillamine has been shown to cause skeletal defects and cleft palates in the fetus when given to pregnant rats at 10 times the dose recommended for human use.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4913" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>A similar teratogenicity might be expected for THIOLA® although no such findings could be related to the drug in studies in mice and rats at doses up to 10 times the highest recommended human dose.There are no adequate and well-controlled studies in pregnant women.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4914" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>THIOLA® should be used during pregnancy only if the potential benefit justifies potential risk to the fetus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4915" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>NURSING MOTHERS: Because THIOLA® may be excreted in milk and because of the potential serious adverse reactions of nursing infants from THIOLA®, mothers taking THIOLA® should not nurse their infants.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4916" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>PEDIATRIC USE: Safety and effectiveness below the age of 9 have not been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4917" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Despite apparent lower toxicity of THIOLA™, THIOLA® may potentially cause all the serious adverse reactions reported for d-penicillamine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4918" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Thus, although no death has been reported to result directly from THIOLA® treatment, a fatal outcome from THIOLA® is possible, as has been reported with d-penicillamine therapy from such complications as aplastic anemia, agranulocytosis, thrombocytopenia, Goodpasture’s syndrome or myasthenia gravis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4919" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Leukopenia of the granulocytic series may develop without eosinophilia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4920" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Thrombocytopenia may be immunologic in origin or occur on an idiosyncratic basis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4921" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The reduction in peripheral blood white count to less than 3500/cubic mm or in platelet count to below 100,000 cubic mm mandates cessation of therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4922" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Patients should be instructed to report promptly the occurrence of any symptom or sign of these hematological abnormalities, such as fever, sore throat, chills, bleeding or easy bruisability.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4923" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Proteinuria, sometimes sufficiently severe to cause nephrotic syndrome, may develop from membranous glomerulopathy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4924" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>A close observation of affected patients is mandatory.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4925" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The following complications, though rare, have been reported during d-penicillamine therapy and could occur during THIOLA® treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4926" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>When there are abnormal urinary findings associated with hemoptysis and pulmonary infiltrates suggestive of Goodpasture’s syndrome, THIOLA® treatment should be stopped.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4927" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Appearance of myasthenic syndrome or myasthenia gravis requires cessation of treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4928" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>When pemphigus-type reactions develop, THIOLA® therapy should be stopped.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4929" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>THIOLA® is an active reducing agent which undergoes thiol-disulfide exchange with cystine to form a mixed disulfide of Thiola-cysteine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4930" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>From this reaction, a water-soluble mixed disulfide is formed and the amount of sparingly soluble cystine is reduced.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4931" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>When THIOLA® is given orally, up to 48% of dose appears in urine during the first 4 hours and up to 78% by 72 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4932" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Thus, in patients with cystinuria, sufficient amount of THIOLA® or its active metabolites could appear in urine to react with cystine, lowering cystine excretion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4933" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The decrement in urinary cystine produced by THIOLA® is generally proportional to the dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4934" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A reduction in urinary cystine of 250-350 mg/day at a THIOLA® dosage of 1 g/day, and a decline of approximately 500 mg/day at a dosage of 2 g/day, might be expected.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4935" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>THIOLA® causes a sustained reduction in cystine excretion without apparent loss of effectiveness.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4936" LabelDrug="Thiola" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>THIOLA® has a rapid onset and offset of action, showing a fall in cystine excretion on the first day of administration and a rise on the first day of drug withdrawal. thiola-formula</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions>
</LabelInteractions></Label>