<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="TOPROL" setid="4a5762c6-d7a2-4e4c-10b7-8832b36fa5f4">
<Text><Section name="Boxed Warning section" id="34066-1">
Following abrupt cessation of therapy with certain beta-blocking agents, exacerbations of angina pectoris and, in some cases, myocardial infarction have occurred. When discontinuing chronically administered TOPROL-XL, particularly in patients with ischemic heart disease, the dosage should be gradually reduced over a period of 1 - 2 weeks and the patient should be carefully monitored. If angina markedly worsens or acute coronary insufficiency develops, TOPROL-XL administration should be reinstated promptly, at least temporarily, and other measures appropriate for the management of unstable angina should be taken. Warn patients against interruption or discontinuation of therapy without the physician’s advice. Because coronary artery disease is common and may be unrecognized, it may be prudent not to discontinue TOPROL-XL therapy abruptly even in patients treated only for hypertension (5.1).       WARNING: ISCHEMIC HEART DISEASE   (See Full Prescribing Information for complete boxed warning)   Following abrupt cessation of therapy with beta-blocking agents, exacerbations of angina pectoris and myocardial infarction have occurred. Warn patients against interruption or discontinuation of therapy without the physician’s advice. (5.1)</Section>
<Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
TOPROL-XL is contraindicated in severe bradycardia, second or third degree heart block, cardiogenic shock, decompensated cardiac failure, sick sinus syndrome (unless a permanent pacemaker is in place), and in patients who are hypersensitive to any component of this product.        •Known hypersensitivity to product components. (4)   •Severe bradycardia. (4)   •Heart block greater than first degree. (4)   •Cardiogenic shock. (4)   •Decompensated cardiac failure. (4)   •Sick sinus syndrome without a pacemaker. (4)</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
TOPROL-XL is an extended-release tablet intended for once daily administration. For treatment of hypertension and angina, when switching from immediate-release metoprolol to TOPROL-XL, use the same total daily dose of TOPROL-XL. Individualize the dosage of TOPROL-XL. Titration may be needed in some patients.  TOPROL-XL tablets are scored and can be divided; however, do not crush or chew the whole or half tablet.        •Administer once daily. Dosing of TOPROL-XL should be individualized. (2)   •Heart Failure: Recommended starting dose is 12.5 mg or 25 mg doubled every two weeks to the highest dose tolerated or up to 200 mg. (2.3)   •Hypertension: Usual initial dosage is 25 to 100 mg once daily. The dosage may be increased at weekly (or longer) intervals until optimum blood pressure reduction is achieved. Dosages above 400 mg per day have not been studied. (2.1)   •Angina Pectoris: Usual initial dosage is 100 mg once daily. Gradually increase the dosage at weekly intervals until optimum clinical response has been obtained or there is an unacceptable bradycardia. Dosages above 400 mg per day have not been studied. (2.2)   •Switching from immediate-release metoprolol to TOPROL-XL: use the same total daily dose of TOPROL-XL. (2)            Adults: The usual initial dosage is 25 to 100 mg daily in a single dose. The dosage may be increased at weekly (or longer) intervals until optimum blood pressure reduction is achieved. In general, the maximum effect of any given dosage level will be apparent after 1 week of therapy. Dosages above 400 mg per day have not been studied.   Pediatric Hypertensive Patients ≥ 6 Years of age: A pediatric clinical hypertension study in patients 6 to 16 years of age did not meet its primary endpoint (dose response for reduction in SBP); however some other endpoints demonstrated effectiveness [see Use in Specific Populations (8.4)]. If selected for treatment, the recommended starting dose of TOPROL-XL is 1.0 mg/kg once daily, but the maximum initial dose should not exceed 50 mg once daily. Dosage should be adjusted according to blood pressure response. Doses above 2.0 mg/kg (or in excess of 200 mg) once daily have not been studied in pediatric patients [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)].  TOPROL-XL is not recommended in pediatric patients &amp;lt; 6 years of age [see Use in Specific Populations (8.4)].          Individualize the dosage of TOPROL-XL. The usual initial dosage is 100 mg daily, given in a single dose. Gradually increase the dosage at weekly intervals until optimum clinical response has been obtained or there is a pronounced slowing of the heart rate. Dosages above 400 mg per day have not been studied. If treatment is to be discontinued, reduce the dosage gradually over a period of 1 - 2 weeks [see Warnings and Precautions (5)].           Dosage must be individualized and closely monitored during up-titration. Prior to initiation of TOPROL-XL, stabilize the dose of other heart failure drug therapy. The recommended starting dose of TOPROL-XL is 25 mg once daily for two weeks in patients with NYHA Class II heart failure and 12.5 mg once daily in patients with more severe heart failure. Double the dose every two weeks to the highest dosage level tolerated by the patient or up to 200 mg of TOPROL-XL. Initial difficulty with titration should not preclude later attempts to introduce TOPROL-XL. If patients experience symptomatic bradycardia, reduce the dose of TOPROL-XL. If transient worsening of heart failure occurs, consider treating with increased doses of diuretics, lowering the dose of TOPROL-XL or temporarily discontinuing it. The dose of TOPROL-XL should not be increased until symptoms of worsening heart failure have been stabilized.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
•Catecholamine-depleting drugs may have an additive effect when given with beta-blocking agents. (7.1)   •CYP2D6 Inhibitors are likely to increase metoprolol concentration. (7.2)   •Concomitant use of glycosides, clonidine, and diltiazem and verapamil with beta-blockers can increase the risk of bradycardia. (7.3)   •Beta-blockers including metoprolol, may exacerbate the rebound hypertension that can follow the withdrawal of clonidine. (7.3)           Catecholamine depleting drugs (eg, reserpine, monoamine oxidase (MAO) inhibitors) may have an additive effect when given with beta-blocking agents. Observe patients treated with TOPROL-XL plus a catecholamine depletor for evidence of hypotension or marked bradycardia, which may produce vertigo, syncope, or postural hypotension.          Drugs that inhibit CYP2D6 such as quinidine, fluoxetine, paroxetine, and propafenone are likely to increase metoprolol concentration. In healthy subjects with CYP2D6 extensive metabolizer phenotype, coadministration of quinidine 100 mg and immediate-release metoprolol 200 mg tripled the concentration of S-metoprolol and doubled the metoprolol elimination half-life. In four patients with cardiovascular disease, coadministration of propafenone 150 mg t.i.d. with immediate-release metoprolol 50 mg t.i.d. resulted in two- to five-fold increases in the steady-state concentration of metoprolol. These increases in plasma concentration would decrease the cardioselectivity of metoprolol.          Digitalis glycosides, clonidine, diltiazem and verapamil slow atrioventricular conduction and decrease heart rate. Concomitant use with beta blockers can increase the risk of bradycardia.  If clonidine and a beta blocker, such as metoprolol are coadministered, withdraw the beta-blocker several days before the gradual withdrawal of clonidine because beta-blockers may exacerbate the rebound hypertension that can follow the withdrawal of clonidine. If replacing clonidine by beta-blocker therapy, delay the introduction of beta-blockers for several days after clonidine administration has stopped [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.11)  ].</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
•Heart Failure: Worsening cardiac failure may occur. (5.2)   •Bronchospastic Disease: Avoid beta blockers. (5.3)   •Pheochromocytoma: If required, first initiate therapy with an alpha blocker. (5.4)   •Major Surgery: Avoid initiation of high-dose extended-release metoprolol in patients undergoing non-cardiac surgery because it has been associated with bradycardia, hypotension, stroke and death. Do not routinely withdraw chronic beta blocker therapy prior to surgery. (5.5, 6.1)  •Diabetes and Hypoglycemia: May mask tachycardia occurring with hypoglycemia. (5.6)   •Patients with Hepatic Impairment: (5.7)   •Thyrotoxicosis: Abrupt withdrawal in patients with thyrotoxicosis might precipitate a thyroid storm. (5.8)   •Anaphylactic Reactions: Patients may be unresponsive to the usual doses of epinephrine used to treat allergic reaction. (5.9)   •Peripheral Vascular Disease: Can aggravate symptoms of arterial insufficiency. (5.10)   •Calcium Channel Blockers: Because of significant inotropic and chronotropic effects in patients treated with beta-blockers and calcium channel blockers of the verapamil and diltiazem type, caution should be exercised in patients treated with these agents concomitantly. (5.11)           Following abrupt cessation of therapy with certain beta-blocking agents, exacerbations of angina pectoris and, in some cases, myocardial infarction have occurred. When discontinuing chronically administered TOPROL-XL, particularly in patients with ischemic heart disease, gradually reduce the dosage over a period of 1 - 2 weeks and monitor the patient. If angina markedly worsens or acute coronary ischemia develops, promptly reinstate TOPROL-XL, and take measures appropriate for the management of unstable angina. Warn patients not to interrupt therapy without their physician’s advice. Because coronary artery disease is common and may be unrecognized, avoid abruptly discontinuing TOPROL-XL in patients treated only for hypertension.          Worsening cardiac failure may occur during up-titration of TOPROL-XL. If such symptoms occur, increase diuretics and restore clinical stability before advancing the dose of TOPROL-XL [see Dosage and Administration (2)]. It may be necessary to lower the dose of TOPROL-XL or temporarily discontinue it. Such episodes do not preclude subsequent successful titration of TOPROL-XL.          PATIENTS WITH BRONCHOSPASTIC DISEASES SHOULD, IN GENERAL, NOT RECEIVE BETA-BLOCKERS. Because of its relative beta1 cardio-selectivity, however, TOPROL-XL may be used in patients with bronchospastic disease who do not respond to, or cannot tolerate, other antihypertensive treatment. Because beta1-selectivity is not absolute, use the lowest possible dose of TOPROL-XL. Bronchodilators, including beta2-agonists, should be readily available or administered concomitantly [see Dosage and Administration (2)].           If TOPROL-XL is used in the setting of pheochromocytoma, it should be given in combination with an alpha blocker, and only after the alpha blocker has been initiated. Administration of beta-blockers alone in the setting of pheochromocytoma has been associated with a paradoxical increase in blood pressure due to the attenuation of beta-mediated vasodilatation in skeletal muscle.          Avoid initiation of a high-dose regimen of extended-release metoprolol in patients undergoing non-cardiac surgery, since such use in patients with cardiovascular risk factors has been associated with bradycardia, hypotension, stroke and death.  Chronically administered beta-blocking therapy should not be routinely withdrawn prior to major surgery, however, the impaired ability of the heart to respond to reflex adrenergic stimuli may augment the risks of general anesthesia and surgical procedures.          Beta-blockers may mask tachycardia occurring with hypoglycemia, but other manifestations such as dizziness and sweating may not be significantly affected.          Consider initiating TOPROL-XL therapy at doses lower than those recommended for a given indication; gradually increase dosage to optimize therapy, while monitoring closely for adverse events.          Beta-adrenergic blockade may mask certain clinical signs of hyperthyroidism, such as tachycardia. Abrupt withdrawal of beta-blockade may precipitate a thyroid storm.          While taking beta-blockers, patients with a history of severe anaphylactic reactions to a variety of allergens may be more reactive to repeated challenge and may be unresponsive to the usual doses of epinephrine used to treat an allergic reaction.          Beta-blockers can precipitate or aggravate symptoms of arterial insufficiency in patients with peripheral vascular disease.          Because of significant inotropic and chronotropic effects in patients treated with beta-blockers and calcium channel blockers of the verapamil and diltiazem type, caution should be exercised in patients treated with these agents concomitantly.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Hypertension: The mechanism of the antihypertensive effects of beta-blocking agents has not been elucidated. However, several possible mechanisms have been proposed: (1) competitive antagonism of catecholamines at peripheral (especially cardiac) adrenergic neuron sites, leading to decreased cardiac output; (2) a central effect leading to reduced sympathetic outflow to the periphery; and (3) suppression of renin activity.   Heart Failure: The precise mechanism for the beneficial effects of beta-blockers in heart failure has not been elucidated.          Clinical pharmacology studies have confirmed the beta-blocking activity of metoprolol in man, as shown by (1) reduction in heart rate and cardiac output at rest and upon exercise, (2) reduction of systolic blood pressure upon exercise, (3) inhibition of isoproterenol-induced tachycardia, and (4) reduction of reflex orthostatic tachycardia.  Metoprolol is a beta1-selective (cardioselective) adrenergic receptor blocking agent. This preferential effect is not absolute, however, and at higher plasma concentrations, metoprolol also inhibits beta2-adrenoreceptors, chiefly located in the bronchial and vascular musculature. Metoprolol has no intrinsic sympathomimetic activity, and membrane-stabilizing activity is detectable only at plasma concentrations much greater than required for beta-blockade. Animal and human experiments indicate that metoprolol slows the sinus rate and decreases AV nodal conduction.  The relative beta1-selectivity of metoprolol has been confirmed by the following: (1) In normal subjects, metoprolol is unable to reverse the beta2-mediated vasodilating effects of epinephrine. This contrasts with the effect of nonselective beta-blockers, which completely reverse the vasodilating effects of epinephrine. (2) In asthmatic patients, metoprolol reduces FEV1 and FVC significantly less than a nonselective beta-blocker, propranolol, at equivalent beta1-receptor blocking doses.  The relationship between plasma metoprolol levels and reduction in exercise heart rate is independent of the pharmaceutical formulation. Using an Emax model, the maximum effect is a 30% reduction in exercise heart rate, which is attributed to beta1-blockade. Beta1-blocking effects in the range of 30-80% of the maximal effect (approximately 8-23% reduction in exercise heart rate) correspond to metoprolol plasma concentrations from 30-540 nmol/L. The relative beta1-selectivity of metoprolol diminishes and blockade of beta2-adrenoceptors increases at plasma concentration above 300 nmol/L.  Although beta-adrenergic receptor blockade is useful in the treatment of angina, hypertension, and heart failure there are situations in which sympathetic stimulation is vital. In patients with severely damaged hearts, adequate ventricular function may depend on sympathetic drive. In the presence of AV block, beta-blockade may prevent the necessary facilitating effect of sympathetic activity on conduction. Beta2-adrenergic blockade results in passive bronchial constriction by interfering with endogenous adrenergic bronchodilator activity in patients subject to bronchospasm and may also interfere with exogenous bronchodilators in such patients.  In other studies, treatment with TOPROL-XL produced an improvement in left ventricular ejection fraction. TOPROL-XL was also shown to delay the increase in left ventricular end-systolic and end-diastolic volumes after 6 months of treatment.           Adults: In man, absorption of metoprolol is rapid and complete. Plasma levels following oral administration of conventional metoprolol tablets, however, approximate 50% of levels following intravenous administration, indicating about 50% first-pass metabolism. Metoprolol crosses the blood-brain barrier and has been reported in the CSF in a concentration 78% of the simultaneous plasma concentration.  Plasma levels achieved are highly variable after oral administration. Only a small fraction of the drug (about 12%) is bound to human serum albumin. Metoprolol is a racemic mixture of R- and S- enantiomers, and is primarily metabolized by CYP2D6. When administered orally, it exhibits stereoselective metabolism that is dependent on oxidation phenotype. Elimination is mainly by biotransformation in the liver, and the plasma half-life ranges from approximately 3 to 7 hours. Less than 5% of an oral dose of metoprolol is recovered unchanged in the urine; the rest is excreted by the kidneys as metabolites that appear to have no beta-blocking activity.  Following intravenous administration of metoprolol, the urinary recovery of unchanged drug is approximately 10%. The systemic availability and half-life of metoprolol in patients with renal failure do not differ to a clinically significant degree from those in normal subjects. Consequently, no reduction in metoprolol succinate dosage is usually needed in patients with chronic renal failure.  Metoprolol is metabolized predominantly by CYP2D6, an enzyme that is absent in about 8% of Caucasians (poor metabolizers) and about 2% of most other populations. CYP2D6 can be inhibited by a number of drugs. Poor metabolizers and extensive metabolizers who concomitantly use CYP2D6 inhibiting drugs will have increased (several-fold) metoprolol blood levels, decreasing metoprolol's cardioselectivity [see Drug Interactions (7.2)].  In comparison to conventional metoprolol, the plasma metoprolol levels following administration of TOPROL-XL are characterized by lower peaks, longer time to peak and significantly lower peak to trough variation. The peak plasma levels following once-daily administration of TOPROL-XL average one-fourth to one-half the peak plasma levels obtained following a corresponding dose of conventional metoprolol, administered once daily or in divided doses. At steady state the average bioavailability of metoprolol following administration of TOPROL-XL, across the dosage range of 50 to 400 mg once daily, was 77% relative to the corresponding single or divided doses of conventional metoprolol. Nevertheless, over the 24-hour dosing interval, β1-blockade is comparable and dose-related [see Clinical Pharmacology (12)]. The bioavailability of metoprolol shows a dose-related, although not directly proportional, increase with dose and is not significantly affected by food following TOPROL-XL administration.   Pediatrics: The pharmacokinetic profile of TOPROL-XL was studied in 120 pediatric hypertensive patients (6-17 years of age) receiving doses ranging from 12.5 to 200 mg once daily. The pharmacokinetics of metoprolol were similar to those described previously in adults. Age, gender, race, and ideal body weight had no significant effects on metoprolol pharmacokinetics. Metoprolol apparent oral clearance (CL/F) increased linearly with body weight. Metoprolol pharmacokinetics have not been investigated in patients &amp;lt; 6 years of age.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="185" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Following abrupt cessation of therapy with certain beta-blocking agents, exacerbations of angina pectoris and, in some cases, myocardial infarction have occurred.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="186" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>When discontinuing chronically administered TOPROL-XL, particularly in patients with ischemic heart disease, the dosage should be gradually reduced over a period of 1 - 2 weeks and the patient should be carefully monitored.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="187" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>If angina markedly worsens or acute coronary insufficiency develops, TOPROL-XL administration should be reinstated promptly, at least temporarily, and other measures appropriate for the management of unstable angina should be taken.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="188" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Warn patients against interruption or discontinuation of therapy without the physician’s advice.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="189" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Because coronary artery disease is common and may be unrecognized, it may be prudent not to discontinue TOPROL-XL therapy abruptly even in patients treated only for hypertension (5.1).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="190" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>WARNING: ISCHEMIC HEART DISEASE See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="191" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Following abrupt cessation of therapy with beta-blocking agents, exacerbations of angina pectoris and myocardial infarction have occurred.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="192" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>TOPROL-XL is contraindicated in severe bradycardia, second or third degree heart block, cardiogenic shock, decompensated cardiac failure, sick sinus syndrome (unless a permanent pacemaker is in place), and in patients who are hypersensitive to any component of this product.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="193" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Known hypersensitivity to product components.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="194" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Heart block greater than first degree.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="195" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Sick sinus syndrome without a pacemaker.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="196" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>TOPROL-XL is an extended-release tablet intended for once daily administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="197" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For treatment of hypertension and angina, when switching from immediate-release metoprolol to TOPROL-XL, use the same total daily dose of TOPROL-XL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="198" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Titration may be needed in some patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="199" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>TOPROL-XL tablets are scored and can be divided; however, do not crush or chew the whole or half tablet.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="200" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dosing of TOPROL-XL should be individualized.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="201" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Heart Failure: Recommended starting dose is 12.5 mg or 25 mg doubled every two weeks to the highest dose tolerated or up to 200 mg. (2.3) Hypertension: Usual initial dosage is 25 to 100 mg once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="202" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The dosage may be increased at weekly (or longer) intervals until optimum blood pressure reduction is achieved.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="203" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dosages above 400 mg per day have not been studied.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="204" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Angina Pectoris: Usual initial dosage is 100 mg once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="205" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Gradually increase the dosage at weekly intervals until optimum clinical response has been obtained or there is an unacceptable bradycardia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="206" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Switching from immediate-release metoprolol to TOPROL-XL: use the same total daily dose of TOPROL-XL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="207" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Adults: The usual initial dosage is 25 to 100 mg daily in a single dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="208" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In general, the maximum effect of any given dosage level will be apparent after 1 week of therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="209" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Pediatric Hypertensive Patients ≥ 6 Years of age: A pediatric clinical hypertension study in patients 6 to 16 years of age did not meet its primary endpoint (dose response for reduction in SBP); however, some other endpoints demonstrated effectiveness.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="210" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If selected for treatment, the recommended starting dose of TOPROL-XL is 1 mg/kg once daily, but the maximum initial dose should not exceed 50 mg once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="211" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dosage should be adjusted according to blood pressure response.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="212" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Doses above 2 mg/kg (or in excess of 200 mg) once daily have not been studied in pediatric patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="213" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>TOPROL-XL is not recommended in pediatric patients &lt; 6 years of age.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="214" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The usual initial dosage is 100 mg daily, given in a single dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="215" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Gradually increase the dosage at weekly intervals until optimum clinical response has been obtained or there is a pronounced slowing of the heart rate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="216" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If treatment is to be discontinued, reduce the dosage gradually over a period of 1 - 2 weeks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="217" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dosage must be individualized and closely monitored during up-titration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="218" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Prior to initiation of TOPROL-XL, stabilize the dose of other heart failure drug therapy.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M1" type="Trigger" span="34 18" str="stabilize the dose"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="62 26" str="heart failure drug therapy" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M1" precipitant="M2"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="219" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommended starting dose of TOPROL-XL is 25 mg once daily for two weeks in patients with NYHA Class II heart failure and 12.5 mg once daily in patients with more severe heart failure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="220" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Double the dose every two weeks to the highest dosage level tolerated by the patient or up to 200 mg of TOPROL-XL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="221" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Initial difficulty with titration should not preclude later attempts to introduce TOPROL-XL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="222" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If patients experience symptomatic bradycardia, reduce the dose of TOPROL-XL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="223" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If transient worsening of heart failure occurs, consider treating with increased doses of diuretics, lowering the dose of TOPROL-XL or temporarily discontinuing it.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="224" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The dose of TOPROL-XL should not be increased until symptoms of worsening heart failure have been stabilized.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="225" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Catecholamine-depleting drugs may have an additive effect when given with beta-blocking agents.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M3" type="Trigger" span="42 15" str="additive effect"/>
<Mention id="M4" type="Precipitant" span="0 29" str="Catecholamine-depleting drugs" code="N0000175640"/>
<Mention id="M5" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 29;42 15" str="Catecholamine-depleting drugs | additive effect" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M3" precipitant="M4" effect="M5"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="226" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>CYP2D6 Inhibitors are likely to increase metoprolol concentration.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M6" type="Trigger" span="32 8;52 13" str="increase | concentration"/>
<Mention id="M7" type="Precipitant" span="0 17" str="CYP2D6 Inhibitors" code="N0000182135"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M6" precipitant="M7" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="227" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant use of glycosides, clonidine, and diltiazem and verapamil with beta-blockers can increase the risk of bradycardia.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M17" type="Trigger" span="93 17" str="increase the risk"/>
<Mention id="M9" type="Precipitant" span="31 9" str="clonidine" code="MN3L5RMN02"/>
<Mention id="M19" type="SpecificInteraction" span="114 11" str="bradycardia" code="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M12" type="Precipitant" span="46 9" str="diltiazem" code="EE92BBP03H"/>
<Mention id="M15" type="Precipitant" span="19 10" str="glycosides" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M18" type="Precipitant" span="60 9" str="verapamil" code="CJ0O37KU29"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M17" precipitant="M9" effect="M19"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M17" precipitant="M12" effect="M19"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M17" precipitant="M15" effect="M19"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M17" precipitant="M18" effect="M19"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="228" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Beta-blockers including metoprolol, may exacerbate the rebound hypertension that can follow the withdrawal of clonidine.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M20" type="Trigger" span="40 10" str="exacerbate"/>
<Mention id="M21" type="Precipitant" span="110 9" str="clonidine" code="MN3L5RMN02"/>
<Mention id="M22" type="SpecificInteraction" span="55 64" str="rebound hypertension that can follow the withdrawal of clonidine" code="84094009: Rebound hypertension (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M20" precipitant="M21" effect="M22"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="229" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Catecholamine depleting drugs (e.g., reserpine, monoamine oxidase (MAO) inhibitors) may have an additive effect when given with beta-blocking agents.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M35" type="Trigger" span="96 15" str="additive effect"/>
<Mention id="M24" type="Precipitant" span="0 29" str="Catecholamine depleting drugs" code="N0000175640"/>
<Mention id="M25" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 29;96 15" str="Catecholamine depleting drugs | additive effect" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M27" type="Precipitant" span="67 3;72 10" str="MAO | inhibitors" code="N0000175744"/>
<Mention id="M28" type="SpecificInteraction" span="67 3;72 10;96 15" str="MAO | inhibitors | additive effect" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M30" type="Precipitant" span="48 34" str="monoamine oxidase (MAO) inhibitors" code="N0000175744"/>
<Mention id="M31" type="SpecificInteraction" span="48 34;96 15" str="monoamine oxidase (MAO) inhibitors | additive effect" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M33" type="Precipitant" span="48 17;72 10" str="monoamine oxidase | inhibitors" code="N0000175744"/>
<Mention id="M34" type="SpecificInteraction" span="48 17;72 10;96 15" str="monoamine oxidase | inhibitors | additive effect" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M36" type="Precipitant" span="37 9" str="reserpine" code="8B1QWR724A"/>
<Mention id="M37" type="SpecificInteraction" span="37 9;96 15" str="reserpine | additive effect" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M24" effect="M25"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M27" effect="M28"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M30" effect="M31"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M33" effect="M34"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M36" effect="M37"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="230" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Observe patients treated with TOPROL-XL plus a catecholamine depletor for evidence of hypotension or marked bradycardia, which may produce vertigo, syncope, or postural hypotension.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M50" type="Trigger" span="131 7" str="produce"/>
<Mention id="M51" type="Precipitant" span="47 22" str="catecholamine depletor" code="N0000175640"/>
<Mention id="M40" type="SpecificInteraction" span="160 20" str="postural hypotension" code="28651003: Orthostatic hypotension (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M47" type="Trigger" span="0 7;70 12" str="Observe | for evidence"/>
<Mention id="M43" type="SpecificInteraction" span="108 11" str="bradycardia" code="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M46" type="SpecificInteraction" span="148 7" str="syncope" code="271594007: Syncope (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M49" type="SpecificInteraction" span="86 11" str="hypotension" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M52" type="SpecificInteraction" span="139 7" str="vertigo" code="399153001: Vertigo (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M50" precipitant="M51" effect="M40"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M47" precipitant="M51" effect="M43"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M50" precipitant="M51" effect="M46"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M47" precipitant="M51" effect="M49"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M50" precipitant="M51" effect="M52"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="231" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Drugs that inhibit CYP2D6 such as quinidine, fluoxetine, paroxetine, and propafenone are likely to increase metoprolol concentration.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M61" type="Trigger" span="99 8;119 13" str="increase | concentration"/>
<Mention id="M54" type="Precipitant" span="0 25" str="Drugs that inhibit CYP2D6" code="N0000182135"/>
<Mention id="M56" type="Precipitant" span="45 10" str="fluoxetine" code="01K63SUP8D"/>
<Mention id="M58" type="Precipitant" span="57 10" str="paroxetine" code="41VRH5220H"/>
<Mention id="M60" type="Precipitant" span="73 11" str="propafenone" code="68IQX3T69U"/>
<Mention id="M62" type="Precipitant" span="34 9" str="quinidine" code="ITX08688JL"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M61" precipitant="M54" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M61" precipitant="M56" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M61" precipitant="M58" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M61" precipitant="M60" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M61" precipitant="M62" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="232" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>In healthy subjects with CYP2D6 extensive metabolizer phenotype, coadministration of quinidine 100 mg and immediate-release metoprolol 200 mg tripled the concentration of S-metoprolol and doubled the metoprolol elimination half-life.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M63" type="Trigger" span="142 25" str="tripled the concentration"/>
<Mention id="M66" type="Precipitant" span="85 9" str="quinidine" code="ITX08688JL"/>
<Mention id="M65" type="Trigger" span="188 7;223 9" str="doubled | half-life"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M63" precipitant="M66" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M65" precipitant="M66" effect="C54603"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="233" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>In four patients with cardiovascular disease, coadministration of propafenone 150 mg t.i.d. with immediate-release metoprolol 50 mg t.i.d. resulted in two- to five-fold increases in the steady-state concentration of metoprolol.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M67" type="Trigger" span="169 43" str="increases in the steady-state concentration"/>
<Mention id="M68" type="Precipitant" span="66 11" str="propafenone" code="68IQX3T69U"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M67" precipitant="M68" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="234" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>These increases in plasma concentration would decrease the cardioselectivity of metoprolol.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="235" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Digitalis glycosides, clonidine, diltiazem and verapamil slow atrioventricular conduction and decrease heart rate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="236" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant use with beta blockers can increase the risk of bradycardia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="237" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>If clonidine and a beta blocker, such as metoprolol are coadministered, withdraw the beta-blocker several days before the gradual withdrawal of clonidine because beta-blockers may exacerbate the rebound hypertension that can follow the withdrawal of clonidine.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M69" type="Trigger" span="180 10" str="exacerbate"/>
<Mention id="M70" type="Precipitant" span="3 9" str="clonidine" code="MN3L5RMN02"/>
<Mention id="M71" type="SpecificInteraction" span="195 64" str="rebound hypertension that can follow the withdrawal of clonidine" code="84094009: Rebound hypertension (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M69" precipitant="M70" effect="M71"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="238" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>If replacing clonidine by beta-blocker therapy, delay the introduction of beta-blockers for several days after clonidine administration has stopped.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M72" type="Trigger" span="48 5;105 5;140 7" str="delay | after | stopped"/>
<Mention id="M73" type="Precipitant" span="13 9" str="clonidine" code="MN3L5RMN02"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M72" precipitant="M73"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="239" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Heart Failure: Worsening cardiac failure may occur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="240" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Bronchospastic Disease: Avoid beta blockers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="241" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Pheochromocytoma: If required, first initiate therapy with an alpha blocker.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="242" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Major Surgery: Avoid initiation of high-dose extended-release metoprolol in patients undergoing non-cardiac surgery because it has been associated with bradycardia, hypotension, stroke and death.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="243" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Do not routinely withdraw chronic beta blocker therapy prior to surgery.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="244" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Diabetes and Hypoglycemia: May mask tachycardia occurring with hypoglycemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="245" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients with Hepatic Impairment: (5.7) Thyrotoxicosis: Abrupt withdrawal in patients with thyrotoxicosis might precipitate a thyroid storm.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="246" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Anaphylactic Reactions: Patients may be unresponsive to the usual doses of epinephrine used to treat allergic reaction.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M74" type="Trigger" span="40 12" str="unresponsive"/>
<Mention id="M75" type="Precipitant" span="75 11" str="epinephrine" code="YKH834O4BH"/>
<Mention id="M76" type="SpecificInteraction" span="40 46" str="unresponsive to the usual doses of epinephrine" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I29" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M74" precipitant="M75" effect="M76"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="247" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Peripheral Vascular Disease: Can aggravate symptoms of arterial insufficiency.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="248" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Calcium Channel Blockers: Because of significant inotropic and chronotropic effects in patients treated with beta-blockers and calcium channel blockers of the verapamil and diltiazem type, caution should be exercised in patients treated with these agents concomitantly.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M97" type="Trigger" span="49 9;76 7" str="inotropic | effects "/>
<Mention id="M98" type="Trigger" span="63 20" str=" chronotropic effects"/>
<Mention id="M83" type="Precipitant" span="127 24" str="calcium channel blockers" code="N0000175566"/>
<Mention id="M96" type="SpecificInteraction" span="49 9;76 7" str="inotropic | effects" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M100" type="SpecificInteraction" span="63 20" str="chronotropic effects" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M91" type="Precipitant" span="173 9" str="diltiazem" code="EE92BBP03H"/>
<Mention id="M99" type="Precipitant" span="159 9" str="verapamil" code="CJ0O37KU29"/>
<Interaction id="I30" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M97;M98" precipitant="M83" effect="M96"/>
<Interaction id="I31" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M97;M98" precipitant="M83" effect="M100"/>
<Interaction id="I32" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M97;M98" precipitant="M91" effect="M96"/>
<Interaction id="I33" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M97;M98" precipitant="M91" effect="M100"/>
<Interaction id="I34" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M97;M98" precipitant="M99" effect="M96"/>
<Interaction id="I35" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M97;M98" precipitant="M99" effect="M100"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="249" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>When discontinuing chronically administered TOPROL-XL, particularly in patients with ischemic heart disease, gradually reduce the dosage over a period of 1 - 2 weeks and monitor the patient.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="250" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If angina markedly worsens or acute coronary ischemia develops, promptly reinstate TOPROL-XL, and take measures appropriate for the management of unstable angina.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="251" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Warn patients not to interrupt therapy without their physician’s advice.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="252" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Because coronary artery disease is common and may be unrecognized, avoid abruptly discontinuing TOPROL-XL in patients treated only for hypertension.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="253" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Worsening cardiac failure may occur during up-titration of TOPROL-XL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="254" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If such symptoms occur, increase diuretics and restore clinical stability before advancing the dose of TOPROL-XL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="255" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>It may be necessary to lower the dose of TOPROL-XL or temporarily discontinue it.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="256" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Such episodes do not preclude subsequent successful titration of TOPROL-XL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="257" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>PATIENTS WITH BRONCHOSPASTIC DISEASES SHOULD, IN GENERAL, NOT RECEIVE BETA-BLOCKERS.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="258" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Because of its relative beta1 cardio-selectivity, however, TOPROL-XL may be used in patients with bronchospastic disease who do not respond to, or cannot tolerate, other antihypertensive treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="259" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Because beta1-selectivity is not absolute, use the lowest possible dose of TOPROL-XL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="260" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Bronchodilators, including beta2-agonists, should be readily available or administered concomitantly.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="261" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If TOPROL-XL is used in the setting of pheochromocytoma, it should be given in combination with an alpha blocker, and only after the alpha blocker has been initiated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="262" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Administration of beta-blockers alone in the setting of pheochromocytoma has been associated with a paradoxical increase in blood pressure due to the attenuation of beta-mediated vasodilatation in skeletal muscle.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="263" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Avoid initiation of a high-dose regimen of extended-release metoprolol in patients undergoing non-cardiac surgery, since such use in patients with cardiovascular risk factors has been associated with bradycardia, hypotension, stroke and death.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="264" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Chronically administered beta-blocking therapy should not be routinely withdrawn prior to major surgery, however, the impaired ability of the heart to respond to reflex adrenergic stimuli may augment the risks of general anesthesia and surgical procedures.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="265" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Beta-blockers may mask tachycardia occurring with hypoglycemia, but other manifestations such as dizziness and sweating may not be significantly affected.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="266" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Consider initiating TOPROL-XL therapy at doses lower than those recommended for a given indication; gradually increase dosage to optimize therapy, while monitoring closely for adverse events.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="267" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Beta-adrenergic blockade may mask certain clinical signs of hyperthyroidism, such as tachycardia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="268" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Abrupt withdrawal of beta-blockade may precipitate a thyroid storm.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="269" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>While taking beta-blockers, patients with a history of severe anaphylactic reactions to a variety of allergens may be more reactive to repeated challenge and may be unresponsive to the usual doses of epinephrine used to treat an allergic reaction.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M101" type="Trigger" span="165 12" str="unresponsive"/>
<Mention id="M102" type="Precipitant" span="200 11" str="epinephrine" code="YKH834O4BH"/>
<Mention id="M103" type="SpecificInteraction" span="165 46" str="unresponsive to the usual doses of epinephrine" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I36" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M101" precipitant="M102" effect="M103"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="270" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Beta-blockers can precipitate or aggravate symptoms of arterial insufficiency in patients with peripheral vascular disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="271" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Because of significant inotropic and chronotropic effects in patients treated with beta-blockers and calcium channel blockers of the verapamil and diltiazem type, caution should be exercised in patients treated with these agents concomitantly.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M124" type="Trigger" span="23 9;50 7" str="inotropic | effects "/>
<Mention id="M125" type="Trigger" span="37 20" str=" chronotropic effects"/>
<Mention id="M110" type="Precipitant" span="101 24" str="calcium channel blockers" code="N0000175566"/>
<Mention id="M127" type="SpecificInteraction" span="37 20" str="chronotropic effects" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M123" type="SpecificInteraction" span="23 9;50 7" str="inotropic | effects" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M118" type="Precipitant" span="147 9" str="diltiazem" code="EE92BBP03H"/>
<Mention id="M126" type="Precipitant" span="133 9" str="verapamil" code="CJ0O37KU29"/>
<Interaction id="I37" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M124;M125" precipitant="M110" effect="M127"/>
<Interaction id="I38" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M124;M125" precipitant="M110" effect="M123"/>
<Interaction id="I39" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M124;M125" precipitant="M118" effect="M123"/>
<Interaction id="I40" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M124;M125" precipitant="M118" effect="M127"/>
<Interaction id="I41" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M124;M125" precipitant="M126" effect="M123"/>
<Interaction id="I42" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M124;M125" precipitant="M126" effect="M127"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="272" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Hypertension: The mechanism of the antihypertensive effects of beta-blocking agents has not been elucidated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="273" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>However, several possible mechanisms have been proposed: (1) competitive antagonism of catecholamines at peripheral (especially cardiac) adrenergic neuron sites, leading to decreased cardiac output; (2) a central effect leading to reduced sympathetic outflow to the periphery; and (3) suppression of renin activity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="274" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Heart Failure: The precise mechanism for the beneficial effects of beta-blockers in heart failure has not been elucidated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="275" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Clinical pharmacology studies have confirmed the beta-blocking activity of metoprolol in man, as shown by (1) reduction in heart rate and cardiac output at rest and upon exercise, (2) reduction of systolic blood pressure upon exercise, (3) inhibition of isoproterenol-induced tachycardia, and (4) reduction of reflex orthostatic tachycardia.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M128" type="Trigger" span="240 10" str="inhibition"/>
<Mention id="M129" type="Precipitant" span="254 13" str="isoproterenol" code="L628TT009W"/>
<Mention id="M130" type="SpecificInteraction" span="240 47" str="inhibition of isoproterenol-induced tachycardia" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I43" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M128" precipitant="M129" effect="M130"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="276" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Metoprolol is a beta1-selective (cardioselective) adrenergic receptor blocking agent.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="277" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This preferential effect is not absolute, however, and at higher plasma concentrations, metoprolol also inhibits beta2-adrenoreceptors, chiefly located in the bronchial and vascular musculature.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="278" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Metoprolol has no intrinsic sympathomimetic activity, and membrane-stabilizing activity is detectable only at plasma concentrations much greater than required for beta-blockade.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="279" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Animal and human experiments indicate that metoprolol slows the sinus rate and decreases AV nodal conduction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="280" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The relative beta1-selectivity of metoprolol has been confirmed by the following: (1) In normal subjects, metoprolol is unable to reverse the beta2-mediated vasodilating effects of epinephrine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="281" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This contrasts with the effect of nonselective beta-blockers, which completely reverse the vasodilating effects of epinephrine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="282" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In asthmatic patients, metoprolol reduces FEV1 and FVC significantly less than a nonselective beta-blocker, propranolol, at equivalent beta1-receptor blocking doses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="283" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The relationship between plasma metoprolol levels and reduction in exercise heart rate is independent of the pharmaceutical formulation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="284" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Using an Emax model, the maximum effect is a 30% reduction in exercise heart rate, which is attributed to beta1-blockade.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="285" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Beta1-blocking effects in the range of 30-80% of the maximal effect (approximately 8-23% reduction in exercise heart rate) correspond to metoprolol plasma concentrations from 30-540 nmol/L.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="286" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The relative beta1-selectivity of metoprolol diminishes and blockade of beta2-adrenoceptors increases at plasma concentration above 300 nmol/L.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="287" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Although beta-adrenergic receptor blockade is useful in the treatment of angina, hypertension, and heart failure there are situations in which sympathetic stimulation is vital.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="288" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In patients with severely damaged hearts, adequate ventricular function may depend on sympathetic drive.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="289" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In the presence of AV block, beta-blockade may prevent the necessary facilitating effect of sympathetic activity on conduction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="290" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Beta2-adrenergic blockade results in passive bronchial constriction by interfering with endogenous adrenergic bronchodilator activity in patients subject to bronchospasm and may also interfere with exogenous bronchodilators in such patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="291" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In other studies, treatment with TOPROL-XL produced an improvement in left ventricular ejection fraction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="292" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>TOPROL-XL was also shown to delay the increase in left ventricular end-systolic and end-diastolic volumes after 6 months of treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="293" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Adults: In man, absorption of metoprolol is rapid and complete.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="294" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Plasma levels following oral administration of conventional metoprolol tablets, however, approximate 50% of levels following intravenous administration, indicating about 50% first-pass metabolism.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="295" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Metoprolol crosses the blood-brain barrier and has been reported in the CSF in a concentration 78% of the simultaneous plasma concentration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="296" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Plasma levels achieved are highly variable after oral administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="297" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Only a small fraction of the drug (about 12%) is bound to human serum albumin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="298" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Metoprolol is a racemic mixture of R- and S- enantiomers, and is primarily metabolized by CYP2D6.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="299" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>When administered orally, it exhibits stereoselective metabolism that is dependent on oxidation phenotype.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="300" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Elimination is mainly by biotransformation in the liver, and the plasma half-life ranges from approximately 3 to 7 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="301" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Less than 5% of an oral dose of metoprolol is recovered unchanged in the urine; the rest is excreted by the kidneys as metabolites that appear to have no beta-blocking activity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="302" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following intravenous administration of metoprolol, the urinary recovery of unchanged drug is approximately 10%.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="303" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The systemic availability and half-life of metoprolol in patients with renal failure do not differ to a clinically significant degree from those in normal subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="304" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Consequently, no reduction in metoprolol succinate dosage is usually needed in patients with chronic renal failure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="305" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Metoprolol is metabolized predominantly by CYP2D6, an enzyme that is absent in about 8% of Caucasians (poor metabolizers) and about 2% of most other populations.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="306" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>CYP2D6 can be inhibited by a number of drugs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="307" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Poor metabolizers and extensive metabolizers who concomitantly use CYP2D6 inhibiting drugs will have increased (several-fold) metoprolol blood levels, decreasing metoprolol's cardioselectivity.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M131" type="Trigger" span="101 9;137 12" str="increased | blood levels"/>
<Mention id="M132" type="Precipitant" span="67 23" str="CYP2D6 inhibiting drugs" code="N0000182135"/>
<Interaction id="I44" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M131" precipitant="M132" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="308" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In comparison to conventional metoprolol, the plasma metoprolol levels following administration of TOPROL-XL are characterized by lower peaks, longer time to peak and significantly lower peak to trough variation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="309" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The peak plasma levels following once-daily administration of TOPROL-XL average one-fourth to one-half the peak plasma levels obtained following a corresponding dose of conventional metoprolol, administered once daily or in divided doses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="310" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>At steady state the average bioavailability of metoprolol following administration of TOPROL-XL, across the dosage range of 50 to 400 mg once daily, was 77% relative to the corresponding single or divided doses of conventional metoprolol.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="311" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Nevertheless, over the 24-hour dosing interval, β1-blockade is comparable and dose-related.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="312" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The bioavailability of metoprolol shows a dose-related, although not directly proportional, increase with dose and is not significantly affected by food following TOPROL-XL administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="313" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Pediatrics: The pharmacokinetic profile of TOPROL-XL was studied in 120 pediatric hypertensive patients (6-17 years of age) receiving doses ranging from 12.5 to 200 mg once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="314" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacokinetics of metoprolol were similar to those described previously in adults.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="315" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Age, gender, race, and ideal body weight had no significant effects on metoprolol pharmacokinetics.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="316" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Metoprolol apparent oral clearance (CL/F) increased linearly with body weight.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="317" LabelDrug="TOPROL" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Metoprolol pharmacokinetics have not been investigated in patients &lt; 6 years of age.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="heart failure drug therapy" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="catecholamine-depleting drugs" precipitantCode="N0000175640" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cyp2d6 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000182135" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="clonidine" precipitantCode="MN3L5RMN02" effect="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="clonidine" precipitantCode="MN3L5RMN02" effect="84094009: Rebound hypertension (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="clonidine" precipitantCode="MN3L5RMN02"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="diltiazem" precipitantCode="EE92BBP03H" effect="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="diltiazem" precipitantCode="EE92BBP03H" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="glycosides" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="verapamil" precipitantCode="CJ0O37KU29" effect="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="verapamil" precipitantCode="CJ0O37KU29" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="catecholamine depleting drugs" precipitantCode="N0000175640" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="mao | inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175744" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="monoamine oxidase (mao) inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175744" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="monoamine oxidase | inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175744" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="reserpine" precipitantCode="8B1QWR724A" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="catecholamine depletor" precipitantCode="N0000175640" effect="271594007: Syncope (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="catecholamine depletor" precipitantCode="N0000175640" effect="28651003: Orthostatic hypotension (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="catecholamine depletor" precipitantCode="N0000175640" effect="399153001: Vertigo (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="catecholamine depletor" precipitantCode="N0000175640" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="catecholamine depletor" precipitantCode="N0000175640" effect="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="drugs that inhibit cyp2d6" precipitantCode="N0000182135" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="fluoxetine" precipitantCode="01K63SUP8D" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="paroxetine" precipitantCode="41VRH5220H" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="propafenone" precipitantCode="68IQX3T69U" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="quinidine" precipitantCode="ITX08688JL" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="quinidine" precipitantCode="ITX08688JL" effect="C54603"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="epinephrine" precipitantCode="YKH834O4BH" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="calcium channel blockers" precipitantCode="N0000175566" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="isoproterenol" precipitantCode="L628TT009W" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cyp2d6 inhibiting drugs" precipitantCode="N0000182135" effect="C54355"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>