<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Twynsta" setid="627146d8-fa8e-4c8b-b703-29ee080a6d5b">
<Text><Section name="BOXED WARNING SECTION" id="34066-1">
When pregnancy is detected, discontinue TWYNSTA as soon as possible [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]  .    Drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause injury and death to the developing fetus [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)].           WARNING: FETAL TOXICITY     [See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning] .    When pregnancy is detected, discontinue TWYNSTA as soon as possible (5.1)      Drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause injury and death to the developing fetus (5.1)</Section>
<Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
TWYNSTA tablets are contraindicated in patients with known hypersensitivity (e.g., anaphylaxis or angioedema) to telmisartan, amlodipine, or any other component of this product  [see Adverse Reactions (6.2)] .   Do not co-administer aliskiren with TWYNSTA in patients with diabetes [see Drug Interactions (7.2)].         Known hypersensitivity (e.g., anaphylaxis or angioedema) to telmisartan, amlodipine or any other component of this product (4)  Do not co-administer aliskiren with TWYNSTA in patients with diabetes (4)</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
Substitute TWYNSTA for its individually titrated components for patients on amlodipine and telmisartan. TWYNSTA may also be given with increased amounts of amlodipine, telmisartan, or both, as needed. (2.2, 2.3)  Use TWYNSTA tablets to provide additional blood pressure lowering for patients not adequately controlled with amlodipine (or another dihydropyridine calcium channel blocker) alone or with telmisartan (or another angiotensin receptor blocker) alone (2.3)  Dosage may be increased after at least 2 weeks to a maximum dose of 80/10 mg once daily, usually by increasing one component at a time but both components can be raised to achieve more rapid control (2.1, 2.2)  Majority of antihypertensive effect is attained within 2 weeks (2.1)  Initiate with 40/5 mg or 80/5 mg once daily (2.4)  Switch patients who experience dose-limiting adverse reactions on amlodipine to TWYNSTA tablets containing a lower dose of that component (2.3)           Telmisartan is an effective treatment of hypertension in once daily doses of 20 to 80 mg while amlodipine is effective in doses of 2.5 to 10 mg. Dosage must be individualized and may be increased after at least 2 weeks. Most of the antihypertensive effect is apparent within 2 weeks and maximal reduction is generally attained after 4 weeks. The maximum recommended dose of TWYNSTA tablets is 80/10 mg once daily.  The adverse reactions of telmisartan are uncommon and independent of dose; those of amlodipine are a mixture of dose-dependent phenomena (primarily peripheral edema) and dose-independent phenomena, the former much more common than the latter  [see Adverse Reactions (6.1)] . TWYNSTA may be taken with or without food.          Patients receiving amlodipine and telmisartan from separate tablets may instead receive TWYNSTA tablets containing the same component doses once daily. When substituting for individual components, increase the dose of TWYNSTA if blood pressure control has not been satisfactory.          TWYNSTA tablets may be used to provide additional blood pressure lowering for patients not adequately controlled with amlodipine (or another dihydropyridine calcium channel blocker) alone or with telmisartan (or another angiotensin receptor blocker) alone. Patients treated with 10 mg amlodipine who experience any dose-limiting adverse reactions such as edema, may be switched to TWYNSTA 40/5 mg tablets once daily, reducing the dose of amlodipine without reducing the overall expected antihypertensive response  [see Adverse Reactions (6.1)] .          A patient may be initiated on TWYNSTA tablets if it is unlikely that control of blood pressure would be achieved with a single agent. The usual starting dose of TWYNSTA is 40/5 mg once daily. Patients requiring larger blood pressure reductions may be started on TWYNSTA 80/5 mg once daily. Initial therapy with TWYNSTA is not recommended in patients ≥75 years old or with hepatic impairment  [see Dosage and Administration (2.5), Warnings and Precautions (5.4), and Use in Specific Populations (8.5, 8.6)] . Correct imbalances of intravascular volume- or salt-depletion, before initiating therapy with TWYNSTA tablets  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)] .            Renal Impairment  No initial dosage adjustment is required for patients with mild or moderate renal impairment. Titrate slowly in patients with severe renal impairment.   Hepatic Impairment  In most patients, initiate amlodipine therapy at 2.5 mg. Titrate slowly in patients with hepatic impairment.   Patients 75 Years of Age and Older  In most patients, initiate amlodipine therapy at 2.5 mg. Titrate slowly in patients 75 years of age and older.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
NSAIDS: Increased risk of renal impairment and loss of antihypertensive effect (7)  If simvastatin is co-administered with amlodipine, do not exceed doses greater than 20 mg daily of simvastatin (7)  Do not co-administer aliskiren with TWYNSTA in patients with diabetes (7.2)           The pharmacokinetics of amlodipine and telmisartan are not altered when the drugs are co-administered. No drug interaction studies have been conducted with TWYNSTA tablets and other drugs, although studies have been conducted with the individual amlodipine and telmisartan components of TWYNSTA tablets, as described below:           Aliskiren: Do not co-administer aliskiren with TWYNSTA in patients with diabetes. Avoid use of aliskiren with TWYNSTA in patients with renal impairment (GFR &amp;lt;60 mL/min).   Digoxin:  When telmisartan was co-administered with digoxin, median increases in digoxin peak plasma concentration (49%) and in trough concentration (20%) were observed. Therefore, monitor digoxin levels when initiating, adjusting, and discontinuing telmisartan for the purpose of keeping the digoxin level within the therapeutic range.   Lithium:  Reversible increases in serum lithium concentrations and toxicity have been reported during concomitant administration of lithium with angiotensin II receptor antagonists including telmisartan. Therefore, monitor serum lithium levels during concomitant use.   Non-Steroidal Anti-Inflammatory Agents including Selective Cyclooxygenase-2 Inhibitors (COX-2 Inhibitors):  In patients who are elderly, volume-depleted (including those on diuretic therapy), or with compromised renal function, co-administration of NSAIDs, including selective COX-2 inhibitors, with angiotensin II receptor antagonists, including telmisartan, may result in deterioration of renal function, including possible acute renal failure. These effects are usually reversible. Monitor renal function periodically in patients receiving telmisartan and NSAID therapy. The antihypertensive effect of angiotensin II receptor antagonists, including telmisartan may be attenuated by NSAIDs including selective COX-2 inhibitors.   Ramipril and Ramiprilat:  Co-administration of telmisartan 80 mg once daily and ramipril 10 mg once daily to healthy subjects increases steady-state Cmax and AUC of ramipril 2.3- and 2.1-fold, respectively, and Cmax and AUC of ramiprilat 2.4- and 1.5-fold, respectively. In contrast, Cmax and AUC of telmisartan decrease by 31% and 16%, respectively. When co-administering telmisartan and ramipril, the response may be greater because of the possibly additive pharmacodynamic effects of the combined drugs, and also because of the increased exposure to ramipril and ramiprilat in the presence of telmisartan.  Co-administration of telmisartan and ramipril is not recommended.   Other Drugs:  Co-administration of telmisartan did not result in a clinically significant interaction with acetaminophen, amlodipine, glyburide, simvastatin, hydrochlorothiazide, warfarin, or ibuprofen. Telmisartan is not metabolized by the cytochrome P450 system and had no effects  in vitro on cytochrome P450 enzymes, except for some inhibition of CYP2C19. Telmisartan is not expected to interact with drugs that inhibit cytochrome P450 enzymes; it is also not expected to interact with drugs metabolized by cytochrome P450 enzymes, except for possible inhibition of the metabolism of drugs metabolized by CYP2C19.          In clinical trials, amlodipine has been safely administered with thiazide diuretics, beta-blockers, angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors, long-acting nitrates, sublingual nitroglycerin, digoxin, warfarin, non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs, antibiotics, and oral hypoglycemic drugs.   Simvastatin: Co-administration of multiple doses of 10 mg of amlodipine with 80 mg simvastatin resulted in a 77% increase in exposure to simvastatin compared to simvastatin alone. Limit the dose of simvastatin in patients on amlodipine to 20 mg daily. The following have no clinically relevant effects on the pharmacokinetics of amlodipine: cimetidine, grapefruit juice, magnesium and aluminum hydroxide antacid, sildenafil. Amlodipine has no clinically relevant effects on the pharmacokinetics or pharmacodynamics of the following: atorvastatin, digoxin, warfarin.  CYP3A4 Inhibitors Co-administration of a 180 mg daily dose of diltiazem with 5 mg amlodipine in elderly hypertensive patients resulted in a 60% increase in amlodipine systemic exposure. Erythromycin co-administration in healthy volunteers did not significantly change amlodipine systemic exposure. However, strong inhibitors of CYP3A4 (e.g., ketoconazole, itraconazole, ritonavir) may increase the plasma concentrations of amlodipine to a greater extent. Monitor for symptoms of hypotension and edema when amlodipine is co-administered with CYP3A4 inhibitors.  CYP3A4 Inducers No information is available on the quantitative effects of CYP3A4 inducers (e.g., carbamazepine, phenobarbital, phenytoin, fosphenytoin, primidone, rifampicin, St. John’s Wort) on amlodipine. Patients should be monitored for adequate clinical effect when amlodipine is co-administered with CYP3A4 inducers.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
Avoid fetal or neonatal exposure (5.1)  Hypotension: Correct any volume or salt depletion before initiating therapy. Observe for signs and symptoms of hypotension. Symptomatic hypotension is possible, particularly in patients with severe aortic stenosis (5.2)  Titrate slowly in patients with hepatic (5.4) or severe renal impairment (5.5)  Heart failure: Monitor for worsening (5.8)  Avoid concomitant use with an ACE inhibitor (5.6)  Myocardial infarction: Worsening angina and acute myocardial infarction can develop after starting or increasing the dose of TWYNSTA, particularly in patients with severe obstructive coronary artery disease (5.7)              Pregnancy Category D       Telmisartan    Use of drugs that act on the renin-angiotensin system during the second and third trimesters of pregnancy reduces fetal renal function and increases fetal and neonatal morbidity and death. Resulting oligohydramnios can be associated with fetal lung hypoplasia and skeletal deformations. Potential neonatal adverse effects include skull hypoplasia, anuria, hypotension, renal failure, and death. When pregnancy is detected, discontinue TWYNSTA as soon as possible  [see Use in Specific Populations (8.1)] .             Telmisartan  In patients with an activated renin-angiotensin system, such as volume- or salt-depleted patients (e.g., those being treated with high doses of diuretics), symptomatic hypotension may occur after initiation of therapy with TWYNSTA tablets. Either correct this condition prior to administration of TWYNSTA tablets, or start treatment under close medical supervision with a reduced dose. If hypotension does occur, place the patient in the supine position and, if necessary, give an intravenous infusion of normal saline. A transient hypotensive response is not a contraindication to further treatment, which usually can be continued without difficulty once the blood pressure has stabilized.   Amlodipine    Symptomatic hypotension is possible, particularly in patients with severe aortic stenosis. Because of the gradual onset of action, acute hypotension is unlikely.             Telmisartan  Hyperkalemia may occur in patients on ARBs, particularly in patients with advanced renal impairment, heart failure, on renal replacement therapy, or on potassium supplements, potassium-sparing diuretics, potassium-containing salt substitutes or other drugs that increase potassium levels. Consider periodic determinations of serum electrolytes to detect possible electrolyte imbalances, particularly in patients at risk.            Telmisartan  As the majority of telmisartan is eliminated by biliary excretion, patients with biliary obstructive disorders or hepatic insufficiency can be expected to have reduced clearance. Initiate telmisartan at low doses and titrate slowly in these patients  [see Dosage and Administration (2.5), Use in Specific Populations (8.6), and Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)] .   Amlodipine  Amlodipine is extensively metabolized by the liver and the plasma elimination half-life (t1/2) is 56 hours in patients with impaired hepatic function. Since patients with hepatic impairment have decreased clearance of amlodipine, start amlodipine or add amlodipine at 2.5 mg in patients with hepatic impairment. The lowest dose of TWYNSTA is 40/5 mg; therefore, initial therapy with TWYNSTA tablets is not recommended in hepatically impaired patients  [see Use in Specific Populations (8.6)] .            Telmisartan  As a consequence of inhibiting the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system, anticipate changes in renal function in susceptible individuals. In patients whose renal function may depend on the activity of the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system (e.g., patients with severe congestive heart failure or renal dysfunction), treatment with angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE) inhibitors and angiotensin receptor antagonists has been associated with oliguria and/or progressive azotemia and (rarely) with acute renal failure and/or death. Similar results may be anticipated in patients treated with telmisartan  [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)] . In studies of ACE inhibitors in patients with unilateral or bilateral renal artery stenosis, increases in serum creatinine or blood urea nitrogen were observed. There has been no long term use of telmisartan in patients with unilateral or bilateral renal artery stenosis, but anticipate an effect similar to that seen with ACE inhibitors.            Telmisartan  As a consequence of inhibiting the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system, changes in renal function (including acute renal failure) have been reported. Dual blockade of the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system (e.g., by adding an ACE-inhibitor to an angiotensin II receptor antagonist) should include close monitoring of renal function. The ONTARGET trial enrolled 25,620 patients ≥55 years old with atherosclerotic disease or diabetes with end-organ damage, randomized them to telmisartan only, ramipril only, or the combination, and followed them for a median of 56 months. Patients receiving the combination of telmisartan and ramipril did not obtain any additional benefit compared to monotherapy, but experienced an increased incidence of renal dysfunction (e.g., acute renal failure) compared with groups receiving telmisartan alone or ramipril alone. Concomitant use of telmisartan and ramipril is not recommended.            Amlodipine    Worsening angina and acute myocardial infarction can develop after starting or increasing the dose of TWYNSTA, particularly in patients with severe obstructive coronary artery disease.             Amlodipine  Closely monitor patients with heart failure. Amlodipine (5 to 10 mg per day) has been studied in a placebo-controlled trial of 1153 patients with NYHA Class III or IV heart failure on stable doses of ACE inhibitor, digoxin, and diuretics. Follow-up was at least 6 months, with a mean of about 14 months. There was no overall adverse effect on survival or cardiac morbidity (as defined by life-threatening arrhythmia, acute myocardial infarction, or hospitalization for worsened heart failure). Amlodipine has been compared to placebo in four 8 to 12 week studies of patients with NYHA class II/III heart failure, involving a total of 697 patients. In these studies, there was no evidence of worsening of heart failure based on measures of exercise tolerance, NYHA classification, symptoms, or LVEF. In the PRAISE-2 study, 1654 patients with NYHA class III (80%) or IV (20%) heart failure without evidence of underlying ischemic disease, on stable doses of ACE inhibitor (99%), digitalis (99%), and diuretics (99%) were randomized 1:1 to receive placebo or amlodipine and followed for a mean of 33 months. While there was no statistically significant difference between amlodipine and placebo in the primary endpoint of all cause mortality (95% confidence limits from 8% reduction to 29% increase on amlodipine), there were more reports of pulmonary edema in the patients on amlodipine.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Telmisartan  Angiotensin II is formed from angiotensin I in a reaction catalyzed by angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE, kininase II). Angiotensin II is the principal pressor agent of the renin-angiotensin system, with effects that include vasoconstriction, stimulation of synthesis and release of aldosterone, cardiac stimulation, and renal reabsorption of sodium. Telmisartan blocks the vasoconstrictor and aldosterone-secreting effects of angiotensin II by selectively blocking the binding of angiotensin II to the AT1 receptor in many tissues, such as vascular smooth muscle and the adrenal gland. Its action is therefore independent of the pathways for angiotensin II synthesis. There is also an AT2 receptor found in many tissues, but AT2 is not known to be associated with cardiovascular homeostasis. Telmisartan has much greater affinity (&amp;gt;3,000 fold) for the AT1 receptor than for the AT2 receptor. Blockade of the renin-angiotensin system with ACE inhibitors, which inhibit the biosynthesis of angiotensin II from angiotensin I, is widely used in the treatment of hypertension. ACE inhibitors also inhibit the degradation of bradykinin, a reaction also catalyzed by ACE. Because telmisartan does not inhibit ACE (kininase II), it does not affect the response to bradykinin. Whether this difference has clinical relevance is not yet known. Telmisartan does not bind to or block other hormone receptors or ion channels known to be important in cardiovascular regulation. Blockade of the angiotensin II receptor inhibits the negative regulatory feedback of angiotensin II on renin secretion, but the resulting increased plasma renin activity and angiotensin II circulating levels do not overcome the effect of telmisartan on blood pressure.   Amlodipine   Amlodipine is a dihydropyridine calcium channel blocker that inhibits the transmembrane influx of calcium ions into vascular smooth muscle and cardiac muscle. Experimental data suggest that amlodipine binds to both dihydropyridine and nondihydropyridine binding sites. The contractile processes of cardiac muscle and vascular smooth muscle are dependent upon the movement of extracellular calcium ions into these cells through specific ion channels. Amlodipine inhibits calcium ion influx across cell membranes selectively, with a greater effect on vascular smooth muscle cells than on cardiac muscle cells. Negative inotropic effects can be detected  in vitro but such effects have not been seen in intact animals at therapeutic doses. Serum calcium concentration is not affected by amlodipine. Within the physiologic pH range, amlodipine is an ionized compound (pKa=8.6), and its kinetic interaction with the calcium channel receptor is characterized by a gradual rate of association and dissociation with the receptor binding site, resulting in a gradual onset of effect. Amlodipine is a peripheral arterial vasodilator that acts directly on vascular smooth muscle to cause a reduction in peripheral vascular resistance and reduction in blood pressure.            TWYNSTA Tablets  TWYNSTA tablets have been shown to be effective in lowering blood pressure. TWYNSTA is a combination of two drugs with antihypertensive properties: a dihydropyridine calcium antagonist (calcium ion antagonist or slow-channel blocker), amlodipine besylate, and an angiotensin II receptor blocker, telmisartan. Both telmisartan and amlodipine lower blood pressure by reducing peripheral resistance but through complementary mechanisms.   Telmisartan  In normal volunteers, a dose of telmisartan 80 mg inhibited the pressor response to an intravenous infusion of angiotensin II by about 90% at peak plasma concentrations with approximately 40% inhibition persisting for 24 hours. Plasma concentration of angiotensin II and plasma renin activity (PRA) increased in a dose-dependent manner after single administration of telmisartan to healthy subjects and repeated administration to hypertensive patients. The once-daily administration of up to 80 mg telmisartan to healthy subjects did not influence plasma aldosterone concentrations. In multiple dose studies with hypertensive patients, there were no clinically significant changes in electrolytes (serum potassium or sodium), or in metabolic function (including serum levels of cholesterol, triglycerides, HDL, LDL, glucose, or uric acid). In 30 hypertensive patients with normal renal function treated for 8 weeks with telmisartan 80 mg or telmisartan 80 mg in combination with hydrochlorothiazide 12.5 mg, there were no clinically significant changes from baseline in renal blood flow, glomerular filtration rate, filtration fraction, renovascular resistance, or creatinine clearance. Telmisartan has indications other than hypertension which can be found in the Micardis® (telmisartan) tablets package insert.   Amlodipine  Following administration of therapeutic doses to patients with hypertension, amlodipine produces vasodilation resulting in a reduction of supine and standing blood pressures. These decreases in blood pressure are not accompanied by a significant change in heart rate or plasma catecholamine levels with chronic dosing. Although the acute intravenous administration of amlodipine decreases arterial blood pressure and increases heart rate in hemodynamic studies of patients with chronic stable angina, chronic oral administration of amlodipine in clinical trials did not lead to clinically significant changes in heart rate or blood pressures in normotensive patients with angina. With chronic once daily administration, antihypertensive effectiveness is maintained for at least 24 hours. Plasma concentrations correlate with effect in both young and elderly patients. The magnitude of reduction in blood pressure with amlodipine is also correlated with the height of pretreatment elevation; thus, individuals with moderate hypertension (diastolic pressure 105 to 114 mmHg) had about a 50% greater response than patients with mild hypertension (diastolic pressure 90 to 104 mmHg). Normotensive subjects experienced no clinically significant change in blood pressure (+1/-2 mmHg). In hypertensive patients with normal renal function, therapeutic doses of amlodipine resulted in a decrease in renal vascular resistance and an increase in glomerular filtration rate and effective renal plasma flow without change in filtration fraction or proteinuria. As with other calcium channel blockers, hemodynamic measurements of cardiac function at rest and during exercise (or pacing) in patients with normal ventricular function treated with amlodipine have generally demonstrated a small increase in cardiac index without significant influence on dP/dt or on left ventricular end diastolic pressure or volume. In hemodynamic studies, amlodipine has not been associated with a negative inotropic effect when administered in the therapeutic dose range to intact animals and man, even when co-administered with beta-blockers to man. Similar findings, however, have been observed in normal or well-compensated patients with heart failure with agents possessing significant negative inotropic effects. Amlodipine does not change sinoatrial nodal function or atrioventricular conduction in intact animals or man. In patients with chronic stable angina, intravenous administration of 10 mg did not significantly alter A-H and H-V conduction and sinus node recovery time after pacing. Similar results were obtained in patients receiving amlodipine and concomitant beta-blockers. In clinical studies in which amlodipine was administered in combination with beta-blockers to patients with either hypertension or angina, no adverse effects of electrocardiographic parameters were observed. In clinical trials with angina patients alone, amlodipine therapy did not alter electrocardiographic intervals or produce higher degrees of AV blocks. Amlodipine has indications other than hypertension which can be found in the Norvasc® package insert.            TWYNSTA Tablets  The pharmacokinetics of amlodipine and telmisartan when combined are similar to the pharmacokinetics of amlodipine and telmisartan when administered separately. After administering TWYNSTA 80/10 mg tablet with a high-fat meal, the total area under the plasma concentration-time curve (AUC) and Cmax for telmisartan decreased by about 24% and 60%, respectively. For amlodipine, AUC and Cmax were not altered  [see Dosage and Administration (2.1)] .   Telmisartan  Following oral administration, peak concentrations (Cmax) of telmisartan are reached in 0.5 to 1 hour after dosing. Food slightly reduces the bioavailability of telmisartan, with a reduction in the area under the plasma concentration-time curve (AUC) of about 6% with the 40 mg tablet and about 20% after a 160 mg dose. The absolute bioavailability of telmisartan is dose dependent. At 40 and 160 mg the bioavailability was 42% and 58%, respectively. The pharmacokinetics of orally administered telmisartan are nonlinear over the dose range 20 to 160 mg, with greater than proportional increases of plasma concentrations (Cmax and AUC) with increasing doses. Telmisartan shows bi-exponential decay kinetics with a terminal elimination half life of approximately 24 hours. Trough plasma concentrations of telmisartan with once daily dosing are about 10% to 25% of peak plasma concentrations. Telmisartan has an accumulation index in plasma of 1.5 to 2.0 upon repeated once daily dosing.   Amlodipine  Peak plasma concentrations of amlodipine are reached 6 to 12 hours after administration of amlodipine alone. Absolute bioavailability has been estimated to be between 64% and 90%. The bioavailability of amlodipine is not altered by the presence of food. Elimination of amlodipine from the plasma is biphasic with a terminal elimination half-life of about 30 to 50 hours. Steady state plasma levels of amlodipine are reached after 7 to 8 days of consecutive daily dosing.    Distribution     Telmisartan  Telmisartan is highly bound to plasma proteins (&amp;gt;99.5%), mainly albumin and α1 - acid glycoprotein. Plasma protein binding is constant over the concentration range achieved with recommended doses. The volume of distribution for telmisartan is approximately 500 liters indicating additional tissue binding.   Amlodipine  The apparent volume of distribution of amlodipine is 21 L/kg. Approximately 93% of circulating amlodipine is bound to plasma proteins in hypertensive patients.     Metabolism and Elimination       Telmisartan  Following either intravenous or oral administration of 14C-labeled telmisartan, most of the administered dose (&amp;gt;97%) was eliminated unchanged in feces via biliary excretion; only minute amounts were found in the urine (0.91% and 0.49% of total radioactivity, respectively). Telmisartan is metabolized by conjugation to form a pharmacologically inactive acylglucuronide; the glucuronide of the parent compound is the only metabolite that has been identified in human plasma and urine. After a single dose, the glucuronide represents approximately 11% of the measured radioactivity in plasma. The cytochrome P450 isoenzymes are not involved in the metabolism of telmisartan. Total plasma clearance of telmisartan is &amp;gt;800 mL/min. Terminal half-life and total clearance appear to be independent of dose.   Amlodipine  Amlodipine is extensively (about 90%) converted to inactive metabolites via hepatic metabolism with 10% of the parent compound and 60% of the metabolites excreted in the urine.     Special Populations        Renal Insufficiency      Telmisartan : No dosage adjustment is necessary in patients with decreased renal function. Telmisartan is not removed from blood by hemofiltration  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.5)] .   Amlodipine : The pharmacokinetics of amlodipine are not significantly influenced by renal impairment. Patients with renal failure may therefore receive the usual initial dose.     Hepatic Insufficiency       Telmisartan : In patients with hepatic insufficiency, plasma concentrations of telmisartan are increased, and absolute bioavailability approaches 100%  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.4) and Use in Specific Populations (8.5)] .   Amlodipine : Patients with hepatic insufficiency have decreased clearance of amlodipine with a resulting increase in AUC of approximately 40% to 60%. Therefore, start with a low initial dose of amlodipine.     Gender     Plasma concentrations of telmisartan are generally 2 to 3 times higher in females than in males. In clinical trials, however, no significant increases in blood pressure response or in the incidence of orthostatic hypotension were found in women. No dosage adjustment is necessary.     Geriatric Patients      Telmisartan : The pharmacokinetics of telmisartan do not differ between the elderly and those younger than 65 years  [see Dosage and Administration (2.1)] .   Amlodipine : Elderly patients have decreased clearance of amlodipine with a resulting increase in AUC of approximately 40% to 60%. Therefore, start with a low initial dose of amlodipine  [see Dosage and Administration (2.5)] .</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="2061" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>When pregnancy is detected, discontinue TWYNSTA as soon as possible.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2062" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause injury and death to the developing fetus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2063" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>WARNING: FETAL TOXICITY See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2064" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>When pregnancy is detected, discontinue TWYNSTA as soon as possible (5.1, 8.1) Drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause injury and death to the developing fetus (5.1, 8.1)</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2065" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>TWYNSTA tablets are contraindicated in patients with known hypersensitivity (e.g., anaphylaxis or angioedema) to telmisartan, amlodipine, or any other component of this product.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2066" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Do not co-administer aliskiren with TWYNSTA in patients with diabetes.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M1" type="Trigger" span="0 20" str="Do not co-administer"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="21 9" str="aliskiren" code="502FWN4Q32"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M1" precipitant="M2"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2067" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Known hypersensitivity (e.g., anaphylaxis or angioedema) to telmisartan, amlodipine or any other component of this product (4) Do not co-administer aliskiren with TWYNSTA in patients with diabetes (4)</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M3" type="Trigger" span="127 20" str="Do not co-administer"/>
<Mention id="M4" type="Precipitant" span="148 9" str="aliskiren" code="502FWN4Q32"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M3" precipitant="M4"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2068" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Substitute TWYNSTA for its individually titrated components for patients on amlodipine and telmisartan.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2069" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>TWYNSTA may also be given with increased amounts of amlodipine, telmisartan, or both, as needed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2070" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Use TWYNSTA tablets to provide additional blood pressure lowering for patients not adequately controlled with amlodipine (or another dihydropyridine calcium channel blocker) alone or with telmisartan (or another angiotensin receptor blocker) alone (2.3) Dosage may be increased after at least 2 weeks to a maximum dose of 80/10 mg once daily, usually by increasing one component at a time but both components can be raised to achieve more rapid control (2.1, 2.2) Majority of antihypertensive effect is attained within 2 weeks (2.1) Initiate with 40/5 mg or 80/5 mg once daily (2.4) Switch patients who experience dose-limiting adverse reactions on amlodipine to TWYNSTA tablets containing a lower dose of that component (2.3) Telmisartan is an effective treatment of hypertension in once daily doses of 20 to 80 mg while amlodipine is effective in doses of 2.5 to 10 mg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2071" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dosage must be individualized and may be increased after at least 2 weeks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2072" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Most of the antihypertensive effect is apparent within 2 weeks and maximal reduction is generally attained after 4 weeks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2073" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The maximum recommended dose of TWYNSTA tablets is 80/10 mg once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2074" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The adverse reactions of telmisartan are uncommon and independent of dose; those of amlodipine are a mixture of dose-dependent phenomena (primarily peripheral edema) and dose-independent phenomena, the former much more common than the latter.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2075" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>TWYNSTA may be taken with or without food.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2076" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Patients receiving amlodipine and telmisartan from separate tablets may instead receive TWYNSTA tablets containing the same component doses once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2077" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>When substituting for individual components, increase the dose of TWYNSTA if blood pressure control has not been satisfactory.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2078" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>TWYNSTA tablets may be used to provide additional blood pressure lowering for patients not adequately controlled with amlodipine (or another dihydropyridine calcium channel blocker) alone or with telmisartan (or another angiotensin receptor blocker) alone.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2079" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Patients treated with 10 mg amlodipine who experience any dose-limiting adverse reactions such as edema, may be switched to TWYNSTA 40/5 mg tablets once daily, reducing the dose of amlodipine without reducing the overall expected antihypertensive response.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2080" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>A patient may be initiated on TWYNSTA tablets if it is unlikely that control of blood pressure would be achieved with a single agent.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2081" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The usual starting dose of TWYNSTA is 40/5 mg once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2082" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Patients requiring larger blood pressure reductions may be started on TWYNSTA 80/5 mg once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2083" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Initial therapy with TWYNSTA is not recommended in patients ≥75 years old or with hepatic impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2084" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Correct imbalances of intravascular volume- or salt-depletion, before initiating therapy with TWYNSTA tablets.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2085" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Renal Impairment No initial dosage adjustment is required for patients with mild or moderate renal impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2086" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Titrate slowly in patients with severe renal impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2087" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Hepatic Impairment In most patients, initiate amlodipine therapy at 2.5 mg. Titrate slowly in patients with hepatic impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2088" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Patients 75 Years of Age and Older In most patients, initiate amlodipine therapy at 2.5 mg. Titrate slowly in patients 75 years of age and older.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2089" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>NSAIDs: Increased risk of renal impairment and loss of anti-hypertensive effect (7) If simvastatin is co-administered with amlodipine, do not exceed doses greater than 20 mg daily of simvastatin (7) Do not co-administer aliskiren with TWYNSTA in patients with diabetes (7.2) The pharmacokinetics of amlodipine and telmisartan are not altered when the drugs are co-administered.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M8" type="Trigger" span="8 14" str="Increased risk"/>
<Mention id="M9" type="Precipitant" span="0 6" str="NSAIDs" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M7" type="SpecificInteraction" span="47 32" str="loss of anti-hypertensive effect" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M10" type="SpecificInteraction" span="26 16" str="renal impairment" code="236423003: Renal impairment (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M11" type="Trigger" span="135 13" str="do not exceed"/>
<Mention id="M12" type="Precipitant" span="87 11" str="simvastatin" code="AGG2FN16EV"/>
<Mention id="M13" type="Trigger" span="199 20" str="Do not co-administer"/>
<Mention id="M14" type="Precipitant" span="220 9" str="aliskiren" code="502FWN4Q32"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M8" precipitant="M9" effect="M7"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M8" precipitant="M9" effect="M10"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M11" precipitant="M12" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M13" precipitant="M14"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2090" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>No drug interaction studies have been conducted with TWYNSTA tablets and other drugs, although studies have been conducted with the individual amlodipine and telmisartan components of TWYNSTA tablets, as described below: Aliskiren: Do not co-administer aliskiren with TWYNSTA in patients with diabetes.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M15" type="Trigger" span="232 20" str="Do not co-administer"/>
<Mention id="M16" type="Precipitant" span="253 9" str="aliskiren" code="502FWN4Q32"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M15" precipitant="M16"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2091" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Avoid use of aliskiren with TWYNSTA in patients with renal impairment (GFR &lt;60 mL/min).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M17" type="Trigger" span="0 9" str="Avoid use"/>
<Mention id="M18" type="Precipitant" span="13 9" str="aliskiren" code="502FWN4Q32"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M17" precipitant="M18"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2092" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Digoxin: When telmisartan was co-administered with digoxin, median increases in digoxin peak plasma concentration (49%) and in trough concentration (20%) were observed.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M19" type="Trigger" span="67 9;127 20" str="increases | trough concentration"/>
<Mention id="M22" type="Precipitant" span="51 7" str="digoxin" code="73K4184T59"/>
<Mention id="M21" type="Trigger" span="67 9;88 25" str="increases | peak plasma concentration"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M19" precipitant="M22" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M21" precipitant="M22" effect="C54610"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2093" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Therefore, monitor digoxin levels when initiating, adjusting, and discontinuing telmisartan for the purpose of keeping the digoxin level within the therapeutic range.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M23" type="Trigger" span="11 7;27 6" str="monitor | levels"/>
<Mention id="M24" type="Precipitant" span="19 7" str="digoxin" code="73K4184T59"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M23" precipitant="M24"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2094" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Lithium: Reversible increases in serum lithium concentrations and toxicity have been reported during concomitant administration of lithium with angiotensin II receptor antagonists including telmisartan.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M25" type="Trigger" span="20 18;47 14" str="increases in serum | concentrations "/>
<Mention id="M26" type="Trigger" span="66 8" str=" toxicity"/>
<Mention id="M27" type="Precipitant" span="39 7" str="lithium" code="9FN79X2M3F"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M25;M26" precipitant="M27" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2095" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Therefore, monitor serum lithium levels during concomitant use.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M28" type="Trigger" span="11 7;33 6" str="monitor | levels"/>
<Mention id="M29" type="Precipitant" span="25 7" str="lithium" code="9FN79X2M3F"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M28" precipitant="M29"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2096" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Non-Steroidal Anti-Inflammatory Agents including Selective Cyclooxygenase-2 Inhibitors (COX-2 Inhibitors): In patients who are elderly, volume-depleted (including those on diuretic therapy), or with compromised renal function, co-administration of NSAIDs, including selective COX-2 inhibitors, with angiotensin II receptor antagonists, including telmisartan, may result in deterioration of renal function, including possible acute renal failure.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M57" type="Trigger" span="363 9" str="result in"/>
<Mention id="M34" type="Precipitant" span="88 16" str="COX-2 Inhibitors" code="N0000008288"/>
<Mention id="M56" type="SpecificInteraction" span="373 31" str="deterioration of renal function" code="236423003: Renal impairment (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M59" type="SpecificInteraction" span="425 19" str="acute renal failure" code="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M40" type="Precipitant" span="0 38" str="Non-Steroidal Anti-Inflammatory Agents" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M46" type="Precipitant" span="248 6" str="NSAIDs" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M52" type="Precipitant" span="266 26" str="selective COX-2 inhibitors" code="N0000008288"/>
<Mention id="M58" type="Precipitant" span="49 37" str="Selective Cyclooxygenase-2 Inhibitors" code="N0000008288"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M57" precipitant="M34" effect="M56"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M57" precipitant="M34" effect="M59"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M57" precipitant="M40" effect="M56"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M57" precipitant="M40" effect="M59"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M57" precipitant="M46" effect="M59"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M57" precipitant="M46" effect="M56"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M57" precipitant="M52" effect="M59"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M57" precipitant="M52" effect="M56"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M57" precipitant="M58" effect="M56"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M57" precipitant="M58" effect="M59"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2097" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor renal function periodically in patients receiving telmisartan and NSAID therapy.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M60" type="Trigger" span="0 7" str="Monitor"/>
<Mention id="M61" type="Precipitant" span="74 5" str="NSAID" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M62" type="SpecificInteraction" span="8 14" str="renal function" code="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M60" precipitant="M61" effect="M62"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2098" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The antihypertensive effect of angiotensin II receptor antagonists, including telmisartan may be attenuated by NSAIDs including selective COX-2 inhibitors.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M66" type="Trigger" span="21 6;97 10" str="effect | attenuated"/>
<Mention id="M64" type="Precipitant" span="111 6" str="NSAIDs" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M68" type="SpecificInteraction" span="4 62;97 10" str="antihypertensive effect of angiotensin II receptor antagonists | attenuated" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M67" type="Precipitant" span="128 26" str="selective COX-2 inhibitors" code="N0000008288"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M66" precipitant="M64" effect="M68"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M66" precipitant="M67" effect="M68"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2099" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>In clinical trials, amlodipine has been safely administered with thiazide diuretics, beta-blockers, angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors, long-acting nitrates, sublingual nitroglycerin, digoxin, warfarin, non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs, antibiotics, and oral hypoglycemic drugs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2100" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Simvastatin: Co-administration of multiple doses of 10 mg of amlodipine with 80 mg simvastatin resulted in a 77% increase in exposure to simvastatin compared to simvastatin alone.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M69" type="Trigger" span="113 20" str="increase in exposure"/>
<Mention id="M70" type="Precipitant" span="83 11" str="simvastatin" code="AGG2FN16EV"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M69" precipitant="M70" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2101" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Limit the dose of simvastatin in patients on amlodipine to 20 mg daily.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M71" type="Trigger" span="0 14" str="Limit the dose"/>
<Mention id="M72" type="Precipitant" span="18 11" str="simvastatin" code="AGG2FN16EV"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M71" precipitant="M72" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2102" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Immunosuppressants: Amlodipine may increase the systemic exposure of cyclosporine or tacrolimus when co-administered.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M75" type="Trigger" span="35 30" str="increase the systemic exposure"/>
<Mention id="M74" type="Precipitant" span="69 12" str="cyclosporine" code="83HN0GTJ6D"/>
<Mention id="M76" type="Precipitant" span="85 10" str="tacrolimus" code="WM0HAQ4WNM"/>
<Interaction id="I29" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M75" precipitant="M74" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I30" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M75" precipitant="M76" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2103" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Frequent monitoring of trough blood levels of cyclosporine and tacrolimus and dose adjustment when appropriate is recommended.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M80" type="Trigger" span="0 19" str="Frequent monitoring "/>
<Mention id="M81" type="Trigger" span="78 15" str=" dose adjustment"/>
<Mention id="M79" type="Precipitant" span="46 12" str="cyclosporine" code="83HN0GTJ6D"/>
<Mention id="M82" type="Precipitant" span="63 10" str="tacrolimus" code="WM0HAQ4WNM"/>
<Interaction id="I31" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M80;M81" precipitant="M79"/>
<Interaction id="I32" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M80;M81" precipitant="M82"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2104" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The following have no clinically relevant effects on the pharmacokinetics of amlodipine: cimetidine, grapefruit juice, magnesium and aluminum hydroxide antacid, sildenafil.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2105" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Amlodipine has no clinically relevant effects on the pharmacokinetics or pharmacodynamics of the following: atorvastatin, digoxin, warfarin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2106" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>CYP3A4 Inhibitors: Co-administration of a 180 mg daily dose of diltiazem with 5 mg amlodipine in elderly hypertensive patients resulted in a 60% increase in amlodipine systemic exposure.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M83" type="Trigger" span="145 8;168 17" str="increase | systemic exposure"/>
<Mention id="M84" type="Precipitant" span="63 9" str="diltiazem" code="EE92BBP03H"/>
<Interaction id="I33" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M83" precipitant="M84" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2107" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Erythromycin co-administration in healthy volunteers did not significantly change amlodipine systemic exposure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2108" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>However, strong inhibitors of CYP3A4 (e.g., ketoconazole, itraconazole, ritonavir) may increase the plasma concentrations of amlodipine to a greater extent.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M91" type="Trigger" span="87 34" str="increase the plasma concentrations"/>
<Mention id="M86" type="Precipitant" span="58 12" str="itraconazole" code="304NUG5GF4"/>
<Mention id="M88" type="Precipitant" span="44 12" str="ketoconazole" code="R9400W927I"/>
<Mention id="M90" type="Precipitant" span="72 9" str="ritonavir" code="O3J8G9O825"/>
<Mention id="M92" type="Precipitant" span="9 27" str="strong inhibitors of CYP3A4" code="N0000182141"/>
<Interaction id="I34" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M91" precipitant="M86" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I35" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M91" precipitant="M88" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I36" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M91" precipitant="M90" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I37" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M91" precipitant="M92" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2109" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor for symptoms of hypotension and edema when amlodipine is co-administered with CYP3A4 inhibitors.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M96" type="Trigger" span="0 20" str="Monitor for symptoms"/>
<Mention id="M97" type="Precipitant" span="86 17" str="CYP3A4 inhibitors" code="N0000182141"/>
<Mention id="M95" type="SpecificInteraction" span="24 11" str="hypotension" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M98" type="SpecificInteraction" span="40 5" str="edema" code="267038008: Edema (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I38" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M96" precipitant="M97" effect="M95"/>
<Interaction id="I39" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M96" precipitant="M97" effect="M98"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2110" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>CYP3A4 Inducers: No information is available on the quantitative effects of CYP3A4 inducers (e.g., carbamazepine, phenobarbital, phenytoin, fosphenytoin, primidone, rifampicin, St. John’s Wort) on amlodipine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2111" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Patients should be monitored for adequate clinical effect when amlodipine is co-administered with CYP3A4 inducers.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M99" type="Trigger" span="0 28" str="Patients should be monitored"/>
<Mention id="M100" type="Precipitant" span="98 15" str="CYP3A4 inducers" code="N0000185506"/>
<Interaction id="I40" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M99" precipitant="M100"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2112" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Avoid fetal or neonatal exposure (5.1) Hypotension: Correct any volume or salt depletion before initiating therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2113" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Observe for signs and symptoms of hypotension.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2114" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Symptomatic hypotension is possible, particularly in patients with severe aortic stenosis (5.2) Titrate slowly in patients with hepatic (5.4) or severe renal impairment (5.5) Heart failure: Monitor for worsening (5.8) Avoid concomitant use with an ACE inhibitor (5.6) Myocardial infarction: Worsening angina and acute myocardial infarction can develop after starting or increasing the dose of TWYNSTA, particularly in patients with severe obstructive coronary artery disease (5.7) Use of drugs that act on the renin-angiotensin system during the second and third trimesters of pregnancy reduces fetal renal function and increases fetal and neonatal morbidity and death.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M101" type="Trigger" span="218 5" str="Avoid"/>
<Mention id="M102" type="Precipitant" span="248 13" str="ACE inhibitor" code="N0000175562"/>
<Interaction id="I41" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M101" precipitant="M102"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2115" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Resulting oligohydramnios can be associated with fetal lung hypoplasia and skeletal deformations.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2116" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Potential neonatal adverse effects include skull hypoplasia, anuria, hypotension, renal failure, and death.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2117" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Telmisartan In patients with an activated renin-angiotensin system, such as volume- or salt-depleted patients (e.g., those being treated with high doses of diuretics), symptomatic hypotension may occur after initiation of therapy with TWYNSTA tablets.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M105" type="SpecificInteraction" span="168 23" str="symptomatic hypotension" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M104" type="Precipitant" span="142 23" str="high doses of diuretics" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I42" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M105" precipitant="M104" effect="M105"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2118" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Either correct this condition prior to administration of TWYNSTA tablets, or start treatment under close medical supervision with a reduced dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2119" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If hypotension does occur, place the patient in the supine position and, if necessary, give an intravenous infusion of normal saline.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2120" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>A transient hypotensive response is not a contraindication to further treatment, which usually can be continued without difficulty once the blood pressure has stabilized.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2121" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Amlodipine Symptomatic hypotension is possible, particularly in patients with severe aortic stenosis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2122" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Because of the gradual onset of action, acute hypotension is unlikely.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2123" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Telmisartan Hyperkalemia may occur in patients on ARBs, particularly in patients with advanced renal impairment, heart failure, on renal replacement therapy, or on potassium supplements, potassium-sparing diuretics, potassium-containing salt substitutes or other drugs that increase potassium levels.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M115" type="Trigger" span="12 12" str="Hyperkalemia"/>
<Mention id="M107" type="Precipitant" span="263 36" str="drugs that increase potassium levels" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M117" type="SpecificInteraction" span="-1 12" str="hyperkalemia" code="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M110" type="Precipitant" span="164 21" str="potassium supplements" code="RWP5GA015D"/>
<Mention id="M113" type="Precipitant" span="216 37" str="potassium-containing salt substitutes" code="N0000175600"/>
<Mention id="M116" type="Precipitant" span="187 27" str="potassium-sparing diuretics" code="N0000175418"/>
<Interaction id="I43" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M115" precipitant="M107" effect="M117"/>
<Interaction id="I44" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M115" precipitant="M110" effect="M117"/>
<Interaction id="I45" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M115" precipitant="M113" effect="M117"/>
<Interaction id="I46" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M115" precipitant="M116" effect="M117"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2124" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Consider periodic determinations of serum electrolytes to detect possible electrolyte imbalances, particularly in patients at risk.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2125" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Telmisartan As the majority of telmisartan is eliminated by biliary excretion, patients with biliary obstructive disorders or hepatic insufficiency can be expected to have reduced clearance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2126" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Initiate telmisartan at low doses and titrate slowly in these patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2127" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Amlodipine Amlodipine is extensively metabolized by the liver and the plasma elimination half-life (t1/2) is 56 hours in patients with impaired hepatic function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2128" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Since patients with hepatic impairment have decreased clearance of amlodipine, start amlodipine or add amlodipine at 2.5 mg in patients with hepatic impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2129" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The lowest dose of TWYNSTA is 40/5 mg; therefore, initial therapy with TWYNSTA tablets is not recommended in hepatically impaired patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2130" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Telmisartan As a consequence of inhibiting the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system, anticipate changes in renal function in susceptible individuals.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2131" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In patients whose renal function may depend on the activity of the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system (e.g., patients with severe congestive heart failure or renal dysfunction), treatment with angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE) inhibitors and angiotensin receptor antagonists has been associated with oliguria and/or progressive azotemia and (rarely) with acute renal failure and/or death.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M151" type="Trigger" span="288 15" str="associated with"/>
<Mention id="M128" type="Precipitant" span="226 3;231 10" str="ACE | inhibitors" code="N0000175562"/>
<Mention id="M147" type="SpecificInteraction" span="386 5" str="death" code="419620001: Death (event)"/>
<Mention id="M150" type="SpecificInteraction" span="304 8" str="oliguria" code="83128009: Oliguria (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M144" type="SpecificInteraction" span="359 19" str="acute renal failure" code="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M153" type="SpecificInteraction" span="320 20" str="progressive azotemia" code="445009001: Azotemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M140" type="Precipitant" span="195 46" str="angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE) inhibitors" code="N0000175562"/>
<Mention id="M152" type="Precipitant" span="195 29;231 10" str="angiotensin-converting enzyme | inhibitors" code="N0000175562"/>
<Interaction id="I47" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M151" precipitant="M128" effect="M147"/>
<Interaction id="I48" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M151" precipitant="M128" effect="M150"/>
<Interaction id="I49" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M151" precipitant="M128" effect="M144"/>
<Interaction id="I50" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M151" precipitant="M128" effect="M153"/>
<Interaction id="I51" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M151" precipitant="M140" effect="M144"/>
<Interaction id="I52" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M151" precipitant="M140" effect="M147"/>
<Interaction id="I53" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M151" precipitant="M140" effect="M150"/>
<Interaction id="I54" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M151" precipitant="M140" effect="M153"/>
<Interaction id="I55" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M151" precipitant="M152" effect="M144"/>
<Interaction id="I56" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M151" precipitant="M152" effect="M147"/>
<Interaction id="I57" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M151" precipitant="M152" effect="M150"/>
<Interaction id="I58" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M151" precipitant="M152" effect="M153"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2132" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Similar results may be anticipated in patients treated with telmisartan.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2133" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In studies of ACE inhibitors in patients with unilateral or bilateral renal artery stenosis, increases in serum creatinine or blood urea nitrogen were observed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2134" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There has been no long-term use of telmisartan in patients with unilateral or bilateral renal artery stenosis, but anticipate an effect similar to that seen with ACE inhibitors.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2135" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Telmisartan Dual blockade of the RAS with angiotensin-receptor blockers, ACE inhibitors, or aliskiren is associated with increased risks of hypotension, hyperkalemia, and changes in renal function (including acute renal failure) compared to monotherapy.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M198" type="Trigger" span="105 15" str="associated with "/>
<Mention id="M199" type="Trigger" span="121 15" str=" increased risks"/>
<Mention id="M168" type="Precipitant" span="73 14" str="ACE inhibitors" code="N0000175562"/>
<Mention id="M197" type="SpecificInteraction" span="153 12" str="hyperkalemia" code="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M189" type="SpecificInteraction" span="208 19" str="acute renal failure" code="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M193" type="SpecificInteraction" span="171 25" str="changes in renal function" code="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M201" type="SpecificInteraction" span="140 11" str="hypotension" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M184" type="Precipitant" span="92 9" str="aliskiren" code="502FWN4Q32"/>
<Mention id="M200" type="Precipitant" span="12 24" str="Dual blockade of the RAS" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I59" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M198;M199" precipitant="M168" effect="M197"/>
<Interaction id="I60" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M198;M199" precipitant="M168" effect="M189"/>
<Interaction id="I61" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M198;M199" precipitant="M168" effect="M193"/>
<Interaction id="I62" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M198;M199" precipitant="M168" effect="M201"/>
<Interaction id="I63" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M198;M199" precipitant="M184" effect="M193"/>
<Interaction id="I64" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M198;M199" precipitant="M184" effect="M197"/>
<Interaction id="I65" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M198;M199" precipitant="M184" effect="M189"/>
<Interaction id="I66" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M198;M199" precipitant="M184" effect="M201"/>
<Interaction id="I67" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M198;M199" precipitant="M200" effect="M189"/>
<Interaction id="I68" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M198;M199" precipitant="M200" effect="M193"/>
<Interaction id="I69" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M198;M199" precipitant="M200" effect="M197"/>
<Interaction id="I70" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M198;M199" precipitant="M200" effect="M201"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2136" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The ONTARGET trial enrolled 25,620 patients ≥55 years old with atherosclerotic disease or diabetes with end-organ damage, randomized them to telmisartan only, ramipril only, or the combination, and followed them for a median of 56 months.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2137" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients receiving the combination of telmisartan and ramipril did not obtain any additional benefit compared to monotherapy, but experienced an increased incidence of renal dysfunction (e.g., acute renal failure) compared with groups receiving telmisartan alone or ramipril alone.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M202" type="Trigger" span="145 19" str="increased incidence"/>
<Mention id="M203" type="Precipitant" span="54 8" str="ramipril" code="L35JN3I7SJ"/>
<Mention id="M204" type="SpecificInteraction" span="168 17" str="renal dysfunction" code="236423003: Renal impairment (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I71" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M202" precipitant="M203" effect="M204"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2138" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In most patients no benefit has been associated with using two RAS inhibitors concomitantly.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2139" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In general, avoid combined use of RAS inhibitors.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M205" type="Trigger" span="12 5" str="avoid"/>
<Mention id="M206" type="Precipitant" span="34 14" str="RAS inhibitors" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I72" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M205" precipitant="M206"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2140" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Closely monitor blood pressure, renal function and electrolytes in patients on TWYNSTA and other agents that affect the RAS.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M213" type="Trigger" span="0 15" str="Closely monitor"/>
<Mention id="M214" type="Precipitant" span="97 26" str="agents that affect the RAS" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M209" type="SpecificInteraction" span="16 14" str="blood pressure" code="38936003: Abnormal blood pressure (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M212" type="SpecificInteraction" span="51 12" str="electrolytes" code="166686006: Electrolytes abnormal (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M215" type="SpecificInteraction" span="32 14" str="renal function" code="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I73" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M213" precipitant="M214" effect="M209"/>
<Interaction id="I74" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M213" precipitant="M214" effect="M212"/>
<Interaction id="I75" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M213" precipitant="M214" effect="M215"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2141" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Avoid concomitant use of aliskiren with TWYNSTA in patients with renal impairment (GFR &lt;60 mL/min /1.73 m2).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M216" type="Trigger" span="0 5" str="Avoid"/>
<Mention id="M217" type="Precipitant" span="25 9" str="aliskiren" code="502FWN4Q32"/>
<Interaction id="I76" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M216" precipitant="M217"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2142" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Amlodipine Worsening angina and acute myocardial infarction can develop after starting or increasing the dose of TWYNSTA, particularly in patients with severe obstructive coronary artery disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2143" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Amlodipine Closely monitor patients with heart failure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2144" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Amlodipine (5 to 10 mg per day) has been studied in a placebo-controlled trial of 1153 patients with NYHA Class III or IV heart failure on stable doses of ACE inhibitor, digoxin, and diuretics.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2145" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Follow-up was at least 6 months, with a mean of about 14 months.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2146" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There was no overall adverse effect on survival or cardiac morbidity (as defined by life-threatening arrhythmia, acute myocardial infarction, or hospitalization for worsened heart failure).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2147" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Amlodipine has been compared to placebo in four 8 to 12 week studies of patients with NYHA class II/III heart failure, involving a total of 697 patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2148" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In these studies, there was no evidence of worsening of heart failure based on measures of exercise tolerance, NYHA classification, symptoms, or LVEF.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2149" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In the PRAISE-2 study, 1654 patients with NYHA class III (80%) or IV (20%) heart failure without evidence of underlying ischemic disease, on stable doses of ACE inhibitor (99%), digitalis (99%), and diuretics (99%) were randomized 1:1 to receive placebo or amlodipine and followed for a mean of 33 months.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2150" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>While there was no statistically significant difference between amlodipine and placebo in the primary endpoint of all-cause mortality (95% confidence limits from 8% reduction to 29% increase on amlodipine), there were more reports of pulmonary edema in the patients on amlodipine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2151" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Telmisartan Angiotensin II is formed from angiotensin I in a reaction catalyzed by angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE, kininase II).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2152" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Angiotensin II is the principal pressor agent of the renin-angiotensin system, with effects that include vasoconstriction, stimulation of synthesis and release of aldosterone, cardiac stimulation, and renal reabsorption of sodium.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2153" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Telmisartan blocks the vasoconstrictor and aldosterone-secreting effects of angiotensin II by selectively blocking the binding of angiotensin II to the AT1 receptor in many tissues, such as vascular smooth muscle and the adrenal gland.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2154" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Its action is therefore independent of the pathways for angiotensin II synthesis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2155" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There is also an AT2 receptor found in many tissues, but AT2 is not known to be associated with cardiovascular homeostasis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2156" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Telmisartan has much greater affinity (&gt;3,000 fold) for the AT1 receptor than for the AT2 receptor.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2157" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Blockade of the renin-angiotensin system with ACE inhibitors, which inhibit the biosynthesis of angiotensin II from angiotensin I, is widely used in the treatment of hypertension.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2158" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>ACE inhibitors also inhibit the degradation of bradykinin, a reaction also catalyzed by ACE.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2159" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Because telmisartan does not inhibit ACE (kininase II), it does not affect the response to bradykinin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2160" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Whether this difference has clinical relevance is not yet known.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2161" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Telmisartan does not bind to or block other hormone receptors or ion channels known to be important in cardiovascular regulation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2162" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Blockade of the angiotensin II receptor inhibits the negative regulatory feedback of angiotensin II on renin secretion, but the resulting increased plasma renin activity and angiotensin II circulating levels do not overcome the effect of telmisartan on blood pressure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2163" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Amlodipine Amlodipine is a dihydropyridine calcium channel blocker that inhibits the transmembrane influx of calcium ions into vascular smooth muscle and cardiac muscle.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2164" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Experimental data suggest that amlodipine binds to both dihydropyridine and nondihydropyridine binding sites.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2165" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The contractile processes of cardiac muscle and vascular smooth muscle are dependent upon the movement of extracellular calcium ions into these cells through specific ion channels.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2166" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Amlodipine inhibits calcium ion influx across cell membranes selectively, with a greater effect on vascular smooth muscle cells than on cardiac muscle cells.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2167" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Negative inotropic effects can be detected in vitro but such effects have not been seen in intact animals at therapeutic doses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2168" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Serum calcium concentration is not affected by amlodipine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2169" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Within the physiologic pH range, amlodipine is an ionized compound (pKa=8.6), and its kinetic interaction with the calcium channel receptor is characterized by a gradual rate of association and dissociation with the receptor binding site, resulting in a gradual onset of effect.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2170" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Amlodipine is a peripheral arterial vasodilator that acts directly on vascular smooth muscle to cause a reduction in peripheral vascular resistance and reduction in blood pressure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2171" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>TWYNSTA Tablets TWYNSTA tablets have been shown to be effective in lowering blood pressure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2172" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>TWYNSTA is a combination of two drugs with antihypertensive properties: a dihydropyridine calcium antagonist (calcium ion antagonist or slow-channel blocker), amlodipine besylate, and an angiotensin II receptor blocker, telmisartan.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2173" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Both telmisartan and amlodipine lower blood pressure by reducing peripheral resistance but through complementary mechanisms.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2174" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Telmisartan In normal volunteers, a dose of telmisartan 80 mg inhibited the pressor response to an intravenous infusion of angiotensin II by about 90% at peak plasma concentrations with approximately 40% inhibition persisting for 24 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2175" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Plasma concentration of angiotensin II and plasma renin activity (PRA) increased in a dose-dependent manner after single administration of telmisartan to healthy subjects and repeated administration to hypertensive patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2176" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The once-daily administration of up to 80 mg telmisartan to healthy subjects did not influence plasma aldosterone concentrations.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2177" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In multiple dose studies with hypertensive patients, there were no clinically significant changes in electrolytes (serum potassium or sodium), or in metabolic function (including serum levels of cholesterol, triglycerides, HDL, LDL, glucose, or uric acid).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2178" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In 30 hypertensive patients with normal renal function treated for 8 weeks with telmisartan 80 mg or telmisartan 80 mg in combination with hydrochlorothiazide 12.5 mg, there were no clinically significant changes from baseline in renal blood flow, glomerular filtration rate, filtration fraction, renovascular resistance, or creatinine clearance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2179" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Telmisartan has indications other than hypertension which can be found in the Micardis® (telmisartan) tablets package insert.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2180" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Amlodipine Following administration of therapeutic doses to patients with hypertension, amlodipine produces vasodilation resulting in a reduction of supine and standing blood pressures.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2181" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>These decreases in blood pressure are not accompanied by a significant change in heart rate or plasma catecholamine levels with chronic dosing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2182" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Although the acute intravenous administration of amlodipine decreases arterial blood pressure and increases heart rate in hemodynamic studies of patients with chronic stable angina, chronic oral administration of amlodipine in clinical trials did not lead to clinically significant changes in heart rate or blood pressures in normotensive patients with angina.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2183" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>With chronic once daily administration, antihypertensive effectiveness is maintained for at least 24 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2184" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Plasma concentrations correlate with effect in both young and elderly patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2185" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The magnitude of reduction in blood pressure with amlodipine is also correlated with the height of pretreatment elevation; thus, individuals with moderate hypertension (diastolic pressure 105 to 114 mmHg) had about a 50% greater response than patients with mild hypertension (diastolic pressure 90 to 104 mmHg).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2186" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Normotensive subjects experienced no clinically significant change in blood pressure (+1/-2 mmHg).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2187" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In hypertensive patients with normal renal function, therapeutic doses of amlodipine resulted in a decrease in renal vascular resistance and an increase in glomerular filtration rate and effective renal plasma flow without change in filtration fraction or proteinuria.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2188" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>As with other calcium channel blockers, hemodynamic measurements of cardiac function at rest and during exercise (or pacing) in patients with normal ventricular function treated with amlodipine have generally demonstrated a small increase in cardiac index without significant influence on dP/dt or on left ventricular end diastolic pressure or volume.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2189" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In hemodynamic studies, amlodipine has not been associated with a negative inotropic effect when administered in the therapeutic dose range to intact animals and man, even when co-administered with beta-blockers to man.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2190" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Similar findings, however, have been observed in normal or well-compensated patients with heart failure with agents possessing significant negative inotropic effects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2191" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Amlodipine does not change sinoatrial nodal function or atrioventricular conduction in intact animals or man.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2192" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In patients with chronic stable angina, intravenous administration of 10 mg did not significantly alter A-H and H-V conduction and sinus node recovery time after pacing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2193" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Similar results were obtained in patients receiving amlodipine and concomitant beta-blockers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2194" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In clinical studies in which amlodipine was administered in combination with beta-blockers to patients with either hypertension or angina, no adverse effects of electrocardiographic parameters were observed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2195" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In clinical trials with angina patients alone, amlodipine therapy did not alter electrocardiographic intervals or produce higher degrees of AV blocks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2196" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Amlodipine has indications other than hypertension which can be found in the Norvasc® package insert.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2197" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>TWYNSTA Tablets The pharmacokinetics of amlodipine and telmisartan when combined are similar to the pharmacokinetics of amlodipine and telmisartan when administered separately.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2198" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>After administering TWYNSTA 80/10 mg tablet with a high-fat meal, the total area under the plasma concentration-time curve (AUC) and Cmax for telmisartan decreased by about 24% and 60%, respectively.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M218" type="Trigger" span="133 4;154 9" str="Cmax | decreased"/>
<Mention id="M223" type="Precipitant" span="51 13" str="high-fat meal" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M220" type="Trigger" span="76 46;154 9" str="area under the plasma concentration-time curve | decreased"/>
<Mention id="M222" type="Trigger" span="124 3;154 9" str="AUC | decreased"/>
<Interaction id="I77" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M218" precipitant="M223" effect="C54606"/>
<Interaction id="I78" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M220" precipitant="M223" effect="C54609"/>
<Interaction id="I79" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M222" precipitant="M223" effect="C54609"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2199" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>For amlodipine, AUC and Cmax were not altered.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2200" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Telmisartan Following oral administration, peak concentrations (Cmax) of telmisartan are reached in 0.5 to 1 hour after dosing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2201" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Food slightly reduces the bioavailability of telmisartan, with a reduction in the area under the plasma concentration-time curve (AUC) of about 6% with the 40 mg tablet and about 20% after a 160 mg dose.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M224" type="Trigger" span="14 27" str="reduces the bioavailability"/>
<Mention id="M229" type="Precipitant" span="0 4" str="Food" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M226" type="Trigger" span="65 9;130 3" str="reduction | AUC"/>
<Mention id="M228" type="Trigger" span="65 63" str="reduction in the area under the plasma concentration-time curve"/>
<Interaction id="I80" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M224" precipitant="M229" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I81" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M226" precipitant="M229" effect="C54609"/>
<Interaction id="I82" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M228" precipitant="M229" effect="C54609"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2202" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The absolute bioavailability of telmisartan is dose dependent.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2203" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>At 40 and 160 mg the bioavailability was 42% and 58%, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2204" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacokinetics of orally administered telmisartan are nonlinear over the dose range 20 to 160 mg, with greater than proportional increases of plasma concentrations (Cmax and AUC) with increasing doses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2205" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Telmisartan shows bi-exponential decay kinetics with a terminal elimination half life of approximately 24 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2206" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Trough plasma concentrations of telmisartan with once daily dosing are about 10% to 25% of peak plasma concentrations.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2207" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Telmisartan has an accumulation index in plasma of 1.5 to 2.0 upon repeated once daily dosing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2208" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Amlodipine Peak plasma concentrations of amlodipine are reached 6 to 12 hours after administration of amlodipine alone.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2209" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Absolute bioavailability has been estimated to be between 64% and 90%.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2210" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The bioavailability of amlodipine is not altered by the presence of food.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2211" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Elimination of amlodipine from the plasma is biphasic with a terminal elimination half-life of about 30 to 50 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2212" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Steady state plasma levels of amlodipine are reached after 7 to 8 days of consecutive daily dosing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2213" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Distribution Telmisartan Telmisartan is highly bound to plasma proteins (&gt;99.5%), mainly albumin and α1 - acid glycoprotein.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2214" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Plasma protein binding is constant over the concentration range achieved with recommended doses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2215" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The volume of distribution for telmisartan is approximately 500 liters indicating additional tissue binding.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2216" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Amlodipine The apparent volume of distribution of amlodipine is 21 L/kg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2217" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Approximately 93% of circulating amlodipine is bound to plasma proteins in hypertensive patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2218" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Metabolism and Elimination Telmisartan Following either intravenous or oral administration of 14C-labeled telmisartan, most of the administered dose (&gt;97%) was eliminated unchanged in feces via biliary excretion; only minute amounts were found in the urine (0.91% and 0.49% of total radioactivity, respectively).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2219" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Telmisartan is metabolized by conjugation to form a pharmacologically inactive acylglucuronide; the glucuronide of the parent compound is the only metabolite that has been identified in human plasma and urine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2220" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>After a single dose, the glucuronide represents approximately 11% of the measured radioactivity in plasma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2221" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The cytochrome P450 isoenzymes are not involved in the metabolism of telmisartan.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2222" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Total plasma clearance of telmisartan is &gt;800 mL/min.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2223" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Terminal half-life and total clearance appear to be independent of dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2224" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Amlodipine Amlodipine is extensively (about 90%) converted to inactive metabolites via hepatic metabolism with 10% of the parent compound and 60% of the metabolites excreted in the urine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2225" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Specific Populations Renal Insufficiency Telmisartan: No dosage adjustment is necessary in patients with decreased renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2226" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Telmisartan is not removed from blood by hemofiltration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2227" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Amlodipine: The pharmacokinetics of amlodipine are not significantly influenced by renal impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2228" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Patients with renal failure may therefore receive the usual initial dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2229" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Hepatic Insufficiency Telmisartan: In patients with hepatic insufficiency, plasma concentrations of telmisartan are increased, and absolute bioavailability approaches 100%.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2230" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Amlodipine: Patients with hepatic insufficiency have decreased clearance of amlodipine with a resulting increase in AUC of approximately 40% to 60%.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2231" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Therefore, start with a low initial dose of amlodipine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2232" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Gender Plasma concentrations of telmisartan are generally 2 to 3 times higher in females than in males.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2233" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In clinical trials, however, no significant increases in blood pressure response or in the incidence of orthostatic hypotension were found in women.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2234" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Geriatric Patients Telmisartan: The pharmacokinetics of telmisartan do not differ between the elderly and those younger than 65 years.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2235" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Amlodipine: Elderly patients have decreased clearance of amlodipine with a resulting increase in AUC of approximately 40% to 60%.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2236" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Drug Interaction Studies Telmisartan Ramipril and Ramiprilat: Co-administration of telmisartan 80 mg once daily and ramipril 10 mg once daily to healthy subjects increases steady-state Cmax and AUC of ramipril 2.3- and 2.1-fold, respectively, and Cmax and AUC of ramiprilat 2.4- and 1.5-fold, respectively.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M230" type="Trigger" span="162 27" str="increases steady-state Cmax"/>
<Mention id="M233" type="Precipitant" span="116 8" str="ramipril" code="L35JN3I7SJ"/>
<Mention id="M232" type="Trigger" span="162 22;194 3" str="increases steady-state | AUC"/>
<Mention id="M234" type="Trigger" span="162 9;185 4" str="increases | Cmax"/>
<Mention id="M237" type="Precipitant" span="263 10" str="ramiprilat" code="6N5U4QFC3G"/>
<Mention id="M236" type="Trigger" span="162 9;194 3" str="increases | AUC"/>
<Interaction id="I83" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M230" precipitant="M233" effect="C54610"/>
<Interaction id="I84" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M232" precipitant="M233" effect="C54613"/>
<Interaction id="I85" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M234" precipitant="M237" effect="C54610"/>
<Interaction id="I86" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M236" precipitant="M237" effect="C54613"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2237" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In contrast, Cmax and AUC of telmisartan decrease by 31% and 16%, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2238" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>When co-administering telmisartan and ramipril, the response may be greater because of the possibly additive pharmacodynamic effects of the combined drugs, and also because of the increased exposure to ramipril and ramiprilat in the presence of telmisartan.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M240" type="SpecificInteraction" span="100 32" str="additive pharmacodynamic effects" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M242" type="Precipitant" span="38 8" str="ramipril" code="L35JN3I7SJ"/>
<Mention id="M243" type="Trigger" span="180 18" str="increased exposure"/>
<Mention id="M244" type="Precipitant" span="215 10" str="ramiprilat" code="6N5U4QFC3G"/>
<Interaction id="I87" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M240" precipitant="M242" effect="M240"/>
<Interaction id="I88" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M243" precipitant="M242" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I89" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M243" precipitant="M244" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2239" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Other Drugs: Co-administration of telmisartan did not result in a clinically significant interaction with acetaminophen, amlodipine, glyburide, simvastatin, hydrochlorothiazide, warfarin, or ibuprofen.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2240" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Telmisartan is not metabolized by the cytochrome P450 system and had no effects in vitro on cytochrome P450 enzymes, except for some inhibition of CYP2C19.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2241" LabelDrug="Twynsta" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Telmisartan is not expected to interact with drugs that inhibit cytochrome P450 enzymes; it is also not expected to interact with drugs metabolized by cytochrome P450 enzymes, except for possible inhibition of the metabolism of drugs metabolized by CYP2C19.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M245" type="Trigger" span="187 37" str="possible inhibition of the metabolism"/>
<Mention id="M246" type="Precipitant" span="228 28" str="drugs metabolized by CYP2C19" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I90" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M245" precipitant="M246" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="aliskiren" precipitantCode="502FWN4Q32" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="aliskiren" precipitantCode="502FWN4Q32" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="aliskiren" precipitantCode="502FWN4Q32" effect="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="aliskiren" precipitantCode="502FWN4Q32" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="aliskiren" precipitantCode="502FWN4Q32"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nsaids" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect=" 39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nsaids" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nsaids" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="236423003: Renal impairment (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nsaids" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="simvastatin" precipitantCode="AGG2FN16EV" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="digoxin" precipitantCode="73K4184T59" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="digoxin" precipitantCode="73K4184T59" effect="C54610"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="digoxin" precipitantCode="73K4184T59"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="lithium" precipitantCode="9FN79X2M3F" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="lithium" precipitantCode="9FN79X2M3F"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cox-2 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000008288" effect=" 39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cox-2 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000008288" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cox-2 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000008288" effect="236423003: Renal impairment (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agents" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect=" 39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agents" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agents" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="236423003: Renal impairment (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="selective cox-2 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000008288" effect=" 39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="selective cox-2 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000008288" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="selective cox-2 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000008288" effect="236423003: Renal impairment (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="selective cox-2 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000008288" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="selective cyclooxygenase-2 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000008288" effect=" 39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="selective cyclooxygenase-2 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000008288" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="selective cyclooxygenase-2 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000008288" effect="236423003: Renal impairment (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nsaid" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cyclosporine" precipitantCode="83HN0GTJ6D" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="cyclosporine" precipitantCode="83HN0GTJ6D"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="tacrolimus" precipitantCode="WM0HAQ4WNM" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="tacrolimus" precipitantCode="WM0HAQ4WNM"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="diltiazem" precipitantCode="EE92BBP03H" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="itraconazole" precipitantCode="304NUG5GF4" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="ketoconazole" precipitantCode="R9400W927I" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="ritonavir" precipitantCode="O3J8G9O825" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="strong inhibitors of cyp3a4" precipitantCode="N0000182141" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cyp3a4 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000182141" effect="267038008: Edema (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cyp3a4 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000182141" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="cyp3a4 inducers" precipitantCode="N0000185506"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="ace inhibitor" precipitantCode="N0000175562"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="high doses of diuretics" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="drugs that increase potassium levels" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="potassium supplements" precipitantCode="RWP5GA015D" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="potassium-containing salt substitutes" precipitantCode="N0000175600" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="potassium-sparing diuretics" precipitantCode="N0000175418" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ace | inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175562" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ace | inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175562" effect="419620001: Death (event)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ace | inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175562" effect="445009001: Azotemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ace | inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175562" effect="83128009: Oliguria (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="angiotensin-converting enzyme (ace) inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175562" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="angiotensin-converting enzyme (ace) inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175562" effect="419620001: Death (event)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="angiotensin-converting enzyme (ace) inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175562" effect="445009001: Azotemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="angiotensin-converting enzyme (ace) inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175562" effect="83128009: Oliguria (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="angiotensin-converting enzyme | inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175562" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="angiotensin-converting enzyme | inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175562" effect="419620001: Death (event)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="angiotensin-converting enzyme | inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175562" effect="445009001: Azotemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="angiotensin-converting enzyme | inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175562" effect="83128009: Oliguria (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ace inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175562" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ace inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175562" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ace inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175562" effect="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ace inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175562" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="dual blockade of the ras" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="14140009: Hyperkalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="dual blockade of the ras" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="dual blockade of the ras" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="dual blockade of the ras" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ramipril" precipitantCode="L35JN3I7SJ" effect="236423003: Renal impairment (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ramipril" precipitantCode="L35JN3I7SJ" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="ramipril" precipitantCode="L35JN3I7SJ" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="ramipril" precipitantCode="L35JN3I7SJ" effect="C54610"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="ramipril" precipitantCode="L35JN3I7SJ" effect="C54613"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="ras inhibitors" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="agents that affect the ras" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="166686006: Electrolytes abnormal (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="agents that affect the ras" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="38936003: Abnormal blood pressure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="agents that affect the ras" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="high-fat meal" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54606"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="high-fat meal" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54609"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="food" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="food" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54609"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="ramiprilat" precipitantCode="6N5U4QFC3G" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="ramiprilat" precipitantCode="6N5U4QFC3G" effect="C54610"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="ramiprilat" precipitantCode="6N5U4QFC3G" effect="C54613"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="drugs metabolized by cyp2c19" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54357"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>