<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="TEMODAR" setid="046a9011-3911-4d3f-a15f-fbb56d5aad56">
<Text><Section name="BOXED WARNING SECTION" id="34066-1">
IMPORTANT DISPENSING INFORMATION For every patient, TEMODAR must be dispensed in a separate vial or in its original package making sure each container lists the strength per capsule and that patients take the appropriate number of capsules from each package or vial. Please see the dispensing instructions below for more information.</Section>
<Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
Known hypersensitivity to any TEMODAR component or to dacarbazine (DTIC). ( 4.1 ) TEMODAR (temozolomide) is contraindicated in patients who have a history of hypersensitivity reaction (such as urticaria, allergic reaction including anaphylaxis, toxic epidermal necrolysis, and Stevens-Johnson syndrome) to any of its components. TEMODAR is also contraindicated in patients who have a history of hypersensitivity to dacarbazine (DTIC), since both drugs are metabolized to 5-(3-methyltriazen-1-yl)-imidazole-4-carboxamide (MTIC).</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
Newly Diagnosed GBM: 75 mg/m 2 for 42 days concomitant with focal radiotherapy followed by initial maintenance dose of 150 mg/m 2 once daily for Days 1–5 of a 28-day cycle of TEMODAR for 6 cycles. ( 2.1 ) Refractory Anaplastic Astrocytoma: Initial dose 150 mg/m 2 once daily for 5 consecutive days per 28-day treatment cycle. ( 2.1 ) The recommended dose for TEMODAR as an intravenous infusion over 90 minutes is the same as the dose for the oral capsule formulation. Bioequivalence has been established only when TEMODAR for Injection was given over 90 minutes. ( 2.1 , 12.3 ) The recommended dose for TEMODAR as an intravenous infusion over 90 minutes is the same as the dose for the oral capsule formulation. Bioequivalence has been established only when TEMODAR for Injection was given over 90 minutes [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3) ]. Dosage of TEMODAR must be adjusted according to nadir neutrophil and platelet counts in the previous cycle and the neutrophil and platelet counts at the time of initiating the next cycle. For TEMODAR dosage calculations based on body surface area (BSA) see Table 5 . For suggested capsule combinations on a daily dose see Table 6 . Patients with Newly Diagnosed High Grade Glioma: Concomitant Phase: TEMODAR is administered at 75 mg/m 2 daily for 42 days concomitant with focal radiotherapy (60 Gy administered in 30 fractions) followed by maintenance TEMODAR for 6 cycles. Focal RT includes the tumor bed or resection site with a 2- to 3-cm margin. No dose reductions are recommended during the concomitant phase; however, dose interruptions or discontinuation may occur based on toxicity. The TEMODAR dose should be continued throughout the 42-day concomitant period up to 49 days if all of the following conditions are met: absolute neutrophil count greater than or equal to 1.5 × 10 9 /L, platelet count greater than or equal to 100 × 10 9 /L, common toxicity criteria (CTC) nonhematological toxicity less than or equal to Grade 1 (except for alopecia, nausea, and vomiting). During treatment a complete blood count should be obtained weekly. Temozolomide dosing should be interrupted or discontinued during concomitant phase according to the hematological and nonhematological toxicity criteria as noted in Table 1 . Pneumocystis pneumonia (PCP) prophylaxis is required during the concomitant administration of TEMODAR and radiotherapy, and should be continued in patients who develop lymphocytopenia until recovery from lymphocytopenia (CTC Grade less than or equal to 1). TABLE 1: Temozolomide Dosing Interruption or Discontinuation During Concomitant Radiotherapy and Temozolomide Toxicity TMZ Interruption Treatment with concomitant TMZ could be continued when all of the following conditions were met: absolute neutrophil count greater than or equal to 1.5 × 10 9 /L; platelet count greater than or equal to 100 × 10 9 /L; CTC nonhematological toxicity less than or equal to Grade 1 (except for alopecia, nausea, vomiting). TMZ Discontinuation TMZ=temozolomide; CTC=Common Toxicity Criteria. Absolute Neutrophil Count greater than or equal to 0.5 and less than 1.5 × 10 9 /L less than 0.5 × 10 9 /L Platelet Count greater than or equal to 10 and less than 100 × 10 9 /L less than 10 × 10 9 /L CTC Nonhematological Toxicity (except for alopecia, nausea, vomiting) CTC Grade 2 CTC Grade 3 or 4 Maintenance Phase: Cycle 1: Four weeks after completing the TEMODAR+RT phase, TEMODAR is administered for an additional 6 cycles of maintenance treatment. Dosage in Cycle 1 (maintenance) is 150 mg/m 2 once daily for 5 days followed by 23 days without treatment. Cycles 2–6: At the start of Cycle 2, the dose can be escalated to 200 mg/m 2 , if the CTC nonhematologic toxicity for Cycle 1 is Grade less than or equal to 2 (except for alopecia, nausea, and vomiting), absolute neutrophil count (ANC) is greater than or equal to 1.5 × 10 9 /L, and the platelet count is greater than or equal to 100 × 10 9 /L. The dose remains at 200 mg/m 2 per day for the first 5 days of each subsequent cycle except if toxicity occurs. If the dose was not escalated at Cycle 2, escalation should not be done in subsequent cycles. Dose Reduction or Discontinuation During Maintenance: Dose reductions during the maintenance phase should be applied according to Tables 2 and 3 . During treatment, a complete blood count should be obtained on Day 22 (21 days after the first dose of TEMODAR) or within 48 hours of that day, and weekly until the ANC is above 1.5 × 10 9 /L (1500/µL) and the platelet count exceeds 100 × 10 9 /L (100,000/µL). The next cycle of TEMODAR should not be started until the ANC and platelet count exceed these levels. Dose reductions during the next cycle should be based on the lowest blood counts and worst nonhematologic toxicity during the previous cycle. Dose reductions or discontinuations during the maintenance phase should be applied according to Tables 2 and 3 . TABLE 2: Temozolomide Dose Levels for Maintenance Treatment Dose Level Dose (mg/m 2 /day) Remarks −1 100 Reduction for prior toxicity 0 150 Dose during Cycle 1 1 200 Dose during Cycles 2–6 in absence of toxicity TABLE 3: Temozolomide Dose Reduction or Discontinuation During Maintenance Treatment Toxicity Reduce TMZ by 1 Dose Level TMZ dose levels are listed in Table 2 . Discontinue TMZ TMZ=temozolomide; CTC=Common Toxicity Criteria. Absolute Neutrophil Count less than 1.0 × 10 9 /L See footnote TMZ is to be discontinued if dose reduction to less than 100 mg/m 2 is required or if the same Grade 3 nonhematological toxicity (except for alopecia, nausea, vomiting) recurs after dose reduction. Platelet Count less than 50 × 10 9 /L See footnote CTC Nonhematological Toxicity (except for alopecia, nausea, vomiting) CTC Grade 3 CTC Grade 4 Patients with Refractory Anaplastic Astrocytoma: For adults the initial dose is 150 mg/m 2 once daily for 5 consecutive days per 28-day treatment cycle. For adult patients, if both the nadir and day of dosing (Day 29, Day 1 of next cycle) ANC are greater than or equal to 1.5 × 10 9 /L (1500/µL) and both the nadir and Day 29, Day 1 of next cycle platelet counts are greater than or equal to 100 × 10 9 /L (100,000/µL), the TEMODAR dose may be increased to 200 mg/m 2 /day for 5 consecutive days per 28-day treatment cycle. During treatment, a complete blood count should be obtained on Day 22 (21 days after the first dose) or within 48 hours of that day, and weekly until the ANC is above 1.5 × 10 9 /L (1500/µL) and the platelet count exceeds 100 × 10 9 /L (100,000/µL). The next cycle of TEMODAR should not be started until the ANC and platelet count exceed these levels. If the ANC falls to less than 1.0 × 10 9 /L (1000/µL) or the platelet count is less than 50 × 10 9 /L (50,000/µL) during any cycle, the next cycle should be reduced by 50 mg/m 2 , but not below 100 mg/m 2 , the lowest recommended dose (see Table 4 ). TEMODAR therapy can be continued until disease progression. In the clinical trial, treatment could be continued for a maximum of 2 years, but the optimum duration of therapy is not known. TABLE 4: Dosing Modification Table TABLE 5: Daily Dose Calculations by Body Surface Area (BSA) Total BSA (m 2 ) 75 mg/m 2 (mg daily) 150 mg/m 2 (mg daily) 200 mg/m 2 (mg daily) 1.0 75 150 200 1.1 82.5 165 220 1.2 90 180 240 1.3 97.5 195 260 1.4 105 210 280 1.5 112.5 225 300 1.6 120 240 320 1.7 127.5 255 340 1.8 135 270 360 1.9 142.5 285 380 2.0 150 300 400 2.1 157.5 315 420 2.2 165 330 440 2.3 172.5 345 460 2.4 180 360 480 2.5 187.5 375 500 TABLE 6: Suggested Capsule Combinations Based on Daily Dose in Adults Number of Daily Capsules by Strength (mg) Total Daily Dose (mg) 250 mg 180 mg 140 mg 100 mg 20 mg 5 mg 75 0 0 0 0 3 3 82.5 0 0 0 0 4 0 90 0 0 0 0 4 2 97.5 0 0 0 1 0 0 105 0 0 0 1 0 1 112.5 0 0 0 1 0 2 120 0 0 0 1 1 0 127.5 0 0 0 1 1 1 135 0 0 0 1 1 3 142.5 0 0 1 0 0 0 150 0 0 1 0 0 2 157.5 0 0 1 0 1 0 165 0 0 1 0 1 1 172.5 0 0 1 0 1 2 180 0 1 0 0 0 0 187.5 0 1 0 0 0 1 195 0 1 0 0 0 3 200 0 1 0 0 1 0 210 0 0 0 2 0 2 220 0 0 0 2 1 0 225 0 0 0 2 1 1 240 0 0 1 1 0 0 255 1 0 0 0 0 1 260 1 0 0 0 0 2 270 1 0 0 0 1 0 280 0 0 2 0 0 0 285 0 0 2 0 0 1 300 0 0 0 3 0 0 315 0 0 0 3 0 3 320 0 1 1 0 0 0 330 0 1 1 0 0 2 340 0 1 1 0 1 0 345 0 1 1 0 1 1 360 0 2 0 0 0 0 375 0 2 0 0 0 3 380 0 1 0 2 0 0 400 0 0 0 4 0 0 420 0 0 3 0 0 0 440 0 0 3 0 1 0 460 0 2 0 1 0 0 480 0 1 0 3 0 0 500 2 0 0 0 0 0 Table 4: Dosing Modification Table Table TEMODAR Capsules: In clinical trials, TEMODAR was administered under both fasting and nonfasting conditions; however, absorption is affected by food [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3) ], and consistency of administration with respect to food is recommended. There are no dietary restrictions with TEMODAR. To reduce nausea and vomiting, TEMODAR should be taken on an empty stomach. Bedtime administration may be advised. Antiemetic therapy may be administered prior to and/or following administration of TEMODAR. TEMODAR (temozolomide) Capsules should not be opened or chewed. They should be swallowed whole with a glass of water. If capsules are accidentally opened or damaged, precautions should be taken to avoid inhalation or contact with the skin or mucous membranes [see How Supplied/Storage and Handling (16.1) ]. TEMODAR for Injection: Each vial of TEMODAR for Injection contains sterile and pyrogen-free temozolomide lyophilized powder. When reconstituted with 41 mL Sterile Water for Injection, the resulting solution will contain 2.5 mg/mL temozolomide. Bring the vial to room temperature prior to reconstitution with Sterile Water for Injection. The vials should be gently swirled and not shaken. Vials should be inspected, and any vial containing visible particulate matter should not be used. Do not further dilute the reconstituted solution. After reconstitution, store at room temperature (25°C [77°F]). Reconstituted product must be used within 14 hours, including infusion time. Using aseptic technique, withdraw up to 40 mL from each vial to make up the total dose based on Table 5 above and transfer into an empty 250 mL infusion bag {2}. TEMODAR for Injection should be infused intravenously using a pump over a period of 90 minutes. TEMODAR for Injection should be administered only by intravenous infusion. Flush the lines before and after each TEMODAR infusion. TEMODAR for Injection may be administered in the same intravenous line with 0.9% Sodium Chloride injection only. Because no data are available on the compatibility of TEMODAR for Injection with other intravenous substances or additives, other medications should not be infused simultaneously through the same intravenous line.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
Valproic acid: decreases oral clearance of temozolomide. ( 7.1 ) Administration of valproic acid decreases oral clearance of temozolomide by about 5%. The clinical implication of this effect is not known [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3) ].</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
Myelosuppression — monitor Absolute Neutrophil Count (ANC) and platelet count prior to dosing and throughout treatment. Geriatric patients and women have a higher risk of developing myelosuppression. ( 5.1 ) Cases of myelodysplastic syndrome and secondary malignancies, including myeloid leukemia, have been observed. ( 5.2 ) Pneumocystis pneumonia (PCP) – PCP prophylaxis required for all patients receiving concomitant TEMODAR and radiotherapy for the 42-day regimen for the treatment of newly diagnosed glioblastoma multiforme. ( 5.3 ) All patients, particularly those receiving steroids, should be observed closely for the development of lymphopenia and PCP. ( 5.4 ) Complete blood counts should be obtained throughout the treatment course as specified. ( 5.4 ) Hepatotoxicity – fatal and severe hepatotoxicity have been reported. Perform liver function tests at baseline, midway through the first cycle, prior to each subsequent cycle, and approximately two to four weeks after the last dose of TEMODAR. ( 5.5 ) Fetal harm can occur when administered to a pregnant woman. Women should be advised to avoid becoming pregnant when receiving TEMODAR. ( 5.6 ) As bioequivalence has been established only when given over 90 minutes, infusion over a shorter or longer period of time may result in suboptimal dosing; the possibility of an increase in infusion-related adverse reactions cannot be ruled out. ( 5.7 ) Patients treated with TEMODAR may experience myelosuppression, including prolonged pancytopenia, which may result in aplastic anemia, which in some cases has resulted in a fatal outcome. In some cases, exposure to concomitant medications associated with aplastic anemia, including carbamazepine, phenytoin, and sulfamethoxazole/trimethoprim, complicates assessment. Prior to dosing, patients must have an absolute neutrophil count (ANC) greater than or equal to 1.5 × 10 9 /L and a platelet count greater than or equal to 100 × 10 9 /L. A complete blood count should be obtained on Day 22 (21 days after the first dose) or within 48 hours of that day, and weekly until the ANC is above 1.5 × 10 9 /L and platelet count exceeds 100 × 10 9 /L. Geriatric patients and women have been shown in clinical trials to have a higher risk of developing myelosuppression. Cases of myelodysplastic syndrome and secondary malignancies, including myeloid leukemia, have been observed. For treatment of newly diagnosed glioblastoma multiforme: Prophylaxis against Pneumocystis pneumonia (PCP) is required for all patients receiving concomitant TEMODAR and radiotherapy for the 42-day regimen. There may be a higher occurrence of PCP when temozolomide is administered during a longer dosing regimen. However, all patients receiving temozolomide, particularly patients receiving steroids, should be observed closely for the development of PCP regardless of the regimen. For the concomitant treatment phase with RT, a complete blood count should be obtained prior to initiation of treatment and weekly during treatment. For the 28-day treatment cycles, a complete blood count should be obtained prior to treatment on Day 1 and on Day 22 (21 days after the first dose) of each cycle. Blood counts should be performed weekly until recovery if the ANC falls below 1.5 × 10 9 /L and the platelet count falls below 100 × 10 9 /L [see Dosage and Administration (2.1) ]. Fatal and severe hepatotoxicity have been reported in patients receiving TEMODAR. Perform liver function tests at baseline, midway through the first cycle, prior to each subsequent cycle, and approximately two to four weeks after the last dose of TEMODAR. TEMODAR can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. Administration of TEMODAR to rats and rabbits during organogenesis at 0.38 and 0.75 times the maximum recommended human dose (75 and 150 mg/m 2 ), respectively, caused numerous fetal malformations of the external organs, soft tissues, and skeleton in both species [see Use in Specific Populations (8.1) ]. As bioequivalence has been established only when TEMODAR for Injection was given over 90 minutes, infusion over a shorter or longer period of time may result in suboptimal dosing. Additionally, the possibility of an increase in infusion-related adverse reactions cannot be ruled out.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Temozolomide is not directly active but undergoes rapid nonenzymatic conversion at physiologic pH to the reactive compound 5-(3-methyltriazen-1-yl)-imidazole-4-carboxamide (MTIC). The cytotoxicity of MTIC is thought to be primarily due to alkylation of DNA. Alkylation (methylation) occurs mainly at the O 6 and N 7 positions of guanine. Absorption: Temozolomide is rapidly and completely absorbed after oral administration with a peak plasma concentration (C max ) achieved in a median T max of 1 hour. Food reduces the rate and extent of temozolomide absorption. Mean peak plasma concentration and AUC decreased by 32% and 9%, respectively, and median T max increased by 2-fold (from 1–2.25 hours) when temozolomide was administered after a modified high-fat breakfast. A pharmacokinetic study comparing oral and intravenous temozolomide in 19 patients with primary CNS malignancies showed that 150 mg/m 2 TEMODAR for injection administered over 90 minutes is bioequivalent to 150 mg/m 2 TEMODAR oral capsules with respect to both C max and AUC of temozolomide and MTIC. Following a single 90-minute intravenous infusion of 150 mg/m 2 , the geometric mean C max values for temozolomide and MTIC were 7.3 mcg/mL and 276 ng/mL, respectively. Following a single oral dose of 150 mg/m 2 , the geometric mean C max values for temozolomide and MTIC were 7.5 mcg/mL and 282 ng/mL, respectively. Following a single 90-minute intravenous infusion of 150 mg/m 2 , the geometric mean AUC values for temozolomide and MTIC were 24.6 mcg∙hr/mL and 891 ng∙hr/mL, respectively. Following a single oral dose of 150 mg/m 2 , the geometric mean AUC values for temozolomide and MTIC were 23.4 mcg∙hr/mL and 864 ng∙hr/mL, respectively. Distribution: Temozolomide has a mean apparent volume of distribution of 0.4 L/kg (%CV=13%). It is weakly bound to human plasma proteins; the mean percent bound of drug-related total radioactivity is 15%. Metabolism and Elimination: Temozolomide is spontaneously hydrolyzed at physiologic pH to the active species, MTIC and to temozolomide acid metabolite. MTIC is further hydrolyzed to 5-amino-imidazole-4-carboxamide (AIC), which is known to be an intermediate in purine and nucleic acid biosynthesis, and to methylhydrazine, which is believed to be the active alkylating species. Cytochrome P450 enzymes play only a minor role in the metabolism of temozolomide and MTIC. Relative to the AUC of temozolomide, the exposure to MTIC and AIC is 2.4% and 23%, respectively. Excretion: About 38% of the administered temozolomide total radioactive dose is recovered over 7 days: 37.7% in urine and 0.8% in feces. The majority of the recovery of radioactivity in urine is unchanged temozolomide (5.6%), AIC (12%), temozolomide acid metabolite (2.3%), and unidentified polar metabolite(s) (17%). Overall clearance of temozolomide is about 5.5 L/hr/m 2 . Temozolomide is rapidly eliminated, with a mean elimination half-life of 1.8 hours, and exhibits linear kinetics over the therapeutic dosing range of 75 to 250 mg/m 2 /day. Effect of Age: A population pharmacokinetic analysis indicated that age (range: 19–78 years) has no influence on the pharmacokinetics of temozolomide. Effect of Gender: A population pharmacokinetic analysis indicated that women have an approximately 5% lower clearance (adjusted for body surface area) for temozolomide than men. Effect of Race: The effect of race on the pharmacokinetics of temozolomide has not been studied. Tobacco Use: A population pharmacokinetic analysis indicated that the oral clearance of temozolomide is similar in smokers and nonsmokers. Effect of Renal Impairment: A population pharmacokinetic analysis indicated that creatinine clearance over the range of 36 to 130 mL/min/m 2 has no effect on the clearance of temozolomide after oral administration. The pharmacokinetics of temozolomide have not been studied in patients with severely impaired renal function (CLcr &amp;lt;36 mL/min/m 2 ). Caution should be exercised when TEMODAR is administered to patients with severe renal impairment [see Use in Special Populations (8.6) ]. TEMODAR has not been studied in patients on dialysis. Effect of Hepatic Impairment: A study showed that the pharmacokinetics of temozolomide in patients with mild-to-moderate hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh Class I – II) were similar to those observed in patients with normal hepatic function. Caution should be exercised when temozolomide is administered to patients with severe hepatic impairment [see Use in Specific Populations (8.7) ]. Effect of Other Drugs on Temozolomide Pharmacokinetics: In a multiple-dose study, administration of TEMODAR Capsules with ranitidine did not change the C max or AUC values for temozolomide or MTIC. A population analysis indicated that administration of valproic acid decreases the clearance of temozolomide by about 5% [see Drug Interactions (7.1) ]. A population analysis did not demonstrate any influence of coadministered dexamethasone, prochlorperazine, phenytoin, carbamazepine, ondansetron, H 2 -receptor antagonists, or phenobarbital on the clearance of orally administered temozolomide.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="6603" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>IMPORTANT DISPENSING INFORMATION For every patient, TEMODAR must be dispensed in a separate vial or in its original package making sure each container lists the strength per capsule and that patients take the appropriate number of capsules from each package or vial.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6604" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Please see the dispensing instructions below for more information.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6605" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Known hypersensitivity to any TEMODAR component or to dacarbazine (DTIC).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6606" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>TEMODAR (temozolomide) is contraindicated in patients who have a history of hypersensitivity reaction (such as urticaria, allergic reaction including anaphylaxis, toxic epidermal necrolysis, and Stevens-Johnson syndrome) to any of its components.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6607" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>TEMODAR is also contraindicated in patients who have a history of hypersensitivity to dacarbazine (DTIC), since both drugs are metabolized to 5-(3-methyltriazen-1-yl)-imidazole-4-carboxamide (MTIC).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6608" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Newly Diagnosed GBM: 75 mg/m2 for 42 days concomitant with focal radiotherapy followed by initial maintenance dose of 150 mg/m2 once daily for Days 1–5 of a 28-day cycle of TEMODAR for 6 cycles.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6609" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Refractory Anaplastic Astrocytoma: Initial dose 150 mg/m2 once daily for 5 consecutive days per 28-day treatment cycle.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6610" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommended dose for TEMODAR as an intravenous infusion over 90 minutes is the same as the dose for the oral capsule formulation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6611" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Bioequivalence has been established only when TEMODAR for Injection was given over 90 minutes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6612" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dosage of TEMODAR must be adjusted according to nadir neutrophil and platelet counts in the previous cycle and the neutrophil and platelet counts at the time of initiating the next cycle.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6613" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For TEMODAR dosage calculations based on body surface area (BSA) see Table 5.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6614" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For suggested capsule combinations on a daily dose see Table 6.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6615" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Patients with Newly Diagnosed High Grade Glioma: Concomitant Phase: TEMODAR is administered at 75 mg/m2 daily for 42 days concomitant with focal radiotherapy (60 Gy administered in 30 fractions) followed by maintenance TEMODAR for 6 cycles.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6616" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Focal RT includes the tumor bed or resection site with a 2- to 3-cm margin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6617" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>No dose reductions are recommended during the concomitant phase; however, dose interruptions or discontinuation may occur based on toxicity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6618" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The TEMODAR dose should be continued throughout the 42-day concomitant period up to 49 days if all of the following conditions are met: absolute neutrophil count greater than or equal to 1.5 Ã— 109/L, platelet count greater than or equal to 100 Ã— 109/L, common toxicity criteria (CTC) nonhematological toxicity less than or equal to Grade 1 (except for alopecia, nausea, and vomiting).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6619" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>During treatment a complete blood count should be obtained weekly.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6620" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Temozolomide dosing should be interrupted or discontinued during concomitant phase according to the hematological and nonhematological toxicity criteria as noted in Table 1.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6621" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Pneumocystis pneumonia (PCP) prophylaxis is required during the concomitant administration of TEMODAR and radiotherapy, and should be continued in patients who develop lymphocytopenia until recovery from lymphocytopenia (CTC Grade less than or equal to 1).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6622" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>TABLE 1: Temozolomide Dosing Interruption or Discontinuation During Concomitant Radiotherapy and Temozolomide Toxicity TMZ InterruptionTreatment with concomitant TMZ could be continued when all of the following conditions were met: absolute neutrophil count greater than or equal to 1.5 Ã— 109/L; platelet count greater than or equal to 100 Ã— 109/L; CTC nonhematological toxicity less than or equal to Grade 1 (except for alopecia, nausea, vomiting).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6623" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>TMZ Discontinuation TMZ=temozolomide; CTC=Common Toxicity Criteria.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6624" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Absolute Neutrophil Count greater than or equal to 0.5 and less than 1.5 Ã— 109/L less than 0.5 Ã— 109/L Platelet Count greater than or equal to 10 and less than 100 Ã— 109/L less than 10 Ã— 109/L CTC Nonhematological Toxicity(except for alopecia, nausea, vomiting) CTC Grade 2 CTC Grade 3 or 4 Maintenance Phase: Cycle 1: Four weeks after completing the TEMODAR+RT phase, TEMODAR is administered for an additional 6 cycles of maintenance treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6625" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dosage in Cycle 1 (maintenance) is 150 mg/m2 once daily for 5 days followed by 23 days without treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6626" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Cycles 2–6: At the start of Cycle 2, the dose can be escalated to 200 mg/m2, if the CTC nonhematologic toxicity for Cycle 1 is Grade less than or equal to 2 (except for alopecia, nausea, and vomiting), absolute neutrophil count (ANC) is greater than or equal to 1.5 Ã— 109/L, and the platelet count is greater than or equal to 100 Ã— 109/L.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6627" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The dose remains at 200 mg/m2 per day for the first 5 days of each subsequent cycle except if toxicity occurs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6628" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If the dose was not escalated at Cycle 2, escalation should not be done in subsequent cycles.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6629" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dose Reduction or Discontinuation During Maintenance: Dose reductions during the maintenance phase should be applied according to Tables 2 and 3.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6630" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>During treatment, a complete blood count should be obtained on Day 22 (21 days after the first dose of TEMODAR) or within 48 hours of that day, and weekly until the ANC is above 1.5 Ã— 109/L (1500/µL) and the platelet count exceeds 100 Ã— 109/L (100,000/µL).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6631" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The next cycle of TEMODAR should not be started until the ANC and platelet count exceed these levels.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6632" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dose reductions during the next cycle should be based on the lowest blood counts and worst nonhematologic toxicity during the previous cycle.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6633" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dose reductions or discontinuations during the maintenance phase should be applied according to Tables 2 and 3.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6634" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>TABLE 2: Temozolomide Dose Levels for Maintenance Treatment Dose Level Dose (mg/m2/day) Remarks −1 100 Reduction for prior toxicity 0 150 Dose during Cycle 1 1 200 Dose during Cycles 2–6 in absence of toxicity TABLE 3: Temozolomide Dose Reduction or Discontinuation During Maintenance Treatment Toxicity Reduce TMZ by 1 Dose LevelTMZ dose levels are listed in Table 2.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6635" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Discontinue TMZ TMZ=temozolomide; CTC=Common Toxicity Criteria.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6636" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Absolute Neutrophil Count less than 1.0 Ã— 109/L See footnoteTMZ is to be discontinued if dose reduction to less than 100 mg/m2 is required or if the same Grade 3 nonhematological toxicity (except for alopecia, nausea, vomiting) recurs after dose reduction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6637" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Platelet Count less than 50 Ã— 109/L See footnote CTC Nonhematological Toxicity(except for alopecia, nausea, vomiting) CTC Grade 3 CTC Grade 4 Patients with Refractory Anaplastic Astrocytoma: For adults the initial dose is 150 mg/m2 once daily for 5 consecutive days per 28-day treatment cycle.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6638" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For adult patients, if both the nadir and day of dosing (Day 29, Day 1 of next cycle) ANC are greater than or equal to 1.5 Ã— 109/L (1500/µL) and both the nadir and Day 29, Day 1 of next cycle platelet counts are greater than or equal to 100 Ã— 109/L (100,000/µL), the TEMODAR dose may be increased to 200 mg/m2/day for 5 consecutive days per 28-day treatment cycle.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6639" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>During treatment, a complete blood count should be obtained on Day 22 (21 days after the first dose) or within 48 hours of that day, and weekly until the ANC is above 1.5 Ã— 109/L (1500/µL) and the platelet count exceeds 100 Ã— 109/L (100,000/µL).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6640" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If the ANC falls to less than 1.0 Ã— 109/L (1000/µL) or the platelet count is less than 50 Ã— 109/L (50,000/µL) during any cycle, the next cycle should be reduced by 50 mg/m2, but not below 100 mg/m2, the lowest recommended dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6641" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>TEMODAR therapy can be continued until disease progression.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6642" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In the clinical trial, treatment could be continued for a maximum of 2 years, but the optimum duration of therapy is not known.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6643" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>TABLE 4: Dosing Modification Table TABLE 5: Daily Dose Calculations by Body Surface Area (BSA) Total BSA(m2) 75 mg/m2 (mg daily) 150 mg/m2 (mg daily) 200 mg/m2 (mg daily) 1.0 75 150 200 1.1 82.5 165 220 1.2 90 180 240 1.3 97.5 195 260 1.4 105 210 280 1.5 112.5 225 300 1.6 120 240 320 1.7 127.5 255 340 1.8 135 270 360 1.9 142.5 285 380 2.0 150 300 400 2.1 157.5 315 420 2.2 165 330 440 2.3 172.5 345 460 2.4 180 360 480 2.5 187.5 375 500 TABLE 6: Suggested Capsule Combinations Based on Daily Dose in Adults Number of Daily Capsules by Strength (mg) Total Daily Dose (mg) 250 mg 180 mg 140 mg 100 mg 20 mg 5 mg 75 0 0 0 0 3 3 82.5 0 0 0 0 4 0 90 0 0 0 0 4 2 97.5 0 0 0 1 0 0 105 0 0 0 1 0 1 112.5 0 0 0 1 0 2 120 0 0 0 1 1 0 127.5 0 0 0 1 1 1 135 0 0 0 1 1 3 142.5 0 0 1 0 0 0 150 0 0 1 0 0 2 157.5 0 0 1 0 1 0 165 0 0 1 0 1 1 172.5 0 0 1 0 1 2 180 0 1 0 0 0 0 187.5 0 1 0 0 0 1 195 0 1 0 0 0 3 200 0 1 0 0 1 0 210 0 0 0 2 0 2 220 0 0 0 2 1 0 225 0 0 0 2 1 1 240 0 0 1 1 0 0 255 1 0 0 0 0 1 260 1 0 0 0 0 2 270 1 0 0 0 1 0 280 0 0 2 0 0 0 285 0 0 2 0 0 1 300 0 0 0 3 0 0 315 0 0 0 3 0 3 320 0 1 1 0 0 0 330 0 1 1 0 0 2 340 0 1 1 0 1 0 345 0 1 1 0 1 1 360 0 2 0 0 0 0 375 0 2 0 0 0 3 380 0 1 0 2 0 0 400 0 0 0 4 0 0 420 0 0 3 0 0 0 440 0 0 3 0 1 0 460 0 2 0 1 0 0 480 0 1 0 3 0 0 500 2 0 0 0 0 0 Table 4: Dosing Modification Table Table TEMODAR Capsules: In clinical trials, TEMODAR was administered under both fasting and nonfasting conditions; however, absorption is affected by food, and consistency of administration with respect to food is recommended.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6644" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>There are no dietary restrictions with TEMODAR.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6645" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>To reduce nausea and vomiting, TEMODAR should be taken on an empty stomach.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6646" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Antiemetic therapy may be administered prior to and/or following administration of TEMODAR.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6647" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>TEMODAR (temozolomide) Capsules should not be opened or chewed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6648" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>They should be swallowed whole with a glass of water.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6649" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If capsules are accidentally opened or damaged, precautions should be taken to avoid inhalation or contact with the skin or mucous membranes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6650" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>TEMODAR for Injection: Each vial of TEMODAR for Injection contains sterile and pyrogen-free temozolomide lyophilized powder.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6651" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>When reconstituted with 41 mL Sterile Water for Injection, the resulting solution will contain 2.5 mg/mL temozolomide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6652" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Bring the vial to room temperature prior to reconstitution with Sterile Water for Injection.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6653" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The vials should be gently swirled and not shaken.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6654" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Vials should be inspected, and any vial containing visible particulate matter should not be used.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6655" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not further dilute the reconstituted solution.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6656" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>After reconstitution, store at room temperature (25°C [77°F]).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6657" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Reconstituted product must be used within 14 hours, including infusion time.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6658" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Using aseptic technique, withdraw up to 40 mL from each vial to make up the total dose based on Table 5 above and transfer into an empty 250 mL infusion bag {2}.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6659" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>TEMODAR for Injection should be infused intravenously using a pump over a period of 90 minutes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6660" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>TEMODAR for Injection should be administered only by intravenous infusion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6661" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Flush the lines before and after each TEMODAR infusion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6662" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>TEMODAR for Injection may be administered in the same intravenous line with 0.9% Sodium Chloride injection only.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6663" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Because no data are available on the compatibility of TEMODAR for Injection with other intravenous substances or additives, other medications should not be infused simultaneously through the same intravenous line.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6664" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Valproic acid: decreases oral clearance of temozolomide.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M1" type="Trigger" span="15 24" str="decreases oral clearance"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="0 13" str="Valproic acid" code="614OI1Z5WI"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M1" precipitant="M2" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6665" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Administration of valproic acid decreases oral clearance of temozolomide by about 5%.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M3" type="Trigger" span="32 24" str="decreases oral clearance"/>
<Mention id="M4" type="Precipitant" span="18 13" str="valproic acid" code="614OI1Z5WI"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M3" precipitant="M4" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6666" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The clinical implication of this effect is not known.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6667" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Myelosuppression — monitor Absolute Neutrophil Count (ANC) and platelet count prior to dosing and throughout treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6668" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Geriatric patients and women have a higher risk of developing myelosuppression.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6669" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Cases of myelodysplastic syndrome and secondary malignancies, including myeloid leukemia, have been observed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6670" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Pneumocystis pneumonia (PCP) — PCP prophylaxis required for all patients receiving concomitant TEMODAR and radiotherapy for the 42-day regimen for the treatment of newly diagnosed glioblastoma multiforme.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6671" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>All patients, particularly those receiving steroids, should be observed closely for the development of lymphopenia and PCP.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M9" type="Trigger" span="53 18" str="should be observed "/>
<Mention id="M10" type="Trigger" span="88 11" str=" development"/>
<Mention id="M11" type="Precipitant" span="43 8" str="steroids" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M8" type="SpecificInteraction" span="103 11" str="lymphopenia" code="48813009: Lymphocytopenia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M12" type="SpecificInteraction" span="119 3" str="PCP" code="415125002: Pneumocystosis jirovecii pneumonia (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M9;M10" precipitant="M11" effect="M8" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M9;M10" precipitant="M11" effect="M12" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6672" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Complete blood counts should be obtained throughout the treatment course as specified.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6673" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hepatotoxicity — fatal and severe hepatotoxicity have been reported.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6674" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Perform liver function tests at baseline, midway through the first cycle, prior to each subsequent cycle, and approximately two to four weeks after the last dose of TEMODAR.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6675" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Fetal harm can occur when administered to a pregnant woman.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6676" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Women should be advised to avoid becoming pregnant when receiving TEMODAR.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6677" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>As bioequivalence has been established only when given over 90 minutes, infusion over a shorter or longer period of time may result in suboptimal dosing; the possibility of an increase in infusion-related adverse reactions cannot be ruled out.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6678" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients treated with TEMODAR may experience myelosuppression, including prolonged pancytopenia, which may result in aplastic anemia, which in some cases has resulted in a fatal outcome.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6679" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In some cases, exposure to concomitant medications associated with aplastic anemia, including carbamazepine, phenytoin, and sulfamethoxazole/trimethoprim, complicates assessment.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M24" type="SpecificInteraction" span="155 22" str="complicates assessment" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M14" type="Precipitant" span="94 13" str="carbamazepine" code="33CM23913M | N0000007470"/>
<Mention id="M17" type="Precipitant" span="39 43" str="medications associated with aplastic anemia" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M20" type="Precipitant" span="109 9" str="phenytoin" code="6158TKW0C5 | N0000006023"/>
<Mention id="M23" type="Precipitant" span="124 29" str="sulfamethoxazole/trimethoprim" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M24" precipitant="M14" effect="M24" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M24" precipitant="M17" effect="M24" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M24" precipitant="M20" effect="M24" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M24" precipitant="M23" effect="M24" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6680" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Prior to dosing, patients must have an absolute neutrophil count (ANC) greater than or equal to 1.5 Ã— 109/L and a platelet count greater than or equal to 100 Ã— 109/L.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6681" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>A complete blood count should be obtained on Day 22 (21 days after the first dose) or within 48 hours of that day, and weekly until the ANC is above 1.5 Ã— 109/L and platelet count exceeds 100 Ã— 109/L.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6682" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Geriatric patients and women have been shown in clinical trials to have a higher risk of developing myelosuppression.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6683" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>For treatment of newly diagnosed glioblastoma multiforme: Prophylaxis against Pneumocystis pneumonia (PCP) is required for all patients receiving concomitant TEMODAR and radiotherapy for the 42-day regimen.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6684" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There may be a higher occurrence of PCP when temozolomide is administered during a longer dosing regimen.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6685" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>However, all patients receiving temozolomide, particularly patients receiving steroids, should be observed closely for the development of PCP regardless of the regimen.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M25" type="Trigger" span="88 18" str="should be observed "/>
<Mention id="M26" type="Trigger" span="123 11" str=" development"/>
<Mention id="M27" type="Precipitant" span="78 8" str="steroids" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M28" type="SpecificInteraction" span="138 3" str="PCP" code="415125002: Pneumocystosis jirovecii pneumonia (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M25;M26" precipitant="M27" effect="M28" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6686" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>For the concomitant treatment phase with RT, a complete blood count should be obtained prior to initiation of treatment and weekly during treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6687" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>For the 28-day treatment cycles, a complete blood count should be obtained prior to treatment on Day 1 and on Day 22 (21 days after the first dose) of each cycle.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6688" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Blood counts should be performed weekly until recovery if the ANC falls below 1.5 Ã— 109/L and the platelet count falls below 100 Ã— 109/L.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6689" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Fatal and severe hepatotoxicity have been reported in patients receiving TEMODAR.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6690" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>TEMODAR can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6691" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Administration of TEMODAR to rats and rabbits during organogenesis at 0.38 and 0.75 times the maximum recommended human dose (75 and 150 mg/m2), respectively, caused numerous fetal malformations of the external organs, soft tissues, and skeleton in both species.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6692" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>As bioequivalence has been established only when TEMODAR for Injection was given over 90 minutes, infusion over a shorter or longer period of time may result in suboptimal dosing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6693" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Additionally, the possibility of an increase in infusion-related adverse reactions cannot be ruled out.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6694" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Temozolomide is not directly active but undergoes rapid nonenzymatic conversion at physiologic pH to the reactive compound 5-(3-methyltriazen-1-yl)-imidazole-4-carboxamide (MTIC).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6695" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The cytotoxicity of MTIC is thought to be primarily due to alkylation of DNA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6696" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Alkylation (methylation) occurs mainly at the O6 and N7 positions of guanine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6697" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Absorption: Temozolomide is rapidly and completely absorbed after oral administration with a peak plasma concentration (Cmax) achieved in a median Tmax of 1 hour.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6698" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Food reduces the rate and extent of temozolomide absorption.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M29" type="Trigger" span="5 7;49 10" str="reduces | absorption"/>
<Mention id="M30" type="Precipitant" span="0 4" str="Food" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M29" precipitant="M30" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6699" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Mean peak plasma concentration and AUC decreased by 32% and 9%, respectively, and median Tmax increased by 2-fold (from 1–2.25 hours) when temozolomide was administered after a modified high-fat breakfast.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M31" type="Trigger" span="35 13" str="AUC decreased"/>
<Mention id="M36" type="Precipitant" span="186 18" str="high-fat breakfast" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M33" type="Trigger" span="5 25;39 9" str="peak plasma concentration | decreased"/>
<Mention id="M35" type="Trigger" span="89 14" str="Tmax increased"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M31" precipitant="M36" effect="C54609"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M33" precipitant="M36" effect="C54606"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M36" effect="C54604"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6700" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A pharmacokinetic study comparing oral and intravenous temozolomide in 19 patients with primary CNS malignancies showed that 150 mg/m2 TEMODAR for injection administered over 90 minutes is bioequivalent to 150 mg/m2 TEMODAR oral capsules with respect to both Cmax and AUC of temozolomide and MTIC.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6701" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following a single 90-minute intravenous infusion of 150 mg/m2, the geometric mean Cmax values for temozolomide and MTIC were 7.3 mcg/mL and 276 ng/mL, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6702" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following a single oral dose of 150 mg/m2, the geometric mean Cmax values for temozolomide and MTIC were 7.5 mcg/mL and 282 ng/mL, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6703" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following a single 90-minute intravenous infusion of 150 mg/m2, the geometric mean AUC values for temozolomide and MTIC were 24.6 mcg∙hr/mL and 891 ng∙hr/mL, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6704" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following a single oral dose of 150 mg/m2, the geometric mean AUC values for temozolomide and MTIC were 23.4 mcg∙hr/mL and 864 ng∙hr/mL, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6705" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Distribution: Temozolomide has a mean apparent volume of distribution of 0.4 L/kg (%CV=13%).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6706" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>It is weakly bound to human plasma proteins; the mean percent bound of drug-related total radioactivity is 15%.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6707" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Metabolism and Elimination: Temozolomide is spontaneously hydrolyzed at physiologic pH to the active species, MTIC and to temozolomide acid metabolite.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6708" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>MTIC is further hydrolyzed to 5-amino-imidazole-4-carboxamide (AIC), which is known to be an intermediate in purine and nucleic acid biosynthesis, and to methylhydrazine, which is believed to be the active alkylating species.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6709" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Cytochrome P450 enzymes play only a minor role in the metabolism of temozolomide and MTIC.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6710" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Relative to the AUC of temozolomide, the exposure to MTIC and AIC is 2.4% and 23%, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6711" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Excretion: About 38% of the administered temozolomide total radioactive dose is recovered over 7 days: 37.7% in urine and 0.8% in feces.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6712" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The majority of the recovery of radioactivity in urine is unchanged temozolomide (5.6%), AIC (12%), temozolomide acid metabolite (2.3%), and unidentified polar metabolite(s) (17%).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6713" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Overall clearance of temozolomide is about 5.5 L/hr/m2.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6714" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Temozolomide is rapidly eliminated, with a mean elimination half-life of 1.8 hours, and exhibits linear kinetics over the therapeutic dosing range of 75 to 250 mg/m2/day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6715" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Effect of Age: A population pharmacokinetic analysis indicated that age (range: 19–78 years) has no influence on the pharmacokinetics of temozolomide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6716" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Effect of Gender: A population pharmacokinetic analysis indicated that women have an approximately 5% lower clearance (adjusted for body surface area) for temozolomide than men.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6717" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Effect of Race: The effect of race on the pharmacokinetics of temozolomide has not been studied.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6718" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Tobacco Use: A population pharmacokinetic analysis indicated that the oral clearance of temozolomide is similar in smokers and nonsmokers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6719" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Effect of Renal Impairment: A population pharmacokinetic analysis indicated that creatinine clearance over the range of 36 to 130 mL/min/m2 has no effect on the clearance of temozolomide after oral administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6720" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacokinetics of temozolomide have not been studied in patients with severely impaired renal function (CLcr &lt;36 mL/min/m2).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6721" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Caution should be exercised when TEMODAR is administered to patients with severe renal impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6722" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>TEMODAR has not been studied in patients on dialysis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6723" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Effect of Hepatic Impairment: A study showed that the pharmacokinetics of temozolomide in patients with mild-to-moderate hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh Class I – II) were similar to those observed in patients with normal hepatic function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6724" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Caution should be exercised when temozolomide is administered to patients with severe hepatic impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6725" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Effect of Other Drugs on Temozolomide Pharmacokinetics: In a multiple-dose study, administration of TEMODAR Capsules with ranitidine did not change the Cmax or AUC values for temozolomide or MTIC.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6726" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A population analysis indicated that administration of valproic acid decreases the clearance of temozolomide by about 5%.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M37" type="Trigger" span="69 23" str="decreases the clearance"/>
<Mention id="M38" type="Precipitant" span="55 13" str="valproic acid" code="614OI1Z5WI"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M37" precipitant="M38" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6727" LabelDrug="TEMODAR" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A population analysis did not demonstrate any influence of coadministered dexamethasone, prochlorperazine, phenytoin, carbamazepine, ondansetron, H2-receptor antagonists, or phenobarbital on the clearance of orally administered temozolomide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="valproic acid" precipitantCode="614OI1Z5WI" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="valproic acid" precipitantCode="614OI1Z5WI" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="steroids" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="415125002: Pneumocystosis jirovecii pneumonia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="steroids" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="48813009: Lymphocytopenia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="carbamazepine" precipitantCode="33CM23913M | N0000007470" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="medications associated with aplastic anemia" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="phenytoin" precipitantCode="6158TKW0C5 | N0000006023" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sulfamethoxazole/trimethoprim" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="food" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="high-fat breakfast" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54604"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="high-fat breakfast" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54606"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="high-fat breakfast" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54609"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>