<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Exelon" setid="07c12e14-bbd5-4ec8-84e4-fbe7b5ba10e0">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
EXELON PATCH is contraindicated in patients with: known hypersensitivity to rivastigmine, other carbamate derivatives, or other components of the formulation [see Description (11)] previous history of application-site reactions with rivastigmine transdermal patch suggestive of allergic contact dermatitis [see Warnings and Precautions (5.3)] . Isolated cases of generalized skin reactions have been described in postmarketing experience [see Adverse Reactions (6.2)] . Known hypersensitivity to rivastigmine, other carbamate derivatives, or other components of the formulation. ( 4 ) History of application-site reactions with rivastigmine transdermal patch suggestive of allergic contact dermatitis. ( 4 , 6.2 )</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
Apply patch on intact skin for a 24-hour period; replace with a new patch every 24 hours. ( 2.1 , 2.4 ) Initial Dose: Initiate treatment with 4.6 mg/24 hours EXELON PATCH. ( 2.1 ) Dose Titration ( 2.1 ): After a minimum of 4 weeks, if tolerated, increase dose to 9.5 mg/24 hours, which is the minimum effective dose. Following a minimum additional 4 weeks, may increase dosage to maximum dosage of 13.3 mg/24 hours. Mild-to-Moderate Alzheimer’s Disease and Parkinson’s Disease Dementia: EXELON PATCH 9.5 mg/24 hours or 13.3 mg/24 hours once daily. ( 2.1 ) Severe Alzheimer’s Disease: EXELON PATCH 13.3 mg/24 hours once daily. ( 2.1 ) For treatment interruption longer than 3 days, retitrate dosage starting at 4.6 mg per 24 hours. ( 2.1 ) Consider dose adjustments in patients with ( 2.2 ): Mild-to-moderate hepatic impairment ( 8.6 ) Low (less than 50 kg) body weight ( 8.7 ) Initial Dose Initiate treatment with one 4.6 mg/24 hours EXELON PATCH applied to the skin once daily [see Dosage and Administration (2.4)] . Dose Titration Increase the dose only after a minimum of 4 weeks at the previous dose, and only if the previous dose has been tolerated. For mild-to-moderate AD and PDD patients, continue the effective dose of 9.5 mg/24 hours for as long as therapeutic benefit persists. Patients can then be increased to the maximum effective dose of 13.3 mg/24 hours dose. For patients with severe AD, 13.3 mg/24 hours is the effective dose. Doses higher than 13.3 mg/24 hours confer no appreciable additional benefit, and are associated with an increase in the incidence of adverse reactions [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2), Adverse Reactions (6.1)] . Mild-to-Moderate Alzheimer’s Disease and Mild-to-Moderate Parkinson’s Disease Dementia The effective dosage of EXELON PATCH is 9.5 mg/24 hours or 13.3 mg/24 hours administered once per day; replace with a new patch every 24 hours. Severe Alzheimer’s Disease The effective dosage of EXELON PATCH in patients with severe Alzheimer’s disease is 13.3 mg/24 hours administered once per day; replace with a new patch every 24 hours. Interruption of Treatment If dosing is interrupted for 3 days or fewer, restart treatment with the same or lower strength EXELON PATCH. If dosing is interrupted for more than 3 days, restart treatment with the 4.6 mg/24 hours EXELON PATCH and titrate as described above. Dosing Modifications in Patients with Hepatic Impairment Consider using the 4.6 mg/24 hours EXELON PATCH as both the initial and maintenance dose in patients with mild (Child-Pugh score 5 to 6) to moderate (Child-Pugh score 7 to 9) hepatic impairment [see Use in Specific Populations (8.6), Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)] .  Dosing Modifications in Patients with Low Body Weight Carefully titrate and monitor patients with low body weight (less than 50 kg) for toxicities (e.g., excessive nausea, vomiting), and consider reducing the maintenance dose to the 4.6 mg/24 hours EXELON PATCH if such toxicities develop. Patients treated with EXELON Capsules or Oral Solution may be switched to EXELON PATCH as follows: A patient who is on a total daily dose of less than 6 mg of oral rivastigmine can be switched to the 4.6 mg/24 hours EXELON PATCH. A patient who is on a total daily dose of 6 mg to 12 mg of oral rivastigmine can be switched to the 9.5 mg/24 hours EXELON PATCH. Instruct patients or caregivers to apply the first patch on the day following the last oral dose. EXELON PATCH is for transdermal use on intact skin. (a) Do not use the patch if the pouch seal is broken or the patch is cut, damaged, or changed in any way. (b) Apply the EXELON PATCH once a day. Press down firmly for 30 seconds until the edges stick well when applying to clean, dry, hairless, intact healthy skin in a place that will not be rubbed against by tight clothing. Use the upper or lower back as the site of application because the patch is less likely to be removed by the patient. If sites on the back are not accessible, apply the patch to the upper arm or chest. Do not apply to a skin area where cream, lotion, or powder has recently been applied. (c) Do not apply to skin that is red, irritated, or cut. (d) Replace the EXELON PATCH with a new patch every 24 hours. Instruct patients to only wear 1 patch at a time (remove the previous day’s patch before applying a new patch) [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1), Overdosage (10)] . If a patch falls off or if a dose is missed, apply a new patch immediately, and then replace this patch the following day at the usual application time. (e) Change the site of patch application daily to minimize potential irritation, although a new patch can be applied to the same general anatomic site (e.g., another spot on the upper back) on consecutive days. Do not apply a new patch to the same location for at least 14 days. (f) May wear the patch during bathing and in hot weather. But avoid long exposure to external heat sources (excessive sunlight, saunas, solariums). (g) Place used patches in the previously saved pouch and discard in the trash, away from pets or children. (h) Wash hands with soap and water after removing the patch. In case of contact with eyes or if the eyes become red after handling the patch, rinse immediately with plenty of water, and seek medical advice if symptoms do not resolve.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
Concomitant use with metoclopramide, beta-blockers, or cholinomimetics and anticholinergic medications is not recommended. ( 7.1 , 7.2 , 7.3 ) Due to the risk of additive extra-pyramidal adverse reactions, the concomitant use of metoclopramide and EXELON PATCH is not recommended. EXELON PATCH may increase the cholinergic effects of other cholinomimetic medications and may also interfere with the activity of anticholinergic medications (e.g., oxybutynin, tolterodine). Concomitant use of EXELON PATCH with medications having these pharmacologic effects is not recommended unless deemed clinically necessary [see Warnings and Precautions (5.4)] . Additive bradycardic effects resulting in syncope may occur when EXELON is used concomitantly with beta-blockers, especially cardioselective beta-blockers (including atenolol). Concomitant use is not recommended when signs of bradycardia including syncope are present.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
Hospitalization and, rarely, death have been reported due to application of multiple patches at same time. Ensure patients or caregivers receive instruction on proper dosing and administration. ( 5.1 ) Gastrointestinal Adverse Reactions: May include significant nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, anorexia/decreased appetite, and weight loss, and may necessitate treatment interruption. Dehydration may result from prolonged vomiting or diarrhea and can be associated with serious outcomes. ( 5.2 ) Application-site reactions may occur with the patch form of rivastigmine. Discontinue treatment if application-site reactions spread beyond the patch size, if there is evidence of a more intense local reaction (e.g., increasing erythema, edema, papules, vesicles), and if symptoms do not significantly improve within 48 hours after patch removal. ( 5.3 ) Medication errors with EXELON PATCH have resulted in serious adverse reactions; some cases have required hospitalization, and rarely, led to death. The majority of medication errors have involved not removing the old patch when putting on a new one and the use of multiple patches at one time. Instruct patients and their caregivers on important administration instructions for EXELON PATCH [see Dosage and Administration (2.4)] . EXELON PATCH can cause gastrointestinal adverse reactions, including significant nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, anorexia/decreased appetite, and weight loss. Dehydration may result from prolonged vomiting or diarrhea and can be associated with serious outcomes. The incidence and severity of these reactions are dose-related [see Adverse Reactions (6.1)] . For this reason, initiate treatment with EXELON PATCH at a dose of 4.6 mg/24 hours, and titrate to a dose of 9.5 mg/24 hours and then to a dose of 13.3 mg/24 hours, if appropriate [see Dosage and Administration (2.1)] . If treatment is interrupted for more than 3 days because of intolerance, reinitiate EXELON PATCH with the 4.6 mg/24 hours dose to reduce the possibility of severe vomiting and its potentially serious sequelae. A postmarketing report described a case of severe vomiting with esophageal rupture following inappropriate reinitiation of treatment of an oral formulation of rivastigmine without retitration after 8 weeks of treatment interruption. Inform caregivers to monitor for gastrointestinal adverse reactions and to inform the physician if they occur.  It is critical to inform caregivers that if therapy has been interrupted for more than 3 days because of intolerance, the next dose should not be administered without contacting the physician regarding proper retitration. Skin application-site reactions may occur with EXELON PATCH. These reactions are not in themselves an indication of sensitization. However, use of rivastigmine patch may lead to allergic contact dermatitis. Allergic contact dermatitis should be suspected if application-site reactions spread beyond the patch size, if there is evidence of a more intense local reaction (e.g., increasing erythema, edema, papules, vesicles), and if symptoms do not significantly improve within 48 hours after patch removal. In these cases, treatment should be discontinued [see Contraindications (4)] . In patients who develop application-site reactions to EXELON PATCH, suggestive of allergic contact dermatitis and who still require rivastigmine, treatment should be switched to oral rivastigmine only after negative allergy testing and under close medical supervision. It is possible that some patients sensitized to rivastigmine by exposure to rivastigmine patch may not be able to take rivastigmine in any form. There have been isolated postmarketing reports of patients experiencing disseminated allergic dermatitis when administered rivastigmine irrespective of the route of administration (oral or transdermal). In these cases, treatment should be discontinued [see Contraindications (4)] . Patients and caregivers should be instructed accordingly. Neurologic Effects Extrapyramidal Symptoms : Cholinomimetics, including rivastigmine, may exacerbate or induce extrapyramidal symptoms. Worsening of parkinsonian symptoms, particularly tremor, has been observed in patients with dementia associated with Parkinson’s disease who were treated with EXELON Capsules. Seizures : Drugs that increase cholinergic activity are believed to have some potential for causing seizures. However, seizure activity also may be a manifestation of Alzheimer's disease. Peptic Ulcers/Gastrointestinal Bleeding Cholinesterase inhibitors, including rivastigmine, may increase gastric acid secretion due to increased cholinergic activity. Monitor patients using EXELON PATCH for symptoms of active or occult gastrointestinal bleeding, especially those at increased risk for developing ulcers, e.g., those with a history of ulcer disease or those receiving concurrent nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs). Clinical studies of rivastigmine have shown no significant increase, relative to placebo, in the incidence of either peptic ulcer disease or gastrointestinal bleeding. Use with Anesthesia Rivastigmine, as a cholinesterase inhibitor, is likely to exaggerate succinylcholine-type muscle relaxation during anesthesia. Cardiac Conduction Effects Because rivastigmine increases cholinergic activity, use of the EXELON PATCH may have vagotonic effects on heart rate (e.g., bradycardia). The potential for this action may be particularly important in patients with sick sinus syndrome or other supraventricular cardiac conduction conditions. In clinical trials, rivastigmine was not associated with any increased incidence of cardiovascular adverse events, heart rate or blood pressure changes, or electrocardiogram (ECG) abnormalities. Genitourinary Effects Although not observed in clinical trials of rivastigmine, drugs that increase cholinergic activity may cause urinary obstruction. Pulmonary Effects Drugs that increase cholinergic activity, including EXELON PATCH, should be used with care in patients with a history of asthma or obstructive pulmonary disease. Dementia may cause gradual impairment of driving performance or compromise the ability to use machinery. The administration of rivastigmine may also result in adverse reactions that are detrimental to these functions. During treatment with EXELON PATCH, routinely evaluate the patient's ability to continue driving or operating machinery.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Figure 2: Rivastigmine Plasma Concentrations Following Dermal 24-Hour Patch Application Although the precise mechanism of action of rivastigmine is unknown, it is thought to exert its therapeutic effect by enhancing cholinergic function. This is accomplished by increasing the concentration of acetylcholine through reversible inhibition of its hydrolysis by cholinesterase. The effect of rivastigmine may lessen as the disease process advances and fewer cholinergic neurons remain functionally intact. There is no evidence that rivastigmine alters the course of the underlying dementing process. After a 6-mg oral dose of rivastigmine in humans, anticholinesterase activity is present in cerebrospinal fluid for about 10 hours, with a maximum inhibition of about 60% 5 hours after dosing. In vitro and in vivo studies demonstrate that the inhibition of cholinesterase by rivastigmine is not affected by the concomitant administration of memantine, an N-methyl-D-aspartate receptor antagonist. Absorption After the initial application of EXELON PATCH, there is a lag time of 0.5 to 1 hour in the absorption of rivastigmine. Concentrations then rise slowly typically reaching a maximum after 8 hours, although maximum values (C max ) can also occur later (at 10 to 16 hours). After the peak, plasma concentrations slowly decrease over the remainder of the 24-hour period of application. At steady state, trough levels are approximately 60% to 80% of peak levels. EXELON PATCH 9.5 mg/24 hours gave exposure approximately the same as that provided by an oral dose of 6 mg twice daily (i.e., 12 mg/day).  Inter-subject variability in exposure was lower (43% to 49%) for the EXELON PATCH formulation as compared with the oral formulations (73% to 103%).  Fluctuation (between C max and C min ) is less for EXELON PATCH than for the oral formulation of rivastigmine. Figure 2 displays rivastigmine plasma concentrations over 24 hours for the 3 available patch strengths. Figure 2: Rivastigmine Plasma Concentrations Following Dermal 24-Hour Patch Application Over a 24-hour dermal application, approximately 50% of the drug content of the patch is released from the system. Exposure area under the plasma concentration-time curve from time zero to infinity (AUC ∞ ) to rivastigmine (and metabolite NAP266-90) was highest when the patch was applied to the upper back, chest, or upper arm. Two other sites (abdomen and thigh) could be used if none of the 3 other sites is available, but the practitioner should be aware that the rivastigmine plasma exposure associated with these sites was approximately 20% to 30% lower. There was no relevant accumulation of rivastigmine or the metabolite NAP226-90 in plasma in patients with Alzheimer’s disease with daily dosing. The pharmacokinetic profile of rivastigmine transdermal patches was comparable in patients with Alzheimer’s disease and in patients with dementia associated with Parkinson’s disease. Distribution Rivastigmine is weakly bound to plasma proteins (approximately 40%) over the therapeutic range. It readily crosses the blood-brain barrier, reaching CSF peak concentrations in 1.4 to 2.6 hours. It has an apparent volume of distribution in the range of 1.8 to 2.7 L/kg. Metabolism Rivastigmine is extensively metabolized primarily via cholinesterase-mediated hydrolysis to the decarbamylated metabolite NAP226-90. In vitro , this metabolite shows minimal inhibition of acetylcholinesterase (less than 10%). Based on evidence from in vitro and animal studies, the major cytochrome P450 isoenzymes are minimally involved in rivastigmine metabolism. The metabolite-to-parent AUC ∞ ratio was about 0.7 after EXELON PATCH application versus 3.5 after oral administration, indicating that much less metabolism occurred after dermal treatment. Less NAP226-90 is formed following patch application, presumably because of the lack of presystemic (hepatic first pass) metabolism. Based on in vitro studies, no unique metabolic routes were detected in human skin. Elimination Renal excretion of the metabolites is the major route of elimination. Unchanged rivastigmine is found in trace amounts in the urine. Following administration of 14 C-rivastigmine, renal elimination was rapid and essentially complete (greater than 90%) within 24 hours. Less than 1% of the administered dose is excreted in the feces. The apparent elimination half-life in plasma is approximately 3 hours after patch removal. Renal clearance was approximately 2.1 to 2.8 L/hr. Age Age had no impact on the exposure to rivastigmine in Alzheimer’s disease patients treated with EXELON PATCH. Gender and Race No specific pharmacokinetic study was conducted to investigate the effect of gender and race on the disposition of EXELON PATCH. A population pharmacokinetic analysis of oral rivastigmine indicated that neither gender (n = 277 males and 348 females) nor race (n = 575 Caucasian, 34 Black, 4 Asian, and 12 Other) affected clearance of the drug. Similar results were seen with analyses of pharmacokinetic data obtained after the administration of EXELON PATCH. Body Weight A relationship between drug exposure at steady state (rivastigmine and metabolite NAP226-90) and body weight was observed in Alzheimer’s dementia patients. Rivastigmine exposure is higher in subjects with low body weight. Compared to a patient with a body weight of 65 kg, the rivastigmine steady-state concentrations in a patient with a body weight of 35 kg would be approximately doubled, while for a patient with a body weight of 100 kg the concentrations would be approximately halved [see Dosage and Administration (2.2)] . Renal Impairment No study was conducted with EXELON PATCH in subjects with renal impairment. Based on population analysis, creatinine clearance did not show any clear effect on steady state concentrations of rivastigmine or its metabolite. Hepatic Impairment No pharmacokinetic study was conducted with EXELON PATCH in subjects with hepatic impairment. Following a single 3-mg dose, mean oral clearance of rivastigmine was 60% lower in hepatically impaired patients (n = 10, biopsy proven) than in healthy subjects (n = 10). After multiple 6-mg twice a day oral dosing, the mean clearance of rivastigmine was 65% lower in mild (n = 7, Child-Pugh score 5 to 6) and moderate (n = 3, Child-Pugh score 7 to 9) hepatically impaired patients (biopsy proven, liver cirrhosis) than in healthy subjects (n = 10) [see Dosage and Administration (2.2), Use in Specific Populations (8.6)] . Smoking Following oral rivastigmine administration (up to 12 mg/day) with nicotine use, population pharmacokinetic analysis showed increased oral clearance of rivastigmine by 23% (n = 75 smokers and 549 nonsmokers). Drug Interaction Studies No specific interaction studies have been conducted with EXELON PATCH. Information presented below is from studies with oral rivastigmine. Effect of Rivastigmine on the Metabolism of Other Drugs Rivastigmine is primarily metabolized through hydrolysis by esterases. Minimal metabolism occurs via the major cytochrome P450 isoenzymes. Based on in vitro studies, no pharmacokinetic drug interactions with drugs metabolized by the following isoenzyme systems are expected: CYP1A2, CYP2D6, CYP3A4/5, CYP2E1, CYP2C9, CYP2C8, CYP2C19, or CYP2B6. No pharmacokinetic interaction was observed between rivastigmine taken orally and digoxin, warfarin, diazepam, or fluoxetine in studies in healthy volunteers. The increase in prothrombin time induced by warfarin is not affected by administration of rivastigmine. Effect of Other Drugs on the Metabolism of Rivastigmine Drugs that induce or inhibit CYP450 metabolism are not expected to alter the metabolism of rivastigmine. Population pharmacokinetic analysis with a database of 625 patients showed that the pharmacokinetics of rivastigmine taken orally were not influenced by commonly prescribed medications such as antacids (n = 77), antihypertensives (n = 72), beta-blockers (n = 42), calcium channel blockers (n = 75), antidiabetics (n = 21), nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (n = 79), estrogens (n = 70), salicylate analgesics (n = 177), antianginals (n = 35), and antihistamines (n = 15).</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="7307" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>EXELON PATCH is contraindicated in patients with: known hypersensitivity to rivastigmine, other carbamate derivatives, or other components of the formulation previous history of application-site reactions with rivastigmine transdermal patch suggestive of allergic contact dermatitis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7308" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Isolated cases of generalized skin reactions have been described in postmarketing experience.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7309" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Known hypersensitivity to rivastigmine, other carbamate derivatives, or other components of the formulation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7310" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>History of application-site reactions with rivastigmine transdermal patch suggestive of allergic contact dermatitis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7311" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Apply patch on intact skin for a 24-hour period; replace with a new patch every 24 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7312" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Initial Dose: Initiate treatment with 4.6 mg/24 hours EXELON PATCH.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7313" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dose Titration (2.1): After a minimum of 4 weeks, if tolerated, increase dose to 9.5 mg/24 hours, which is the minimum effective dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7314" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Following a minimum additional 4 weeks, may increase dosage to maximum dosage of 13.3 mg/24 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7315" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Mild-to-Moderate Alzheimer’s Disease and Parkinson’s Disease Dementia: EXELON PATCH 9.5 mg/24 hours or 13.3 mg/24 hours once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7316" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Severe Alzheimer’s Disease: EXELON PATCH 13.3 mg/24 hours once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7317" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For treatment interruption longer than 3 days, retitrate dosage starting at 4.6 mg per 24 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7318" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Consider dose adjustments in patients with (2.2): Mild-to-moderate hepatic impairment (8.6) Low (less than 50 kg) body weight (8.7) Initial Dose Initiate treatment with one 4.6 mg/24 hours EXELON PATCH applied to the skin once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7319" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dose Titration Increase the dose only after a minimum of 4 weeks at the previous dose, and only if the previous dose has been tolerated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7320" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For mild-to-moderate AD and PDD patients, continue the effective dose of 9.5 mg/24 hours for as long as therapeutic benefit persists.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7321" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Patients can then be increased to the maximum effective dose of 13.3 mg/24 hours dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7322" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For patients with severe AD, 13.3 mg/24 hours is the effective dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7323" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Doses higher than 13.3 mg/24 hours confer no appreciable additional benefit, and are associated with an increase in the incidence of adverse reactions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7324" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Mild-to-Moderate Alzheimer’s Disease and Mild-to-Moderate Parkinson’s Disease Dementia The effective dosage of EXELON PATCH is 9.5 mg/24 hours or 13.3 mg/24 hours administered once per day; replace with a new patch every 24 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7325" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Severe Alzheimer’s Disease The effective dosage of EXELON PATCH in patients with severe Alzheimer’s disease is 13.3 mg/24 hours administered once per day; replace with a new patch every 24 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7326" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Interruption of Treatment If dosing is interrupted for 3 days or fewer, restart treatment with the same or lower strength EXELON PATCH.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7327" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If dosing is interrupted for more than 3 days, restart treatment with the 4.6 mg/24 hours EXELON PATCH and titrate as described above.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7328" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dosing Modifications in Patients with Hepatic Impairment Consider using the 4.6 mg/24 hours EXELON PATCH as both the initial and maintenance dose in patients with mild (Child-Pugh score 5 to 6) to moderate (Child-Pugh score 7 to 9) hepatic impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7329" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dosing Modifications in Patients with Low Body Weight Carefully titrate and monitor patients with low body weight (less than 50 kg) for toxicities (e.g., excessive nausea, vomiting), and consider reducing the maintenance dose to the 4.6 mg/24 hours EXELON PATCH if such toxicities develop.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7330" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Patients treated with EXELON Capsules or Oral Solution may be switched to EXELON PATCH as follows: A patient who is on a total daily dose of less than 6 mg of oral rivastigmine can be switched to the 4.6 mg/24 hours EXELON PATCH.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7331" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>A patient who is on a total daily dose of 6 mg to 12 mg of oral rivastigmine can be switched to the 9.5 mg/24 hours EXELON PATCH.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7332" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Instruct patients or caregivers to apply the first patch on the day following the last oral dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7333" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>EXELON PATCH is for transdermal use on intact skin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7334" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>(a) Do not use the patch if the pouch seal is broken or the patch is cut, damaged, or changed in any way.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7335" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Press down firmly for 30 seconds until the edges stick well when applying to clean, dry, hairless, intact healthy skin in a place that will not be rubbed against by tight clothing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7336" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Use the upper or lower back as the site of application because the patch is less likely to be removed by the patient.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7337" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If sites on the back are not accessible, apply the patch to the upper arm or chest.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7338" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not apply to a skin area where cream, lotion, or powder has recently been applied.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7339" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>(c) Do not apply to skin that is red, irritated, or cut.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7340" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>(d) Replace the EXELON PATCH with a new patch every 24 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7341" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Instruct patients to only wear 1 patch at a time (remove the previous day’s patch before applying a new patch).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7342" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If a patch falls off or if a dose is missed, apply a new patch immediately, and then replace this patch the following day at the usual application time.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7343" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>(e) Change the site of patch application daily to minimize potential irritation, although a new patch can be applied to the same general anatomic site (e.g., another spot on the upper back) on consecutive days.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7344" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not apply a new patch to the same location for at least 14 days.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7345" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>(f) May wear the patch during bathing and in hot weather.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7346" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>But avoid long exposure to external heat sources (excessive sunlight, saunas, solariums).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7347" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>(g) Place used patches in the previously saved pouch and discard in the trash, away from pets or children.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7348" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>(h) Wash hands with soap and water after removing the patch.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7349" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In case of contact with eyes or if the eyes become red after handling the patch, rinse immediately with plenty of water, and seek medical advice if symptoms do not resolve.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7350" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant use with metoclopramide, beta-blockers, or cholinomimetics and anticholinergic medications is not recommended.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M7" type="Trigger" span="106 15" str="not recommended"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="75 27" str="anticholinergic medications" code="N0000175574"/>
<Mention id="M4" type="Precipitant" span="37 13" str="beta-blockers" code="N0000000161 | N0000175556"/>
<Mention id="M6" type="Precipitant" span="55 15" str="cholinomimetics" code="N0000175369"/>
<Mention id="M8" type="Precipitant" span="21 14" str="metoclopramide" code="L4YEB44I46"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M7" precipitant="M2"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M7" precipitant="M4"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M7" precipitant="M6"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M7" precipitant="M8"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7351" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Due to the risk of additive extra-pyramidal adverse reactions, the concomitant use of metoclopramide and EXELON PATCH is not recommended.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M9" type="Trigger" span="11 7" str="risk of "/>
<Mention id="M10" type="Trigger" span="19 8" str=" additive "/>
<Mention id="M11" type="Trigger" span="44 17" str=" adverse reactions"/>
<Mention id="M12" type="Precipitant" span="86 14" str="metoclopramide" code="L4YEB44I46"/>
<Mention id="M13" type="SpecificInteraction" span="19 42" str="additive extra-pyramidal adverse reactions" code="43378000: Extrapyramidal sign (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M9;M10;M11" precipitant="M12" effect="M13" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7352" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>EXELON PATCH may increase the cholinergic effects of other cholinomimetic medications and may also interfere with the activity of anticholinergic medications (e.g., oxybutynin, tolterodine).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M14" type="Trigger" span="17 8;42 7" str="increase | effects"/>
<Mention id="M15" type="Precipitant" span="59 26" str="cholinomimetic medications" code="N0000175369"/>
<Mention id="M16" type="SpecificInteraction" span="17 32" str="increase the cholinergic effects" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M21" type="Trigger" span="99 14" str="interfere with"/>
<Mention id="M18" type="Precipitant" span="130 27" str="anticholinergic medications" code="N0000175574"/>
<Mention id="M20" type="Precipitant" span="165 10" str="oxybutynin" code="K9P6MC7092"/>
<Mention id="M22" type="Precipitant" span="177 11" str="tolterodine" code="WHE7A56U7K"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M14" precipitant="M15" effect="M16" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M21" precipitant="M18"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M21" precipitant="M20"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M21" precipitant="M22"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7353" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant use of EXELON PATCH with medications having these pharmacologic effects is not recommended unless deemed clinically necessary.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7354" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Additive bradycardic effects resulting in syncope may occur when EXELON is used concomitantly with beta-blockers, especially cardioselective beta-blockers (including atenolol).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M48" type="Trigger" span="0 8;21 7" str="Additive | effects "/>
<Mention id="M49" type="Trigger" span="29 12" str=" resulting in "/>
<Mention id="M50" type="Trigger" span="54 5" str=" occur"/>
<Mention id="M31" type="Precipitant" span="166 8" str="atenolol" code="50VV3VW0TI"/>
<Mention id="M47" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 28" str="Additive bradycardic effects" code="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M52" type="SpecificInteraction" span="42 7" str="syncope" code="271594007: Syncope (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M41" type="Precipitant" span="99 13" str="beta-blockers" code="N0000000161 | N0000175556"/>
<Mention id="M51" type="Precipitant" span="125 29" str="cardioselective beta-blockers" code="N0000000161"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M48;M49;M50" precipitant="M31" effect="M47" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M48;M49;M50" precipitant="M31" effect="M52" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M48;M49;M50" precipitant="M41" effect="M47" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M48;M49;M50" precipitant="M41" effect="M52" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M48;M49;M50" precipitant="M51" effect="M47" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M48;M49;M50" precipitant="M51" effect="M52" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7355" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant use is not recommended when signs of bradycardia including syncope are present.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7356" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hospitalization and, rarely, death have been reported due to application of multiple patches at same time.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7357" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Ensure patients or caregivers receive instruction on proper dosing and administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7358" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Gastrointestinal Adverse Reactions: May include significant nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, anorexia/decreased appetite, and weight loss, and may necessitate treatment interruption.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7359" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Dehydration may result from prolonged vomiting or diarrhea and can be associated with serious outcomes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7360" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Application-site reactions may occur with the patch form of rivastigmine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7361" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Discontinue treatment if application-site reactions spread beyond the patch size, if there is evidence of a more intense local reaction (e.g., increasing erythema, edema, papules, vesicles), and if symptoms do not significantly improve within 48 hours after patch removal.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7362" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Medication errors with EXELON PATCH have resulted in serious adverse reactions; some cases have required hospitalization, and rarely, led to death.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7363" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The majority of medication errors have involved not removing the old patch when putting on a new one and the use of multiple patches at one time.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7364" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Instruct patients and their caregivers on important administration instructions for EXELON PATCH.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7365" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>EXELON PATCH can cause gastrointestinal adverse reactions, including significant nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, anorexia/decreased appetite, and weight loss.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7366" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The incidence and severity of these reactions are dose-related.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7367" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>For this reason, initiate treatment with EXELON PATCH at a dose of 4.6 mg/24 hours, and titrate to a dose of 9.5 mg/24 hours and then to a dose of 13.3 mg/24 hours, if appropriate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7368" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If treatment is interrupted for more than 3 days because of intolerance, reinitiate EXELON PATCH with the 4.6 mg/24 hours dose to reduce the possibility of severe vomiting and its potentially serious sequelae.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7369" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>A postmarketing report described a case of severe vomiting with esophageal rupture following inappropriate reinitiation of treatment of an oral formulation of rivastigmine without retitration after 8 weeks of treatment interruption.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7370" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Inform caregivers to monitor for gastrointestinal adverse reactions and to inform the physician if they occur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7371" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>It is critical to inform caregivers that if therapy has been interrupted for more than 3 days because of intolerance, the next dose should not be administered without contacting the physician regarding proper retitration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7372" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Skin application-site reactions may occur with EXELON PATCH.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7373" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>These reactions are not in themselves an indication of sensitization.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7374" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>However, use of rivastigmine patch may lead to allergic contact dermatitis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7375" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Allergic contact dermatitis should be suspected if application-site reactions spread beyond the patch size, if there is evidence of a more intense local reaction (e.g., increasing erythema, edema, papules, vesicles), and if symptoms do not significantly improve within 48 hours after patch removal.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7376" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In these cases, treatment should be discontinued.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7377" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In patients who develop application-site reactions to EXELON PATCH, suggestive of allergic contact dermatitis and who still require rivastigmine, treatment should be switched to oral rivastigmine only after negative allergy testing and under close medical supervision.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7378" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>It is possible that some patients sensitized to rivastigmine by exposure to rivastigmine patch may not be able to take rivastigmine in any form.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7379" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There have been isolated postmarketing reports of patients experiencing disseminated allergic dermatitis when administered rivastigmine irrespective of the route of administration (oral or transdermal).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7380" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients and caregivers should be instructed accordingly.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7381" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Neurologic Effects Extrapyramidal Symptoms: Cholinomimetics, including rivastigmine, may exacerbate or induce extrapyramidal symptoms.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M53" type="Trigger" span="89 10" str="exacerbate "/>
<Mention id="M54" type="Trigger" span="103 6" str=" induce"/>
<Mention id="M55" type="Precipitant" span="44 15" str="Cholinomimetics" code="N0000175369"/>
<Mention id="M56" type="SpecificInteraction" span="19 23" str="extrapyramidal symptoms" code="43378000: Extrapyramidal sign (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M53;M54" precipitant="M55" effect="M56" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7382" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Worsening of parkinsonian symptoms, particularly tremor, has been observed in patients with dementia associated with Parkinson’s disease who were treated with EXELON Capsules.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7383" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Seizures: Drugs that increase cholinergic activity are believed to have some potential for causing seizures.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7384" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>However, seizure activity also may be a manifestation of Alzheimer's disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7385" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Peptic Ulcers/Gastrointestinal Bleeding Cholinesterase inhibitors, including rivastigmine, may increase gastric acid secretion due to increased cholinergic activity.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M66" type="Trigger" span="134 9" str="increased"/>
<Mention id="M67" type="Precipitant" span="40 25" str="Cholinesterase inhibitors" code="N0000000177 | N0000175723"/>
<Mention id="M59" type="SpecificInteraction" span="14 25" str="Gastrointestinal Bleeding" code="61401005: Gastric hemorrhage (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M62" type="SpecificInteraction" span="95 31" str="increase gastric acid secretion" code="61627001: Hyperchlorhydria (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M65" type="SpecificInteraction" span="134 30" str="increased cholinergic activity" code="61356009: Poisoning caused by parasympathomimetic drug (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M68" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 13" str="Peptic Ulcers" code="13200003: Peptic ulcer (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M66" precipitant="M67" effect="M59" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M66" precipitant="M67" effect="M62" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M66" precipitant="M67" effect="M65" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M66" precipitant="M67" effect="M68" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7386" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor patients using EXELON PATCH for symptoms of active or occult gastrointestinal bleeding, especially those at increased risk for developing ulcers, e.g., those with a history of ulcer disease or those receiving concurrent nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M84" type="Trigger" span="0 7" str="Monitor "/>
<Mention id="M85" type="Trigger" span="40 8" str=" symptoms "/>
<Mention id="M86" type="Trigger" span="116 14" str=" increased risk"/>
<Mention id="M77" type="Precipitant" span="228 36" str="nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M83" type="SpecificInteraction" span="69 25" str="gastrointestinal bleeding" code="61401005: Gastric hemorrhage (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M88" type="SpecificInteraction" span="146 6" str="ulcers" code="429040005: Ulcer (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M87" type="Precipitant" span="266 6" str="NSAIDs" code="N0000175722"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M84;M85;M86" precipitant="M77" effect="M83" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M84;M85;M86" precipitant="M77" effect="M88" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M84;M85;M86" precipitant="M87" effect="M83" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M84;M85;M86" precipitant="M87" effect="M88" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7387" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Clinical studies of rivastigmine have shown no significant increase, relative to placebo, in the incidence of either peptic ulcer disease or gastrointestinal bleeding.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7388" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Use with Anesthesia Rivastigmine, as a cholinesterase inhibitor, is likely to exaggerate succinylcholine-type muscle relaxation during anesthesia.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M89" type="Trigger" span="78 10" str="exaggerate"/>
<Mention id="M90" type="Precipitant" span="9 10" str="anesthesia" code="N0000029138 | N0000175975"/>
<Mention id="M91" type="SpecificInteraction" span="78 49" str="exaggerate succinylcholine-type muscle relaxation" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M89" precipitant="M90" effect="M91" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7389" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Cardiac Conduction Effects Because rivastigmine increases cholinergic activity, use of the EXELON PATCH may have vagotonic effects on heart rate (e.g., bradycardia).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7390" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The potential for this action may be particularly important in patients with sick sinus syndrome or other supraventricular cardiac conduction conditions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7391" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In clinical trials, rivastigmine was not associated with any increased incidence of cardiovascular adverse events, heart rate or blood pressure changes, or electrocardiogram (ECG) abnormalities.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7392" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Genitourinary Effects Although not observed in clinical trials of rivastigmine, drugs that increase cholinergic activity may cause urinary obstruction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7393" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Pulmonary Effects Drugs that increase cholinergic activity, including EXELON PATCH, should be used with care in patients with a history of asthma or obstructive pulmonary disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7394" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Dementia may cause gradual impairment of driving performance or compromise the ability to use machinery.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7395" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The administration of rivastigmine may also result in adverse reactions that are detrimental to these functions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7396" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>During treatment with EXELON PATCH, routinely evaluate the patient's ability to continue driving or operating machinery.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7397" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Figure 2: Rivastigmine Plasma Concentrations Following Dermal 24-Hour Patch Application Although the precise mechanism of action of rivastigmine is unknown, it is thought to exert its therapeutic effect by enhancing cholinergic function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7398" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This is accomplished by increasing the concentration of acetylcholine through reversible inhibition of its hydrolysis by cholinesterase.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7399" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The effect of rivastigmine may lessen as the disease process advances and fewer cholinergic neurons remain functionally intact.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7400" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There is no evidence that rivastigmine alters the course of the underlying dementing process.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7401" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>After a 6-mg oral dose of rivastigmine in humans, anticholinesterase activity is present in cerebrospinal fluid for about 10 hours, with a maximum inhibition of about 60% 5 hours after dosing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7402" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In vitro and in vivo studies demonstrate that the inhibition of cholinesterase by rivastigmine is not affected by the concomitant administration of memantine, an N-methyl-D-aspartate receptor antagonist.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7403" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Absorption After the initial application of EXELON PATCH, there is a lag time of 0.5 to 1 hour in the absorption of rivastigmine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7404" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Concentrations then rise slowly typically reaching a maximum after 8 hours, although maximum values (Cmax) can also occur later (at 10 to 16 hours).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7405" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>After the peak, plasma concentrations slowly decrease over the remainder of the 24-hour period of application.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7406" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>At steady state, trough levels are approximately 60% to 80% of peak levels.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7407" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>EXELON PATCH 9.5 mg/24 hours gave exposure approximately the same as that provided by an oral dose of 6 mg twice daily (i.e., 12 mg/day).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7408" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Inter-subject variability in exposure was lower (43% to 49%) for the EXELON PATCH formulation as compared with the oral formulations (73% to 103%).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7409" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Fluctuation (between Cmax and Cmin) is less for EXELON PATCH than for the oral formulation of rivastigmine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7410" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Figure 2 displays rivastigmine plasma concentrations over 24 hours for the 3 available patch strengths.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7411" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Figure 2: Rivastigmine Plasma Concentrations Following Dermal 24-Hour Patch Application Over a 24-hour dermal application, approximately 50% of the drug content of the patch is released from the system.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7412" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Exposure area under the plasma concentration-time curve from time zero to infinity (AUC∞) to rivastigmine (and metabolite NAP266-90) was highest when the patch was applied to the upper back, chest, or upper arm.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7413" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Two other sites (abdomen and thigh) could be used if none of the 3 other sites is available, but the practitioner should be aware that the rivastigmine plasma exposure associated with these sites was approximately 20% to 30% lower.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7414" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There was no relevant accumulation of rivastigmine or the metabolite NAP226-90 in plasma in patients with Alzheimer’s disease with daily dosing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7415" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacokinetic profile of rivastigmine transdermal patches was comparable in patients with Alzheimer’s disease and in patients with dementia associated with Parkinson’s disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7416" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Distribution Rivastigmine is weakly bound to plasma proteins (approximately 40%) over the therapeutic range.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7417" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>It readily crosses the blood-brain barrier, reaching CSF peak concentrations in 1.4 to 2.6 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7418" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>It has an apparent volume of distribution in the range of 1.8 to 2.7 L/kg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7419" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Metabolism Rivastigmine is extensively metabolized primarily via cholinesterase-mediated hydrolysis to the decarbamylated metabolite NAP226-90.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7420" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In vitro, this metabolite shows minimal inhibition of acetylcholinesterase (less than 10%).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7421" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Based on evidence from in vitro and animal studies, the major cytochrome P450 isoenzymes are minimally involved in rivastigmine metabolism.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7422" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The metabolite-to-parent AUC∞ ratio was about 0.7 after EXELON PATCH application versus 3.5 after oral administration, indicating that much less metabolism occurred after dermal treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7423" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Less NAP226-90 is formed following patch application, presumably because of the lack of presystemic (hepatic first pass) metabolism.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7424" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Based on in vitro studies, no unique metabolic routes were detected in human skin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7425" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Elimination Renal excretion of the metabolites is the major route of elimination.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7426" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Unchanged rivastigmine is found in trace amounts in the urine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7427" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following administration of 14C-rivastigmine, renal elimination was rapid and essentially complete (greater than 90%) within 24 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7428" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Less than 1% of the administered dose is excreted in the feces.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7429" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The apparent elimination half-life in plasma is approximately 3 hours after patch removal.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7430" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Renal clearance was approximately 2.1 to 2.8 L/hr.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7431" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Age Age had no impact on the exposure to rivastigmine in Alzheimer’s disease patients treated with EXELON PATCH.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7432" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Gender and Race No specific pharmacokinetic study was conducted to investigate the effect of gender and race on the disposition of EXELON PATCH.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7433" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A population pharmacokinetic analysis of oral rivastigmine indicated that neither gender (n = 277 males and 348 females) nor race (n = 575 Caucasian, 34 Black, 4 Asian, and 12 Other) affected clearance of the drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7434" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Similar results were seen with analyses of pharmacokinetic data obtained after the administration of EXELON PATCH.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7435" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Body Weight A relationship between drug exposure at steady state (rivastigmine and metabolite NAP226-90) and body weight was observed in Alzheimer’s dementia patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7436" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Rivastigmine exposure is higher in subjects with low body weight.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7437" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Compared to a patient with a body weight of 65 kg, the rivastigmine steady-state concentrations in a patient with a body weight of 35 kg would be approximately doubled, while for a patient with a body weight of 100 kg the concentrations would be approximately halved.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7438" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Renal Impairment No study was conducted with EXELON PATCH in subjects with renal impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7439" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Based on population analysis, creatinine clearance did not show any clear effect on steady state concentrations of rivastigmine or its metabolite.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7440" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Hepatic Impairment No pharmacokinetic study was conducted with EXELON PATCH in subjects with hepatic impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7441" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following a single 3-mg dose, mean oral clearance of rivastigmine was 60% lower in hepatically impaired patients (n = 10, biopsy proven) than in healthy subjects (n = 10).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7442" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>After multiple 6-mg twice a day oral dosing, the mean clearance of rivastigmine was 65% lower in mild (n = 7, Child-Pugh score 5 to 6) and moderate (n = 3, Child-Pugh score 7 to 9) hepatically impaired patients (biopsy proven, liver cirrhosis) than in healthy subjects (n = 10).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7443" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Smoking Following oral rivastigmine administration (up to 12 mg/day) with nicotine use, population pharmacokinetic analysis showed increased oral clearance of rivastigmine by 23% (n = 75 smokers and 549 nonsmokers).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7444" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Drug Interaction Studies No specific interaction studies have been conducted with EXELON PATCH.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7445" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Information presented below is from studies with oral rivastigmine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7446" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Effect of Rivastigmine on the Metabolism of Other Drugs Rivastigmine is primarily metabolized through hydrolysis by esterases.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7447" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Minimal metabolism occurs via the major cytochrome P450 isoenzymes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7448" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Based on in vitro studies, no pharmacokinetic drug interactions with drugs metabolized by the following isoenzyme systems are expected: CYP1A2, CYP2D6, CYP3A4/5, CYP2E1, CYP2C9, CYP2C8, CYP2C19, or CYP2B6.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7449" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No pharmacokinetic interaction was observed between rivastigmine taken orally and digoxin, warfarin, diazepam, or fluoxetine in studies in healthy volunteers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7450" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The increase in prothrombin time induced by warfarin is not affected by administration of rivastigmine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7451" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Effect of Other Drugs on the Metabolism of Rivastigmine Drugs that induce or inhibit CYP450 metabolism are not expected to alter the metabolism of rivastigmine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7452" LabelDrug="Exelon" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Population pharmacokinetic analysis with a database of 625 patients showed that the pharmacokinetics of rivastigmine taken orally were not influenced by commonly prescribed medications such as antacids (n = 77), antihypertensives (n = 72), beta-blockers (n = 42), calcium channel blockers (n = 75), antidiabetics (n = 21), nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (n = 79), estrogens (n = 70), salicylate analgesics (n = 177), antianginals (n = 35), and antihistamines (n = 15).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="anticholinergic medications" precipitantCode="N0000175574"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="beta-blockers" precipitantCode="N0000000161 | N0000175556" effect="271594007: Syncope (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="beta-blockers" precipitantCode="N0000000161 | N0000175556" effect="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="beta-blockers" precipitantCode="N0000000161 | N0000175556"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cholinomimetics" precipitantCode="N0000175369" effect="43378000: Extrapyramidal sign (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="cholinomimetics" precipitantCode="N0000175369"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="metoclopramide" precipitantCode="L4YEB44I46" effect="43378000: Extrapyramidal sign (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="metoclopramide" precipitantCode="L4YEB44I46"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cholinomimetic medications" precipitantCode="N0000175369" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="oxybutynin" precipitantCode="K9P6MC7092"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="tolterodine" precipitantCode="WHE7A56U7K"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="atenolol" precipitantCode="50VV3VW0TI" effect="271594007: Syncope (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="atenolol" precipitantCode="50VV3VW0TI" effect="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cardioselective beta-blockers" precipitantCode="N0000000161" effect="271594007: Syncope (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cardioselective beta-blockers" precipitantCode="N0000000161" effect="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cholinesterase inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000000177 | N0000175723" effect="13200003: Peptic ulcer (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cholinesterase inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000000177 | N0000175723" effect="61356009: Poisoning caused by parasympathomimetic drug (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cholinesterase inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000000177 | N0000175723" effect="61401005: Gastric hemorrhage (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cholinesterase inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000000177 | N0000175723" effect="61627001: Hyperchlorhydria (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="429040005: Ulcer (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="61401005: Gastric hemorrhage (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nsaids" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="429040005: Ulcer (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nsaids" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="61401005: Gastric hemorrhage (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="anesthesia" precipitantCode="N0000029138 | N0000175975" effect="NO MAP"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>