<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="SEREVENT" setid="12d9728e-6b5c-4aee-bfb0-745e542ed2e4">
<Text><Section name="Boxed Warning section" id="34066-1">
WARNING: ASTHMA-RELATED DEATH Long-acting beta 2 -adrenergic agonists (LABA), such as salmeterol, the active ingredient in SEREVENT DISKUS, as monotherapy (without inhaled corticosteroids [ICS]) increase the risk of asthma-related death. Data from a large placebo-controlled U.S. trial that compared the safety of salmeterol with placebo added to usual asthma therapy showed an increase in asthma-related deaths in subjects receiving salmeterol (13 deaths out of 13,176 subjects treated for 28 weeks on salmeterol versus 3 deaths out of 13,179 subjects on placebo). Use of background ICS was not required in this study. When LABA are used in fixed-dose combination with ICS, data from large clinical trials do not show a significant increase in the risk of serious asthma-related events (hospitalizations, intubations, death) compared with ICS alone. Use of SEREVENT DISKUS for the treatment of asthma as monotherapy without a concomitant ICS is contraindicated. Use SEREVENT DISKUS only as additional therapy for patients with asthma who are currently taking but are inadequately controlled on an ICS. Do not use SEREVENT DISKUS for patients whose asthma is adequately controlled on low- or medium-dose ICS. Pediatric and Adolescent Patients Available data from controlled clinical trials suggest that LABA as monotherapy increase the risk of asthma-related hospitalization in pediatric and adolescent patients. For pediatric and adolescent patients with asthma who require addition of a LABA to an ICS, a fixed-dose combination product containing both an ICS and a LABA should ordinarily be used to ensure adherence with both drugs. In cases where use of an ICS and a LABA is clinically indicated, appropriate steps must be taken to ensure adherence with both treatment components. If adherence cannot be assured, a fixed-dose combination product containing both an ICS and a LABA is recommended. WARNING: ASTHMA-RELATED DEATH See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning • Long-acting beta 2 -adrenergic agonists (LABA), such as salmeterol, the active in gre dient in SEREVENT DISKUS, as monotherapy (without inhaled corticosteroids [ICS]) increase the risk of asthma-related death. A U.S. trial showed an increase in asthma-related deaths in subjects receiving salmeterol (13 deaths out of 13,176 subjects treated for 28 weeks on salmeterol versus 3 out of 13,179 subjects on placebo). When LABA are used in fixed-dose combination with ICS, data from large clinical trials do not show a significant increase in the risk of serious asthma-related events (hospitalizations, intubations, death) compared with ICS alone. (5.1) • Prescribe SEREVENT DISKUS only as additional therapy for patients with asthma who are currently taking but are inadequately controlled on an ICS. Do not use SEREVENT DISKUS for patients whose asthma is adequately controlled on low- or medium-dose ICS. ( 1.1 , 5.1 ) • Available data from controlled clinical trials suggest that LABA as monotherapy increase the risk of asthma-related hospitalization in pediatric and adolescent patients. (5.1)</Section>
<Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
Use of SEREVENT DISKUS for the treatment of asthma without concomitant use of an ICS is contraindicated [see Warnings and Precautions ( 5.1 )] . The use of SEREVENT DISKUS is contraindicated in the following conditions: • Primary treatment of status asthmaticus or other acute episodes of asthma or COPD where intensive measures are required [see Warnings and Precautions ( 5.2 )] • Severe hypersensitivity to milk proteins or demonstrated hypersensitivity to salmeterol or any of the excipients [see Warnings and Precautions ( 5.7 ), Adverse Reactions ( 6.3 ), Description ( 11 )] • Asthma: Without concomitant use of an ICS. (4) • Primary treatment of status asthmaticus or acute episodes of asthma or COPD requiring intensive measures. (4) • Severe hypersensitivity to milk proteins or demonstrated hypersensitivity to salmeterol or any of the excipients. (4)</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
SEREVENT DISKUS should be administered by the orally inhaled route only. More frequent administration or a greater number of inhalations (more than 1 inhalation twice daily) is not recommended as some patients are more likely to experience adverse effects. Patients using SEREVENT DISKUS should not use additional LABA for any reason. [See Warnings and Precautions ( 5.4 , 5.6 ).] • For oral inhalation only. ( 2 ) • Treatment of asthma in patients aged 4 years and older: 1 inhalation twice daily in addition to concomitant treatment with an ICS. (2.1) • EIB: 1 inhalation at least 30 minutes before exercise. (2.2) • Maintenance treatment of bronchospasm associated with COPD: 1 inhalation twice daily. (2.3) LABA, such as salmeterol, the active ingredient in SEREVENT DISKUS, as monotherapy (without ICS) increase the risk of asthma-related death [see Warnings and Precautions ( 5.1 )] . Because of this risk, use of SEREVENT DISKUS for the treatment of asthma without concomitant use of an ICS is contraindicated. Use SEREVENT DISKUS only as additional therapy for patients with asthma who are currently taking but are inadequately controlled on an ICS . Do not use SEREVENT DISKUS for patients whose asthma is adequately controlled on low- or medium-dose ICS. Pediatric and Adolescent Patients Available data from controlled clinical trials suggest that LABA as monotherapy increase the risk of asthma-related hospitalization in pediatric and adolescent patients. For patients with asthma younger than 18 years who require addition of a LABA to an ICS, a fixed-dose combination product containing both an ICS and a LABA should ordinarily be used to ensure adherence with both drugs. In cases where use of a separate ICS and a LABA is clinically indicated, appropriate steps must be taken to ensure adherence with both treatment components. If adherence cannot be assured, a fixed-dose combination product containing both an ICS and a LABA is recommended. For bronchodilatation and prevention of symptoms of asthma, including the symptoms of nocturnal asthma, the usual dosage for adults and children aged 4 years and older is 1 inhalation (50 mcg) twice daily, approximately 12 hours apart. If a previously effective dosage regimen fails to provide the usual response, medical advice should be sought immediately as this is often a sign of destabilization of asthma. Under these circumstances, the therapeutic regimen should be reevaluated. If symptoms arise in the period between doses, an inhaled, short-acting beta 2 -agonist should be taken for immediate relief. Use of SEREVENT DISKUS as a single agent for the prevention of EIB may be clinically indicated in patients who do not have persistent asthma. In patients with persistent asthma, use of SEREVENT DISKUS for the prevention of EIB may be clinically indicated, but the treatment of asthma should include an ICS . One inhalation of SEREVENT DISKUS at least 30 minutes before exercise has been shown to protect patients against EIB. When used intermittently as needed for prevention of EIB, this protection may last up to 9 hours in adults and adolescents and up to 12 hours in patients aged 4 to 11 years. Additional doses of SEREVENT should not be used for 12 hours after the administration of this drug. Patients who are receiving SEREVENT DISKUS twice daily should not use additional SEREVENT for prevention of EIB. For maintenance treatment of bronchospasm associated with COPD (including chronic bronchitis and emphysema), the dosage for adults is 1 inhalation (50 mcg) twice daily approximately 12 hours apart.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
• Strong cytochrome P450 3A4 inhibitors (e.g., ritonavir, ketoconazole): Use not recommended. May increase risk of cardiovascular effects. (7.1) • Monoamine oxidase inhibitors and tricyclic antidepressants: Use with extreme caution. May potentiate effect of salmeterol on vascular system. (7.2) • Beta-blockers: Use with caution. May block bronchodilatory effects of beta-agonists and produce severe bronchospasm. (7.3) • Diuretics: Use with caution. Electrocardiographic changes and/or hypokalemia associated with non–potassium-sparing diuretics may worsen with concomitant beta-agonists. (7.4) Salmeterol is a substrate of CYP3A4. The use of strong CYP3A4 inhibitors (e.g., ritonavir, atazanavir, clarithromycin, indinavir, itraconazole, nefazodone, nelfinavir, saquinavir, ketoconazole, telithromycin) with SEREVENT DISKUS is not recommended because increased cardiovascular adverse effects may occur. In a drug interaction trial in 20 healthy subjects, coadministration of inhaled salmeterol (50 mcg twice daily) and oral ketoconazole (400 mg once daily) for 7 days resulted in greater systemic exposure to salmeterol (AUC increased 16-fold and C max increased 1.4-fold). Three (3) subjects were withdrawn due to beta 2 -agonist side effects (2 with prolonged QTc and 1 with palpitations and sinus tachycardia). Although there was no statistical effect on the mean QTc, coadministration of salmeterol and ketoconazole was associated with more frequent increases in QTc duration compared with salmeterol and placebo administration. SEREVENT DISKUS should be administered with extreme caution to patients being treated with monoamine oxidase inhibitors or tricyclic antidepressants, or within 2 weeks of discontinuation of such agents, because the action of salmeterol on the vascular system may be potentiated by these agents. Beta-blockers not only block the pulmonary effect of beta-agonists, such as salmeterol, but may also produce severe bronchospasm in patients with asthma or COPD. Therefore, patients with asthma or COPD should not normally be treated with beta-blockers. However, under certain circumstances, there may be no acceptable alternatives to the use of beta-adrenergic blocking agents for these patients; cardioselective beta-blockers could be considered, although they should be administered with caution. The ECG changes and/or hypokalemia that may result from the administration of non–potassium-sparing diuretics (such as loop or thiazide diuretics) can be acutely worsened by beta-agonists, especially when the recommended dose of the beta-agonist is exceeded. Although the clinical significance of these effects is not known, caution is advised in the coadministration of SEREVENT DISKUS with non–potassium-sparing diuretics.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
• LABA as monotherapy (without ICS) for asthma increase the risk of asthma-related death and asthma-related hospitalizations. Prescribe for asthma only as concomitant therapy with an inhaled corticosteroid. (5.1) • Do not initiate in acutely deteriorating asthma or COPD. Do not use to treat acute symptoms. (5.2) • Not a substitute for corticosteroids. Patients with asthma must take a concomitant ICS. (5.3) • Do not use in combination with an additional medicine containing a LABA because of risk of overdose. (5.4) • If paradoxical bronchospasm occurs, discontinue SEREVENT DISKUS and institute alternative therapy. (5.5) • Use with caution in patients with cardiovascular or central nervous system disorders because of beta-adrenergic stimulation. (5.6) • Use with caution in patients with convulsive disorders, thyrotoxicosis, diabetes mellitus, and ketoacidosis. (5.9) • Be alert to hypokalemia and hyperglycemia. (5.10) LABA, such as salmeterol, the active ingredient in SEREVENT DISKUS, as monotherapy (without ICS) increase the risk of asthma-related death. When LABA are used in fixed‑dose combination with ICS, data from large clinical trials do not show a significant increase in the risk of serious asthma-related events (hospitalizations, intubations, death) compared with ICS alone. Use of SEREVENT DISKUS for the treatment of asthma without concomitant use of an ICS is contraindicated. Use SEREVENT DISKUS only as additional therapy for patients with asthma who are currently taking but are inadequately controlled on an ICS. Do not use SEREVENT DISKUS for patients whose asthma is adequately controlled on low- or medium-dose ICS. Pediatric and Adolescent Patients Available data from controlled clinical trials suggest that LABA as monotherapy increase the risk of asthma-related hospitalization in pediatric and adolescent patients. For pediatric and adolescent patients with asthma who require addition of a LABA to an ICS, a fixed-dose combination product containing both an ICS and a LABA should ordinarily be used to ensure adherence with both drugs. In cases where use of a separate ICS and a LABA is clinically indicated, appropriate steps must be taken to ensure adherence with both treatment components. If adherence cannot be assured, a fixed-dose combination product containing both an ICS and a LABA is recommended. The Salmeterol Multicenter Asthma Research Trial (SMART) was a large 28-week placebo-controlled U.S. trial comparing the safety of salmeterol (SEREVENT Inhalation Aerosol) with placebo, each added to usual asthma therapy, that showed an increase in asthma-related deaths in subjects receiving salmeterol [see Clinical Studies ( 14.1 )] . Given the similar basic mechanisms of action of beta 2 -agonists, the findings seen in the SMART trial are considered a class effect. A 16-week clinical trial performed in the United Kingdom, the Salmeterol Nationwide Surveillance (SNS) trial, showed results similar to the SMART trial. In the SNS trial, the rate of asthma-related death was numerically, though not statistically significantly, greater in subjects with asthma treated with salmeterol (42 mcg twice daily) than those treated with albuterol (180 mcg 4 times daily) added to usual asthma therapy. The SNS and SMART trials enrolled subjects with asthma. Available data do not suggest an increased risk of death with use of LABA in patients with COPD. SEREVENT DISKUS should not be initiated in patients during rapidly deteriorating or potentially life-threatening episodes of asthma or COPD. SEREVENT DISKUS has not been studied in subjects with acutely deteriorating asthma or COPD. The initiation of SEREVENT DISKUS in this setting is not appropriate. Serious acute respiratory events, including fatalities, have been reported when salmeterol has been initiated in patients with significantly worsening or acutely deteriorating asthma. In most cases, these have occurred in patients with severe asthma (e.g., patients with a history of corticosteroid dependence, low pulmonary function, intubation, mechanical ventilation, frequent hospitalizations, previous life-threatening acute asthma exacerbations) and in some patients with acutely deteriorating asthma (e.g., patients with significantly increasing symptoms; increasing need for inhaled, short-acting beta 2 -agonists; decreasing response to usual medications; increasing need for systemic corticosteroids; recent emergency room visits; deteriorating lung function). However, these events have occurred in a few patients with less severe asthma as well. It was not possible from these reports to determine whether salmeterol contributed to these events. Increasing use of inhaled, short-acting beta 2 -agonists is a marker of deteriorating asthma. In this situation, the patient requires immediate reevaluation with reassessment of the treatment regimen, giving special consideration to the possible need for adding additional ICS or initiating systemic corticosteroids. Patients should not use more than 1 inhalation twice daily of SEREVENT DISKUS. SEREVENT DISKUS should not be used for the relief of acute symptoms, i.e., as rescue therapy for the treatment of acute episodes of bronchospasm. An inhaled, short-acting beta 2 -agonist, not SEREVENT DISKUS, should be used to relieve acute symptoms such as shortness of breath. When prescribing SEREVENT DISKUS, the healthcare provider should also prescribe an inhaled, short-acting beta 2 -agonist (e.g., albuterol) for treatment of acute symptoms. When beginning treatment with SEREVENT DISKUS, patients who have been taking oral or inhaled, short-acting beta 2 -agonists on a regular basis (e.g., 4 times a day) should be instructed to discontinue the regular use of these drugs. There are no data demonstrating that SEREVENT DISKUS has a clinical anti-inflammatory effect such as that associated with corticosteroids. When initiating and throughout treatment with SEREVENT DISKUS in patients receiving oral or ICS for treatment of asthma, patients must continue taking a suitable dosage of corticosteroids to maintain clinical stability even if they feel better as a result of initiating SEREVENT DISKUS. Any change in corticosteroid dosage should be made ONLY after clinical evaluation. SEREVENT DISKUS should not be used more often than recommended, at higher doses than recommended, or in conjunction with other medicines containing LABA, as an overdose may result. Clinically significant cardiovascular effects and fatalities have been reported in association with excessive use of inhaled sympathomimetic drugs. Patients using SEREVENT DISKUS should not use another medicine containing a LABA (e.g., formoterol fumarate, arformoterol tartrate, indacaterol) for any reason. As with other inhaled medicines, SEREVENT DISKUS can produce paradoxical bronchospasm, which may be life threatening. If paradoxical bronchospasm occurs following dosing with SEREVENT DISKUS, it should be treated immediately with an inhaled, short-acting bronchodilator; SEREVENT DISKUS should be discontinued immediately; and alternative therapy should be instituted. Upper airway symptoms of laryngeal spasm, irritation, or swelling, such as stridor and choking, have been reported in patients receiving SEREVENT DISKUS. Excessive beta-adrenergic stimulation has been associated with seizures, angina, hypertension or hypotension, tachycardia with rates up to 200 beats/min, arrhythmias, nervousness, headache, tremor, palpitation, nausea, dizziness, fatigue, malaise, and insomnia [see Overdosage ( 10 )] . Therefore, SEREVENT DISKUS, like all products containing sympathomimetic amines, should be used with caution in patients with cardiovascular disorders, especially coronary insufficiency, cardiac arrhythmias, and hypertension. Salmeterol can produce a clinically significant cardiovascular effect in some patients as measured by pulse rate, blood pressure, and/or symptoms. Although such effects are uncommon after administration of salmeterol at recommended doses, if they occur, the drug may need to be discontinued. In addition, beta-agonists have been reported to produce electrocardiogram (ECG) changes, such as flattening of the T wave, prolongation of the QTc interval, and ST segment depression. The clinical significance of these findings is unknown. Large doses of inhaled or oral salmeterol (12 to 20 times the recommended dose) have been associated with clinically significant prolongation of the QTc interval, which has the potential for producing ventricular arrhythmias. Fatalities have been reported in association with excessive use of inhaled sympathomimetic drugs. Immediate hypersensitivity reactions (e.g., urticaria, angioedema, rash, bronchospasm, hypotension), including anaphylaxis, may occur after administration of SEREVENT DISKUS. There have been reports of anaphylactic reactions in patients with severe milk protein allergy after inhalation of powder products containing lactose; therefore, patients with severe milk protein allergy should not use SEREVENT DISKUS [see Contraindications ( 4 )] . The use of strong cytochrome P450 3A4 (CYP3A4) inhibitors (e.g., ritonavir, atazanavir, clarithromycin, indinavir, itraconazole, nefazodone, nelfinavir, saquinavir, ketoconazole, telithromycin) with SEREVENT DISKUS is not recommended because increased cardiovascular adverse effects may occur [see Drug Interactions ( 7.1 ), Clinical Pharmacology ( 12.3 )] . SEREVENT DISKUS, like all medicines containing sympathomimetic amines, should be used with caution in patients with convulsive disorders or thyrotoxicosis and in those who are unusually responsive to sympathomimetic amines. Doses of the related beta 2 -adrenoceptor agonist albuterol, when administered intravenously, have been reported to aggravate preexisting diabetes mellitus and ketoacidosis. Beta-adrenergic agonist medicines may produce significant hypokalemia in some patients, possibly through intracellular shunting, which has the potential to produce adverse cardiovascular effects [see Clinical Pharmacology ( 12.2 )] . The decrease in serum potassium is usually transient, not requiring supplementation. Clinically significant and dose-related changes in blood glucose and/or serum potassium were seen infrequently during clinical trials with SEREVENT DISKUS at recommended doses.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Salmeterol is a selective LABA. In vitro studies show salmeterol to be at least 50 times more selective for beta 2 -adrenoceptors than albuterol. Although beta 2 -adrenoceptors are the predominant adrenergic receptors in bronchial smooth muscle and beta 1 -adrenoceptors are the predominant receptors in the heart, there are also beta 2 -adrenoceptors in the human heart comprising 10% to 50% of the total beta-adrenoceptors. The precise function of these receptors has not been established, but their presence raises the possibility that even selective beta 2 -agonists may have cardiac effects. The pharmacologic effects of beta 2 -adrenoceptor agonist drugs, including salmeterol, are at least in part attributable to stimulation of intracellular adenyl cyclase, the enzyme that catalyzes the conversion of adenosine triphosphate (ATP) to cyclic-3′,5′-adenosine monophosphate (cyclic AMP). Increased cyclic AMP levels cause relaxation of bronchial smooth muscle and inhibition of release of mediators of immediate hypersensitivity from cells, especially from mast cells. In vitro tests show that salmeterol is a potent and long-lasting inhibitor of the release of mast cell mediators, such as histamine, leukotrienes, and prostaglandin D 2 , from human lung. Salmeterol inhibits histamine-induced plasma protein extravasation and inhibits platelet-activating factor–induced eosinophil accumulation in the lungs of guinea pigs when administered by the inhaled route. In humans, single doses of salmeterol administered via inhalation aerosol attenuate allergen-induced bronchial hyper-responsiveness. Inhaled salmeterol, like other beta-adrenergic agonist drugs, can produce dose-related cardiovascular effects and effects on blood glucose and/or serum potassium [see Warnings and Precautions (5.6, 5.10)] . The cardiovascular effects (heart rate, blood pressure) associated with salmeterol inhalation aerosol occur with similar frequency, and are of similar type and severity, as those noted following albuterol administration. The effects of rising inhaled doses of salmeterol and standard inhaled doses of albuterol were studied in volunteers and in subjects with asthma. Salmeterol doses up to 84 mcg administered as inhalation aerosol resulted in heart rate increases of 3 to 16 beats/min, about the same as albuterol dosed at 180 mcg by inhalation aerosol (4 to 10 beats/min). Adult and adolescent subjects receiving 50-mcg doses of salmeterol inhalation powder (n = 60) underwent continuous electrocardiographic monitoring during two 12-hour periods after the first dose and after 1 month of therapy, and no clinically significant dysrhythmias were noted. Also, pediatric patients receiving 50-mcg doses of salmeterol inhalation powder (n = 67) underwent continuous electrocardiographic monitoring during two 12-hour periods after the first dose and after 3 months of therapy, and no clinically significant dysrhythmias were noted. In 24-week clinical studies in patients with COPD, the incidence of clinically significant abnormalities on the predose ECGs at Weeks 12 and 24 in patients who received salmeterol 50 mcg was not different compared with placebo. No effect of treatment with salmeterol 50 mcg was observed on pulse rate and systolic and diastolic blood pressure in a subset of patients with COPD who underwent 12-hour serial vital sign measurements after the first dose (n = 91) and after 12 weeks of therapy (n = 74). Median changes from baseline in pulse rate and systolic and diastolic blood pressure were similar for patients receiving either salmeterol or placebo [see Adverse Reactions ( 6.1 )] . Concomitant Use of SEREVENT DISKUS with Other Respiratory Medications Short-acting Beta 2 -agonists: In two 12-week repetitive-dose clinical trials in adult and adolescent subjects with asthma (N = 149), the mean daily need for additional beta 2 -agonist in subjects using SEREVENT DISKUS was approximately 1½ inhalations/day. Twenty-six percent (26%) of the subjects in these trials used between 8 and 24 inhalations of short-acting beta-agonist per day on 1 or more occasions. Nine percent (9%) of the subjects in these trials averaged over 4 inhalations/day over the course of the 12-week trials. No increase in frequency of cardiovascular events was observed among the 3 subjects who averaged 8 to 11 inhalations/day; however, the safety of concomitant use of more than 8 inhalations/day of short-acting beta 2 -agonist with SEREVENT DISKUS has not been established. In 29 subjects who experienced worsening of asthma while receiving SEREVENT DISKUS during these trials, albuterol therapy administered via either nebulizer or inhalation aerosol (1 dose in most cases) led to improvement in FEV 1 and no increase in occurrence of cardiovascular adverse events. In 2 clinical trials in subjects with COPD, the mean daily need for additional beta 2 -agonist for subjects using SEREVENT DISKUS was approximately 4 inhalations/day. Twenty-four percent (24%) of subjects using SEREVENT DISKUS averaged 6 or more inhalations of albuterol per day over the course of the 24-week trials. No increase in frequency of cardiovascular adverse reactions was observed among subjects who averaged 6 or more inhalations per day. Methylxanthines: The concurrent use of intravenously or orally administered methylxanthines (e.g., aminophylline, theophylline) by subjects receiving salmeterol has not been completely evaluated. In 1 clinical trial in subjects with asthma, 87 subjects receiving SEREVENT Inhalation Aerosol 42 mcg twice daily concurrently with a theophylline product had adverse event rates similar to those in 71 subjects receiving SEREVENT Inhalation Aerosol without theophylline. Resting heart rates were slightly higher in the subjects on theophylline but were little affected by therapy with SEREVENT Inhalation Aerosol. In 2 clinical trials in subjects with COPD, 39 subjects receiving SEREVENT DISKUS concurrently with a theophylline product had adverse event rates similar to those in 302 subjects receiving SEREVENT DISKUS without theophylline. Based on the available data, the concomitant administration of methylxanthines with SEREVENT DISKUS did not alter the observed adverse event profile. Cromoglycate: In clinical trials, inhaled cromolyn sodium did not alter the safety profile of salmeterol when administered concurrently. Salmeterol xinafoate, an ionic salt, dissociates in solution so that the salmeterol and 1-hydroxy-2-naphthoic acid (xinafoate) moieties are absorbed, distributed, metabolized, and eliminated independently. Salmeterol acts locally in the lung; therefore, plasma levels do not predict therapeutic effect. Absorption Because of the small therapeutic dose, systemic levels of salmeterol are low or undetectable after inhalation of recommended doses (50 mcg of salmeterol inhalation powder twice daily). Following chronic administration of an inhaled dose of 50 mcg of salmeterol inhalation powder twice daily, salmeterol was detected in plasma within 5 to 45 minutes in 7 subjects with asthma; plasma concentrations were very low, with mean peak concentrations of 167 pg/mL at 20 minutes and no accumulation with repeated doses. Distribution The percentage of salmeterol bound to human plasma proteins averages 96% in vitro over the concentration range of 8 to 7,722 ng of salmeterol base per milliliter, much higher concentrations than those achieved following therapeutic doses of salmeterol. Metabolism Salmeterol base is extensively metabolized by hydroxylation, with subsequent elimination predominantly in the feces. No significant amount of unchanged salmeterol base was detected in either urine or feces. An in vitro study using human liver microsomes showed that salmeterol is extensively metabolized to α-hydroxysalmeterol (aliphatic oxidation) by CYP3A4. Ketoconazole, a strong inhibitor of CYP3A4, essentially completely inhibited the formation of α-hydroxysalmeterol in vitro. Elimination In 2 healthy adult subjects who received 1 mg of radiolabeled salmeterol (as salmeterol xinafoate) orally, approximately 25% and 60% of the radiolabeled salmeterol was eliminated in urine and feces, respectively, over a period of 7 days. The terminal elimination half-life was about 5.5 hours (1 volunteer only). The xinafoate moiety has no apparent pharmacologic activity. The xinafoate moiety is highly protein bound (&amp;gt;99%) and has a long elimination half-life of 11 days. Drug Interaction Studies Inhibitors of Cytochrome P450 3A4: Ketoconazole: In a placebo-controlled crossover drug interaction trial in 20 healthy male and female subjects, coadministration of salmeterol (50 mcg twice daily) and the strong CYP3A4 inhibitor ketoconazole (400 mg once daily) for 7 days resulted in a significant increase in plasma salmeterol exposure as determined by a 16-fold increase in AUC (ratio with and without ketoconazole 15.76 [90% CI: 10.66, 23.31]) mainly due to increased bioavailability of the swallowed portion of the dose. Peak plasma salmeterol concentrations were increased by 1.4-fold (90% CI: 1.23, 1.68). Three (3) out of 20 subjects (15%) were withdrawn from salmeterol and ketoconazole coadministration due to beta-agonist–mediated systemic effects (2 with QTc prolongation and 1 with palpitations and sinus tachycardia). Coadministration of salmeterol and ketoconazole did not result in a clinically significant effect on mean heart rate, mean blood potassium, or mean blood glucose. Although there was no statistical effect on the mean QTc, coadministration of salmeterol and ketoconazole was associated with more frequent increases in QTc duration compared with salmeterol and placebo administration. Erythromycin: In a repeat-dose trial in 13 healthy subjects, concomitant administration of erythromycin (a moderate CYP3A4 inhibitor) and salmeterol inhalation aerosol resulted in a 40% increase in salmeterol C max at steady state (ratio with and without erythromycin 1.4 [90% CI: 0.96, 2.03], P = 0.12), a 3.6-beat/min increase in heart rate ([95% CI: 0.19, 7.03], P &amp;lt;0.04), a 5.8-msec increase in QTc interval ([95% CI: -6.14, 17.77], P = 0.34), and no change in plasma potassium.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="244" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>WARNING: ASTHMA-RELATED DEATH Long-acting beta2-adrenergic agonists (LABA), such as salmeterol, the active ingredient in SEREVENT DISKUS, as monotherapy (without inhaled corticosteroids [ICS]) increase the risk of asthma-related death.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="245" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Data from a large placebo-controlled U.S. trial that compared the safety of salmeterol with placebo added to usual asthma therapy showed an increase in asthma-related deaths in subjects receiving salmeterol (13 deaths out of 13,176 subjects treated for 28 weeks on salmeterol versus 3 deaths out of 13,179 subjects on placebo).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M1" type="Trigger" span="140 8" str="increase"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="109 20" str="usual asthma therapy" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M3" type="SpecificInteraction" span="152 21" str="asthma-related deaths" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M1" precipitant="M2" effect="M3" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="246" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Use of background ICS was not required in this study.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="247" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>When LABA are used in fixed-dose combination with ICS, data from large clinical trials do not show a significant increase in the risk of serious asthma-related events (hospitalizations, intubations, death) compared with ICS alone.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="248" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Use of SEREVENT DISKUS for the treatment of asthma as monotherapy without a concomitant ICS is contraindicated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="249" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Use SEREVENT DISKUS only as additional therapy for patients with asthma who are currently taking but are inadequately controlled on an ICS.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="250" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Do not use SEREVENT DISKUS for patients whose asthma is adequately controlled on low- or medium-dose ICS.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M4" type="Trigger" span="0 10" str="Do not use"/>
<Mention id="M5" type="Precipitant" span="81 23" str="low- or medium-dose ICS" code="N0000175576"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M4" precipitant="M5"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="251" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Pediatric and Adolescent Patients Available data from controlled clinical trials suggest that LABA as monotherapy increase the risk of asthma-related hospitalization in pediatric and adolescent patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="252" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>For pediatric and adolescent patients with asthma who require addition of a LABA to an ICS, a fixed-dose combination product containing both an ICS and a LABA should ordinarily be used to ensure adherence with both drugs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="253" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>In cases where use of an ICS and a LABA is clinically indicated, appropriate steps must be taken to ensure adherence with both treatment components.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="254" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>If adherence cannot be assured, a fixed-dose combination product containing both an ICS and a LABA is recommended.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="255" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>WARNING: ASTHMA-RELATED DEATH See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning Long-acting beta2-adrenergic agonists (LABA), such as salmeterol, the active in gre dient in SEREVENT DISKUS, as monotherapy (without inhaled corticosteroids [ICS]) increase the risk of asthma-related death.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="256" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>A U.S. trial showed an increase in asthma-related deaths in subjects receiving salmeterol (13 deaths out of 13,176 subjects treated for 28 weeks on salmeterol versus 3 out of 13,179 subjects on placebo).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="257" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Prescribe SEREVENT DISKUS only as additional therapy for patients with asthma who are currently taking but are inadequately controlled on an ICS.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="258" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Available data from controlled clinical trials suggest that LABA as monotherapy increase the risk of asthma-related hospitalization in pediatric and adolescent patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="259" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Use of SEREVENT DISKUS for the treatment of asthma without concomitant use of an ICS is contraindicated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="260" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>The use of SEREVENT DISKUS is contraindicated in the following conditions: Primary treatment of status asthmaticus or other acute episodes of asthma or COPD where intensive measures are required Severe hypersensitivity to milk proteins or demonstrated hypersensitivity to salmeterol or any of the excipients Asthma: Without concomitant use of an ICS.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="261" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Primary treatment of status asthmaticus or acute episodes of asthma or COPD requiring intensive measures.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="262" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Severe hypersensitivity to milk proteins or demonstrated hypersensitivity to salmeterol or any of the excipients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="263" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>SEREVENT DISKUS should be administered by the orally inhaled route only.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="264" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>More frequent administration or a greater number of inhalations (more than 1 inhalation twice daily) is not recommended as some patients are more likely to experience adverse effects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="265" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Patients using SEREVENT DISKUS should not use additional LABA for any reason.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M6" type="Trigger" span="31 14" str="should not use"/>
<Mention id="M7" type="Precipitant" span="57 4" str="LABA" code="N0000000245"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M6" precipitant="M7"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="266" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Treatment of asthma in patients aged 4 years and older: 1 inhalation twice daily in addition to concomitant treatment with an ICS.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="267" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>EIB: 1 inhalation at least 30 minutes before exercise.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="268" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Maintenance treatment of bronchospasm associated with COPD: 1 inhalation twice daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="269" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>LABA, such as salmeterol, the active ingredient in SEREVENT DISKUS, as monotherapy (without ICS) increase the risk of asthma-related death.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="270" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Because of this risk, use of SEREVENT DISKUS for the treatment of asthma without concomitant use of an ICS is contraindicated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="271" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For patients with asthma younger than 18 years who require addition of a LABA to an ICS, a fixed-dose combination product containing both an ICS and a LABA should ordinarily be used to ensure adherence with both drugs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="272" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In cases where use of a separate ICS and a LABA is clinically indicated, appropriate steps must be taken to ensure adherence with both treatment components.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="273" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For bronchodilatation and prevention of symptoms of asthma, including the symptoms of nocturnal asthma, the usual dosage for adults and children aged 4 years and older is 1 inhalation (50 mcg) twice daily, approximately 12 hours apart.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="274" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If a previously effective dosage regimen fails to provide the usual response, medical advice should be sought immediately as this is often a sign of destabilization of asthma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="275" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Under these circumstances, the therapeutic regimen should be reevaluated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="276" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If symptoms arise in the period between doses, an inhaled, short-acting beta2-agonist should be taken for immediate relief.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="277" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Use of SEREVENT DISKUS as a single agent for the prevention of EIB may be clinically indicated in patients who do not have persistent asthma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="278" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In patients with persistent asthma, use of SEREVENT DISKUS for the prevention of EIB may be clinically indicated, but the treatment of asthma should include an ICS.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="279" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>One inhalation of SEREVENT DISKUS at least 30 minutes before exercise has been shown to protect patients against EIB.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="280" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>When used intermittently as needed for prevention of EIB, this protection may last up to 9 hours in adults and adolescents and up to 12 hours in patients aged 4 to 11 years.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="281" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Additional doses of SEREVENT should not be used for 12 hours after the administration of this drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="282" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Patients who are receiving SEREVENT DISKUS twice daily should not use additional SEREVENT for prevention of EIB.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="283" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For maintenance treatment of bronchospasm associated with COPD (including chronic bronchitis and emphysema), the dosage for adults is 1 inhalation (50 mcg) twice daily approximately 12 hours apart.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="284" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Strong cytochrome P450 3A4 inhibitors (e.g., ritonavir, ketoconazole): Use not recommended.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M12" type="Trigger" span="75 15" str="not recommended"/>
<Mention id="M9" type="Precipitant" span="56 12" str="ketoconazole" code="N0000007319 | R9400W927I"/>
<Mention id="M11" type="Precipitant" span="45 9" str="ritonavir" code="O3J8G9O825 | N0000007423"/>
<Mention id="M13" type="Precipitant" span="0 37" str="Strong cytochrome P450 3A4 inhibitors" code="N0000182141"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M12" precipitant="M9"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M12" precipitant="M11"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M12" precipitant="M13"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="285" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>May increase risk of cardiovascular effects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="286" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Monoamine oxidase inhibitors and tricyclic antidepressants: Use with extreme caution.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M16" type="Trigger" span="77 7" str="caution"/>
<Mention id="M15" type="Precipitant" span="0 28" str="Monoamine oxidase inhibitors" code="N0000000184 | N0000175744"/>
<Mention id="M17" type="Precipitant" span="33 25" str="tricyclic antidepressants" code="N0000029148 | N0000175752"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M16" precipitant="M15"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M16" precipitant="M17"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="287" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>May potentiate effect of salmeterol on vascular system.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="288" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Beta-blockers: Use with caution.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M18" type="Trigger" span="24 7" str="caution"/>
<Mention id="M19" type="Precipitant" span="0 13" str="Beta-blockers" code="N0000000161 | N0000175556"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M18" precipitant="M19"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="289" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>May block bronchodilatory effects of beta-agonists and produce severe bronchospasm.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M20" type="Trigger" span="4 5;26 7" str="block | effects"/>
<Mention id="M24" type="Precipitant" span="37 13" str="beta-agonists" code="N0000175555 | N0000000245"/>
<Mention id="M22" type="SpecificInteraction" span="4 29" str="block bronchodilatory effects" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M23" type="Trigger" span="55 7" str="produce"/>
<Mention id="M25" type="SpecificInteraction" span="63 19" str="severe bronchospasm" code="4386001: Bronchospasm (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M20" precipitant="M24" effect="M22" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M23" precipitant="M24" effect="M25" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="290" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Electrocardiographic changes and/or hypokalemia associated with non–potassium-sparing diuretics may worsen with concomitant beta-agonists.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M26" type="Trigger" span="100 6" str="worsen "/>
<Mention id="M27" type="Trigger" span="48 15" str=" associated with"/>
<Mention id="M28" type="Precipitant" span="64 31" str="non–potassium-sparing diuretics" code="N0000175359"/>
<Mention id="M29" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 28;36 11" str="Electrocardiographic changes | hypokalemia" code="102594003: Electrocardiogram abnormal (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M26;M27" precipitant="M28" effect="M29" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="291" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Salmeterol is a substrate of CYP3A4.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="292" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The use of strong CYP3A4 inhibitors (e.g., ritonavir, atazanavir, clarithromycin, indinavir, itraconazole, nefazodone, nelfinavir, saquinavir, ketoconazole, telithromycin) with SEREVENT DISKUS is not recommended because increased cardiovascular adverse effects may occur.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M60" type="Trigger" span="220 9;245 15" str="increased | adverse effects"/>
<Mention id="M31" type="Precipitant" span="54 10" str="atazanavir" code="N0000022320 | QZU4H47A3S"/>
<Mention id="M62" type="SpecificInteraction" span="230 30" str="cardiovascular adverse effects" code="267037003: Cardiovascular symptoms (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M34" type="Precipitant" span="66 14" str="clarithromycin" code="H1250JIK0A | N0000007316"/>
<Mention id="M37" type="Precipitant" span="82 9" str="indinavir" code="N0000005722 | 5W6YA9PKKH"/>
<Mention id="M40" type="Precipitant" span="93 12" str="itraconazole" code="304NUG5GF4 | N0000006753"/>
<Mention id="M43" type="Precipitant" span="143 12" str="ketoconazole" code="N0000007319 | R9400W927I"/>
<Mention id="M46" type="Precipitant" span="107 10" str="nefazodone" code="N0000007250 | 59H4FCV1TF"/>
<Mention id="M49" type="Precipitant" span="119 10" str="nelfinavir" code="HO3OGH5D7I | N0000006047"/>
<Mention id="M52" type="Precipitant" span="43 9" str="ritonavir" code="O3J8G9O825 | N0000007423"/>
<Mention id="M55" type="Precipitant" span="131 10" str="saquinavir" code="N0000007376 | L3JE09KZ2F"/>
<Mention id="M58" type="Precipitant" span="11 24" str="strong CYP3A4 inhibitors" code="N0000182141"/>
<Mention id="M61" type="Precipitant" span="157 13" str="telithromycin" code="N0000010551 | KI8H7H19WL"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M60" precipitant="M31" effect="M62" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M60" precipitant="M34" effect="M62" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M60" precipitant="M37" effect="M62" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M60" precipitant="M40" effect="M62" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M60" precipitant="M43" effect="M62" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M60" precipitant="M46" effect="M62" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M60" precipitant="M49" effect="M62" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M60" precipitant="M52" effect="M62" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M60" precipitant="M55" effect="M62" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M60" precipitant="M58" effect="M62" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M60" precipitant="M61" effect="M62" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="293" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>In a drug interaction trial in 20 healthy subjects, coadministration of inhaled salmeterol (50 mcg twice daily) and oral ketoconazole (400 mg once daily) for 7 days resulted in greater systemic exposure to salmeterol (AUC increased 16-fold and Cmax increased 1.4-fold).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M63" type="Trigger" span="218 13" str="AUC increased"/>
<Mention id="M68" type="Precipitant" span="116 17" str="oral ketoconazole" code="R9400W927I"/>
<Mention id="M65" type="Trigger" span="244 14" str="Cmax increased"/>
<Mention id="M67" type="Trigger" span="177 25" str="greater systemic exposure"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M63" precipitant="M68" effect="C54605"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M65" precipitant="M68" effect="C54602"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M67" precipitant="M68" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="294" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Three (3) subjects were withdrawn due to beta2-agonist side effects (2 with prolonged QTc and 1 with palpitations and sinus tachycardia).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="295" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Although there was no statistical effect on the mean QTc, coadministration of salmeterol and ketoconazole was associated with more frequent increases in QTc duration compared with salmeterol and placebo administration.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M69" type="Trigger" span="110 15" str="associated with "/>
<Mention id="M70" type="Trigger" span="126 13" str=" more frequent"/>
<Mention id="M71" type="Precipitant" span="93 12" str="ketoconazole" code="N0000007319 | R9400W927I"/>
<Mention id="M72" type="SpecificInteraction" span="140 25" str="increases in QTc duration" code="111975006:  Prolonged QT interval (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M69;M70" precipitant="M71" effect="M72" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="296" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>SEREVENT DISKUS should be administered with extreme caution to patients being treated with monoamine oxidase inhibitors or tricyclic antidepressants, or within 2 weeks of discontinuation of such agents, because the action of salmeterol on the vascular system may be potentiated by these agents.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M76" type="Trigger" span="266 11" str="potentiated"/>
<Mention id="M74" type="Precipitant" span="91 28" str="monoamine oxidase inhibitors" code="N0000000184 | N0000175744"/>
<Mention id="M78" type="SpecificInteraction" span="215 6;236 22" str="action | on the vascular system" code="293416008: Drug groups primarily affecting cardiovascular system adverse reaction (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M77" type="Precipitant" span="123 25" str="tricyclic antidepressants" code="N0000029148 | N0000175752"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M76" precipitant="M74" effect="M78" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I29" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M76" precipitant="M77" effect="M78" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="297" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Beta-blockers not only block the pulmonary effect of beta-agonists, such as salmeterol, but may also produce severe bronchospasm in patients with asthma or COPD.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M79" type="Trigger" span="5 5;43 6" str="block | effect"/>
<Mention id="M83" type="Precipitant" span="0 13" str="Beta-blockers" code="N0000000161 | N0000175556"/>
<Mention id="M81" type="SpecificInteraction" span="23 26" str="block the pulmonary effect" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M82" type="Trigger" span="101 7" str="produce"/>
<Mention id="M84" type="SpecificInteraction" span="109 19" str="severe bronchospasm" code="4386001: Bronchospasm (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I30" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M79" precipitant="M83" effect="M81" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I31" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M82" precipitant="M83" effect="M84" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="298" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Therefore, patients with asthma or COPD should not normally be treated with beta-blockers.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M85" type="Trigger" span="40 10;60 10" str="should not | be treated"/>
<Mention id="M86" type="Precipitant" span="76 13" str="beta-blockers" code="N0000000161 | N0000175556"/>
<Interaction id="I32" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M85" precipitant="M86"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="299" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>However, under certain circumstances, there may be no acceptable alternatives to the use of beta-adrenergic blocking agents for these patients; cardioselective beta-blockers could be considered, although they should be administered with caution.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M87" type="Trigger" span="65 12" str="alternatives"/>
<Mention id="M88" type="Precipitant" span="92 31" str="beta-adrenergic blocking agents" code="N0000000161 | N0000175556"/>
<Mention id="M89" type="Trigger" span="237 7" str="caution"/>
<Mention id="M90" type="Precipitant" span="144 29" str="cardioselective beta-blockers" code="N0000000161"/>
<Interaction id="I33" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M87" precipitant="M88"/>
<Interaction id="I34" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M89" precipitant="M90"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="300" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The ECG changes and/or hypokalemia that may result from the administration of non–potassium-sparing diuretics (such as loop or thiazide diuretics) can be acutely worsened by beta-agonists, especially when the recommended dose of the beta-agonist is exceeded.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M106" type="Trigger" span="162 8" str="worsened"/>
<Mention id="M95" type="Precipitant" span="119 4;100 9" str="loop | diuretics" code="N0000175590"/>
<Mention id="M105" type="SpecificInteraction" span="4 11" str="ECG changes" code="102594003: Electrocardiogram abnormal (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M108" type="SpecificInteraction" span="23 11" str="hypokalemia" code="43339004: Hypokalemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M101" type="Precipitant" span="78 31" str="non–potassium-sparing diuretics" code="N0000175359"/>
<Mention id="M107" type="Precipitant" span="127 18" str="thiazide diuretics" code="N0000175419"/>
<Interaction id="I35" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M106" precipitant="M95" effect="M105" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I36" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M106" precipitant="M95" effect="M108" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I37" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M106" precipitant="M101" effect="M105" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I38" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M106" precipitant="M101" effect="M108" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I39" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M106" precipitant="M107" effect="M105" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I40" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M106" precipitant="M107" effect="M108" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="301" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Although the clinical significance of these effects is not known, caution is advised in the coadministration of SEREVENT DISKUS with non–potassium-sparing diuretics.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M109" type="Trigger" span="66 7" str="caution"/>
<Mention id="M110" type="Precipitant" span="133 31" str="non–potassium-sparing diuretics" code="N0000175359"/>
<Interaction id="I41" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M109" precipitant="M110"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="302" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>LABA as monotherapy (without ICS) for asthma increase the risk of asthma-related death and asthma-related hospitalizations.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="303" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Prescribe for asthma only as concomitant therapy with an inhaled corticosteroid.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="304" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Do not initiate in acutely deteriorating asthma or COPD.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="305" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Not a substitute for corticosteroids.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="306" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients with asthma must take a concomitant ICS.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="307" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Do not use in combination with an additional medicine containing a LABA because of risk of overdose.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M114" type="Trigger" span="83 7" str="risk of"/>
<Mention id="M112" type="Precipitant" span="67 4" str="LABA" code="N0000000245"/>
<Mention id="M116" type="SpecificInteraction" span="91 8" str="overdose" code="55680006: Drug overdose (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M115" type="Precipitant" span="45 26" str="medicine containing a LABA" code="N0000000245"/>
<Interaction id="I42" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M114" precipitant="M112" effect="M116" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I43" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M114" precipitant="M115" effect="M116" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="308" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If paradoxical bronchospasm occurs, discontinue SEREVENT DISKUS and institute alternative therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="309" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Use with caution in patients with cardiovascular or central nervous system disorders because of beta-adrenergic stimulation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="310" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Use with caution in patients with convulsive disorders, thyrotoxicosis, diabetes mellitus, and ketoacidosis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="311" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Be alert to hypokalemia and hyperglycemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="312" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>When LABA are used in fixed‑dose combination with ICS, data from large clinical trials do not show a significant increase in the risk of serious asthma-related events (hospitalizations, intubations, death) compared with ICS alone.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="313" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The Salmeterol Multicenter Asthma Research Trial (SMART) was a large 28-week placebo-controlled U.S. trial comparing the safety of salmeterol (SEREVENT Inhalation Aerosol) with placebo, each added to usual asthma therapy, that showed an increase in asthma-related deaths in subjects receiving salmeterol.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M117" type="Trigger" span="237 8" str="increase"/>
<Mention id="M118" type="Precipitant" span="200 20" str="usual asthma therapy" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M119" type="SpecificInteraction" span="249 21" str="asthma-related deaths" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I44" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M117" precipitant="M118" effect="M119" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="314" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Given the similar basic mechanisms of action of beta2-agonists, the findings seen in the SMART trial are considered a class effect.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="315" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>A 16-week clinical trial performed in the United Kingdom, the Salmeterol Nationwide Surveillance (SNS) trial, showed results similar to the SMART trial.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="316" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In the SNS trial, the rate of asthma-related death was numerically, though not statistically significantly, greater in subjects with asthma treated with salmeterol (42 mcg twice daily) than those treated with albuterol (180 mcg 4 times daily) added to usual asthma therapy.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M120" type="Trigger" span="22 4;108 7" str="rate | greater"/>
<Mention id="M121" type="Precipitant" span="252 20" str="usual asthma therapy" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M122" type="SpecificInteraction" span="30 20" str="asthma-related death" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I45" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M120" precipitant="M121" effect="M122" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="317" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The SNS and SMART trials enrolled subjects with asthma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="318" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Available data do not suggest an increased risk of death with use of LABA in patients with COPD.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="319" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>SEREVENT DISKUS should not be initiated in patients during rapidly deteriorating or potentially life-threatening episodes of asthma or COPD.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="320" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>SEREVENT DISKUS has not been studied in subjects with acutely deteriorating asthma or COPD.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="321" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The initiation of SEREVENT DISKUS in this setting is not appropriate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="322" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Serious acute respiratory events, including fatalities, have been reported when salmeterol has been initiated in patients with significantly worsening or acutely deteriorating asthma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="323" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In most cases, these have occurred in patients with severe asthma (e.g., patients with a history of corticosteroid dependence, low pulmonary function, intubation, mechanical ventilation, frequent hospitalizations, previous life-threatening acute asthma exacerbations) and in some patients with acutely deteriorating asthma (e.g., patients with significantly increasing symptoms; increasing need for inhaled, short-acting beta2-agonists; decreasing response to usual medications; increasing need for systemic corticosteroids; recent emergency room visits; deteriorating lung function).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="324" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>However, these events have occurred in a few patients with less severe asthma as well.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="325" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>It was not possible from these reports to determine whether salmeterol contributed to these events.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="326" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Increasing use of inhaled, short-acting beta2-agonists is a marker of deteriorating asthma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="327" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In this situation, the patient requires immediate reevaluation with reassessment of the treatment regimen, giving special consideration to the possible need for adding additional ICS or initiating systemic corticosteroids.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M123" type="Trigger" span="152 8" str="need for"/>
<Mention id="M124" type="Precipitant" span="197 24" str="systemic corticosteroids" code="N0000175576"/>
<Interaction id="I46" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M123" precipitant="M124"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="328" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients should not use more than 1 inhalation twice daily of SEREVENT DISKUS.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="329" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>SEREVENT DISKUS should not be used for the relief of acute symptoms, i.e., as rescue therapy for the treatment of acute episodes of bronchospasm.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="330" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>An inhaled, short-acting beta2-agonist, not SEREVENT DISKUS, should be used to relieve acute symptoms such as shortness of breath.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="331" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>When prescribing SEREVENT DISKUS, the healthcare provider should also prescribe an inhaled, short-acting beta2-agonist (e.g., albuterol) for treatment of acute symptoms.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="332" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>When beginning treatment with SEREVENT DISKUS, patients who have been taking oral or inhaled, short-acting beta2-agonists on a regular basis (e.g., 4 times a day) should be instructed to discontinue the regular use of these drugs.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M125" type="Trigger" span="187 11" str="discontinue"/>
<Mention id="M126" type="Precipitant" span="94 27" str="short-acting beta2-agonists" code="N0000009922"/>
<Interaction id="I47" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M125" precipitant="M126"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="333" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There are no data demonstrating that SEREVENT DISKUS has a clinical anti-inflammatory effect such as that associated with corticosteroids.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="334" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>When initiating and throughout treatment with SEREVENT DISKUS in patients receiving oral or ICS for treatment of asthma, patients must continue taking a suitable dosage of corticosteroids to maintain clinical stability even if they feel better as a result of initiating SEREVENT DISKUS.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="335" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Any change in corticosteroid dosage should be made ONLY after clinical evaluation.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M127" type="Trigger" span="4 6;29 6" str="change | dosage "/>
<Mention id="M128" type="Trigger" span="71 10" str=" evaluation"/>
<Mention id="M129" type="Precipitant" span="14 14" str="corticosteroid" code="N0000175576"/>
<Interaction id="I48" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M127;M128" precipitant="M129"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="336" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>SEREVENT DISKUS should not be used more often than recommended, at higher doses than recommended, or in conjunction with other medicines containing LABA, as an overdose may result.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M133" type="Trigger" span="173 6" str="result"/>
<Mention id="M131" type="Precipitant" span="148 4" str="LABA" code="N0000000245"/>
<Mention id="M135" type="SpecificInteraction" span="160 8" str="overdose" code="55680006: Drug overdose (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M134" type="Precipitant" span="127 25" str="medicines containing LABA" code="N0000000245"/>
<Interaction id="I49" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M133" precipitant="M131" effect="M135" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I50" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M133" precipitant="M134" effect="M135" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="337" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Clinically significant cardiovascular effects and fatalities have been reported in association with excessive use of inhaled sympathomimetic drugs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="338" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients using SEREVENT DISKUS should not use another medicine containing a LABA (e.g., formoterol fumarate, arformoterol tartrate, indacaterol) for any reason.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M144" type="Trigger" span="31 14" str="should not use"/>
<Mention id="M137" type="Precipitant" span="109 21" str="arformoterol tartrate" code="5P8VJ2I235"/>
<Mention id="M139" type="Precipitant" span="88 19" str="formoterol fumarate" code="W34SHF8J2K"/>
<Mention id="M141" type="Precipitant" span="132 11" str="indacaterol" code="8OR09251MQ"/>
<Mention id="M143" type="Precipitant" span="76 4" str="LABA" code="N0000000245"/>
<Mention id="M145" type="Precipitant" span="54 26" str="medicine containing a LABA" code="N0000000245"/>
<Interaction id="I51" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M144" precipitant="M137"/>
<Interaction id="I52" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M144" precipitant="M139"/>
<Interaction id="I53" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M144" precipitant="M141"/>
<Interaction id="I54" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M144" precipitant="M143"/>
<Interaction id="I55" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M144" precipitant="M145"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="339" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>As with other inhaled medicines, SEREVENT DISKUS can produce paradoxical bronchospasm, which may be life threatening.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="340" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If paradoxical bronchospasm occurs following dosing with SEREVENT DISKUS, it should be treated immediately with an inhaled, short-acting bronchodilator; SEREVENT DISKUS should be discontinued immediately; and alternative therapy should be instituted.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="341" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Upper airway symptoms of laryngeal spasm, irritation, or swelling, such as stridor and choking, have been reported in patients receiving SEREVENT DISKUS.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="342" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Excessive beta-adrenergic stimulation has been associated with seizures, angina, hypertension or hypotension, tachycardia with rates up to 200 beats/min, arrhythmias, nervousness, headache, tremor, palpitation, nausea, dizziness, fatigue, malaise, and insomnia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="343" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Therefore, SEREVENT DISKUS, like all products containing sympathomimetic amines, should be used with caution in patients with cardiovascular disorders, especially coronary insufficiency, cardiac arrhythmias, and hypertension.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="344" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Salmeterol can produce a clinically significant cardiovascular effect in some patients as measured by pulse rate, blood pressure, and/or symptoms.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="345" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Although such effects are uncommon after administration of salmeterol at recommended doses, if they occur, the drug may need to be discontinued.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="346" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In addition, beta-agonists have been reported to produce electrocardiogram (ECG) changes, such as flattening of the T wave, prolongation of the QTc interval, and ST segment depression.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="347" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The clinical significance of these findings is unknown.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="348" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Large doses of inhaled or oral salmeterol (12 to 20 times the recommended dose) have been associated with clinically significant prolongation of the QTc interval, which has the potential for producing ventricular arrhythmias.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="349" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Fatalities have been reported in association with excessive use of inhaled sympathomimetic drugs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="350" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Immediate hypersensitivity reactions (e.g., urticaria, angioedema, rash, bronchospasm, hypotension), including anaphylaxis, may occur after administration of SEREVENT DISKUS.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="351" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There have been reports of anaphylactic reactions in patients with severe milk protein allergy after inhalation of powder products containing lactose; therefore, patients with severe milk protein allergy should not use SEREVENT DISKUS.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="352" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The use of strong cytochrome P450 3A4 (CYP3A4) inhibitors (e.g., ritonavir, atazanavir, clarithromycin, indinavir, itraconazole, nefazodone, nelfinavir, saquinavir, ketoconazole, telithromycin) with SEREVENT DISKUS is not recommended because increased cardiovascular adverse effects may occur.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M194" type="Trigger" span="242 9" str="increased "/>
<Mention id="M195" type="Trigger" span="267 15" str=" adverse effects"/>
<Mention id="M148" type="Precipitant" span="76 10" str="atazanavir" code="N0000022320 | QZU4H47A3S"/>
<Mention id="M197" type="SpecificInteraction" span="252 30" str="cardiovascular adverse effects" code="267037003: Cardiovascular symptoms (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M152" type="Precipitant" span="88 14" str="clarithromycin" code="H1250JIK0A | N0000007316"/>
<Mention id="M156" type="Precipitant" span="104 9" str="indinavir" code="N0000005722 | 5W6YA9PKKH"/>
<Mention id="M160" type="Precipitant" span="115 12" str="itraconazole" code="304NUG5GF4 | N0000006753"/>
<Mention id="M164" type="Precipitant" span="165 12" str="ketoconazole" code="N0000007319 | R9400W927I"/>
<Mention id="M168" type="Precipitant" span="129 10" str="nefazodone" code="N0000007250 | 59H4FCV1TF"/>
<Mention id="M172" type="Precipitant" span="141 10" str="nelfinavir" code="HO3OGH5D7I | N0000006047"/>
<Mention id="M176" type="Precipitant" span="65 9" str="ritonavir" code="O3J8G9O825 | N0000007423"/>
<Mention id="M180" type="Precipitant" span="153 10" str="saquinavir" code="N0000007376 | L3JE09KZ2F"/>
<Mention id="M184" type="Precipitant" span="11 6;39 6;47 10" str="strong | CYP3A4 | inhibitors" code="N0000182141"/>
<Mention id="M188" type="Precipitant" span="11 46" str="strong cytochrome P450 3A4 (CYP3A4) inhibitors" code="N0000182141"/>
<Mention id="M192" type="Precipitant" span="11 26;47 10" str="strong cytochrome P450 3A4 | inhibitors" code="N0000182141"/>
<Mention id="M196" type="Precipitant" span="179 13" str="telithromycin" code="N0000010551 | KI8H7H19WL"/>
<Interaction id="I56" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M194;M195" precipitant="M148" effect="M197" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I57" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M194;M195" precipitant="M152" effect="M197" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I58" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M194;M195" precipitant="M156" effect="M197" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I59" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M194;M195" precipitant="M160" effect="M197" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I60" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M194;M195" precipitant="M164" effect="M197" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I61" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M194;M195" precipitant="M168" effect="M197" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I62" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M194;M195" precipitant="M172" effect="M197" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I63" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M194;M195" precipitant="M176" effect="M197" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I64" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M194;M195" precipitant="M180" effect="M197" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I65" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M194;M195" precipitant="M184" effect="M197" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I66" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M194;M195" precipitant="M188" effect="M197" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I67" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M194;M195" precipitant="M192" effect="M197" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I68" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M194;M195" precipitant="M196" effect="M197" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="353" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>SEREVENT DISKUS, like all medicines containing sympathomimetic amines, should be used with caution in patients with convulsive disorders or thyrotoxicosis and in those who are unusually responsive to sympathomimetic amines.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="354" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Doses of the related beta2-adrenoceptor agonist albuterol, when administered intravenously, have been reported to aggravate preexisting diabetes mellitus and ketoacidosis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="355" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Beta-adrenergic agonist medicines may produce significant hypokalemia in some patients, possibly through intracellular shunting, which has the potential to produce adverse cardiovascular effects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="356" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The decrease in serum potassium is usually transient, not requiring supplementation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="357" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Clinically significant and dose-related changes in blood glucose and/or serum potassium were seen infrequently during clinical trials with SEREVENT DISKUS at recommended doses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="358" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In vitro studies show salmeterol to be at least 50 times more selective for beta2-adrenoceptors than albuterol.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="359" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Although beta2-adrenoceptors are the predominant adrenergic receptors in bronchial smooth muscle and beta1-adrenoceptors are the predominant receptors in the heart, there are also beta2-adrenoceptors in the human heart comprising 10% to 50% of the total beta-adrenoceptors.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="360" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The precise function of these receptors has not been established, but their presence raises the possibility that even selective beta2-agonists may have cardiac effects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="361" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacologic effects of beta2-adrenoceptor agonist drugs, including salmeterol, are at least in part attributable to stimulation of intracellular adenyl cyclase, the enzyme that catalyzes the conversion of adenosine triphosphate (ATP) to cyclic-3′,5′-adenosine monophosphate (cyclic AMP).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="362" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Increased cyclic AMP levels cause relaxation of bronchial smooth muscle and inhibition of release of mediators of immediate hypersensitivity from cells, especially from mast cells.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="363" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In vitro tests show that salmeterol is a potent and long-lasting inhibitor of the release of mast cell mediators, such as histamine, leukotrienes, and prostaglandin D2, from human lung.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="364" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Salmeterol inhibits histamine-induced plasma protein extravasation and inhibits platelet-activating factor–induced eosinophil accumulation in the lungs of guinea pigs when administered by the inhaled route.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="365" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In humans, single doses of salmeterol administered via inhalation aerosol attenuate allergen-induced bronchial hyper-responsiveness.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="366" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Inhaled salmeterol, like other beta-adrenergic agonist drugs, can produce dose-related cardiovascular effects and effects on blood glucose and/or serum potassium.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="367" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The cardiovascular effects (heart rate, blood pressure) associated with salmeterol inhalation aerosol occur with similar frequency, and are of similar type and severity, as those noted following albuterol administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="368" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The effects of rising inhaled doses of salmeterol and standard inhaled doses of albuterol were studied in volunteers and in subjects with asthma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="369" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Salmeterol doses up to 84 mcg administered as inhalation aerosol resulted in heart rate increases of 3 to 16 beats/min, about the same as albuterol dosed at 180 mcg by inhalation aerosol (4 to 10 beats/min).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="370" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Adult and adolescent subjects receiving 50-mcg doses of salmeterol inhalation powder (n = 60) underwent continuous electrocardiographic monitoring during two 12-hour periods after the first dose and after 1 month of therapy, and no clinically significant dysrhythmias were noted.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="371" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Also, pediatric patients receiving 50-mcg doses of salmeterol inhalation powder (n = 67) underwent continuous electrocardiographic monitoring during two 12-hour periods after the first dose and after 3 months of therapy, and no clinically significant dysrhythmias were noted.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="372" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In 24-week clinical studies in patients with COPD, the incidence of clinically significant abnormalities on the predose ECGs at Weeks 12 and 24 in patients who received salmeterol 50 mcg was not different compared with placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="373" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No effect of treatment with salmeterol 50 mcg was observed on pulse rate and systolic and diastolic blood pressure in a subset of patients with COPD who underwent 12-hour serial vital sign measurements after the first dose (n = 91) and after 12 weeks of therapy (n = 74).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="374" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Median changes from baseline in pulse rate and systolic and diastolic blood pressure were similar for patients receiving either salmeterol or placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="375" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Concomitant Use of SEREVENT DISKUS with Other Respiratory Medications Short-acting Beta2-agonists: In two 12-week repetitive-dose clinical trials in adult and adolescent subjects with asthma (N = 149), the mean daily need for additional beta2-agonist in subjects using SEREVENT DISKUS was approximately 1½ inhalations/day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="376" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Twenty-six percent (26%) of the subjects in these trials used between 8 and 24 inhalations of short-acting beta-agonist per day on 1 or more occasions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="377" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Nine percent (9%) of the subjects in these trials averaged over 4 inhalations/day over the course of the 12-week trials.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="378" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No increase in frequency of cardiovascular events was observed among the 3 subjects who averaged 8 to 11 inhalations/day; however, the safety of concomitant use of more than 8 inhalations/day of short-acting beta2-agonist with SEREVENT DISKUS has not been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="379" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In 29 subjects who experienced worsening of asthma while receiving SEREVENT DISKUS during these trials, albuterol therapy administered via either nebulizer or inhalation aerosol (1 dose in most cases) led to improvement in FEV1 and no increase in occurrence of cardiovascular adverse events.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="380" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In 2 clinical trials in subjects with COPD, the mean daily need for additional beta2-agonist for subjects using SEREVENT DISKUS was approximately 4 inhalations/day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="381" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Twenty-four percent (24%) of subjects using SEREVENT DISKUS averaged 6 or more inhalations of albuterol per day over the course of the 24-week trials.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="382" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No increase in frequency of cardiovascular adverse reactions was observed among subjects who averaged 6 or more inhalations per day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="383" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Methylxanthines: The concurrent use of intravenously or orally administered methylxanthines (e.g., aminophylline, theophylline) by subjects receiving salmeterol has not been completely evaluated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="384" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In 1 clinical trial in subjects with asthma, 87 subjects receiving SEREVENT Inhalation Aerosol 42 mcg twice daily concurrently with a theophylline product had adverse event rates similar to those in 71 subjects receiving SEREVENT Inhalation Aerosol without theophylline.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="385" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Resting heart rates were slightly higher in the subjects on theophylline but were little affected by therapy with SEREVENT Inhalation Aerosol.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="386" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In 2 clinical trials in subjects with COPD, 39 subjects receiving SEREVENT DISKUS concurrently with a theophylline product had adverse event rates similar to those in 302 subjects receiving SEREVENT DISKUS without theophylline.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="387" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Based on the available data, the concomitant administration of methylxanthines with SEREVENT DISKUS did not alter the observed adverse event profile.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="388" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Cromoglycate: In clinical trials, inhaled cromolyn sodium did not alter the safety profile of salmeterol when administered concurrently.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="389" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Salmeterol xinafoate, an ionic salt, dissociates in solution so that the salmeterol and 1-hydroxy-2-naphthoic acid (xinafoate) moieties are absorbed, distributed, metabolized, and eliminated independently.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="390" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Salmeterol acts locally in the lung; therefore, plasma levels do not predict therapeutic effect.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="391" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Absorption Because of the small therapeutic dose, systemic levels of salmeterol are low or undetectable after inhalation of recommended doses (50 mcg of salmeterol inhalation powder twice daily).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="392" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following chronic administration of an inhaled dose of 50 mcg of salmeterol inhalation powder twice daily, salmeterol was detected in plasma within 5 to 45 minutes in 7 subjects with asthma; plasma concentrations were very low, with mean peak concentrations of 167 pg/mL at 20 minutes and no accumulation with repeated doses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="393" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Distribution The percentage of salmeterol bound to human plasma proteins averages 96% in vitro over the concentration range of 8 to 7,722 ng of salmeterol base per milliliter, much higher concentrations than those achieved following therapeutic doses of salmeterol.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="394" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Metabolism Salmeterol base is extensively metabolized by hydroxylation, with subsequent elimination predominantly in the feces.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="395" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No significant amount of unchanged salmeterol base was detected in either urine or feces.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="396" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>An in vitro study using human liver microsomes showed that salmeterol is extensively metabolized to α-hydroxysalmeterol (aliphatic oxidation) by CYP3A4.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="397" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Ketoconazole, a strong inhibitor of CYP3A4, essentially completely inhibited the formation of α-hydroxysalmeterol in vitro.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="398" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Elimination In 2 healthy adult subjects who received 1 mg of radiolabeled salmeterol (as salmeterol xinafoate) orally, approximately 25% and 60% of the radiolabeled salmeterol was eliminated in urine and feces, respectively, over a period of 7 days.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="399" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The terminal elimination half-life was about 5.5 hours (1 volunteer only).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="400" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The xinafoate moiety has no apparent pharmacologic activity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="401" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The xinafoate moiety is highly protein bound (&gt;99%) and has a long elimination half-life of 11 days.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="402" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Drug Interaction Studies Inhibitors of Cytochrome P450 3A4: Ketoconazole: In a placebo-controlled crossover drug interaction trial in 20 healthy male and female subjects, coadministration of salmeterol (50 mcg twice daily) and the strong CYP3A4 inhibitor ketoconazole (400 mg once daily) for 7 days resulted in a significant increase in plasma salmeterol exposure as determined by a 16-fold increase in AUC (ratio with and without ketoconazole 15.76 [90% CI: 10.66, 23.31]) mainly due to increased bioavailability of the swallowed portion of the dose.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M206" type="Trigger" span="391 15" str="increase in AUC"/>
<Mention id="M202" type="Precipitant" span="60 12" str="ketoconazole" code="N0000007319 | R9400W927I"/>
<Mention id="M203" type="Trigger" span="488 25" str="increased bioavailability "/>
<Mention id="M204" type="Trigger" span="325 18;355 8" str=" increase in plasma | exposure"/>
<Mention id="M207" type="Precipitant" span="231 23" str="strong CYP3A4 inhibitor" code="N0000182141"/>
<Interaction id="I69" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M206" precipitant="M202" effect="C54605"/>
<Interaction id="I70" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M203;M204" precipitant="M202" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I71" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M203;M204" precipitant="M207" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I72" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M206" precipitant="M207" effect="C54605"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="403" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Peak plasma salmeterol concentrations were increased by 1.4-fold (90% CI: 1.23, 1.68).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="404" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Three (3) out of 20 subjects (15%) were withdrawn from salmeterol and ketoconazole coadministration due to beta-agonist–mediated systemic effects (2 with QTc prolongation and 1 with palpitations and sinus tachycardia).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M217" type="Trigger" span="40 9;100 6" str="withdrawn | due to"/>
<Mention id="M218" type="Precipitant" span="70 12" str="ketoconazole" code="N0000007319 | R9400W927I"/>
<Mention id="M210" type="SpecificInteraction" span="107 38" str="beta-agonist–mediated systemic effects" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M213" type="SpecificInteraction" span="182 12" str="palpitations" code="80313002: Palpitations (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M216" type="SpecificInteraction" span="154 16" str="QTc prolongation" code="111975006:  Prolonged QT interval (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M219" type="SpecificInteraction" span="199 17" str="sinus tachycardia" code="11092001: Sinus tachycardia (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I73" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M217" precipitant="M218" effect="M210" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I74" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M217" precipitant="M218" effect="M213" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I75" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M217" precipitant="M218" effect="M216" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I76" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M217" precipitant="M218" effect="M219" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="405" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Coadministration of salmeterol and ketoconazole did not result in a clinically significant effect on mean heart rate, mean blood potassium, or mean blood glucose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="406" LabelDrug="SEREVENT" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Erythromycin: In a repeat-dose trial in 13 healthy subjects, concomitant administration of erythromycin (a moderate CYP3A4 inhibitor) and salmeterol inhalation aerosol resulted in a 40% increase in salmeterol Cmax at steady state (ratio with and without erythromycin 1.4 [90% CI: 0.96, 2.03], P = 0.12), a 3.6-beat/min increase in heart rate ([95% CI: 0.19, 7.03], P&lt;0.04), a 5.8-msec increase in QTc interval ([95% CI: -6.14, 17.77], P = 0.34), and no change in plasma potassium.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M229" type="Trigger" span="186 8" str="increase"/>
<Mention id="M233" type="Precipitant" span="0 12" str="erythromycin" code="N0000007133 | 63937KV33D"/>
<Mention id="M228" type="SpecificInteraction" span="319 22" str="increase in heart rate" code="3424008: Tachycardia (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M231" type="SpecificInteraction" span="385 24" str="increase in QTc interval" code="111975006:  Prolonged QT interval (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M235" type="Precipitant" span="107 25" str="moderate CYP3A4 inhibitor" code="N0000182141"/>
<Mention id="M234" type="Trigger" span="186 8;209 4" str="increase | Cmax"/>
<Interaction id="I77" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M229" precipitant="M233" effect="M228" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I78" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M229" precipitant="M233" effect="M231" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I79" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M229" precipitant="M235" effect="M228" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I80" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M229" precipitant="M235" effect="M231" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I81" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M234" precipitant="M233" effect="C54602"/>
<Interaction id="I82" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M234" precipitant="M235" effect="C54602"/>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="usual asthma therapy" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="low- or medium-dose ics" precipitantCode="N0000175576"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="laba" precipitantCode="N0000000245" effect="55680006: Drug overdose (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="laba" precipitantCode="N0000000245"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ketoconazole" precipitantCode="N0000007319 | R9400W927I" effect="11092001: Sinus tachycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ketoconazole" precipitantCode="N0000007319 | R9400W927I" effect="111975006:  Prolonged QT interval (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ketoconazole" precipitantCode="N0000007319 | R9400W927I" effect="267037003: Cardiovascular symptoms (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ketoconazole" precipitantCode="N0000007319 | R9400W927I" effect="80313002: Palpitations (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ketoconazole" precipitantCode="N0000007319 | R9400W927I" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="ketoconazole" precipitantCode="N0000007319 | R9400W927I" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="ketoconazole" precipitantCode="N0000007319 | R9400W927I" effect="C54605"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="ketoconazole" precipitantCode="N0000007319 | R9400W927I"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ritonavir" precipitantCode="O3J8G9O825 | N0000007423" effect="267037003: Cardiovascular symptoms (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="ritonavir" precipitantCode="O3J8G9O825 | N0000007423"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="strong cytochrome p450 3a4 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000182141"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="monoamine oxidase inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000000184 | N0000175744" effect="293416008: Drug groups primarily affecting cardiovascular system adverse reaction (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="monoamine oxidase inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000000184 | N0000175744"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="tricyclic antidepressants" precipitantCode="N0000029148 | N0000175752" effect="293416008: Drug groups primarily affecting cardiovascular system adverse reaction (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="tricyclic antidepressants" precipitantCode="N0000029148 | N0000175752"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="beta-blockers" precipitantCode="N0000000161 | N0000175556" effect="4386001: Bronchospasm (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="beta-blockers" precipitantCode="N0000000161 | N0000175556" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="beta-blockers" precipitantCode="N0000000161 | N0000175556"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="beta-agonists" precipitantCode="N0000175555 | N0000000245" effect="4386001: Bronchospasm (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="beta-agonists" precipitantCode="N0000175555 | N0000000245" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="non–potassium-sparing diuretics" precipitantCode="N0000175359" effect=" 43339004: Hypokalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="non–potassium-sparing diuretics" precipitantCode="N0000175359" effect="102594003: Electrocardiogram abnormal (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="non–potassium-sparing diuretics" precipitantCode="N0000175359" effect="43339004: Hypokalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="non–potassium-sparing diuretics" precipitantCode="N0000175359"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="atazanavir" precipitantCode="N0000022320 | QZU4H47A3S" effect="267037003: Cardiovascular symptoms (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="clarithromycin" precipitantCode="H1250JIK0A | N0000007316" effect="267037003: Cardiovascular symptoms (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="indinavir" precipitantCode="N0000005722 | 5W6YA9PKKH" effect="267037003: Cardiovascular symptoms (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="itraconazole" precipitantCode="304NUG5GF4 | N0000006753" effect="267037003: Cardiovascular symptoms (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nefazodone" precipitantCode="N0000007250 | 59H4FCV1TF" effect="267037003: Cardiovascular symptoms (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nelfinavir" precipitantCode="HO3OGH5D7I | N0000006047" effect="267037003: Cardiovascular symptoms (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="saquinavir" precipitantCode="N0000007376 | L3JE09KZ2F" effect="267037003: Cardiovascular symptoms (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="strong cyp3a4 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000182141" effect="267037003: Cardiovascular symptoms (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="telithromycin" precipitantCode="N0000010551 | KI8H7H19WL" effect="267037003: Cardiovascular symptoms (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="oral ketoconazole" precipitantCode="R9400W927I" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="oral ketoconazole" precipitantCode="R9400W927I" effect="C54602"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="oral ketoconazole" precipitantCode="R9400W927I" effect="C54605"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="beta-adrenergic blocking agents" precipitantCode="N0000000161 | N0000175556"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="cardioselective beta-blockers" precipitantCode="N0000000161"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="loop | diuretics" precipitantCode="N0000175590" effect="102594003: Electrocardiogram abnormal (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="loop | diuretics" precipitantCode="N0000175590" effect="43339004: Hypokalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="thiazide diuretics" precipitantCode="N0000175419" effect="102594003: Electrocardiogram abnormal (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="thiazide diuretics" precipitantCode="N0000175419" effect="43339004: Hypokalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="medicine containing a laba" precipitantCode="N0000000245" effect="55680006: Drug overdose (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="medicine containing a laba" precipitantCode="N0000000245"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="systemic corticosteroids" precipitantCode="N0000175576"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="short-acting beta2-agonists" precipitantCode="N0000009922"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="corticosteroid" precipitantCode="N0000175576"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="medicines containing laba" precipitantCode="N0000000245" effect="55680006: Drug overdose (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="arformoterol tartrate" precipitantCode="5P8VJ2I235"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="formoterol fumarate" precipitantCode="W34SHF8J2K"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="indacaterol" precipitantCode="8OR09251MQ"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="strong | cyp3a4 | inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000182141" effect="267037003: Cardiovascular symptoms (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="strong cytochrome p450 3a4 (cyp3a4) inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000182141" effect="267037003: Cardiovascular symptoms (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="strong cytochrome p450 3a4 | inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000182141" effect="267037003: Cardiovascular symptoms (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="strong cyp3a4 inhibitor" precipitantCode="N0000182141" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="strong cyp3a4 inhibitor" precipitantCode="N0000182141" effect="C54605"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="erythromycin" precipitantCode="N0000007133 | 63937KV33D" effect="111975006:  Prolonged QT interval (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="erythromycin" precipitantCode="N0000007133 | 63937KV33D" effect="3424008: Tachycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="erythromycin" precipitantCode="N0000007133 | 63937KV33D" effect="C54602"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="moderate cyp3a4 inhibitor" precipitantCode="N0000182141" effect="111975006:  Prolonged QT interval (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="moderate cyp3a4 inhibitor" precipitantCode="N0000182141" effect="3424008: Tachycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="moderate cyp3a4 inhibitor" precipitantCode="N0000182141" effect="C54602"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>