<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Ketalar" setid="14e8f864-8b8a-4e7e-8439-e510d3107063">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
Ketamine hydrochloride is contraindicated in those in whom a significant elevation of blood pressure would constitute a serious hazard and in those who have shown hypersensitivity to the drug.</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
Note : Barbiturates and KETALAR, being chemically incompatible because of precipitate formation, should not be injected from the same syringe. If the KETALAR dose is augmented with diazepam, the two drugs must be given separately. Do not mix KETALAR and diazepam in syringe or infusion flask. For additional information on the use of diazepam, refer to the WARNINGS and DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION Sections of the diazepam insert. 1.     While vomiting has been reported following KETALAR administration, some airway protection may be afforded because of active laryngeal-pharyngeal reflexes. However, since aspiration may occur with KETALAR and since protective reflexes may also be diminished by supplementary anesthetics and muscle relaxants, the possibility of aspiration must be considered. KETALAR is recommended for use in the patient whose stomach is not empty when, in the judgment of the practitioner, the benefits of the drug outweigh the possible risks. 2.     Atropine, scopolamine, or another drying agent should be given at an appropriate interval prior to induction. Because of rapid induction following the initial intravenous injection, the patient should be in a supported position during administration. The onset of action of KETALAR is rapid; an intravenous dose of 2 mg/kg of body weight usually produces surgical anesthesia within 30 seconds after injection, with the anesthetic effect usually lasting five to ten minutes. If a longer effect is desired, additional increments can be administered intravenously or intramuscularly to maintain anesthesia without producing significant cumulative effects. Intramuscular doses, in a range of 9 to 13 mg/kg usually produce surgical anesthesia within 3 to 4 minutes following injection, with the anesthetic effect usually lasting 12 to 25 minutes. As with other general anesthetic agents, the individual response to KETALAR is somewhat varied depending on the dose, route of administration, and age of patient, so that dosage recommendation cannot be absolutely fixed. The drug should be titrated against the patient's requirements. In individuals with a history of chronic ketamine use for off-label indications, there have been case reports of genitourinary pain that may be related to the ketamine treatment, not the underlying condition (see Adverse Reactions Section). Consider cessation of ketamine if genitourinary pain continues in the setting of other genitourinary symptoms. Intravenous Route: The initial dose of KETALAR administered intravenously may range from 1 mg/kg to 4.5 mg/kg. The average amount required to produce five to ten minutes of surgical anesthesia has been 2 mg/kg. Alternatively, in adult patients an induction dose of 1 mg to 2 mg/kg intravenous ketamine at a rate of 0.5 mg/kg/min may be used for induction of anesthesia. In addition, diazepam in 2 mg to 5 mg doses, administered in a separate syringe over 60 seconds, may be used. In most cases, 15 mg of intravenous diazepam or less will suffice. The incidence of psychological manifestations during emergence, particularly dream-like observations and emergence delirium, may be reduced by this induction dosage program. Note: The 100 mg/mL concentration of KETALAR should not be injected intravenously without proper dilution. It is recommended the drug be diluted with an equal volume of either Sterile Water for injection, USP, Normal Saline, or 5% Dextrose in Water. Rate of Administration: It is recommended that KETALAR be administered slowly (over a period of 60 seconds). More rapid administration may result in respiratory depression and enhanced pressor response. Intramuscular Route: The initial dose of KETALAR administered intramuscularly may range from 6.5 to 13 mg/kg. A dose of 10 mg/kg will usually produce 12 to 25 minutes of surgical anesthesia. The maintenance dose should be adjusted according to the patient's anesthetic needs and whether an additional anesthetic agent is employed. Increments of one-half to the full induction dose may be repeated as needed for maintenance of anesthesia. However, it should be noted that purposeless and tonic-clonic movements of extremities may occur during the course of anesthesia. These movements do not imply a light plane and are not indicative of the need for additional doses of the anesthetic. It should be recognized that the larger the total dose of KETALAR administered, the longer will be the time to complete recovery. Adult patients induced with KETALAR augmented with intravenous diazepam may be maintained on KETALAR given by slow microdrip infusion technique at a dose of 0.1 to 0.5 mg/minute, augmented with diazepam 2 to 5 mg administered intravenously as needed. In many cases 20 mg or less of intravenous diazepam total for combined induction and maintenance will suffice. However, slightly more diazepam may be required depending on the nature and duration of the operation, physical status of the patient, and other factors. The incidence of psychological manifestations during emergence, particularly dream-like observations and emergence delirium, may be reduced by this maintenance dosage program. Dilution: To prepare a dilute solution containing 1 mg of ketamine per mL, aseptically transfer 10 mL from a 50 mg per mL vial or 5 mL from a 100 mg per mL vial to 500 mL of 5% Dextrose Injection, USP or Sodium Chloride (0.9%) Injection, USP (Normal Saline) and mix well. The resultant solution will contain 1 mg of ketamine per mL. The fluid requirements of the patient and duration of anesthesia must be considered when selecting the appropriate dilution of KETALAR. If fluid restriction is required, KETALAR can be added to a 250 mL infusion as described above to provide a KETALAR concentration of 2 mg/mL. KETALAR 10 mg/mL vials are not recommended for dilution. KETALAR is clinically compatible with the commonly used general and local anesthetic agents when an adequate respiratory exchange is maintained. The regimen of a reduced dose of KETALAR supplemented with diazepam can be used to produce balanced anesthesia by combination with other agents such as nitrous oxide and oxygen.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
Prolonged recovery time may occur if barbiturates and/or narcotics are used concurrently with KETALAR. KETALAR is clinically compatible with the commonly used general and local anesthetic agents when an adequate respiratory exchange is maintained.</Section>
<Section name="PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="42232-9">
KETALAR should be used by or under the direction of physicians experienced in administering general anesthetics and in maintenance of an airway and in the control of respiration. Because pharyngeal and laryngeal reflexes are usually active, KETALAR should not be used alone in surgery or diagnostic procedures of the pharynx, larynx, or bronchial tree. Mechanical stimulation of the pharynx should be avoided, whenever possible, if KETALAR is used alone. Muscle relaxants, with proper attention to respiration, may be required in both of these instances. Resuscitative equipment should be ready for use. The incidence of emergence reactions may be reduced if verbal and tactile stimulation of the patient is minimized during the recovery period. This does not preclude the monitoring of vital signs (see Special Note ). The intravenous dose should be administered over a period of 60 seconds. More rapid administration may result in respiratory depression or apnea and enhanced pressor response. In surgical procedures involving visceral pain pathways, KETALAR should be supplemented with an agent which obtunds visceral pain. Use with caution in the chronic alcoholic and the acutely alcohol-intoxicated patient. An increase in cerebrospinal fluid pressure has been reported following administration of ketamine hydrochloride. Use with extreme caution in patients with preanesthetic elevated cerebrospinal fluid pressure. Carcinogenesis Long-term animal studies have not been conducted to evaluate the carcinogenic potential of ketamine. Mutagenesis In a published report, ketamine was clastogenic in the in vitro chromosomal aberration assay. Impairment of Fertility Adequate studies to evaluate the impact of ketamine on male or female fertility have not been conducted.  Male and female rats were treated with 10 mg/kg ketamine IV (0.8 times the average human induction dose of 2 mg/kg IV based on body surface area) on Days 11, 10, and 9 prior to mating.  No impact on fertility was noted; however, this study design does not adequately characterize the impact of a drug on fertility endpoints. There are no adequate and well-controlled studies of KETALAR in pregnant women.  In animal reproduction studies in rats developmental delays (hypoplasia of skeletal tissues) were noted at 0.3 times the human intramuscular dose of 10 mg/kg.  In rabbits, developmental delays and increased fetal resorptions were noted at 0.6 times the human dose.  Published studies in pregnant primates demonstrate that the administration of anesthetic and sedation drugs that block NMDA receptors and/or potentiate GABA activity during the period of peak brain development increases neuronal apoptosis in the developing brain of the offspring when used for longer than 3 hours.  There are no data on pregnancy exposures in primates corresponding to periods prior to the third trimester in humans. The estimated background risk of major birth defects and miscarriage for the indicated population is unknown. All pregnancies have a background risk of birth defect, loss, or other adverse outcomes. In the U.S. general population, the estimated background risk of major birth defects and miscarriage in clinically recognized pregnancies is 2-4% and 15-20%, respectively. Since the safe use in pregnancy, including obstetrics (either vaginal or abdominal delivery), has not been established, such use is not recommended (see ANIMAL PHARMACOLOGY AND TOXICOLOGY ). Animal Data Pregnant rats were treated intramuscularly with 20 mg/kg ketamine (0.3 times the human dose of 10 mg/kg IM based on body surface area) on either Gestation Days 6 to 10 or Gestation Days 11 to 15.  Ketamine treatment produced an increased incidence of hypoplastic skull, phalanges, and sternebrae in the pups. Pregnant rabbits were treated intramuscularly with 20 mg/kg ketamine (0.6 times the human dose of 10 mg/kg IM based on body surface area) on either Gestation Days 6 to 10 or Gestation Days 11 to 15.  An increase in resorptions and skeletal hypoplasia of the fetuses were noted.  Additional pregnant rabbits were treated intramuscularly with a single dose 60 mg/kg (1.9 times the human dose of 10 mg/kg IM based on body surface area) on Gestation Day 6 only.  Skeletal hypoplasia was reported in the fetuses. In a study where pregnant rats were treated intramuscularly with 20 mg/kg ketamine (0.3 times the human dose of 10 mg/kg IM based on body surface area) from Gestation Day 18 to 21.  There was a slight increase in incidence of delayed parturition by one day in treated dams of this group.  No adverse effects on the litters or pups were noted; however, learning and memory assessments were not completed.  Three pregnant beagle dogs were treated intramuscularly with 25 mg/kg ketamine (1.3 times the human dose of 10 mg/kg IM based on body surface area) twice weekly for the three weeks of the first, second, and third trimesters of pregnancy, respectively, without the development of adverse effects in the pups. In a published study in primates, administration of an anesthetic dose of ketamine for 24 hours on Gestation Day 122 increased neuronal apoptosis in the developing brain of the fetus. In other published studies, administration of either isoflurane or propofol for 5 hours on Gestation Day 120 resulted in increased neuronal and oligodendrocyte apoptosis in the developing brain of the offspring. With respect to brain development, this time period corresponds to the third trimester of gestation in the human. The clinical significance of these findings is not clear; however, studies in juvenile animals suggest neuroapoptosis correlates with long-term cognitive deficits. (See WARNINGS/Pediatric Neurotoxicity , Pediatric Use , and ANIMAL TOXICOLOGY AND PHARMACOLOGY ). Risk of Drowsiness As appropriate, especially in cases where early discharge is possible, the duration of KETALAR and other drugs employed during the conduct of anesthesia should be considered. The patients should be cautioned that driving an automobile, operating hazardous machinery or engaging in hazardous activities should not be undertaken for 24 hours or more (depending upon the dosage of KETALAR and consideration of other drugs employed) after anesthesia. Effect of anesthetic and sedation drugs on early brain development Studies conducted in young animals and children suggest repeated or prolonged use of general anesthetic or sedation drugs in children younger than 3 years may have negative effects on their developing brains. Discuss with parents and caregivers the benefits, risks, and timing and duration of surgery or procedures requiring anesthetic and sedation drugs (See WARNINGS/Pediatric Neurotoxicity ). Prolonged recovery time may occur if barbiturates and/or narcotics are used concurrently with KETALAR. KETALAR is clinically compatible with the commonly used general and local anesthetic agents when an adequate respiratory exchange is maintained. Clinical studies of ketamine hydrochloride did not include sufficient numbers of subjects aged 65 and over to determine whether they respond differently from younger subjects. Other reported clinical experience has not identified differences in responses between the elderly and younger patients. In general, dose selection for an elderly patient should be cautious, usually starting at the low end of the dosing range, reflecting the greater frequency of decreased hepatic, renal, or cardiac function, and of concomitant disease or other drug therapy. Safety and effectiveness in pediatric patients below the age of 16 have not been established. Published juvenile animal studies demonstrate that the administration of anesthetic and sedation drugs, such as KETALAR, that either block NMDA receptors or potentiate the activity of GABA during the period of rapid brain growth or synaptogenesis, results in widespread neuronal and oligodendrocyte cell loss in the developing brain and alterations in synaptic morphology and neurogenesis. Based on comparisons across species, the window of vulnerability to these changes is believed to correlate with exposures in the third trimester of gestation through the first several months of life, but may extend out to approximately 3 years of age in humans. In primates, exposure to 3 hours of ketamine that produced a light surgical plane of anesthesia did not increase neuronal cell loss, however, treatment regimens of 5 hours or longer of isoflurane increased neuronal cell loss. Data from isoflurane-treated rodents and ketamine-treated primates suggest that the neuronal and oligodendrocyte cell losses are associated with prolonged cognitive deficits in learning and memory. The clinical significance of these nonclinical findings is not known, and healthcare providers should balance the benefits of appropriate anesthesia in pregnant women, neonates, and young children who require procedures with the potential risks suggested by the nonclinical data. (See WARNINGS / Pediatric Neurotoxicity , Pregnancy ).</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS SECTION" id="34071-1">
Cardiac function should be continually monitored during the procedure in patients found to have hypertension or cardiac decompensation. Postoperative confusional states may occur during the recovery period. (See Special Note ). Respiratory depression may occur with overdosage or too rapid a rate of administration of KETALAR, in which case supportive ventilation should be employed. Mechanical support of respiration is preferred to administration of analeptics. Published animal studies demonstrate that the administration of anesthetic and sedation drugs that block NMDA receptors and/or potentiate GABA activity increase neuronal apoptosis in the developing brain and result in long-term cognitive deficits when used for longer than 3 hours. The clinical significance of these findings is not clear. However, based on the available data, the window of vulnerability to these changes is believed to correlate with exposures in the third trimester of gestation through the first several months of life, but may extend out to approximately three years of age in humans. (See PRECAUTIONS/ Pregnancy ). Some published studies in children suggest that similar deficits may occur after repeated or prolonged exposures to anesthetic agents early in life and may result in adverse cognitive or behavioral effects. These studies have substantial limitations, and it is not clear if the observed effects are due to the anesthetic/sedation drug administration or other factors such as the surgery or underlying illness. Anesthetic and sedation drugs are a necessary part of the care of children needing surgery, other procedures, or tests that cannot be delayed, and no specific medications have been shown to be safer than any other. Decisions regarding the timing of any elective procedures requiring anesthesia should take into consideration the benefits of the procedure weighed against the potential risks.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
KETALAR is a rapid-acting general anesthetic producing an anesthetic state characterized by profound analgesia, normal pharyngeal-laryngeal reflexes, normal or slightly enhanced skeletal muscle tone, cardiovascular and respiratory stimulation, and occasionally a transient and minimal respiratory depression. The mechanism of action is primarily due to antagonism of N-methyl-D-aspartate (NMDA receptors) in the central nervous system. A patent airway is maintained partly by virtue of unimpaired pharyngeal and laryngeal reflexes. (See WARNINGS and PRECAUTIONS Sections). The biotransformation of KETALAR includes N-dealkylation (metabolite I), hydroxylation of the cyclohexone ring (metabolites III and IV), conjugation with glucuronic acid and dehydration of the hydroxylated metabolites to form the cyclohexene derivative (metabolite II). Following intravenous administration, the ketamine concentration has an initial slope (alpha phase) lasting about 45 minutes with a half-life of 10 to 15 minutes. This first phase corresponds clinically to the anesthetic effect of the drug. The anesthetic action is terminated by a combination of redistribution from the CNS to slower equilibrating peripheral tissues and by hepatic biotransformation to metabolite I. This metabolite is about 1/3 as active as ketamine in reducing halothane requirements (MAC) of the rat. The later half-life of ketamine (beta phase) is 2.5 hours. The anesthetic state produced by KETALAR has been termed "dissociative anesthesia" in that it appears to selectively interrupt association pathways of the brain before producing somatesthetic sensory blockade. It may selectively depress the thalamoneocortical system before significantly obtunding the more ancient cerebral centers and pathways (reticular-activating and limbic systems). Elevation of blood pressure begins shortly after injection, reaches a maximum within a few minutes and usually returns to preanesthetic values within 15 minutes after injection. In the majority of cases, the systolic and diastolic blood pressure peaks from 10% to 50% above preanesthetic levels shortly after induction of anesthesia, but the elevation can be higher or longer in individual cases (see CONTRAINDICATIONS Section). Ketamine has a wide margin of safety; several instances of unintentional administration of overdoses of KETALAR (up to ten times that usually required) have been followed by prolonged but complete recovery. KETALAR has been studied in over 12,000 operative and diagnostic procedures, involving over 10,000 patients from 105 separate studies. During the course of these studies KETALAR was administered as the sole agent, as induction for other general agents, or to supplement low-potency agents. Specific areas of application have included the following: 1.     debridement, painful dressings, and skin grafting in burn patients, as well as other superficial surgical procedures. 2.     neurodiagnostic procedures such as pneumonencephalograms, ventriculograms, myelograms, and lumbar punctures. See also Precaution concerning increased intracranial pressure. 3.     diagnostic and operative procedures of the eye, ear, nose, and mouth, including dental extractions. 4.     diagnostic and operative procedures of the pharynx, larynx, or bronchial tree. NOTE: Muscle relaxants, with proper attention to respiration, may be required (see PRECAUTIONS Section). 5.     sigmoidoscopy and minor surgery of the anus and rectum, and circumcision. 6.     extraperitoneal procedures used in gynecology such as dilatation and curettage. 7.     orthopedic procedures such as closed reductions, manipulations, femoral pinning, amputations, and biopsies. 8.     as an anesthetic in poor-risk patients with depression of vital functions. 9.     in procedures where the intramuscular route of administration is preferred. 10.     in cardiac catheterization procedures. In these studies, the anesthesia was rated either "excellent" or "good" by the anesthesiologist and the surgeon at 90% and 93%, respectively; rated "fair" at 6% and 4%, respectively; and rated "poor" at 4% and 3%, respectively. In a second method of evaluation, the anesthesia was rated "adequate" in at least 90%, and "inadequate" in 10% or less of the procedures.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="4339" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Ketamine hydrochloride is contraindicated in those in whom a significant elevation of blood pressure would constitute a serious hazard and in those who have shown hypersensitivity to the drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4340" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Note: Barbiturates and KETALAR, being chemically incompatible because of precipitate formation, should not be injected from the same syringe.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M3" type="SpecificInteraction" span="38 23" str="chemically incompatible" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="6 12" str="Barbiturates" code="N0000175693 | N0000008016"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M3" precipitant="M2" effect="M3" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4341" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If the KETALAR dose is augmented with diazepam, the two drugs must be given separately.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M4" type="Trigger" span="62 24" str="must be given separately"/>
<Mention id="M5" type="Precipitant" span="38 8" str="diazepam" code="Q3JTX2Q7TU"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M4" precipitant="M5"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4342" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not mix KETALAR and diazepam in syringe or infusion flask.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M6" type="Trigger" span="0 10" str="Do not mix"/>
<Mention id="M7" type="Precipitant" span="23 8" str="diazepam" code="Q3JTX2Q7TU"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M6" precipitant="M7"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4343" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For additional information on the use of diazepam, refer to the WARNINGS and DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION Sections of the diazepam insert.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M8" type="Trigger" span="51 21" str="refer to the WARNINGS"/>
<Mention id="M9" type="Precipitant" span="41 8" str="diazepam" code="Q3JTX2Q7TU"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M8" precipitant="M9"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4344" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>While vomiting has been reported following KETALAR administration, some airway protection may be afforded because of active laryngeal-pharyngeal reflexes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4345" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>However, since aspiration may occur with KETALAR and since protective reflexes may also be diminished by supplementary anesthetics and muscle relaxants, the possibility of aspiration must be considered.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M13" type="Trigger" span="30 5" str="occur"/>
<Mention id="M11" type="Precipitant" span="119 11" str="anesthetics" code="N0000029138 | N0000175681"/>
<Mention id="M15" type="SpecificInteraction" span="15 10" str="aspiration" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M14" type="Precipitant" span="135 16" str="muscle relaxants" code="N0000175737"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M13" precipitant="M11" effect="M15" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M13" precipitant="M14" effect="M15" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4346" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>KETALAR is recommended for use in the patient whose stomach is not empty when, in the judgment of the practitioner, the benefits of the drug outweigh the possible risks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4347" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Atropine, scopolamine, or another drying agent should be given at an appropriate interval prior to induction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4348" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Because of rapid induction following the initial intravenous injection, the patient should be in a supported position during administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4349" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The onset of action of KETALAR is rapid; an intravenous dose of 2 mg/kg of body weight usually produces surgical anesthesia within 30 seconds after injection, with the anesthetic effect usually lasting five to ten minutes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4350" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If a longer effect is desired, additional increments can be administered intravenously or intramuscularly to maintain anesthesia without producing significant cumulative effects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4351" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Intramuscular doses, in a range of 9 to 13 mg/kg usually produce surgical anesthesia within 3 to 4 minutes following injection, with the anesthetic effect usually lasting 12 to 25 minutes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4352" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>As with other general anesthetic agents, the individual response to KETALAR is somewhat varied depending on the dose, route of administration, and age of patient, so that dosage recommendation cannot be absolutely fixed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4353" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The drug should be titrated against the patient's requirements.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4354" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In individuals with a history of chronic ketamine use for off-label indications, there have been case reports of genitourinary pain that may be related to the ketamine treatment, not the underlying condition.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4355" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Consider cessation of ketamine if genitourinary pain continues in the setting of other genitourinary symptoms.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4356" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Intravenous Route: The initial dose of KETALAR administered intravenously may range from 1 mg/kg to 4.5 mg/kg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4357" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The average amount required to produce five to ten minutes of surgical anesthesia has been 2 mg/kg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4358" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Alternatively, in adult patients an induction dose of 1 mg to 2 mg/kg intravenous ketamine at a rate of 0.5 mg/kg/min may be used for induction of anesthesia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4359" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In addition, diazepam in 2 mg to 5 mg doses, administered in a separate syringe over 60 seconds, may be used.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4360" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In most cases, 15 mg of intravenous diazepam or less will suffice.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4361" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The incidence of psychological manifestations during emergence, particularly dream-like observations and emergence delirium, may be reduced by this induction dosage program.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4362" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Note: The 100 mg/mL concentration of KETALAR should not be injected intravenously without proper dilution.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4363" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>It is recommended the drug be diluted with an equal volume of either Sterile Water for injection, USP, Normal Saline, or 5% Dextrose in Water.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4364" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Rate of Administration: It is recommended that KETALAR be administered slowly (over a period of 60 seconds).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4365" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>More rapid administration may result in respiratory depression and enhanced pressor response.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4366" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Intramuscular Route: The initial dose of KETALAR administered intramuscularly may range from 6.5 to 13 mg/kg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4367" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>A dose of 10 mg/kg will usually produce 12 to 25 minutes of surgical anesthesia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4368" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The maintenance dose should be adjusted according to the patient's anesthetic needs and whether an additional anesthetic agent is employed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4369" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Increments of one-half to the full induction dose may be repeated as needed for maintenance of anesthesia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4370" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>However, it should be noted that purposeless and tonic-clonic movements of extremities may occur during the course of anesthesia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4371" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>These movements do not imply a light plane and are not indicative of the need for additional doses of the anesthetic.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4372" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>It should be recognized that the larger the total dose of KETALAR administered, the longer will be the time to complete recovery.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4373" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Adult patients induced with KETALAR augmented with intravenous diazepam may be maintained on KETALAR given by slow microdrip infusion technique at a dose of 0.1 to 0.5 mg/minute, augmented with diazepam 2 to 5 mg administered intravenously as needed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4374" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In many cases 20 mg or less of intravenous diazepam total for combined induction and maintenance will suffice.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4375" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>However, slightly more diazepam may be required depending on the nature and duration of the operation, physical status of the patient, and other factors.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4376" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The incidence of psychological manifestations during emergence, particularly dream-like observations and emergence delirium, may be reduced by this maintenance dosage program.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4377" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dilution: To prepare a dilute solution containing 1 mg of ketamine per mL, aseptically transfer 10 mL from a 50 mg per mL vial or 5 mL from a 100 mg per mL vial to 500 mL of 5% Dextrose Injection, USP or Sodium Chloride (0.9%) Injection, USP (Normal Saline) and mix well.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4378" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The resultant solution will contain 1 mg of ketamine per mL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4379" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The fluid requirements of the patient and duration of anesthesia must be considered when selecting the appropriate dilution of KETALAR.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4380" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If fluid restriction is required, KETALAR can be added to a 250 mL infusion as described above to provide a KETALAR concentration of 2 mg/mL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4381" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>KETALAR 10 mg/mL vials are not recommended for dilution.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4382" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>KETALAR is clinically compatible with the commonly used general and local anesthetic agents when an adequate respiratory exchange is maintained.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4383" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The regimen of a reduced dose of KETALAR supplemented with diazepam can be used to produce balanced anesthesia by combination with other agents such as nitrous oxide and oxygen.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4384" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Prolonged recovery time may occur if barbiturates and/or narcotics are used concurrently with KETALAR.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M19" type="Trigger" span="28 5" str="occur"/>
<Mention id="M17" type="Precipitant" span="37 12" str="barbiturates" code="N0000175693 | N0000008016"/>
<Mention id="M21" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 23" str="Prolonged recovery time" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M20" type="Precipitant" span="57 9" str="narcotics" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M19" precipitant="M17" effect="M21" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M19" precipitant="M20" effect="M21" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4385" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>KETALAR should be used by or under the direction of physicians experienced in administering general anesthetics and in maintenance of an airway and in the control of respiration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4386" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because pharyngeal and laryngeal reflexes are usually active, KETALAR should not be used alone in surgery or diagnostic procedures of the pharynx, larynx, or bronchial tree.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4387" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Mechanical stimulation of the pharynx should be avoided, whenever possible, if KETALAR is used alone.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4388" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Muscle relaxants, with proper attention to respiration, may be required in both of these instances.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4389" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Resuscitative equipment should be ready for use.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4390" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The incidence of emergence reactions may be reduced if verbal and tactile stimulation of the patient is minimized during the recovery period.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4391" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>This does not preclude the monitoring of vital signs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4392" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The intravenous dose should be administered over a period of 60 seconds.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4393" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>More rapid administration may result in respiratory depression or apnea and enhanced pressor response.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4394" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In surgical procedures involving visceral pain pathways, KETALAR should be supplemented with an agent which obtunds visceral pain.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4395" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Use with caution in the chronic alcoholic and the acutely alcohol-intoxicated patient.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M22" type="Trigger" span="9 7" str="caution"/>
<Mention id="M23" type="Precipitant" span="32 7" str="alcohol" code="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M22" precipitant="M23"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4396" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>An increase in cerebrospinal fluid pressure has been reported following administration of ketamine hydrochloride.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4397" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Use with extreme caution in patients with preanesthetic elevated cerebrospinal fluid pressure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4398" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Carcinogenesis Long-term animal studies have not been conducted to evaluate the carcinogenic potential of ketamine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4399" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Mutagenesis In a published report, ketamine was clastogenic in the in vitro chromosomal aberration assay.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4400" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Impairment of Fertility Adequate studies to evaluate the impact of ketamine on male or female fertility have not been conducted.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4401" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Male and female rats were treated with 10 mg/kg ketamine IV (0.8 times the average human induction dose of 2 mg/kg IV based on body surface area) on Days 11, 10, and 9 prior to mating.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4402" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>No impact on fertility was noted; however, this study design does not adequately characterize the impact of a drug on fertility endpoints.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4403" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>There are no adequate and well-controlled studies of KETALAR in pregnant women.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4404" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In animal reproduction studies in rats developmental delays (hypoplasia of skeletal tissues) were noted at 0.3 times the human intramuscular dose of 10 mg/kg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4405" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In rabbits, developmental delays and increased fetal resorptions were noted at 0.6 times the human dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4406" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Published studies in pregnant primates demonstrate that the administration of anesthetic and sedation drugs that block NMDA receptors and/or potentiate GABA activity during the period of peak brain development increases neuronal apoptosis in the developing brain of the offspring when used for longer than 3 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4407" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>There are no data on pregnancy exposures in primates corresponding to periods prior to the third trimester in humans.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4408" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The estimated background risk of major birth defects and miscarriage for the indicated population is unknown.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4409" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>All pregnancies have a background risk of birth defect, loss, or other adverse outcomes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4410" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In the U.S. general population, the estimated background risk of major birth defects and miscarriage in clinically recognized pregnancies is 2-4% and 15-20%, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4411" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Since the safe use in pregnancy, including obstetrics (either vaginal or abdominal delivery), has not been established, such use is not recommended.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4412" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Animal Data Pregnant rats were treated intramuscularly with 20 mg/kg ketamine (0.3 times the human dose of 10 mg/kg IM based on body surface area) on either Gestation Days 6 to 10 or Gestation Days 11 to 15.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4413" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Ketamine treatment produced an increased incidence of hypoplastic skull, phalanges, and sternebrae in the pups.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4414" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Pregnant rabbits were treated intramuscularly with 20 mg/kg ketamine (0.6 times the human dose of 10 mg/kg IM based on body surface area) on either Gestation Days 6 to 10 or Gestation Days 11 to 15.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4415" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>An increase in resorptions and skeletal hypoplasia of the fetuses were noted.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4416" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Additional pregnant rabbits were treated intramuscularly with a single dose 60 mg/kg (1.9 times the human dose of 10 mg/kg IM based on body surface area) on Gestation Day 6 only.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4417" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Skeletal hypoplasia was reported in the fetuses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4418" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In a study where pregnant rats were treated intramuscularly with 20 mg/kg ketamine (0.3 times the human dose of 10 mg/kg IM based on body surface area) from Gestation Day 18 to 21.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4419" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>There was a slight increase in incidence of delayed parturition by one day in treated dams of this group.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4420" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>No adverse effects on the litters or pups were noted; however, learning and memory assessments were not completed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4421" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Three pregnant beagle dogs were treated intramuscularly with 25 mg/kg ketamine (1.3 times the human dose of 10 mg/kg IM based on body surface area) twice weekly for the three weeks of the first, second, and third trimesters of pregnancy, respectively, without the development of adverse effects in the pups.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4422" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In a published study in primates, administration of an anesthetic dose of ketamine for 24 hours on Gestation Day 122 increased neuronal apoptosis in the developing brain of the fetus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4423" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In other published studies, administration of either isoflurane or propofol for 5 hours on Gestation Day 120 resulted in increased neuronal and oligodendrocyte apoptosis in the developing brain of the offspring.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4424" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>With respect to brain development, this time period corresponds to the third trimester of gestation in the human.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4425" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The clinical significance of these findings is not clear; however, studies in juvenile animals suggest neuroapoptosis correlates with long-term cognitive deficits.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4426" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Risk of Drowsiness As appropriate, especially in cases where early discharge is possible, the duration of KETALAR and other drugs employed during the conduct of anesthesia should be considered.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4427" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The patients should be cautioned that driving an automobile, operating hazardous machinery or engaging in hazardous activities should not be undertaken for 24 hours or more (depending upon the dosage of KETALAR and consideration of other drugs employed) after anesthesia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4428" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Effect of anesthetic and sedation drugs on early brain development Studies conducted in young animals and children suggest repeated or prolonged use of general anesthetic or sedation drugs in children younger than 3 years may have negative effects on their developing brains.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4429" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Discuss with parents and caregivers the benefits, risks, and timing and duration of surgery or procedures requiring anesthetic and sedation drugs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4430" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Clinical studies of ketamine hydrochloride did not include sufficient numbers of subjects aged 65 and over to determine whether they respond differently from younger subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4431" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Other reported clinical experience has not identified differences in responses between the elderly and younger patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4432" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In general, dose selection for an elderly patient should be cautious, usually starting at the low end of the dosing range, reflecting the greater frequency of decreased hepatic, renal, or cardiac function, and of concomitant disease or other drug therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4433" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Safety and effectiveness in pediatric patients below the age of 16 have not been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4434" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Published juvenile animal studies demonstrate that the administration of anesthetic and sedation drugs, such as KETALAR, that either block NMDA receptors or potentiate the activity of GABA during the period of rapid brain growth or synaptogenesis, results in widespread neuronal and oligodendrocyte cell loss in the developing brain and alterations in synaptic morphology and neurogenesis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4435" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Based on comparisons across species, the window of vulnerability to these changes is believed to correlate with exposures in the third trimester of gestation through the first several months of life, but may extend out to approximately 3 years of age in humans.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4436" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In primates, exposure to 3 hours of ketamine that produced a light surgical plane of anesthesia did not increase neuronal cell loss, however, treatment regimens of 5 hours or longer of isoflurane increased neuronal cell loss.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4437" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Data from isoflurane-treated rodents and ketamine-treated primates suggest that the neuronal and oligodendrocyte cell losses are associated with prolonged cognitive deficits in learning and memory.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4438" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The clinical significance of these nonclinical findings is not known, and healthcare providers should balance the benefits of appropriate anesthesia in pregnant women, neonates, and young children who require procedures with the potential risks suggested by the nonclinical data.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4439" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Cardiac function should be continually monitored during the procedure in patients found to have hypertension or cardiac decompensation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4440" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Postoperative confusional states may occur during the recovery period.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4441" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Respiratory depression may occur with overdosage or too rapid a rate of administration of KETALAR, in which case supportive ventilation should be employed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4442" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Mechanical support of respiration is preferred to administration of analeptics.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4443" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Published animal studies demonstrate that the administration of anesthetic and sedation drugs that block NMDA receptors and/or potentiate GABA activity increase neuronal apoptosis in the developing brain and result in long-term cognitive deficits when used for longer than 3 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4444" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The clinical significance of these findings is not clear.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4445" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>However, based on the available data, the window of vulnerability to these changes is believed to correlate with exposures in the third trimester of gestation through the first several months of life, but may extend out to approximately three years of age in humans.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4446" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Some published studies in children suggest that similar deficits may occur after repeated or prolonged exposures to anesthetic agents early in life and may result in adverse cognitive or behavioral effects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4447" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>These studies have substantial limitations, and it is not clear if the observed effects are due to the anesthetic/sedation drug administration or other factors such as the surgery or underlying illness.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4448" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Anesthetic and sedation drugs are a necessary part of the care of children needing surgery, other procedures, or tests that cannot be delayed, and no specific medications have been shown to be safer than any other.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4449" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Decisions regarding the timing of any elective procedures requiring anesthesia should take into consideration the benefits of the procedure weighed against the potential risks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4450" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>KETALAR is a rapid-acting general anesthetic producing an anesthetic state characterized by profound analgesia, normal pharyngeal-laryngeal reflexes, normal or slightly enhanced skeletal muscle tone, cardiovascular and respiratory stimulation, and occasionally a transient and minimal respiratory depression.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4451" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mechanism of action is primarily due to antagonism of N-methyl-D-aspartate (NMDA receptors) in the central nervous system.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4452" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A patent airway is maintained partly by virtue of unimpaired pharyngeal and laryngeal reflexes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4453" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The biotransformation of KETALAR includes N-dealkylation (metabolite I), hydroxylation of the cyclohexone ring (metabolites III and IV), conjugation with glucuronic acid and dehydration of the hydroxylated metabolites to form the cyclohexene derivative (metabolite II).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4454" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following intravenous administration, the ketamine concentration has an initial slope (alpha phase) lasting about 45 minutes with a half-life of 10 to 15 minutes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4455" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This first phase corresponds clinically to the anesthetic effect of the drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4456" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The anesthetic action is terminated by a combination of redistribution from the CNS to slower equilibrating peripheral tissues and by hepatic biotransformation to metabolite I.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4457" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This metabolite is about 1/3 as active as ketamine in reducing halothane requirements (MAC) of the rat.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4458" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The later half-life of ketamine (beta phase) is 2.5 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4459" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The anesthetic state produced by KETALAR has been termed dissociative anesthesia in that it appears to selectively interrupt association pathways of the brain before producing somatesthetic sensory blockade.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4460" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>It may selectively depress the thalamoneocortical system before significantly obtunding the more ancient cerebral centers and pathways (reticular-activating and limbic systems).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4461" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Elevation of blood pressure begins shortly after injection, reaches a maximum within a few minutes and usually returns to preanesthetic values within 15 minutes after injection.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4462" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In the majority of cases, the systolic and diastolic blood pressure peaks from 10% to 50% above preanesthetic levels shortly after induction of anesthesia, but the elevation can be higher or longer in individual cases.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4463" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Ketamine has a wide margin of safety; several instances of unintentional administration of overdoses of KETALAR (up to ten times that usually required) have been followed by prolonged but complete recovery.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4464" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>KETALAR has been studied in over 12,000 operative and diagnostic procedures, involving over 10,000 patients from 105 separate studies.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4465" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>During the course of these studies KETALAR was administered as the sole agent, as induction for other general agents, or to supplement low-potency agents.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4466" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Specific areas of application have included the following: 1. debridement, painful dressings, and skin grafting in burn patients, as well as other superficial surgical procedures.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4467" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>2. neurodiagnostic procedures such as pneumonencephalograms, ventriculograms, myelograms, and lumbar punctures.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4468" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>See also Precaution concerning increased intracranial pressure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4469" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>3. diagnostic and operative procedures of the eye, ear, nose, and mouth, including dental extractions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4470" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>4. diagnostic and operative procedures of the pharynx, larynx, or bronchial tree.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4471" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>NOTE: Muscle relaxants, with proper attention to respiration, may be required.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4472" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>5. sigmoidoscopy and minor surgery of the anus and rectum, and circumcision.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4473" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>6. extraperitoneal procedures used in gynecology such as dilatation and curettage.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4474" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>7. orthopedic procedures such as closed reductions, manipulations, femoral pinning, amputations, and biopsies.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4475" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>8. as an anesthetic in poor-risk patients with depression of vital functions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4476" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>9. in procedures where the intramuscular route of administration is preferred.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4477" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>10. in cardiac catheterization procedures.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4478" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In these studies, the anesthesia was rated either excellent or good by the anesthesiologist and the surgeon at 90% and 93%, respectively; rated fair at 6% and 4%, respectively; and rated poor at 4% and 3%, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4479" LabelDrug="Ketalar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In a second method of evaluation, the anesthesia was rated adequate in at least 90%, and inadequate in 10% or less of the procedures.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="barbiturates" precipitantCode="N0000175693 | N0000008016" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="diazepam" precipitantCode="Q3JTX2Q7TU"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="anesthetics" precipitantCode="N0000029138 | N0000175681" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="muscle relaxants" precipitantCode="N0000175737" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="narcotics" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="alcohol" precipitantCode="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>