<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="ASMANEX HFA" setid="1f608abd-d414-41e9-89bd-32dd2ef33cb8">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
Primary treatment of status asthmaticus or acute episodes of asthma requiring intensive measures. ( 4.1 ) Hypersensitivity to any of the ingredients of ASMANEX HFA. ( 4.2 ) ASMANEX HFA is contraindicated in the primary treatment of status asthmaticus or other acute episodes of asthma where intensive measures are required. ASMANEX HFA is contraindicated in patients with known hypersensitivity to mometasone furoate or any of the ingredients in ASMANEX HFA [see Warnings and Precautions (5.8) ] .</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
For oral inhalation only. ( 2.1 ) Treatment of asthma in patients 12 years of age and older: 2 inhalations twice daily of ASMANEX HFA 100 mcg or 200 mcg. ( 2.2 ) Starting dosage is based on prior asthma therapy. ( 2.2 ) ASMANEX HFA should be administered only by the orally inhaled route [see Instructions for Use in the Patient Information leaflet ] . After each dose, the patient should be advised to rinse his/her mouth with water without swallowing. The cap from the mouthpiece of the actuator should be removed before using ASMANEX HFA. ASMANEX HFA should be primed before using for the first time by releasing 4 test sprays into the air, away from the face, shaking well before each spray. In cases where the inhaler has not been used for more than 5 days, prime the inhaler again by releasing 4 test sprays into the air, away from the face, shaking well before each spray. The ASMANEX HFA canister should only be used with the ASMANEX HFA actuator. The ASMANEX HFA actuator should not be used with any other inhalation drug product. Actuators from other products should not be used with the ASMANEX HFA canister. ASMANEX HFA should be administered as two inhalations twice daily every day (morning and evening) by the orally inhaled route. Shake well prior to each inhalation. The recommended doses for ASMANEX HFA treatment based on prior asthma therapy are provided in Table 1 . TABLE 1: Recommended Dosages for ASMANEX HFA Treatment Previous Therapy Recommended Dose Inhaled medium-dose corticosteroids ASMANEX HFA 100 mcg, 2 inhalations twice daily Inhaled high-dose corticosteroids ASMANEX HFA 200 mcg, 2 inhalations twice daily Oral corticosteroids For Patients Currently Receiving Chronic Oral Corticosteroid Therapy: Prednisone should be weaned slowly, beginning after at least 1 week of ASMANEX HFA therapy. Monitor patients carefully for signs of asthma instability, including serial objective measures of airflow, and for signs of adrenal insufficiency during steroid taper and following discontinuation of oral corticosteroid therapy [see Warnings and Precautions (5.4) ] . ASMANEX HFA 200 mcg, 2 inhalations twice daily If a dosage regimen of ASMANEX HFA fails to provide adequate control of asthma, the therapeutic regimen should be re-evaluated and additional therapeutic options, e.g., replacing the current strength of ASMANEX HFA with a higher strength, initiating an inhaled corticosteroid and long-acting beta 2 -agonist combination product, or initiating oral corticosteroids, should be considered. The maximum daily recommended dose is two inhalations of ASMANEX HFA 200 mcg twice daily (maximum of 800 mcg a day). If symptoms arise between doses, an inhaled short-acting beta 2 -agonist should be taken for immediate relief. The maximum benefit may not be achieved for 1 week or longer after beginning treatment. Individual patients may experience a variable time to onset and degree of symptom relief. For patients who do not respond adequately after 2 weeks of therapy, higher strength may provide additional asthma control. After asthma stability has been achieved, it is desirable to titrate to the lowest effective dosage to reduce the possibility of side effects.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
In clinical trials, concurrent administration of ASMANEX HFA and other drugs, such as short-acting beta 2 -agonist and intranasal corticosteroids have not resulted in an increased frequency of adverse drug reactions. No formal drug interaction studies have been performed with ASMANEX HFA. Strong cytochrome P450 3A4 inhibitors (e.g., ritonavir): Use with caution. May cause increased systemic corticosteroid effects. ( 7.1 ) The main route of metabolism of corticosteroids, including mometasone furoate, is via CYP3A4. After oral administration of ketoconazole, a strong inhibitor of CYP3A4, the mean plasma concentration of orally inhaled mometasone furoate increased. Concomitant administration of CYP3A4 inhibitors may inhibit the metabolism of, and increase the systemic exposure to, mometasone furoate and potentially increase the risk for systemic corticosteroid side effects. Caution should be exercised when considering the coadministration of ASMANEX HFA with long-term ketoconazole and other known strong CYP3A4 inhibitors (e.g., ritonavir, cobicistat-containing products, atazanavir, clarithromycin, indinavir, itraconazole, nefazodone, nelfinavir, saquinavir, telithromycin) [see Warnings and Precautions (5.6) and Clinical Pharmacology (12.3) ] . Consider the benefit of coadministration versus the potential risk of systemic corticosteroid effects, in which case patients should be monitored for systemic corticosteroid side effects.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
Deterioration of asthma and acute episodes: ASMANEX HFA should not be used for relief of acute symptoms. Patients require immediate re-evaluation during rapidly deteriorating asthma. ( 5.1 ) Localized infections: Candida albicans infection of the mouth and throat may occur. Monitor patients periodically for signs of adverse effects on the oral cavity. Advise patients to rinse the mouth following inhalation. ( 5.2 ) Immunosuppression: Potential worsening of existing tuberculosis, fungal, bacterial, viral, or parasitic infection; or ocular herpes simplex infections. More serious or even fatal course of chickenpox or measles can occur in susceptible patients. Use with caution in patients with these infections because of the potential for worsening of these infections. ( 5.3 ) Transferring patients from systemic corticosteroids: Risk of impaired adrenal function when transferring from oral steroids. Wean patients slowly from systemic corticosteroids if transferring to ASMANEX HFA. ( 5.4 ) Hypercorticism and adrenal suppression: May occur with very high dosages or at the regular dosage in susceptible individuals. If such changes occur, discontinue ASMANEX HFA slowly. ( 5.5 ) Strong cytochrome P450 3A4 inhibitors (e.g., ritonavir): Risk of increased systemic corticosteroid effects. Exercise caution when used with ASMANEX HFA. ( 5.6 ) Paradoxical bronchospasm: Discontinue ASMANEX HFA and institute alternative therapy if paradoxical bronchospasm occurs. ( 5.7 ) Hypersensitivity reactions including anaphylaxis: Hypersensitivity reactions, such as urticaria, flushing, allergic dermatitis, bronchospasm, rash, pruritus, angioedema, and anaphylactic reaction may occur. Discontinue ASMANEX HFA if such reactions occur. ( 5.8 ) Decreases in bone mineral density: Monitor patients with major risk factors for decreased bone mineral content. ( 5.9 ) Effects on growth: Monitor growth of pediatric patients. ( 5.10 ) Glaucoma and cataracts: Consider referral to an ophthalmologist in patients who develop ocular symptoms or use ASMANEX HFA long term. ( 5.11 ) ASMANEX HFA is not indicated for the relief of acute symptoms, i.e., as rescue therapy for the treatment of acute episodes of bronchospasm. An inhaled, short-acting beta 2 -agonist, not ASMANEX HFA, should be used to relieve acute symptoms such as shortness of breath. When prescribing ASMANEX HFA, the physician must also provide the patient with an inhaled, short-acting beta 2 -agonist (e.g., albuterol) for treatment of acute symptoms, despite regular twice-daily (morning and evening) use of ASMANEX HFA. Instruct patients to contact their physician immediately if episodes of asthma that are not responsive to bronchodilators occur during the course of treatment with ASMANEX HFA. During such episodes, patients may require therapy with oral corticosteroids. In clinical trials, the development of localized infections of the mouth and pharynx with Candida albicans have occurred in patients treated with ASMANEX HFA. If oropharyngeal candidiasis develops, it should be treated with appropriate local or systemic (i.e., oral) antifungal therapy while remaining on treatment with ASMANEX HFA therapy, but at times therapy with ASMANEX HFA may need to be interrupted. Advise patients to rinse the mouth after inhalation of ASMANEX HFA. Persons who are using drugs that suppress the immune system are more susceptible to infections than healthy individuals. Chickenpox and measles, for example, can have a more serious or even fatal course in susceptible children or adults using corticosteroids. In such children or adults who have not had these diseases or who are not properly immunized, particular care should be taken to avoid exposure. How the dose, route, and duration of corticosteroid administration affect the risk of developing a disseminated infection is not known. The contribution of the underlying disease and/or prior corticosteroid treatment to the risk is also not known. If exposed to chickenpox, prophylaxis with varicella zoster immune globulin (VZIG) or pooled intravenous immunoglobulin (IVIG) may be indicated. If exposed to measles, prophylaxis with pooled intramuscular immunoglobulin (IG) may be indicated. (See the respective package inserts for complete VZIG and IG prescribing information.) If chickenpox develops, treatment with antiviral agents may be considered. Inhaled corticosteroids should be used with caution, if at all, in patients with active or quiescent tuberculosis infection of the respiratory tract, untreated systemic fungal, bacterial, viral, or parasitic infections; or ocular herpes simplex. Particular care is needed for patients who are transferred from systemically active corticosteroids to ASMANEX HFA because deaths due to adrenal insufficiency have occurred in asthmatic patients during and after transfer from systemic corticosteroids to less systemically available inhaled corticosteroids. After withdrawal from systemic corticosteroids, a number of months are required for recovery of hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) function. Patients who have been previously maintained on 20 mg or more per day of prednisone (or its equivalent) may be most susceptible, particularly when their systemic corticosteroids have been almost completely withdrawn. During this period of HPA suppression, patients may exhibit signs and symptoms of adrenal insufficiency when exposed to trauma, surgery, or infection (particularly gastroenteritis) or other conditions associated with severe electrolyte loss. Although ASMANEX HFA may improve control of asthma symptoms during these episodes, in recommended doses it supplies less than normal physiological amounts of corticosteroid systemically and does NOT provide the mineralocorticoid activity necessary for coping with these emergencies. During periods of stress or severe asthma attack, patients who have been withdrawn from systemic corticosteroids should be instructed to resume oral corticosteroids (in large doses) immediately and to contact their physicians for further instruction. These patients should also be instructed to carry a medical identification card indicating that they may need supplementary systemic corticosteroids during periods of stress or severe asthma attack. Patients requiring oral or other systemic corticosteroids should be weaned slowly from oral or other systemic corticosteroid use after transferring to ASMANEX HFA. Lung function (FEV 1 or PEF), beta-agonist use, and asthma symptoms should be carefully monitored during withdrawal of oral or other systemic corticosteroids. In addition to monitoring asthma signs and symptoms, patients should be observed for signs and symptoms of adrenal insufficiency such as fatigue, lassitude, weakness, nausea and vomiting, and hypotension. Transfer of patients from systemic corticosteroid therapy to ASMANEX HFA may unmask allergic conditions previously suppressed by the systemic corticosteroid therapy, e.g., rhinitis, conjunctivitis, eczema, arthritis, and eosinophilic conditions. During withdrawal from oral corticosteroids, some patients may experience symptoms of systemically active corticosteroid withdrawal, e.g., joint and/or muscular pain, lassitude, and depression, despite maintenance or even improvement of respiratory function. ASMANEX HFA will often help control asthma symptoms with less suppression of HPA function than therapeutically equivalent oral doses of prednisone. Since mometasone furoate is absorbed into the circulation and can be systemically active at higher doses, the beneficial effects of ASMANEX HFA in minimizing HPA dysfunction may be expected only when recommended dosages are not exceeded and individual patients are titrated to the lowest effective dose. Because of the possibility of systemic absorption of inhaled corticosteroids, patients treated with ASMANEX HFA should be observed carefully for any evidence of systemic corticosteroid effects. Particular care should be taken in observing patients postoperatively or during periods of stress for evidence of inadequate adrenal response. It is possible that systemic corticosteroid effects such as hypercorticism and adrenal suppression (including adrenal crisis) may appear in a small number of patients, particularly when mometasone furoate is administered at higher than recommended doses over prolonged periods of time. If such effects occur, the dosage of ASMANEX HFA should be reduced slowly, consistent with accepted procedures for reducing systemic corticosteroids and for management of asthma symptoms. Caution should be exercised when considering the coadministration of ASMANEX HFA with ketoconazole, and other known strong cytochrome P450 (CYP) isoenzyme 3A4 (CYP3A4) inhibitors (e.g., ritonavir, cobicistat-containing products, atazanavir, clarithromycin, indinavir, itraconazole, nefazodone, nelfinavir, saquinavir, telithromycin) because adverse effects related to increased systemic exposure to mometasone furoate may occur [see Drug Interactions (7.1) and Clinical Pharmacology (12.3) ]. ASMANEX HFA may produce inhalation induced bronchospasm with an immediate increase in wheezing after dosing that may be life-threatening. If inhalation induced bronchospasm occurs, it should be treated immediately with an inhaled, short-acting bronchodilator. ASMANEX HFA should be discontinued immediately and alternative therapy instituted. Hypersensitivity reactions such as urticaria, flushing, allergic dermatitis, and bronchospasm, may occur after administration of ASMANEX HFA. Discontinue ASMANEX HFA if such reactions occur [see Contraindications (4.2) ]. The following additional hypersensitivity reactions, such as rash, pruritus, angioedema, and anaphylactic reaction, have been reported after administration of mometasone furoate dry powder inhaler [see Adverse Reactions (6.2) ]. Decreases in bone mineral density (BMD) have been observed with long-term administration of products containing inhaled corticosteroids, including mometasone furoate. The clinical significance of small changes in BMD with regard to long-term outcomes, such as fracture, is unknown. Patients with major risk factors for decreased bone mineral content, such as prolonged immobilization, family history of osteoporosis, or chronic use of drugs that can reduce bone mass (e.g., anticonvulsants and corticosteroids) should be monitored and treated with established standards of care. In a 2-year double-blind study in 103 male and female asthma patients 18 to 50 years of age previously maintained on bronchodilator therapy (Baseline FEV 1 85%-88% predicted), treatment with mometasone furoate dry powder inhaler 200 mcg twice daily resulted in significant reductions in lumbar spine (LS) BMD at the end of the treatment period compared to placebo. The mean change from Baseline to Endpoint in the lumbar spine BMD was -0.015 (-1.43%) for the mometasone furoate dry powder inhaler group compared to 0.002 (0.25%) for the placebo group. In another 2-year double-blind study in 87 male and female asthma patients 18 to 50 years of age previously maintained on bronchodilator therapy (Baseline FEV 1 82%-83% predicted), treatment with mometasone furoate dry powder inhaler 400 mcg twice daily demonstrated no statistically significant changes in lumbar spine BMD at the end of the treatment period compared to placebo. The mean change from Baseline to Endpoint in the lumbar spine BMD was -0.018 (-1.57%) for the mometasone furoate group compared to -0.006 (-0.43%) for the placebo group. Orally inhaled corticosteroids, including ASMANEX HFA, may cause a reduction in growth velocity when administered to pediatric patients. Monitor the growth of pediatric patients receiving ASMANEX HFA routinely (e.g., via stadiometry). To minimize the systemic effects of orally inhaled corticosteroids, including ASMANEX HFA, titrate each patient's dose to the lowest dosage that effectively controls his/her symptoms [see Use in Specific Populations (8.4) ] . Glaucoma, increased intraocular pressure, and cataracts have been reported following the use of long-term administration of inhaled corticosteroids, including mometasone furoate. Consider referral to an ophthalmologist in patients who develop ocular symptoms or use ASMANEX HFA long term [see Adverse Reactions (6) ] .</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Mometasone furoate is a corticosteroid demonstrating potent anti-inflammatory activity. The precise mechanism of corticosteroid action on asthma is not known. Inflammation is an important component in the pathogenesis of asthma. Corticosteroids have been shown to have a wide range of inhibitory effects on multiple cell types (e.g., mast cells, eosinophils, neutrophils, macrophages, and lymphocytes) and mediators (e.g., histamine, eicosanoids, leukotrienes, and cytokines) involved in inflammation and in the asthmatic response. These anti-inflammatory actions of corticosteroids may contribute to their efficacy in asthma. Mometasone furoate has been shown in vitro to exhibit a binding affinity for the human glucocorticoid receptor, which is approximately 12 times that of dexamethasone, 7 times that of triamcinolone acetonide, 5 times that of budesonide, and 1.5 times that of fluticasone. The clinical significance of these findings is unknown. HPA Axis Effects The effects of inhaled mometasone furoate administered via ASMANEX HFA on adrenal function have not been directly evaluated. However, the effects of inhaled mometasone furoate, administered as part of a mometasone furoate/formoterol fumarate inhalation aerosol combination product, on adrenal function were evaluated in two clinical trials in patients with asthma. As no evidence of a pharmacokinetic drug interaction between mometasone furoate and formoterol was observed when the two drugs were administered in combination, the HPA axis effects from the combination product are applicable to ASMANEX HFA. For the mometasone furoate/formoterol fumarate combination product clinical program, HPA-axis function was assessed by 24-hour plasma cortisol AUC. Although both these trials have open-label design and contain a small number of subjects per treatment arm, results from these trials taken together demonstrated suppression of 24-hour plasma cortisol AUC for the combination mometasone furoate/formoterol fumarate 200 mcg/5 mcg compared to placebo consistent with the known systemic effects of inhaled corticosteroid. In a 42-day, open-label, placebo- and active-controlled study, the mean change from baseline plasma cortisol AUC (0-24 hr) was 8%, 22% and 34% lower compared to placebo for the mometasone furoate/formoterol fumarate 100 mcg/5 mcg (n=13), mometasone furoate/formoterol fumarate 200 mcg/5 mcg (n=15) and fluticasone propionate/salmeterol xinafoate 230 mcg/21 mcg (n=16) treatment groups, respectively. In a 52-week, open-label safety study, the mean plasma cortisol AUC (0-24 hr) was 2.2%, 29.6%, 16.7%, and 32.2% lower from baseline for the mometasone furoate/formoterol fumarate 100 mcg/5 mcg (n=18), mometasone furoate/formoterol fumarate 200 mcg/5 mcg (n=20), fluticasone propionate/salmeterol xinafoate 125/25 mcg (n=8), and fluticasone propionate/salmeterol xinafoate 250/25 mcg (n=11) treatment groups, respectively. The potential effect of mometasone furoate via a dry powder inhaler (DPI) on the HPA axis was also assessed in a 29-day study. A total of 64 adult patients with mild to moderate asthma were randomized to one of 4 treatment groups: mometasone furoate DPI 440 mcg twice daily, mometasone furoate DPI 880 mcg twice daily, oral prednisone 10 mg once daily, or placebo. The 30-minute post-Cosyntropin stimulation serum cortisol concentration on Day 29 was 23.2 mcg/dL for the mometasone furoate DPI 440 mcg twice daily group and 20.8 mcg/dL for the mometasone furoate DPI 880 mcg twice daily group, compared to 14.5 mcg/dL for the oral prednisone 10 mg group and 25 mcg/dL for the placebo group. The difference between mometasone furoate DPI 880 mcg twice daily (twice the maximum recommended dose) and placebo was statistically significant. As no evidence of a pharmacokinetic drug interaction between mometasone furoate and formoterol was observed when the two drugs were administered from a mometasone furoate/formoterol fumarate combination product, the pharmacokinetics information from the combination product is applicable to ASMANEX HFA. Absorption Healthy Subjects: Following oral inhalation of single doses of ASMANEX HFA, mometasone furoate was absorbed in healthy subjects with median T max values ranging from 0.50 to 2 hours. Following single-dose administration of higher than recommended dose of ASMANEX HFA (4 inhalations of ASMANEX HFA 200 mcg) in healthy subjects, the arithmetic mean (CV%) C max and AUC (0-tf) values for mometasone furoate were 53 (102) pg/mL and 992 (80) pg∙hr/mL, respectively. Studies using oral dosing of labeled and unlabeled drug have demonstrated that the oral systemic bioavailability of mometasone furoate is negligible (&amp;lt;1%). Asthma Patients: Following oral inhalation of single and multiple doses of the mometasone furoate/formoterol fumarate combination product, mometasone furoate was absorbed in asthma patients with median T max values ranging from 1 to 2 hours. Following single-dose administration of mometasone furoate/formoterol fumarate 400 mcg/10 mcg, the arithmetic mean (CV%) C max and AUC (0-12 hr) values for mometasone furoate were 20 (88) pg/mL and 170 (94) pg∙hr/mL, respectively, while the corresponding estimates following twice daily dosing of mometasone furoate/formoterol fumarate 400 mcg/10 mcg at steady-state were 60 (36) pg/mL and 577 (40) pg∙hr/mL. Distribution Based on the study employing a 1000 mcg inhaled dose of tritiated mometasone furoate inhalation powder in humans, no appreciable accumulation of mometasone furoate in the red blood cells was found. Following an intravenous 400 mcg dose of mometasone furoate, the plasma concentrations showed a biphasic decline, with a mean steady-state volume of distribution of 152 liters. The in vitro protein binding for mometasone furoate was reported to be 98% to 99% (in a concentration range of 5 to 500 ng/mL). Metabolism Studies have shown that mometasone furoate is primarily and extensively metabolized in the liver of all species investigated and undergoes extensive metabolism to multiple metabolites. In vitro studies have confirmed the primary role of human liver CYP3A4 in the metabolism of this compound; however, no major metabolites were identified. Human liver CYP3A4 metabolizes mometasone furoate to 6-beta hydroxy mometasone furoate. Excretion Following an intravenous dosing, the terminal half-life was reported to be about 5 hours. Following the inhaled dose of tritiated 1000 mcg mometasone furoate, the radioactivity is excreted mainly in the feces (a mean of 74%), and to a small extent in the urine (a mean of 8%) up to 7 days. No radioactivity was associated with unchanged mometasone furoate in the urine. Absorbed mometasone furoate is cleared from plasma at a rate of approximately 12.5 mL/min/kg, independent of dose. The effective t ½ for mometasone furoate following inhalation with DULERA was 25 hours in healthy subjects and in patients with asthma. Special Populations Hepatic/Renal Impairment: There are no data regarding the specific use of ASMANEX HFA in patients with hepatic or renal impairment. A study evaluating the administration of a single inhaled dose of 400 mcg mometasone furoate by a dry powder inhaler to subjects with mild (n=4), moderate (n=4), and severe (n=4) hepatic impairment resulted in only 1 or 2 subjects in each group having detectable peak plasma concentrations of mometasone furoate (ranging from 50-105 pg/mL). The observed peak plasma concentrations appear to increase with severity of hepatic impairment; however, the numbers of detectable levels were few. Gender and Race: Specific studies to examine the effects of gender and race on the pharmacokinetics of ASMANEX HFA have not been specifically studied. Geriatrics: The pharmacokinetics of ASMANEX HFA have not been specifically studied in the elderly population. Drug-Drug Interactions A single-dose crossover study was conducted to compare the pharmacokinetics of 4 inhalations of the following: mometasone furoate MDI, formoterol MDI, mometasone furoate/formoterol fumarate MDI combination product, and mometasone furoate MDI plus formoterol fumarate MDI administered concurrently. The results of the study indicated that there was no evidence of a pharmacokinetic interaction between mometasone furoate and formoterol. Inhibitors of Cytochrome P450 Enzymes: Ketoconazole: In a drug interaction study, an inhaled dose of mometasone furoate 400 mcg delivered by a dry powder inhaler was given to 24 healthy subjects twice daily for 9 days and ketoconazole 200 mg (as well as placebo) were given twice daily concomitantly on Days 4 to 9. Mometasone furoate plasma concentrations were &amp;lt;150 pg/mL on Day 3 prior to coadministration of ketoconazole or placebo. Following concomitant administration of ketoconazole, 4 out of 12 subjects in the ketoconazole treatment group (n=12) had peak plasma concentrations of mometasone furoate &amp;gt;200 pg/mL on Day 9 (211-324 pg/mL). Mometasone furoate plasma levels appeared to increase and plasma cortisol levels appeared to decrease upon concomitant administration of ketoconazole.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="586" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Primary treatment of status asthmaticus or acute episodes of asthma requiring intensive measures.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="587" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Hypersensitivity to any of the ingredients of ASMANEX HFA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="588" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>ASMANEX HFA is contraindicated in the primary treatment of status asthmaticus or other acute episodes of asthma where intensive measures are required.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="589" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>ASMANEX HFA is contraindicated in patients with known hypersensitivity to mometasone furoate or any of the ingredients in ASMANEX HFA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="590" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Treatment of asthma in patients 12 years of age and older: 2 inhalations twice daily of ASMANEX HFA 100 mcg or 200 mcg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="591" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Starting dosage is based on prior asthma therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="592" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>ASMANEX HFA should be administered only by the orally inhaled route.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="593" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>After each dose, the patient should be advised to rinse his/her mouth with water without swallowing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="594" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The cap from the mouthpiece of the actuator should be removed before using ASMANEX HFA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="595" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>ASMANEX HFA should be primed before using for the first time by releasing 4 test sprays into the air, away from the face, shaking well before each spray.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="596" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In cases where the inhaler has not been used for more than 5 days, prime the inhaler again by releasing 4 test sprays into the air, away from the face, shaking well before each spray.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="597" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The ASMANEX HFA canister should only be used with the ASMANEX HFA actuator.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="598" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The ASMANEX HFA actuator should not be used with any other inhalation drug product.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="599" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Actuators from other products should not be used with the ASMANEX HFA canister.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="600" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>ASMANEX HFA should be administered as two inhalations twice daily every day (morning and evening) by the orally inhaled route.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="601" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommended doses for ASMANEX HFA treatment based on prior asthma therapy are provided in Table 1.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="602" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>TABLE 1: Recommended Dosages for ASMANEX HFA Treatment Previous Therapy Recommended Dose Inhaled medium-dose corticosteroids ASMANEX HFA 100 mcg, 2 inhalations twice daily Inhaled high-dose corticosteroids ASMANEX HFA 200 mcg, 2 inhalations twice daily Oral corticosteroids For Patients Currently Receiving Chronic Oral Corticosteroid Therapy: Prednisone should be weaned slowly, beginning after at least 1 week of ASMANEX HFA therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="603" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor patients carefully for signs of asthma instability, including serial objective measures of airflow, and for signs of adrenal insufficiency during steroid taper and following discontinuation of oral corticosteroid therapy.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M1" type="Trigger" span="0 7;172 25" str="Monitor | following discontinuation"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="201 27" str="oral corticosteroid therapy" code="N0000175576"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M1" precipitant="M2"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="604" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>ASMANEX HFA 200 mcg, 2 inhalations twice daily If a dosage regimen of ASMANEX HFA fails to provide adequate control of asthma, the therapeutic regimen should be re-evaluated and additional therapeutic options, e.g., replacing the current strength of ASMANEX HFA with a higher strength, initiating an inhaled corticosteroid and long-acting beta2-agonist combination product, or initiating oral corticosteroids, should be considered.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="605" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The maximum daily recommended dose is two inhalations of ASMANEX HFA 200 mcg twice daily (maximum of 800 mcg a day).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="606" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If symptoms arise between doses, an inhaled short-acting beta2-agonist should be taken for immediate relief.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="607" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The maximum benefit may not be achieved for 1 week or longer after beginning treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="608" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Individual patients may experience a variable time to onset and degree of symptom relief.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="609" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For patients who do not respond adequately after 2 weeks of therapy, higher strength may provide additional asthma control.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="610" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>After asthma stability has been achieved, it is desirable to titrate to the lowest effective dosage to reduce the possibility of side effects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="611" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>In clinical trials, concurrent administration of ASMANEX HFA and other drugs, such as short-acting beta2-agonist and intranasal corticosteroids have not resulted in an increased frequency of adverse drug reactions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="612" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>No formal drug interaction studies have been performed with ASMANEX HFA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="613" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Strong cytochrome P450 3A4 inhibitors (e.g., ritonavir): Use with caution.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M5" type="Trigger" span="66 7" str="caution"/>
<Mention id="M4" type="Precipitant" span="45 9" str="ritonavir" code="O3J8G9O825 | N0000007423"/>
<Mention id="M6" type="Precipitant" span="0 37" str="Strong cytochrome P450 3A4 inhibitors" code="N0000182141"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M5" precipitant="M4"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M5" precipitant="M6"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="614" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>May cause increased systemic corticosteroid effects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="615" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The main route of metabolism of corticosteroids, including mometasone furoate, is via CYP3A4.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="616" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>After oral administration of ketoconazole, a strong inhibitor of CYP3A4, the mean plasma concentration of orally inhaled mometasone furoate increased.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M9" type="Trigger" span="82 20;140 9" str="plasma concentration | increased"/>
<Mention id="M8" type="Precipitant" span="29 12" str="ketoconazole" code="N0000007319 | R9400W927I"/>
<Mention id="M10" type="Precipitant" span="45 26" str="strong inhibitor of CYP3A4" code="N0000182141"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M9" precipitant="M8" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M9" precipitant="M10" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="617" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant administration of CYP3A4 inhibitors may inhibit the metabolism of, and increase the systemic exposure to, mometasone furoate and potentially increase the risk for systemic corticosteroid side effects.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M11" type="Trigger" span="153 17" str="increase the risk "/>
<Mention id="M12" type="Trigger" span="199 12" str=" side effects"/>
<Mention id="M17" type="Precipitant" span="30 17" str="CYP3A4 inhibitors" code="N0000182141"/>
<Mention id="M14" type="SpecificInteraction" span="175 36" str="systemic corticosteroid side effects" code="293141009: Corticosteroids adverse reaction (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M15" type="Trigger" span="52 22" str="inhibit the metabolism "/>
<Mention id="M16" type="Trigger" span="83 30" str=" increase the systemic exposure"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M11;M12" precipitant="M17" effect="M14" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M15;M16" precipitant="M17" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="618" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Caution should be exercised when considering the coadministration of ASMANEX HFA with long-term ketoconazole and other known strong CYP3A4 inhibitors (e.g., ritonavir, cobicistat-containing products, atazanavir, clarithromycin, indinavir, itraconazole, nefazodone, nelfinavir, saquinavir, telithromycin).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M42" type="Trigger" span="0 7" str="Caution"/>
<Mention id="M19" type="Precipitant" span="200 10" str="atazanavir" code="N0000022320 | QZU4H47A3S"/>
<Mention id="M21" type="Precipitant" span="212 14" str="clarithromycin" code="H1250JIK0A | N0000007316"/>
<Mention id="M23" type="Precipitant" span="168 10" str="cobicistat" code="LW2E03M5PG"/>
<Mention id="M25" type="Precipitant" span="168 30" str="cobicistat-containing products" code="LW2E03M5PG | N0000191982"/>
<Mention id="M27" type="Precipitant" span="228 9" str="indinavir" code="N0000005722 | 5W6YA9PKKH"/>
<Mention id="M29" type="Precipitant" span="239 12" str="itraconazole" code="304NUG5GF4 | N0000006753"/>
<Mention id="M31" type="Precipitant" span="96 12" str="ketoconazole" code="N0000007319 | R9400W927I"/>
<Mention id="M33" type="Precipitant" span="253 10" str="nefazodone" code="N0000007250 | 59H4FCV1TF"/>
<Mention id="M35" type="Precipitant" span="265 10" str="nelfinavir" code="HO3OGH5D7I | N0000006047"/>
<Mention id="M37" type="Precipitant" span="157 9" str="ritonavir" code="O3J8G9O825 | N0000007423"/>
<Mention id="M39" type="Precipitant" span="277 10" str="saquinavir" code="N0000007376 | L3JE09KZ2F"/>
<Mention id="M41" type="Precipitant" span="125 24" str="strong CYP3A4 inhibitors" code="N0000182141"/>
<Mention id="M43" type="Precipitant" span="289 13" str="telithromycin" code="N0000010551 | KI8H7H19WL"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M42" precipitant="M19"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M42" precipitant="M21"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M42" precipitant="M23"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M42" precipitant="M25"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M42" precipitant="M27"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M42" precipitant="M29"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M42" precipitant="M31"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M42" precipitant="M33"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M42" precipitant="M35"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M42" precipitant="M37"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M42" precipitant="M39"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M42" precipitant="M41"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M42" precipitant="M43"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="619" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Consider the benefit of coadministration versus the potential risk of systemic corticosteroid effects, in which case patients should be monitored for systemic corticosteroid side effects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="620" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Deterioration of asthma and acute episodes: ASMANEX HFA should not be used for relief of acute symptoms.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="621" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients require immediate re-evaluation during rapidly deteriorating asthma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="622" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Localized infections: Candida albicans infection of the mouth and throat may occur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="623" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor patients periodically for signs of adverse effects on the oral cavity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="624" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Advise patients to rinse the mouth following inhalation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="625" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Immunosuppression: Potential worsening of existing tuberculosis, fungal, bacterial, viral, or parasitic infection; or ocular herpes simplex infections.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="626" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>More serious or even fatal course of chickenpox or measles can occur in susceptible patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="627" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Use with caution in patients with these infections because of the potential for worsening of these infections.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="628" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Transferring patients from systemic corticosteroids: Risk of impaired adrenal function when transferring from oral steroids.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M47" type="Trigger" span="53 7" str="Risk of"/>
<Mention id="M45" type="Precipitant" span="110 13" str="oral steroids" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M49" type="SpecificInteraction" span="61 25" str="impaired adrenal function" code="386584007: Adrenal cortical hypofunction (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M48" type="Precipitant" span="27 24" str="systemic corticosteroids" code="N0000175576"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M47" precipitant="M45" effect="M49" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M47" precipitant="M48" effect="M49" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="629" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Wean patients slowly from systemic corticosteroids if transferring to ASMANEX HFA.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M50" type="Trigger" span="0 20" str="Wean patients slowly"/>
<Mention id="M51" type="Precipitant" span="26 24" str="systemic corticosteroids" code="N0000175576"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M50" precipitant="M51"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="630" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hypercorticism and adrenal suppression: May occur with very high dosages or at the regular dosage in susceptible individuals.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="631" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If such changes occur, discontinue ASMANEX HFA slowly.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="632" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Strong cytochrome P450 3A4 inhibitors (e.g., ritonavir): Risk of increased systemic corticosteroid effects.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M55" type="Trigger" span="57 7" str="Risk of"/>
<Mention id="M53" type="Precipitant" span="45 9" str="ritonavir" code="O3J8G9O825 | N0000007423"/>
<Mention id="M57" type="SpecificInteraction" span="65 41" str="increased systemic corticosteroid effects" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M56" type="Precipitant" span="0 37" str="Strong cytochrome P450 3A4 inhibitors" code="N0000182141"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M55" precipitant="M53" effect="M57" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M55" precipitant="M56" effect="M57" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="633" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Exercise caution when used with ASMANEX HFA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="634" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Paradoxical bronchospasm: Discontinue ASMANEX HFA and institute alternative therapy if paradoxical bronchospasm occurs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="635" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hypersensitivity reactions including anaphylaxis: Hypersensitivity reactions, such as urticaria, flushing, allergic dermatitis, bronchospasm, rash, pruritus, angioedema, and anaphylactic reaction may occur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="636" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Discontinue ASMANEX HFA if such reactions occur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="637" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Decreases in bone mineral density: Monitor patients with major risk factors for decreased bone mineral content.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="638" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Effects on growth: Monitor growth of pediatric patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="639" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Glaucoma and cataracts: Consider referral to an ophthalmologist in patients who develop ocular symptoms or use ASMANEX HFA long term.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="640" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>ASMANEX HFA is not indicated for the relief of acute symptoms, i.e., as rescue therapy for the treatment of acute episodes of bronchospasm.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="641" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>An inhaled, short-acting beta2-agonist, not ASMANEX HFA, should be used to relieve acute symptoms such as shortness of breath.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="642" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>When prescribing ASMANEX HFA, the physician must also provide the patient with an inhaled, short-acting beta2-agonist (e.g., albuterol) for treatment of acute symptoms, despite regular twice-daily (morning and evening) use of ASMANEX HFA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="643" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Instruct patients to contact their physician immediately if episodes of asthma that are not responsive to bronchodilators occur during the course of treatment with ASMANEX HFA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="644" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>During such episodes, patients may require therapy with oral corticosteroids.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="645" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In clinical trials, the development of localized infections of the mouth and pharynx with Candida albicans have occurred in patients treated with ASMANEX HFA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="646" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If oropharyngeal candidiasis develops, it should be treated with appropriate local or systemic (i.e., oral) antifungal therapy while remaining on treatment with ASMANEX HFA therapy, but at times therapy with ASMANEX HFA may need to be interrupted.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="647" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Advise patients to rinse the mouth after inhalation of ASMANEX HFA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="648" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Persons who are using drugs that suppress the immune system are more susceptible to infections than healthy individuals.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="649" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Chickenpox and measles, for example, can have a more serious or even fatal course in susceptible children or adults using corticosteroids.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="650" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In such children or adults who have not had these diseases or who are not properly immunized, particular care should be taken to avoid exposure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="651" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>How the dose, route, and duration of corticosteroid administration affect the risk of developing a disseminated infection is not known.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="652" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The contribution of the underlying disease and/or prior corticosteroid treatment to the risk is also not known.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="653" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If exposed to chickenpox, prophylaxis with varicella zoster immune globulin (VZIG) or pooled intravenous immunoglobulin (IVIG) may be indicated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="654" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If exposed to measles, prophylaxis with pooled intramuscular immunoglobulin (IG) may be indicated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="655" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If chickenpox develops, treatment with antiviral agents may be considered.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="656" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Inhaled corticosteroids should be used with caution, if at all, in patients with active or quiescent tuberculosis infection of the respiratory tract, untreated systemic fungal, bacterial, viral, or parasitic infections; or ocular herpes simplex.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="657" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Particular care is needed for patients who are transferred from systemically active corticosteroids to ASMANEX HFA because deaths due to adrenal insufficiency have occurred in asthmatic patients during and after transfer from systemic corticosteroids to less systemically available inhaled corticosteroids.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M58" type="Trigger" span="212 13" str="transfer from"/>
<Mention id="M59" type="Precipitant" span="226 24" str="systemic corticosteroids" code="N0000175576"/>
<Mention id="M60" type="SpecificInteraction" span="123 35" str="deaths due to adrenal insufficiency" code="419620001: Death (event)"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M58" precipitant="M59" effect="M60" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="658" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>After withdrawal from systemic corticosteroids, a number of months are required for recovery of hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="659" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients who have been previously maintained on 20 mg or more per day of prednisone (or its equivalent) may be most susceptible, particularly when their systemic corticosteroids have been almost completely withdrawn.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M63" type="Trigger" span="111 16" str="most susceptible"/>
<Mention id="M62" type="Precipitant" span="73 10" str="prednisone" code="VB0R961HZT"/>
<Mention id="M64" type="Precipitant" span="153 24" str="systemic corticosteroids" code="N0000175576"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M63" precipitant="M62"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M63" precipitant="M64"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="660" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>During this period of HPA suppression, patients may exhibit signs and symptoms of adrenal insufficiency when exposed to trauma, surgery, or infection (particularly gastroenteritis) or other conditions associated with severe electrolyte loss.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="661" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Although ASMANEX HFA may improve control of asthma symptoms during these episodes, in recommended doses it supplies less than normal physiological amounts of corticosteroid systemically and does NOT provide the mineralocorticoid activity necessary for coping with these emergencies.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="662" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>During periods of stress or severe asthma attack, patients who have been withdrawn from systemic corticosteroids should be instructed to resume oral corticosteroids (in large doses) immediately and to contact their physicians for further instruction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="663" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>These patients should also be instructed to carry a medical identification card indicating that they may need supplementary systemic corticosteroids during periods of stress or severe asthma attack.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="664" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients requiring oral or other systemic corticosteroids should be weaned slowly from oral or other systemic corticosteroid use after transferring to ASMANEX HFA.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M67" type="Trigger" span="58 23" str="should be weaned slowly"/>
<Mention id="M66" type="Precipitant" span="19 4;42 14" str="oral | corticosteroid" code="N0000175576"/>
<Mention id="M68" type="Precipitant" span="33 23" str="systemic corticosteroid" code="N0000175576"/>
<Interaction id="I29" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M67" precipitant="M66"/>
<Interaction id="I30" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M67" precipitant="M68"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="665" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Lung function (FEV1 or PEF), beta-agonist use, and asthma symptoms should be carefully monitored during withdrawal of oral or other systemic corticosteroids.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M73" type="Trigger" span="58 8" str="symptoms "/>
<Mention id="M74" type="Trigger" span="87 9" str=" monitored"/>
<Mention id="M71" type="Precipitant" span="118 4;141 15" str="oral | corticosteroids" code="N0000175576"/>
<Mention id="M76" type="SpecificInteraction" span="51 15" str="asthma symptoms" code="195967001: Asthma (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M75" type="Precipitant" span="132 24" str="systemic corticosteroids" code="N0000175576"/>
<Interaction id="I31" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M73;M74" precipitant="M71" effect="M76" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I32" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M73;M74" precipitant="M75" effect="M76" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="666" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In addition to monitoring asthma signs and symptoms, patients should be observed for signs and symptoms of adrenal insufficiency such as fatigue, lassitude, weakness, nausea and vomiting, and hypotension.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="667" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Transfer of patients from systemic corticosteroid therapy to ASMANEX HFA may unmask allergic conditions previously suppressed by the systemic corticosteroid therapy, e.g., rhinitis, conjunctivitis, eczema, arthritis, and eosinophilic conditions.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M92" type="Trigger" span="0 8;77 6" str="Transfer | unmask"/>
<Mention id="M93" type="Precipitant" span="26 23" str="systemic corticosteroid" code="N0000175576"/>
<Mention id="M79" type="SpecificInteraction" span="84 19" str="allergic conditions" code="473011001: Allergic condition (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M82" type="SpecificInteraction" span="206 9" str="arthritis" code="3723001: Arthritis (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M85" type="SpecificInteraction" span="182 14" str="conjunctivitis" code="9826008: Conjunctivitis (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M88" type="SpecificInteraction" span="198 6" str="eczema" code="43116000: Eczema (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M91" type="SpecificInteraction" span="221 23" str="eosinophilic conditions" code="386789004: Eosinophil count raised (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M94" type="SpecificInteraction" span="172 8" str="rhinitis" code="70076002: Rhinitis (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I33" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M92" precipitant="M93" effect="M79" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I34" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M92" precipitant="M93" effect="M82" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I35" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M92" precipitant="M93" effect="M85" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I36" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M92" precipitant="M93" effect="M88" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I37" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M92" precipitant="M93" effect="M91" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I38" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M92" precipitant="M93" effect="M94" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="668" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>During withdrawal from oral corticosteroids, some patients may experience symptoms of systemically active corticosteroid withdrawal, e.g., joint and/or muscular pain, lassitude, and depression, despite maintenance or even improvement of respiratory function.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M111" type="Trigger" span="0 17" str="During withdrawal "/>
<Mention id="M112" type="Trigger" span="74 8" str=" symptoms"/>
<Mention id="M113" type="Precipitant" span="23 20" str="oral corticosteroids" code="N0000175576"/>
<Mention id="M98" type="SpecificInteraction" span="106 25" str="corticosteroid withdrawal" code="84584008: Steroid withdrawal syndrome (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M102" type="SpecificInteraction" span="182 10" str="depression" code="35489007: Depressive disorder (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M106" type="SpecificInteraction" span="139 5;161 4" str="joint | pain" code="57676002: Joint pain (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M110" type="SpecificInteraction" span="167 9" str="lassitude" code="13791008: Asthenia (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M114" type="SpecificInteraction" span="152 13" str="muscular pain" code="68962001: Muscle pain (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I39" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M111;M112" precipitant="M113" effect="M98" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I40" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M111;M112" precipitant="M113" effect="M102" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I41" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M111;M112" precipitant="M113" effect="M106" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I42" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M111;M112" precipitant="M113" effect="M110" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I43" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M111;M112" precipitant="M113" effect="M114" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="669" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>ASMANEX HFA will often help control asthma symptoms with less suppression of HPA function than therapeutically equivalent oral doses of prednisone.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="670" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Since mometasone furoate is absorbed into the circulation and can be systemically active at higher doses, the beneficial effects of ASMANEX HFA in minimizing HPA dysfunction may be expected only when recommended dosages are not exceeded and individual patients are titrated to the lowest effective dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="671" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Because of the possibility of systemic absorption of inhaled corticosteroids, patients treated with ASMANEX HFA should be observed carefully for any evidence of systemic corticosteroid effects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="672" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Particular care should be taken in observing patients postoperatively or during periods of stress for evidence of inadequate adrenal response.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="673" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>It is possible that systemic corticosteroid effects such as hypercorticism and adrenal suppression (including adrenal crisis) may appear in a small number of patients, particularly when mometasone furoate is administered at higher than recommended doses over prolonged periods of time.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="674" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If such effects occur, the dosage of ASMANEX HFA should be reduced slowly, consistent with accepted procedures for reducing systemic corticosteroids and for management of asthma symptoms.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="675" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Caution should be exercised when considering the coadministration of ASMANEX HFA with ketoconazole, and other known strong cytochrome P450 (CYP) isoenzyme 3A4 (CYP3A4) inhibitors (e.g., ritonavir, cobicistat-containing products, atazanavir, clarithromycin, indinavir, itraconazole, nefazodone, nelfinavir, saquinavir, telithromycin) because adverse effects related to increased systemic exposure to mometasone furoate may occur.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M147" type="Trigger" span="368 27" str="increased systemic exposure"/>
<Mention id="M116" type="Precipitant" span="229 10" str="atazanavir" code="N0000022320 | QZU4H47A3S"/>
<Mention id="M118" type="Precipitant" span="241 14" str="clarithromycin" code="H1250JIK0A | N0000007316"/>
<Mention id="M120" type="Precipitant" span="197 10" str="cobicistat" code="LW2E03M5PG"/>
<Mention id="M122" type="Precipitant" span="197 30" str="cobicistat-containing products" code="LW2E03M5PG | N0000191982"/>
<Mention id="M124" type="Precipitant" span="257 9" str="indinavir" code="N0000005722 | 5W6YA9PKKH"/>
<Mention id="M126" type="Precipitant" span="268 12" str="itraconazole" code="304NUG5GF4 | N0000006753"/>
<Mention id="M128" type="Precipitant" span="86 12" str="ketoconazole" code="N0000007319 | R9400W927I"/>
<Mention id="M130" type="Precipitant" span="282 10" str="nefazodone" code="N0000007250 | 59H4FCV1TF"/>
<Mention id="M132" type="Precipitant" span="294 10" str="nelfinavir" code="HO3OGH5D7I | N0000006047"/>
<Mention id="M134" type="Precipitant" span="186 9" str="ritonavir" code="O3J8G9O825 | N0000007423"/>
<Mention id="M136" type="Precipitant" span="306 10" str="saquinavir" code="N0000007376 | L3JE09KZ2F"/>
<Mention id="M138" type="Precipitant" span="116 6;140 3;155 3;168 10" str="strong | CYP | 3A4 | inhibitors" code="N0000182141"/>
<Mention id="M140" type="Precipitant" span="116 6;160 6;168 10" str="strong | CYP3A4 | inhibitors" code="N0000182141"/>
<Mention id="M142" type="Precipitant" span="116 62" str="strong cytochrome P450 (CYP) isoenzyme 3A4 (CYP3A4) inhibitors" code="N0000182141"/>
<Mention id="M144" type="Precipitant" span="116 42;168 10" str="strong cytochrome P450 (CYP) isoenzyme 3A4 | inhibitors" code="N0000182141"/>
<Mention id="M146" type="Precipitant" span="116 22;155 3;168 10" str="strong cytochrome P450 | 3A4 | inhibitors" code="N0000182141"/>
<Mention id="M148" type="Precipitant" span="318 13" str="telithromycin" code="N0000010551 | KI8H7H19WL"/>
<Interaction id="I44" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M147" precipitant="M116" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I45" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M147" precipitant="M118" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I46" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M147" precipitant="M120" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I47" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M147" precipitant="M122" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I48" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M147" precipitant="M124" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I49" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M147" precipitant="M126" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I50" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M147" precipitant="M128" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I51" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M147" precipitant="M130" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I52" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M147" precipitant="M132" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I53" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M147" precipitant="M134" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I54" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M147" precipitant="M136" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I55" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M147" precipitant="M138" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I56" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M147" precipitant="M140" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I57" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M147" precipitant="M142" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I58" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M147" precipitant="M144" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I59" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M147" precipitant="M146" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I60" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M147" precipitant="M148" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="676" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>ASMANEX HFA may produce inhalation induced bronchospasm with an immediate increase in wheezing after dosing that may be life-threatening.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="677" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If inhalation induced bronchospasm occurs, it should be treated immediately with an inhaled, short-acting bronchodilator.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="678" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>ASMANEX HFA should be discontinued immediately and alternative therapy instituted.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="679" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hypersensitivity reactions such as urticaria, flushing, allergic dermatitis, and bronchospasm, may occur after administration of ASMANEX HFA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="680" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The following additional hypersensitivity reactions, such as rash, pruritus, angioedema, and anaphylactic reaction, have been reported after administration of mometasone furoate dry powder inhaler.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="681" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Decreases in bone mineral density (BMD) have been observed with long-term administration of products containing inhaled corticosteroids, including mometasone furoate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="682" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The clinical significance of small changes in BMD with regard to long-term outcomes, such as fracture, is unknown.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="683" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients with major risk factors for decreased bone mineral content, such as prolonged immobilization, family history of osteoporosis, or chronic use of drugs that can reduce bone mass (e.g., anticonvulsants and corticosteroids) should be monitored and treated with established standards of care.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M157" type="Trigger" span="20 12" str="risk factors "/>
<Mention id="M158" type="Trigger" span="229 19" str=" should be monitored"/>
<Mention id="M151" type="Precipitant" span="192 15" str="anticonvulsants" code="N0000029145 | N0000175753"/>
<Mention id="M160" type="SpecificInteraction" span="37 30" str="decreased bone mineral content" code="449781000: Bone density below reference range (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M155" type="Precipitant" span="212 15" str="corticosteroids" code="N0000011309 | N0000175576"/>
<Mention id="M159" type="Precipitant" span="153 31" str="drugs that can reduce bone mass" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I61" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M157;M158" precipitant="M151" effect="M160" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I62" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M157;M158" precipitant="M155" effect="M160" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I63" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M157;M158" precipitant="M159" effect="M160" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="684" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In a 2-year double-blind study in 103 male and female asthma patients 18 to 50 years of age previously maintained on bronchodilator therapy (Baseline FEV1 85%-88% predicted), treatment with mometasone furoate dry powder inhaler 200 mcg twice daily resulted in significant reductions in lumbar spine (LS) BMD at the end of the treatment period compared to placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="685" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The mean change from Baseline to Endpoint in the lumbar spine BMD was -0.015 (-1.43%) for the mometasone furoate dry powder inhaler group compared to 0.002 (0.25%) for the placebo group.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="686" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In another 2-year double-blind study in 87 male and female asthma patients 18 to 50 years of age previously maintained on bronchodilator therapy (Baseline FEV1 82%-83% predicted), treatment with mometasone furoate dry powder inhaler 400 mcg twice daily demonstrated no statistically significant changes in lumbar spine BMD at the end of the treatment period compared to placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="687" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The mean change from Baseline to Endpoint in the lumbar spine BMD was -0.018 (-1.57%) for the mometasone furoate group compared to -0.006 (-0.43%) for the placebo group.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="688" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Orally inhaled corticosteroids, including ASMANEX HFA, may cause a reduction in growth velocity when administered to pediatric patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="689" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor the growth of pediatric patients receiving ASMANEX HFA routinely (e.g., via stadiometry).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="690" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>To minimize the systemic effects of orally inhaled corticosteroids, including ASMANEX HFA, titrate each patient's dose to the lowest dosage that effectively controls his/her symptoms.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="691" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Glaucoma, increased intraocular pressure, and cataracts have been reported following the use of long-term administration of inhaled corticosteroids, including mometasone furoate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="692" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Consider referral to an ophthalmologist in patients who develop ocular symptoms or use ASMANEX HFA long term.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="693" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Mometasone furoate is a corticosteroid demonstrating potent anti-inflammatory activity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="694" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The precise mechanism of corticosteroid action on asthma is not known.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="695" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Inflammation is an important component in the pathogenesis of asthma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="696" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Corticosteroids have been shown to have a wide range of inhibitory effects on multiple cell types (e.g., mast cells, eosinophils, neutrophils, macrophages, and lymphocytes) and mediators (e.g., histamine, eicosanoids, leukotrienes, and cytokines) involved in inflammation and in the asthmatic response.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="697" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>These anti-inflammatory actions of corticosteroids may contribute to their efficacy in asthma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="698" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Mometasone furoate has been shown in vitro to exhibit a binding affinity for the human glucocorticoid receptor, which is approximately 12 times that of dexamethasone, 7 times that of triamcinolone acetonide, 5 times that of budesonide, and 1.5 times that of fluticasone.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="699" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The clinical significance of these findings is unknown.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="700" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>HPA Axis Effects The effects of inhaled mometasone furoate administered via ASMANEX HFA on adrenal function have not been directly evaluated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="701" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>However, the effects of inhaled mometasone furoate, administered as part of a mometasone furoate/formoterol fumarate inhalation aerosol combination product, on adrenal function were evaluated in two clinical trials in patients with asthma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="702" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>As no evidence of a pharmacokinetic drug interaction between mometasone furoate and formoterol was observed when the two drugs were administered in combination, the HPA axis effects from the combination product are applicable to ASMANEX HFA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="703" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>For the mometasone furoate/formoterol fumarate combination product clinical program, HPA-axis function was assessed by 24-hour plasma cortisol AUC.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="704" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Although both these trials have open-label design and contain a small number of subjects per treatment arm, results from these trials taken together demonstrated suppression of 24-hour plasma cortisol AUC for the combination mometasone furoate/formoterol fumarate 200 mcg/5 mcg compared to placebo consistent with the known systemic effects of inhaled corticosteroid.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="705" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In a 42-day, open-label, placebo- and active-controlled study, the mean change from baseline plasma cortisol AUC(0-24 hr) was 8%, 22% and 34% lower compared to placebo for the mometasone furoate/formoterol fumarate 100 mcg/5 mcg (n=13), mometasone furoate/formoterol fumarate 200 mcg/5 mcg (n=15) and fluticasone propionate/salmeterol xinafoate 230 mcg/21 mcg (n=16) treatment groups, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="706" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In a 52-week, open-label safety study, the mean plasma cortisol AUC(0-24 hr) was 2.2%, 29.6%, 16.7%, and 32.2% lower from baseline for the mometasone furoate/formoterol fumarate 100 mcg/5 mcg (n=18), mometasone furoate/formoterol fumarate 200 mcg/5 mcg (n=20), fluticasone propionate/salmeterol xinafoate 125/25 mcg (n=8), and fluticasone propionate/salmeterol xinafoate 250/25 mcg (n=11) treatment groups, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="707" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The potential effect of mometasone furoate via a dry powder inhaler (DPI) on the HPA axis was also assessed in a 29-day study.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="708" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A total of 64 adult patients with mild to moderate asthma were randomized to one of 4 treatment groups: mometasone furoate DPI 440 mcg twice daily, mometasone furoate DPI 880 mcg twice daily, oral prednisone 10 mg once daily, or placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="709" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The 30-minute post-Cosyntropin stimulation serum cortisol concentration on Day 29 was 23.2 mcg/dL for the mometasone furoate DPI 440 mcg twice daily group and 20.8 mcg/dL for the mometasone furoate DPI 880 mcg twice daily group, compared to 14.5 mcg/dL for the oral prednisone 10 mg group and 25 mcg/dL for the placebo group.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="710" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The difference between mometasone furoate DPI 880 mcg twice daily (twice the maximum recommended dose) and placebo was statistically significant.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="711" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>As no evidence of a pharmacokinetic drug interaction between mometasone furoate and formoterol was observed when the two drugs were administered from a mometasone furoate/formoterol fumarate combination product, the pharmacokinetics information from the combination product is applicable to ASMANEX HFA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="712" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Absorption Healthy Subjects: Following oral inhalation of single doses of ASMANEX HFA, mometasone furoate was absorbed in healthy subjects with median Tmax values ranging from 0.50 to 2 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="713" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following single-dose administration of higher than recommended dose of ASMANEX HFA (4 inhalations of ASMANEX HFA 200 mcg) in healthy subjects, the arithmetic mean (CV%) Cmax and AUC(0-tf) values for mometasone furoate were 53 (102) pg/mL and 992 (80) pg∙hr/mL, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="714" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Studies using oral dosing of labeled and unlabeled drug have demonstrated that the oral systemic bioavailability of mometasone furoate is negligible (&lt;1%).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="715" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Asthma Patients: Following oral inhalation of single and multiple doses of the mometasone furoate/formoterol fumarate combination product, mometasone furoate was absorbed in asthma patients with median Tmax values ranging from 1 to 2 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="716" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following single-dose administration of mometasone furoate/formoterol fumarate 400 mcg/10 mcg, the arithmetic mean (CV%) Cmax and AUC(0-12 hr) values for mometasone furoate were 20 (88) pg/mL and 170 (94) pg∙hr/mL, respectively, while the corresponding estimates following twice daily dosing of mometasone furoate/formoterol fumarate 400 mcg/10 mcg at steady-state were 60 (36) pg/mL and 577 (40) pg∙hr/mL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="717" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Distribution Based on the study employing a 1000 mcg inhaled dose of tritiated mometasone furoate inhalation powder in humans, no appreciable accumulation of mometasone furoate in the red blood cells was found.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="718" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following an intravenous 400 mcg dose of mometasone furoate, the plasma concentrations showed a biphasic decline, with a mean steady-state volume of distribution of 152 liters.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="719" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The in vitro protein binding for mometasone furoate was reported to be 98% to 99% (in a concentration range of 5 to 500 ng/mL).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="720" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Metabolism Studies have shown that mometasone furoate is primarily and extensively metabolized in the liver of all species investigated and undergoes extensive metabolism to multiple metabolites.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="721" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In vitro studies have confirmed the primary role of human liver CYP3A4 in the metabolism of this compound; however, no major metabolites were identified.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="722" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Human liver CYP3A4 metabolizes mometasone furoate to 6-beta hydroxy mometasone furoate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="723" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Excretion Following an intravenous dosing, the terminal half-life was reported to be about 5 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="724" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following the inhaled dose of tritiated 1000 mcg mometasone furoate, the radioactivity is excreted mainly in the feces (a mean of 74%), and to a small extent in the urine (a mean of 8%) up to 7 days.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="725" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No radioactivity was associated with unchanged mometasone furoate in the urine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="726" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Absorbed mometasone furoate is cleared from plasma at a rate of approximately 12.5 mL/min/kg, independent of dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="727" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The effective t½ for mometasone furoate following inhalation with DULERA was 25 hours in healthy subjects and in patients with asthma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="728" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Special Populations Hepatic/Renal Impairment: There are no data regarding the specific use of ASMANEX HFA in patients with hepatic or renal impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="729" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A study evaluating the administration of a single inhaled dose of 400 mcg mometasone furoate by a dry powder inhaler to subjects with mild (n=4), moderate (n=4), and severe (n=4) hepatic impairment resulted in only 1 or 2 subjects in each group having detectable peak plasma concentrations of mometasone furoate (ranging from 50-105 pg/mL).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="730" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The observed peak plasma concentrations appear to increase with severity of hepatic impairment; however, the numbers of detectable levels were few.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="731" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Gender and Race: Specific studies to examine the effects of gender and race on the pharmacokinetics of ASMANEX HFA have not been specifically studied.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="732" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Geriatrics: The pharmacokinetics of ASMANEX HFA have not been specifically studied in the elderly population.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="733" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Drug-Drug Interactions A single-dose crossover study was conducted to compare the pharmacokinetics of 4 inhalations of the following: mometasone furoate MDI, formoterol MDI, mometasone furoate/formoterol fumarate MDI combination product, and mometasone furoate MDI plus formoterol fumarate MDI administered concurrently.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="734" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The results of the study indicated that there was no evidence of a pharmacokinetic interaction between mometasone furoate and formoterol.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="735" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Inhibitors of Cytochrome P450 Enzymes: Ketoconazole: In a drug interaction study, an inhaled dose of mometasone furoate 400 mcg delivered by a dry powder inhaler was given to 24 healthy subjects twice daily for 9 days and ketoconazole 200 mg (as well as placebo) were given twice daily concomitantly on Days 4 to 9.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="736" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Mometasone furoate plasma concentrations were &lt;150 pg/mL on Day 3 prior to coadministration of ketoconazole or placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="737" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following concomitant administration of ketoconazole, 4 out of 12 subjects in the ketoconazole treatment group (n=12) had peak plasma concentrations of mometasone furoate &gt;200 pg/mL on Day 9 (211-324 pg/mL).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="738" LabelDrug="ASMANEX HFA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Mometasone furoate plasma levels appeared to increase and plasma cortisol levels appeared to decrease upon concomitant administration of ketoconazole.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M161" type="Trigger" span="19 13;45 8" str="plasma levels | increase"/>
<Mention id="M162" type="Precipitant" span="137 12" str="ketoconazole" code="N0000007319 | R9400W927I"/>
<Interaction id="I64" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M161" precipitant="M162" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="oral corticosteroid therapy" precipitantCode="N0000175576"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ritonavir" precipitantCode="O3J8G9O825 | N0000007423" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="ritonavir" precipitantCode="O3J8G9O825 | N0000007423" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="ritonavir" precipitantCode="O3J8G9O825 | N0000007423"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="strong cytochrome p450 3a4 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000182141" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="strong cytochrome p450 3a4 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000182141"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="ketoconazole" precipitantCode="N0000007319 | R9400W927I" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="ketoconazole" precipitantCode="N0000007319 | R9400W927I"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="strong inhibitor of cyp3a4" precipitantCode="N0000182141" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cyp3a4 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000182141" effect="293141009: Corticosteroids adverse reaction (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cyp3a4 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000182141" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="atazanavir" precipitantCode="N0000022320 | QZU4H47A3S" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="atazanavir" precipitantCode="N0000022320 | QZU4H47A3S"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="clarithromycin" precipitantCode="H1250JIK0A | N0000007316" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="clarithromycin" precipitantCode="H1250JIK0A | N0000007316"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cobicistat" precipitantCode="LW2E03M5PG" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="cobicistat" precipitantCode="LW2E03M5PG"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cobicistat-containing products" precipitantCode="LW2E03M5PG | N0000191982" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="cobicistat-containing products" precipitantCode="LW2E03M5PG | N0000191982"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="indinavir" precipitantCode="N0000005722 | 5W6YA9PKKH" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="indinavir" precipitantCode="N0000005722 | 5W6YA9PKKH"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="itraconazole" precipitantCode="304NUG5GF4 | N0000006753" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="itraconazole" precipitantCode="304NUG5GF4 | N0000006753"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="nefazodone" precipitantCode="N0000007250 | 59H4FCV1TF" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="nefazodone" precipitantCode="N0000007250 | 59H4FCV1TF"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="nelfinavir" precipitantCode="HO3OGH5D7I | N0000006047" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="nelfinavir" precipitantCode="HO3OGH5D7I | N0000006047"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="saquinavir" precipitantCode="N0000007376 | L3JE09KZ2F" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="saquinavir" precipitantCode="N0000007376 | L3JE09KZ2F"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="strong cyp3a4 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000182141"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="telithromycin" precipitantCode="N0000010551 | KI8H7H19WL" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="telithromycin" precipitantCode="N0000010551 | KI8H7H19WL"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="oral steroids" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="386584007: Adrenal cortical hypofunction (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="systemic corticosteroids" precipitantCode="N0000175576" effect=" 386584007: Adrenal cortical hypofunction (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="systemic corticosteroids" precipitantCode="N0000175576" effect="195967001: Asthma (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="systemic corticosteroids" precipitantCode="N0000175576" effect="386584007: Adrenal cortical hypofunction (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="systemic corticosteroids" precipitantCode="N0000175576" effect="419620001: Death (event)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="systemic corticosteroids" precipitantCode="N0000175576"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="prednisone" precipitantCode="VB0R961HZT"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="oral | corticosteroid" precipitantCode="N0000175576"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="systemic corticosteroid" precipitantCode="N0000175576" effect="3723001: Arthritis (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="systemic corticosteroid" precipitantCode="N0000175576" effect="386789004: Eosinophil count raised (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="systemic corticosteroid" precipitantCode="N0000175576" effect="43116000: Eczema (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="systemic corticosteroid" precipitantCode="N0000175576" effect="473011001: Allergic condition (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="systemic corticosteroid" precipitantCode="N0000175576" effect="70076002: Rhinitis (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="systemic corticosteroid" precipitantCode="N0000175576" effect="9826008: Conjunctivitis (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="systemic corticosteroid" precipitantCode="N0000175576"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="oral | corticosteroids" precipitantCode="N0000175576" effect="195967001: Asthma (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="oral corticosteroids" precipitantCode="N0000175576" effect="13791008: Asthenia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="oral corticosteroids" precipitantCode="N0000175576" effect="35489007: Depressive disorder (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="oral corticosteroids" precipitantCode="N0000175576" effect="57676002: Joint pain (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="oral corticosteroids" precipitantCode="N0000175576" effect="68962001: Muscle pain (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="oral corticosteroids" precipitantCode="N0000175576" effect="84584008: Steroid withdrawal syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="strong | cyp | 3a4 | inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000182141" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="strong | cyp3a4 | inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000182141" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="strong cytochrome p450 (cyp) isoenzyme 3a4 (cyp3a4) inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000182141" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="strong cytochrome p450 (cyp) isoenzyme 3a4 | inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000182141" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="strong cytochrome p450 | 3a4 | inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000182141" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="anticonvulsants" precipitantCode="N0000029145 | N0000175753" effect="449781000: Bone density below reference range (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="corticosteroids" precipitantCode="N0000011309 | N0000175576" effect="449781000: Bone density below reference range (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="drugs that can reduce bone mass" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="449781000: Bone density below reference range (finding)"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>