<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Afinitor" setid="2150f73a-179b-4afc-b8ce-67c85cc72f04">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ is contraindicated in patients with clinically significant hypersensitivity to everolimus or to other rapamycin derivatives [see Warnings and Precautions (5.3)] . Clinically significant hypersensitivity to everolimus or to other rapamycin derivatives. ( 4 )</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
Do not combine AFINITOR and AFINITOR DISPERZ to achieve the total daily dose. ( 2.1 ) Modify the dose for patients with hepatic impairment or for patients taking drugs that inhibit or induce P-glycoprotein (P-gp) and CYP3A4. ( 2.1 ) Breast Cancer: 10 mg orally once daily. ( 2.2 ) NET: 10 mg orally once daily. ( 2.3 ) RCC: 10 mg orally once daily. ( 2.4 ) TSC-Associated Renal Angiomyolipoma: 10 mg orally once daily. ( 2.5 ) TSC-Associated SEGA: 4.5 mg/m 2 orally once daily; adjust dose to attain trough concentrations of 5-15 ng/mL. ( 2.6 , 2.8 ) TSC-Associated Partial-Onset Seizures: 5 mg/m 2 orally once daily; adjust dose to attain trough concentrations of 5-15 ng/mL. ( 2.7 , 2.8 ) AFINITOR and AFINITOR DISPERZ are two different dosage forms. Select the recommended dosage form based on the indication [see Indications and Usage (1)] . Do not combine AFINITOR and AFINITOR DISPERZ to achieve the total dose. Modify the dosage for patients with hepatic impairment or for patients taking drugs that inhibit or induce P-glycoprotein (P-gp) and CYP3A4 [see Dosage and Administration (2.10, 2.11, 2.12)] . The recommended dosage of AFINITOR is 10 mg orally once daily until disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. The recommended dosage of AFINITOR is 10 mg orally once daily until disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. The recommended dosage of AFINITOR is 10 mg orally once daily until disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. The recommended dosage of AFINITOR is 10 mg orally once daily until disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. The recommended starting dosage of AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ is 4.5 mg/m 2 orally once daily until disease progression or unacceptable toxicity [see Dosage and Administration (2.8)] .  The recommended starting dosage of AFINITOR DISPERZ is 5 mg/m 2 orally once daily until disease progression or unacceptable toxicity [see Dosage and Administration (2.8)] . Monitor everolimus whole blood trough concentrations at time points recommended in Table 1. Titrate the dose to attain trough concentrations of 5 ng/mL to 15 ng/mL. Adjust the dose using the following equation: New dose * = current dose x (target concentration divided by current concentration) * The maximum dose increment at any titration must not exceed 5 mg. Multiple dose titrations may be required to attain the target trough concentration. When possible, use the same assay and laboratory for therapeutic drug monitoring throughout treatment. Table 1: Recommended Timing of Therapeutic Drug Monitoring Event When to Assess Trough Concentrations After Event Initiation of AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ 1 to 2 weeks Modification of AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ dose 1 to 2 weeks Switch between AFINITOR and AFINITOR DISPERZ 1 to 2 weeks Initiation or discontinuation of P-gp and moderate CYP3A4 inhibitor 2 weeks Initiation or discontinuation of P-gp and strong CYP3A4 inducer 2 weeks Change in hepatic function 2 weeks Stable dose with changing body surface area Every 3 to 6 months Stable dose with stable body surface area Every 6 to 12 months Table 2 summarizes recommendations for dosage modifications of AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ for the management of adverse reactions. Table 2: Recommended Dosage Modifications for AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ for Adverse Reactions Adverse Reaction Severity Dosage Modification Non-infectious pneumonitis [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)] Grade 2 Withhold until improvement to Grade 0 or 1. Resume at 50% of previous dose; change to every other day dosing if the reduced dose is lower than the lowest available strength. Permanently discontinue if toxicity does not resolve or improve to Grade 1 within 4 weeks. Grade 3 Withhold until improvement to Grade 0 or 1. Resume at 50% of previous dose; change to every other day dosing if the reduced dose is lower than the lowest available strength. If toxicity recurs at Grade 3, permanently discontinue. Grade 4 Permanently discontinue. Stomatitis [see Warnings and Precautions (5.5)] Grade 2 Withhold until improvement to Grade 0 or 1. Resume at same dose. If recurs at Grade 2, withhold until improvement to Grade 0 or 1. Resume at 50% of previous dose; change to every other day dosing if the reduced dose is lower than the lowest available strength. Grade 3 Withhold until improvement to Grade 0 or 1. Resume at 50% of previous dose; change to every other day dosing if the reduced dose is lower than the lowest available strength. Grade 4 Permanently discontinue. Metabolic events (e.g., hyperglycemia, dyslipidemia) [see Warnings and Precautions (5.9)] Grade 3 Withhold until improvement to Grade 0, 1, or 2. Resume at 50% of previous dose; change to every other day dosing if the reduced dose is lower than the lowest available strength. Grade 4 Permanently discontinue. Other non-hematologic toxicities Grade 2 If toxicity becomes intolerable, withhold until improvement to Grade 0 or 1. Resume at same dose. If toxicity recurs at Grade 2, withhold until improvement to Grade 0 or 1. Resume at 50% of previous dose; change to every other day dosing if the reduced dose is lower than the lowest available strength. Grade 3 Withhold until improvement to Grade 0 or 1. Consider resuming at 50% of previous dose; change to every other day dosing if the reduced dose is lower than the lowest available strength. If recurs at Grade 3, permanently discontinue. Grade 4 Permanently discontinue. Thrombocytopenia [see Warnings and Precautions (5.10)] Grade 2 Withhold until improvement to Grade 0 or 1. Resume at same dose. Grade 3 OR Grade 4 Withhold until improvement to Grade 0 or 1. Resume at 50% of previous dose; change to every other day dosing if the reduced dose is lower than the lowest available strength. Neutropenia [see Warnings and Precautions (5.10)] Grade 3 Withhold until improvement to Grade 0, 1 or 2. Resume at same dose. Grade 4 Withhold until improvement to Grade 0, 1 or 2. Resume at 50% of previous dose; change to every other day dosing if the reduced dose is lower than the lowest available strength. Febrile neutropenia [see Warnings and Precautions (5.10)] Grade 3 Withhold until improvement to Grade 0, 1 or 2 and no fever. Resume at 50% of previous dose; change to every other day dosing if the reduced dose is lower than the lowest available strength. Grade 4 Permanently discontinue. The recommended dosages of AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ for patients with hepatic impairment are described in Table 3 [see Use in Specific Populations (8.6)] :  Table 3: Recommended Dosage Modifications for Patients with Hepatic Impairment Indication Dose Modification for AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ Breast Cancer, NET, RCC, and TSC-Associated Renal Angiomyolipoma  Mild hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh class A) – 7.5 mg orally once daily; decrease the dose to 5 mg orally once daily if a dose of 7.5 mg once daily is not tolerated. Moderate hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh class B) – 5 mg orally once daily; decrease the dose to 2.5 mg orally once daily if a dose of 5 mg once daily is not tolerated. Severe hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh class C) – 2.5 mg orally once daily if the desired benefit outweighs the risk; do not exceed a dose of 2.5 mg once daily. TSC-Associated SEGA and TSC- Associated Partial-Onset Seizures  Severe hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh class C) – 2.5 mg/m 2 orally once daily. Adjust dose based on everolimus trough concentrations as recommended [see Dosage and Administration (2.8)] . Avoid the concomitant use of P-gp and strong CYP3A4 inhibitors [see Drug Interactions (7.1)] . Avoid ingesting grapefruit and grapefruit juice. Reduce the dose for patients taking AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ with a P-gp and moderate CYP3A4 inhibitor as recommended in Table 4 [see Drug Interactions (7.1), Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)] . Table 4: Recommended Dosage Modifications for Concurrent Use of AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ with a P-gp and Moderate CYP3A4 Inhibitor Indication Dose Modification for AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ Breast Cancer, NET, RCC, and TSC-Associated Renal Angiomyolipoma  Reduce dose to 2.5 mg once daily. May increase dose to 5 mg once daily if tolerated. Resume dose administered prior to inhibitor initiation, once the inhibitor is discontinued for 3 days. TSC-Associated SEGA and TSC- Associated Partial-Onset Seizures  Reduce the daily dose by 50%. Change to every other day dosing if the reduced dose is lower than the lowest available strength. Resume dose administered prior to inhibitor initiation, once the inhibitor is discontinued for 3 days. Assess trough concentrations when initiating and discontinuing the inhibitor [see Dosage and Administration (2.8)] . Avoid concomitant use of St. John’s Wort (Hypericum perforatum) . Increase the dose for patients taking AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ with a P-gp and strong CYP3A4 inducer as recommended in Table 5 [see Drug Interactions (7.1), Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)] . Table 5: Recommended Dosage Modifications for Concurrent Use of AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ with P-gp and Strong CYP3A4 Inducers Indication Dose Modification for AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ Breast Cancer, NET, RCC, and TSC-Associated Renal Angiomyolipoma  Avoid coadministration where alternatives exist. If coadministration cannot be avoided, double the daily dose using increments of 5 mg or less. Multiple increments may be required. Resume the dose administered prior to inducer initiation, once an inducer is discontinued for 5 days. TSC-Associated SEGA and TSC- Associated Partial-Onset Seizures  Double the daily dose using increments of 5 mg or less. Multiple increments may be required. Addition of another strong CYP3A4 inducer in a patient already receiving treatment with a strong CYP3A4 inducer may not require additional dosage modification. Assess trough concentrations when initiating and discontinuing the inducer [see Dosage and Administration (2.8)] . Resume the dose administered before starting any inducer, once all inducers are discontinued for 5 days. Administer AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ at the same time each day. Administer AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ consistently either with or without food [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)] . If a dose of AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ is missed, it can be administered up to 6 hours after the time it is normally administered. After more than 6 hours, the dose should be skipped for that day. The next day, AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ should be administered at its usual time. Double doses should not be administered to make up for the dose that was missed. AFINITOR AFINITOR should be swallowed whole with a glass of water. Do not break or crush tablets. AFINITOR DISPERZ Wear gloves to avoid possible contact with everolimus when preparing suspensions of AFINITOR DISPERZ for another person. Administer as a suspension only. Administer suspension immediately after preparation. Discard suspension if not administered within 60 minutes after preparation. Prepare suspension in water only. Using an Oral Syringe to Prepare Oral Suspension: Place the prescribed dose into a 10-mL syringe. Do not exceed a total of 10 mg per syringe. If higher doses are required, prepare an additional syringe. Do not break or crush tablets. Draw approximately 5 mL of water and 4 mL of air into the syringe. Place the filled syringe into a container (tip up) for 3 minutes, until the tablets are in suspension. Gently invert the syringe 5 times immediately prior to administration. After administration of the prepared suspension, draw approximately 5 mL of water and 4 mL of air into the same syringe, and swirl the contents to suspend remaining particles. Administer the entire contents of the syringe. Using a Small Drinking Glass to Prepare Oral Suspension: Place the prescribed dose into a small drinking glass (maximum size 100 mL) containing approximately 25 mL of water. Do not exceed a total of 10 mg per glass. If higher doses are required, prepare an additional glass. Do not break or crush tablets. Allow 3 minutes for suspension to occur. Stir the contents gently with a spoon, immediately prior to drinking. After administration of the prepared suspension, add 25 mL of water and stir with the same spoon to re-suspend remaining particles. Administer the entire contents of the glass.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
P-gp and strong CYP3A4 inhibitors: Avoid concomitant use. ( 2.11 , 7.1 ) P-gp and moderate CYP3A4 inhibitors: Reduce the dose as recommended. ( 2.11 , 7.1 ) P-gp and strong CYP3A4 inducers: Increase the dose as recommended. ( 2.12 , 7.1 ) Inhibitors Avoid the concomitant use of P-gp and strong CYP3A4 inhibitors [see Dosage and Administration (2.11), Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)] . Reduce the dose for patients taking AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ with a P-gp and moderate CYP3A4 inhibitor as recommended [see Dosage and Administration (2.11), Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)] . Inducers Increase the dose for patients taking AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ with a P-gp and strong CYP3A4 inducer as recommended [see Dosage and Administration (2.12), Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)] . Patients taking concomitant ACE inhibitors with AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ may be at increased risk for angioedema. Avoid the concomitant use of ACE inhibitors with AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ [see Warnings and Precautions (5.4)] .</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
Non-Infectious Pneumonitis: Monitor for clinical symptoms or radiological changes. Withhold or permanently discontinue based on severity. ( 2.9 , 5.1 ) Infections: Monitor for signs and symptoms of infection. Withhold or permanently discontinue based on severity. ( 2.9 , 5.2 ) Severe Hypersensitivity Reactions: Permanently discontinue for clinically significant hypersensitivity. ( 5.3 ) Angioedema: Patients taking concomitant ACE inhibitors may be at increased risk for angioedema. Permanently discontinue for angioedema. ( 5.4 , 7.2 ) Stomatitis: Initiate dexamethasone alcohol-free mouthwash when starting treatment. ( 5.5 , 6.1 ) Renal Failure: Monitor renal function prior to treatment and periodically thereafter. ( 5.6 ) Impaired Wound Healing: Exercise caution in the peri-surgical period. ( 5.7 ) Geriatric Patients: Monitor and adjust dose for adverse reactions. ( 5.8 ) Metabolic Disorders: Monitor serum glucose and lipids prior to treatment and periodically thereafter. Withhold or permanently discontinue based on severity ( 2.9 , 5.9 ) Myelosuppression: Monitor hematologic parameters prior to treatment and periodically thereafter. Withhold or permanently discontinue based on severity. ( 2.9 , 5.10 ) Risk of Infection or Reduced Immune Response with Vaccination: Avoid live vaccines and close contact with those who have received live vaccines. Complete recommended childhood vaccinations prior to starting treatment. ( 5.11 ) Embryo-Fetal Toxicity: Can cause fetal harm. Advise patients of reproductive potential of the potential risk to a fetus and to use effective contraception. ( 5.12 , 8.1 , 8.3 ) Non-infectious pneumonitis is a class effect of rapamycin derivatives. Non-infectious pneumonitis was reported in up to 19% of patients treated with AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ in clinical trials, some cases were reported with pulmonary hypertension (including pulmonary arterial hypertension) as a secondary event. The incidence of Grade 3 and 4 non-infectious pneumonitis was up to 4% and up to 0.2%, respectively [see Adverse Reactions (6.1)] . Fatal outcomes have been observed. Consider a diagnosis of non-infectious pneumonitis in patients presenting with non-specific respiratory signs and symptoms. Consider opportunistic infections such as pneumocystis jiroveci pneumonia (PJP) in the differential diagnosis. Advise patients to report promptly any new or worsening respiratory symptoms. Continue AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ without dose alteration in patients who develop radiological changes suggestive of non-infectious pneumonitis and have few or no symptoms. Imaging appears to overestimate the incidence of clinical pneumonitis. For Grade 2 to 4 non-infectious pneumonitis, withhold or permanently discontinue AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ based on severity [see Dosage and Administration (2.9)] . Corticosteroids may be indicated until clinical symptoms resolve. Administer prophylaxis for PJP when concomitant use of corticosteroids or other immunosuppressive agents are required. The development of pneumonitis has been reported even at a reduced dose. AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ has immunosuppressive properties and may predispose patients to bacterial, fungal, viral, or protozoal infections, including infections with opportunistic pathogens [see Adverse Reactions (6.1)] . Localized and systemic infections, including pneumonia, mycobacterial infections, other bacterial infections, invasive fungal infections (e.g., aspergillosis, candidiasis, or PJP) and viral infections (e.g., reactivation of hepatitis B virus) have occurred. Some of these infections have been severe (e.g., sepsis, septic shock, or resulting in multisystem organ failure) or fatal. The incidence of Grade 3 and 4 infections was up to 10% and up to 3%, respectively. The incidence of serious infections was reported at a higher frequency in patients &amp;lt; 6 years of age [see Use in Specific Populations (8.4)] . Complete treatment of preexisting invasive fungal infections prior to starting treatment. Monitor for signs and symptoms of infection. Withhold or permanently discontinue AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ based on severity of infection [see Dosage and Administration (2.9)] .  Administer prophylaxis for PJP when concomitant use of corticosteroids or other immunosuppressive agents are required. Hypersensitivity reactions to AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ have been observed and include anaphylaxis, dyspnea, flushing, chest pain, and angioedema (e.g., swelling of the airways or tongue, with or without respiratory impairment) [see Contraindications (4)] . The incidence of Grade 3 hypersensitivity reactions was up to 1%. Permanently discontinue AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ for the development of clinically significant hypersensitivity. Patients taking concomitant ACE inhibitors with AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ may be at increased risk for angioedema (e.g., swelling of the airways or tongue, with or without respiratory impairment). In a pooled analysis of randomized double-blind oncology clinical trials, the incidence of angioedema in patients taking AFINITOR with an ACE inhibitor was 6.8% compared to 1.3% in the control arm with an ACE inhibitor. Permanently discontinue AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ for angioedema. Stomatitis, including mouth ulcers and oral mucositis, has occurred in patients treated with AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ at an incidence ranging from 44% to 78% across clinical trials. Grades 3-4 stomatitis was reported in 4% to 9% of patients [see Adverse Reactions (6.1)] . Stomatitis most often occurs within the first 8 weeks of treatment. When starting AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ, initiating dexamethasone alcohol-free oral solution as a swish and spit mouthwash reduces the incidence and severity of stomatitis [see Adverse Reactions (6.1)] . If stomatitis does occur, mouthwashes and/or other topical treatments are recommended. Avoid alcohol-, hydrogen peroxide-, iodine-, or thyme- containing products, as they may exacerbate the condition. Do not administer antifungal agents, unless fungal infection has been diagnosed. Cases of renal failure (including acute renal failure), some with a fatal outcome, have occurred in patients taking AFINITOR. Elevations of serum creatinine and proteinuria have been reported in patients taking AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ [see Adverse Reactions (6.1)] . The incidence of Grade 3 and 4 elevations of serum creatinine was up to 2% and up to 1%, respectively. The incidence of Grade 3 and 4 proteinuria was up to 1% and up to 0.5%, respectively. Monitor renal function prior to starting AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ and annually thereafter. Monitor renal function at least every 6 months in patients who have additional risk factors for renal failure. AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ delays wound healing and increases the occurrence of wound-related complications like wound dehiscence, wound infection, incisional hernia, lymphocele, and seroma. These wound-related complications may require surgical intervention. Exercise caution with the use of AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ in the peri-surgical period. In the randomized hormone receptor-positive, HER2-negative breast cancer study (BOLERO-2), the incidence of deaths due to any cause within 28 days of the last AFINITOR dose was 6% in patients ≥ 65 years of age compared to 2% in patients &amp;lt; 65 years of age. Adverse reactions leading to permanent treatment discontinuation occurred in 33% of patients ≥ 65 years of age compared to 17% in patients &amp;lt; 65 years of age. Careful monitoring and appropriate dose adjustments for adverse reactions are recommended [see Dosage and Administration (2.9), Use in Specific Populations (8.5)] . Hyperglycemia, hypercholesterolemia, and hypertriglyceridemia have been reported in patients taking AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ at an incidence up to 75%, 86%, and 73%, respectively. The incidence of these Grade 3 and 4 laboratory abnormalities was up to 15% and up to 0.4%, respectively [see Adverse Reactions (6.1)] . In non-diabetic patients, monitor fasting serum glucose prior to starting AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ and annually thereafter. In diabetic patients, monitor fasting serum glucose more frequently as clinically indicated. Monitor lipid profile prior to starting AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ and annually thereafter. When possible, achieve optimal glucose and lipid control prior to starting AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ. For Grade 3 to 4 metabolic events, withhold or permanently discontinue AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ based on severity [see Dosage and Administration (2.9)] . Anemia, lymphopenia, neutropenia, and thrombocytopenia have been reported in patients taking AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ. The incidence of these Grade 3 and 4 laboratory abnormalities was up to 16% and up to 2%, respectively [see Adverse Reactions (6.1)] . Monitor complete blood count prior to starting AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ every 6 months for the first year of treatment and annually thereafter. Withhold or permanently discontinue AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ based on severity [see Dosage and Administration (2.9)] . The safety of immunization with live vaccines during AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ therapy has not been studied. Due to the potential increased risk of infection, avoid the use of live vaccines and close contact with individuals who have received live vaccines during treatment with AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ. Due to the potential increased risk of infection or reduced immune response with vaccination, complete the recommended childhood series of vaccinations according to American Council on Immunization Practices (ACIP) guidelines prior to the start of therapy. An accelerated vaccination schedule may be appropriate. Based on animal studies and the mechanism of action, AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. In animal studies, everolimus caused embryo-fetal toxicities in rats when administered during the period of organogenesis at maternal exposures that were lower than human exposures at the clinical dose of 10 mg once daily. Advise pregnant women of the potential risk to a fetus. Advise female patients of reproductive potential to avoid becoming pregnant and to use effective contraception during treatment with AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ and for 8 weeks after the last dose. Advise male patients with female partners of reproductive potential to use effective contraception during treatment with AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ and for 4 weeks after the last dose [see Use in Specific Populations (8.1, 8.3)] .</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Everolimus is an inhibitor of mammalian target of rapamycin (mTOR), a serine-threonine kinase, downstream of the PI3K/AKT pathway. The mTOR pathway is dysregulated in several human cancers and in tuberous sclerosis complex (TSC). Everolimus binds to an intracellular protein, FKBP-12, resulting in an inhibitory complex formation with mTOR complex 1 (mTORC1) and thus inhibition of mTOR kinase activity. Everolimus reduced the activity of S6 ribosomal protein kinase (S6K1) and eukaryotic initiation factor 4E-binding protein (4E-BP1), downstream effectors of mTOR, involved in protein synthesis. S6K1 is a substrate of mTORC1 and phosphorylates the activation domain 1 of the estrogen receptor which results in ligand-independent activation of the receptor. In addition, everolimus inhibited the expression of hypoxia-inducible factor (e.g., HIF-1) and reduced the expression of vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF). Inhibition of mTOR by everolimus has been shown to reduce cell proliferation, angiogenesis, and glucose uptake in in vitro and/or in vivo studies. Constitutive activation of the PI3K/Akt/mTOR pathway can contribute to endocrine resistance in breast cancer. In vitro studies show that estrogen-dependent and HER2+ breast cancer cells are sensitive to the inhibitory effects of everolimus, and that combination treatment with everolimus and Akt, HER2, or aromatase inhibitors enhances the anti-tumor activity of everolimus in a synergistic manner. Two regulators of mTORC1 signaling are the oncogene suppressors tuberin-sclerosis complexes 1 and 2 ( TSC1, TSC2 ). Loss or inactivation of either TSC1 or TSC2 leads to activation of downstream signaling. In TSC, a genetic disorder, inactivating mutations in either the TSC1 or the TSC2 gene lead to hamartoma formation throughout the body as well as seizures and epileptogenesis. Overactivation of mTOR results in neuronal dysplasia, aberrant axonogenesis and dendrite formation, increased excitatory synaptic currents, reduced myelination, and disruption of the cortical laminar structure causing abnormalities in neuronal development and function. Treatment with an mTOR inhibitor in animal models of mTOR dysregulation in the brain resulted in seizure suppression, prevention of the development of new-onset seizures, and prevention of premature death. Exposure-Response Relationship In patients with TSC-associated subependymal giant cell astrocytoma (SEGA), the magnitude of the reduction in SEGA volume was correlated with the everolimus trough concentration. In patients with TSC-associated partial-onset seizures, the magnitude of the reduction in absolute seizure frequency was correlated with the everolimus trough concentration. Cardiac Electrophysiology In a randomized, placebo-controlled, cross-over study, 59 healthy subjects were administered a single oral dose of AFINITOR (20 mg and 50 mg) and placebo. AFINITOR at single doses up to 50 mg did not prolong the QT/QTc interval. Absorption After administration of AFINITOR in patients with advanced solid tumors, peak everolimus concentrations are reached 1 to 2 hours after administration of oral doses ranging from 5 mg to 70 mg. Following single doses, C max is dose-proportional with daily dosing between 5 mg and 10 mg. With single doses of 20 mg and higher, the increase in C max is less than dose-proportional; however, AUC shows dose-proportionality over the 5 mg to 70 mg dose range. Steady-state was achieved within 2 weeks following once-daily dosing. In patients with TSC-associated SEGA, everolimus C min was approximately dose-proportional within the dose range from 1.35 mg/m 2 to 14.4 mg/m 2 . Effect of Food: In healthy subjects, a high-fat meal (containing approximately 1000 calories and 55 grams of fat) reduced systemic exposure to AFINITOR 10 mg (as measured by AUC) by 22% and the peak blood concentration C max by 54%. Light-fat meals (containing approximately 500 calories and 20 grams of fat) reduced AUC by 32% and C max by 42%. In healthy subjects who received 9 mg of AFINITOR DISPERZ, high-fat meals (containing approximately 1000 calories and 55 grams of fat) reduced everolimus AUC by 12% and C max by 60% and low-fat meals (containing approximately 500 calories and 20 grams of fat) reduced everolimus AUC by 30% and C max by 50%. Relative Bioavailability: The AUC inf of everolimus was equivalent between AFINITOR DISPERZ and AFINITOR; the C max of everolimus in the AFINITOR DISPERZ dosage form was 20% to 36% lower than that of AFINITOR. The predicted trough concentrations at steady-state were similar after daily administration. Distribution The blood-to-plasma ratio of everolimus, which is concentration-dependent over the range of 5 to 5000 ng/mL, is 17% to 73%. The amount of everolimus confined to the plasma is approximately 20% at blood concentrations observed in cancer patients given AFINITOR 10 mg orally once daily. Plasma protein binding is approximately 74% both in healthy subjects and in patients with moderate hepatic impairment. Elimination The mean elimination half-life of everolimus is approximately 30 hours. Metabolism: Everolimus is a substrate of CYP3A4. Following oral administration, everolimus is the main circulating component in human blood. Six main metabolites of everolimus have been detected in human blood, including three monohydroxylated metabolites, two hydrolytic ring-opened products, and a phosphatidylcholine conjugate of everolimus. These metabolites were also identified in animal species used in toxicity studies, and showed approximately 100-times less activity than everolimus itself. Excretion: No specific elimination studies have been undertaken in cancer patients. Following the administration of a 3 mg single dose of radiolabeled everolimus in patients who were receiving cyclosporine, 80% of the radioactivity was recovered from the feces, while 5% was excreted in the urine. The parent substance was not detected in urine or feces. Specific Populations No relationship was apparent between oral clearance and age or sex in patients with cancer. Patients with Renal Impairment: No significant influence of creatinine clearance (25 to 178 mL/min) was detected on oral clearance (CL/F) of everolimus. Patients with Hepatic Impairment: Compared to normal subjects, there was a 1.8-fold, 3.2-fold, and 3.6-fold increase in AUC for subjects with mild (Child-Pugh class A), moderate (Child-Pugh class B), and severe (Child-Pugh class C) hepatic impairment, respectively. In another study, the average AUC of everolimus in subjects with moderate hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh class B) was twice that found in subjects with normal hepatic function [see Dosage and Administration (2.10), Use in Specific Populations (8.6)] . Pediatric Patients: In patients with TSC-associated SEGA or TSC-associated partial-onset seizures, the mean C min values normalized to mg/m 2 dose in pediatric patients (&amp;lt; 18 years of age) were lower than those observed in adults, suggesting that everolimus clearance adjusted to body surface area was higher in pediatric patients as compared to adults. Race or Ethnicity: Based on a cross-study comparison, Japanese patients had on average exposures that were higher than non-Japanese patients receiving the same dose. Oral clearance (CL/F) is on average 20% higher in Black patients than in White patients. Drug Interaction Studies Effect of CYP3A4 and P-glycoprotein (P-gp) Inhibitors on Everolimus: Everolimus exposure increased when AFINITOR was coadministered with: ketoconazole (a P-gp and strong CYP3A4 inhibitor) - C max and AUC increased by 3.9- and 15-fold, respectively. erythromycin (a P-gp and moderate CYP3A4 inhibitor) - C max and AUC increased by 2- and 4.4-fold, respectively. verapamil (a P-gp and moderate CYP3A4 inhibitor) - C max and AUC increased by 2.3- and 3.5-fold, respectively. Effect of CYP3A4 and P-gp Inducers on Everolimus: The coadministration of AFINITOR with rifampin, a P-gp and strong inducer of CYP3A4, decreased everolimus AUC by 63% and Cmax by 58% compared to AFINITOR alone [see Dosage and Administration (2.12)] . Effect of Everolimus on CYP3A4 Substrates: No clinically significant pharmacokinetic interactions were observed between AFINITOR and the HMG-CoA reductase inhibitors atorvastatin (a CYP3A4 substrate), pravastatin (a non-CYP3A4 substrate), and simvastatin (a CYP3A4 substrate). The coadministration of an oral dose of midazolam (sensitive CYP3A4 substrate) with AFINITOR resulted in a 25% increase in midazolam C max and a 30% increase in midazolam AUC 0-inf . The coadministration of AFINITOR with exemestane increased exemestane Cmin by 45% and C2 h by 64%; however, the corresponding estradiol levels at steady state (4 weeks) were not different between the 2 treatment arms. No increase in adverse reactions related to exemestane was observed in patients with hormone receptor-positive, HER2-negative advanced breast cancer receiving the combination. The coadministration of AFINITOR with long acting octreotide increased octreotide C min by approximately 50%. Effect of Everolimus on Antiepileptic drugs (AEDs): Everolimus increased pre-dose concentrations of the carbamazepine, clobazam, oxcarbazepine, and clobazam’s metabolite N-desmethylclobazam by about 10%. Everolimus had no impact on pre-dose concentrations of AEDs that are substrates of CYP3A4 (e.g., clonazepam and zonisamide) or other AEDs, including valproic acid, topiramate, phenobarbital, and phenytoin.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="5297" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ is contraindicated in patients with clinically significant hypersensitivity to everolimus or to other rapamycin derivatives.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5298" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Clinically significant hypersensitivity to everolimus or to other rapamycin derivatives.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5299" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not combine AFINITOR and AFINITOR DISPERZ to achieve the total daily dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5300" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Modify the dose for patients with hepatic impairment or for patients taking drugs that inhibit or induce P-glycoprotein (P-gp) and CYP3A4.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M11" type="Trigger" span="0 15" str="Modify the dose"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="76 10;98 6;131 6" str="drugs that | induce | CYP3A4" code="N0000185506"/>
<Mention id="M4" type="Precipitant" span="76 10;98 6;121 4" str="drugs that | induce | P-gp" code="N0000191264"/>
<Mention id="M6" type="Precipitant" span="76 10;98 21" str="drugs that | induce P-glycoprotein" code="N0000191264"/>
<Mention id="M8" type="Precipitant" span="76 18;131 6" str="drugs that inhibit | CYP3A4" code="N0000182141"/>
<Mention id="M10" type="Precipitant" span="76 18;105 14" str="drugs that inhibit | P-glycoprotein" code="N0000185503"/>
<Mention id="M12" type="Precipitant" span="76 18;121 4" str="drugs that inhibit | P-gp" code="N0000185503"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M11" precipitant="M2"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M11" precipitant="M4"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M11" precipitant="M6"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M11" precipitant="M8"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M11" precipitant="M10"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M11" precipitant="M12"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5301" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Breast Cancer: 10 mg orally once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5302" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>NET: 10 mg orally once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5303" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>RCC: 10 mg orally once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5304" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>TSC-Associated Renal Angiomyolipoma: 10 mg orally once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5305" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>TSC-Associated SEGA: 4.5 mg/m2 orally once daily; adjust dose to attain trough concentrations of 5-15 ng/mL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5306" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>TSC-Associated Partial-Onset Seizures: 5 mg/m2 orally once daily; adjust dose to attain trough concentrations of 5-15 ng/mL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5307" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>AFINITOR and AFINITOR DISPERZ are two different dosage forms.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5308" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Select the recommended dosage form based on the indication.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5309" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not combine AFINITOR and AFINITOR DISPERZ to achieve the total dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5310" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Modify the dosage for patients with hepatic impairment or for patients taking drugs that inhibit or induce P-glycoprotein (P-gp) and CYP3A4.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M23" type="Trigger" span="0 17" str="Modify the dosage"/>
<Mention id="M14" type="Precipitant" span="78 10;100 6;133 6" str="drugs that | induce | CYP3A4" code="N0000185506"/>
<Mention id="M16" type="Precipitant" span="78 10;100 6;123 4" str="drugs that | induce | P-gp" code="N0000191264"/>
<Mention id="M18" type="Precipitant" span="78 10;100 21" str="drugs that | induce P-glycoprotein" code="N0000191264"/>
<Mention id="M20" type="Precipitant" span="78 18;133 6" str="drugs that inhibit | CYP3A4" code="N0000182141"/>
<Mention id="M22" type="Precipitant" span="78 18;107 14" str="drugs that inhibit | P-glycoprotein" code="N0000185503"/>
<Mention id="M24" type="Precipitant" span="78 18;123 4" str="drugs that inhibit | P-gp" code="N0000185503"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M23" precipitant="M14"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M23" precipitant="M16"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M23" precipitant="M18"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M23" precipitant="M20"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M23" precipitant="M22"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M23" precipitant="M24"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5311" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommended dosage of AFINITOR is 10 mg orally once daily until disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5312" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommended starting dosage of AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ is 4.5 mg/m2 orally once daily until disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5313" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommended starting dosage of AFINITOR DISPERZ is 5 mg/m2 orally once daily until disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5314" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor everolimus whole blood trough concentrations at time points recommended in Table 1.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5315" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Titrate the dose to attain trough concentrations of 5 ng/mL to 15 ng/mL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5316" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Adjust the dose using the following equation: New dose* = current dose x (target concentration divided by current concentration) *The maximum dose increment at any titration must not exceed 5 mg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5317" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Multiple dose titrations may be required to attain the target trough concentration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5318" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>When possible, use the same assay and laboratory for therapeutic drug monitoring throughout treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5319" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Table 1: Recommended Timing of Therapeutic Drug Monitoring Event When to Assess Trough Concentrations After Event Initiation of AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ 1 to 2 weeks Modification of AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ dose 1 to 2 weeks Switch between AFINITOR and AFINITOR DISPERZ 1 to 2 weeks Initiation or discontinuation of P-gp and moderate CYP3A4 inhibitor 2 weeks Initiation or discontinuation of P-gp and strong CYP3A4 inducer 2 weeks Change in hepatic function 2 weeks Stable dose with changing body surface area Every 3 to 6 months Stable dose with stable body surface area Every 6 to 12 months Table 2 summarizes recommendations for dosage modifications of AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ for the management of adverse reactions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5320" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Table 2: Recommended Dosage Modifications for AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ for Adverse Reactions Adverse Reaction Severity Dosage Modification Non-infectious pneumonitis Grade 2 Withhold until improvement to Grade 0 or 1.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5321" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Resume at 50% of previous dose; change to every other day dosing if the reduced dose is lower than the lowest available strength.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5322" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Permanently discontinue if toxicity does not resolve or improve to Grade 1 within 4 weeks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5323" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Grade 3 Withhold until improvement to Grade 0 or 1.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5324" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Resume at 50% of previous dose; change to every other day dosing if the reduced dose is lower than the lowest available strength.If toxicity recurs at Grade 3, permanently discontinue.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5325" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Stomatitis Grade 2 Withhold until improvement to Grade 0 or 1.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5326" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If recurs at Grade 2, withhold until improvement to Grade 0 or 1.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5327" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Metabolic events (e.g., hyperglycemia, dyslipidemia) Grade 3 Withhold until improvement to Grade 0, 1, or 2.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5328" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Other non-hematologic toxicities Grade 2 If toxicity becomes intolerable, withhold until improvement to Grade 0 or 1.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5329" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If toxicity recurs at Grade 2, withhold until improvement to Grade 0 or 1.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5330" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Consider resuming at 50% of previous dose; change to every other day dosing if the reduced dose is lower than the lowest available strength.If recurs at Grade 3, permanently discontinue.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5331" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Thrombocytopenia Grade 2 Withhold until improvement to Grade 0 or 1.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5332" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Grade 3 OR Grade 4 Withhold until improvement to Grade 0 or 1.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5333" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Neutropenia Grade 3 Withhold until improvement to Grade 0, 1 or 2.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5334" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Grade 4 Withhold until improvement to Grade 0, 1 or 2.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5335" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Febrile neutropenia Grade 3 Withhold until improvement to Grade 0, 1 or 2 and no fever.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5336" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommended dosages of AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ for patients with hepatic impairment are described in Table 3 : Table 3: Recommended Dosage Modifications for Patients with Hepatic Impairment Indication Dose Modification for AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ Breast Cancer, NET, RCC, and TSC-Associated Renal Angiomyolipoma Mild hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh class A) – 7.5 mg orally once daily; decrease the dose to 5 mg orally once daily if a dose of 7.5 mg once daily is not tolerated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5337" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Moderate hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh class B) – 5 mg orally once daily; decrease the dose to 2.5 mg orally once daily if a dose of 5 mg once daily is not tolerated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5338" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Severe hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh class C) – 2.5 mg orally once daily if the desired benefit outweighs the risk; do not exceed a dose of 2.5 mg once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5339" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>TSC-Associated SEGA and TSC-Associated Partial-Onset Seizures Severe hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh class C) – 2.5 mg/m2 orally once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5340" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Adjust dose based on everolimus trough concentrations as recommended.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5341" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Avoid the concomitant use of P-gp and strong CYP3A4 inhibitors.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M27" type="Trigger" span="0 5" str="Avoid"/>
<Mention id="M26" type="Precipitant" span="29 4;52 10" str="P-gp | inhibitors" code="N0000185503"/>
<Mention id="M28" type="Precipitant" span="38 24" str="strong CYP3A4 inhibitors" code="N0000182141"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M27" precipitant="M26"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M27" precipitant="M28"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5342" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Avoid ingesting grapefruit and grapefruit juice.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M31" type="Trigger" span="0 5" str="Avoid"/>
<Mention id="M30" type="Precipitant" span="16 10" str="grapefruit" code="O82C39RR8C"/>
<Mention id="M32" type="Precipitant" span="31 16" str="grapefruit juice" code="n0000164879 | JQ9EK2H6BG"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M31" precipitant="M30"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M31" precipitant="M32"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5343" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Reduce the dose for patients taking AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ with a P-gp and moderate CYP3A4 inhibitor as recommended in Table 4.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M35" type="Trigger" span="0 15" str="Reduce the dose"/>
<Mention id="M34" type="Precipitant" span="78 25" str="moderate CYP3A4 inhibitor" code="N0000182141"/>
<Mention id="M36" type="Precipitant" span="69 4;94 9" str="P-gp | inhibitor" code="N0000185503"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M34" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M36" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5344" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Table 4: Recommended Dosage Modifications for Concurrent Use of AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ with a P-gp and Moderate CYP3A4 Inhibitor Indication Dose Modification for AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ Breast Cancer, NET, RCC, and TSC-Associated Renal Angiomyolipoma Reduce dose to 2.5 mg once daily.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M39" type="Trigger" span="256 11" str="Reduce dose"/>
<Mention id="M38" type="Precipitant" span="106 25" str="Moderate CYP3A4 Inhibitor" code="N0000182141"/>
<Mention id="M40" type="Precipitant" span="97 4;122 9" str="P-gp | Inhibitor" code="N0000185503"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M39" precipitant="M38" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M39" precipitant="M40" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5345" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>May increase dose to 5 mg once daily if tolerated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5346" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Resume dose administered prior to inhibitor initiation, once the inhibitor is discontinued for 3 days.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5347" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>TSC-Associated SEGA and TSC-Associated Partial-Onset Seizures Reduce the daily dose by 50%.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5348" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Change to every other day dosing if the reduced dose is lower than the lowest available strength.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5349" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Assess trough concentrations when initiating and discontinuing the inhibitor.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5350" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Avoid concomitant use of St. John’s Wort (Hypericum perforatum).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M43" type="Trigger" span="0 5" str="Avoid"/>
<Mention id="M42" type="Precipitant" span="42 20" str="Hypericum perforatum" code="XK4IUX8MNB"/>
<Mention id="M44" type="Precipitant" span="25 15" str="St. John’s Wort" code="N0000022261 | UFH8805FKA"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M43" precipitant="M42"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M43" precipitant="M44"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5351" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Increase the dose for patients taking AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ with a P-gp and strong CYP3A4 inducer as recommended in Table 5.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M47" type="Trigger" span="0 17" str="Increase the dose"/>
<Mention id="M46" type="Precipitant" span="71 4;94 7" str="P-gp | inducer" code="N0000191264"/>
<Mention id="M48" type="Precipitant" span="80 21" str="strong CYP3A4 inducer" code="N0000185506"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M47" precipitant="M46" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M47" precipitant="M48" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5352" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Table 5: Recommended Dosage Modifications for Concurrent Use of AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ with P-gp and Strong CYP3A4 Inducers Indication Dose Modification for AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ Breast Cancer, NET, RCC, and TSC-Associated Renal Angiomyolipoma Avoid coadministration where alternatives exist.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M51" type="Trigger" span="138 17" str="Dose Modification"/>
<Mention id="M50" type="Precipitant" span="95 4;118 8" str="P-gp | Inducers" code="N0000191264"/>
<Mention id="M52" type="Precipitant" span="104 22" str="Strong CYP3A4 Inducers" code="N0000185506"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M51" precipitant="M50"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M51" precipitant="M52"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5353" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If coadministration cannot be avoided, double the daily dose using increments of 5 mg or less.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5354" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Resume the dose administered prior to inducer initiation, once an inducer is discontinued for 5 days.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5355" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>TSC-Associated SEGA and TSC-Associated Partial-Onset Seizures Double the daily dose using increments of 5 mg or less.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5356" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Addition of another strong CYP3A4 inducer in a patient already receiving treatment with a strong CYP3A4 inducer may not require additional dosage modification.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M53" type="Trigger" span="139 19" str="dosage modification"/>
<Mention id="M54" type="Precipitant" span="20 21" str="strong CYP3A4 inducer" code="N0000185506"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M53" precipitant="M54"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5357" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Assess trough concentrations when initiating and discontinuing the inducer.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5358" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Resume the dose administered before starting any inducer, once all inducers are discontinued for 5 days.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5359" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Administer AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ at the same time each day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5360" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Administer AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ consistently either with or without food.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5361" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If a dose of AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ is missed, it can be administered up to 6 hours after the time it is normally administered.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5362" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>After more than 6 hours, the dose should be skipped for that day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5363" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The next day, AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ should be administered at its usual time.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5364" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Double doses should not be administered to make up for the dose that was missed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5365" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>AFINITOR AFINITOR should be swallowed whole with a glass of water.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5366" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>AFINITOR DISPERZ Wear gloves to avoid possible contact with everolimus when preparing suspensions of AFINITOR DISPERZ for another person.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5367" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Administer suspension immediately after preparation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5368" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Discard suspension if not administered within 60 minutes after preparation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5369" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Using an Oral Syringe to Prepare Oral Suspension: Place the prescribed dose into a 10-mL syringe.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5370" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not exceed a total of 10 mg per syringe.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5371" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If higher doses are required, prepare an additional syringe.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5372" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Draw approximately 5 mL of water and 4 mL of air into the syringe.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5373" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Place the filled syringe into a container (tip up) for 3 minutes, until the tablets are in suspension.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5374" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Gently invert the syringe 5 times immediately prior to administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5375" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>After administration of the prepared suspension, draw approximately 5 mL of water and 4 mL of air into the same syringe, and swirl the contents to suspend remaining particles.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5376" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Administer the entire contents of the syringe.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5377" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Using a Small Drinking Glass to Prepare Oral Suspension: Place the prescribed dose into a small drinking glass (maximum size 100 mL) containing approximately 25 mL of water.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5378" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not exceed a total of 10 mg per glass.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5379" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If higher doses are required, prepare an additional glass.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5380" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Stir the contents gently with a spoon, immediately prior to drinking.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5381" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>After administration of the prepared suspension, add 25 mL of water and stir with the same spoon to re-suspend remaining particles.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5382" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Administer the entire contents of the glass.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5383" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>P-gp and strong CYP3A4 inhibitors: Avoid concomitant use.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M57" type="Trigger" span="35 5" str="Avoid"/>
<Mention id="M56" type="Precipitant" span="0 4;23 10" str="P-gp | inhibitors" code="N0000185503"/>
<Mention id="M58" type="Precipitant" span="9 24" str="strong CYP3A4 inhibitors" code="N0000182141"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M57" precipitant="M56"/>
<Interaction id="I29" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M57" precipitant="M58"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5384" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>P-gp and moderate CYP3A4 inhibitors: Reduce the dose as recommended.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M61" type="Trigger" span="37 15" str="Reduce the dose"/>
<Mention id="M60" type="Precipitant" span="9 26" str="moderate CYP3A4 inhibitors" code="N0000182141"/>
<Mention id="M62" type="Precipitant" span="0 4;25 10" str="P-gp | inhibitors" code="N0000185503"/>
<Interaction id="I30" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M61" precipitant="M60" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I31" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M61" precipitant="M62" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5385" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>P-gp and strong CYP3A4 inducers: Increase the dose as recommended.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M65" type="Trigger" span="33 17" str="Increase the dose"/>
<Mention id="M64" type="Precipitant" span="0 4;23 8" str="P-gp | inducers" code="N0000191264"/>
<Mention id="M66" type="Precipitant" span="9 22" str="strong CYP3A4 inducers" code="N0000185506"/>
<Interaction id="I32" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M65" precipitant="M64" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I33" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M65" precipitant="M66" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5386" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Inhibitors Avoid the concomitant use of P-gp and strong CYP3A4 inhibitors.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M69" type="Trigger" span="11 5" str="Avoid"/>
<Mention id="M68" type="Precipitant" span="40 4;0 10" str="P-gp | inhibitors" code="N0000185503"/>
<Mention id="M70" type="Precipitant" span="49 24" str="strong CYP3A4 inhibitors" code="N0000182141"/>
<Interaction id="I34" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M69" precipitant="M68"/>
<Interaction id="I35" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M69" precipitant="M70"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5387" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Reduce the dose for patients taking AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ with a P-gp and moderate CYP3A4 inhibitor as recommended.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M73" type="Trigger" span="0 15" str="Reduce the dose"/>
<Mention id="M72" type="Precipitant" span="78 25" str="moderate CYP3A4 inhibitor" code="N0000182141"/>
<Mention id="M74" type="Precipitant" span="69 4;94 9" str="P-gp | inhibitor" code="N0000185503"/>
<Interaction id="I36" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M73" precipitant="M72" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I37" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M73" precipitant="M74" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5388" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Inducers Increase the dose for patients taking AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ with a P-gp and strong CYP3A4 inducer as recommended.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M77" type="Trigger" span="9 17" str="Increase the dose"/>
<Mention id="M76" type="Precipitant" span="80 4;0 7" str="P-gp | inducer" code="N0000191264"/>
<Mention id="M78" type="Precipitant" span="89 21" str="strong CYP3A4 inducer" code="N0000185506"/>
<Interaction id="I38" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M77" precipitant="M76" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I39" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M77" precipitant="M78" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5389" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Patients taking concomitant ACE inhibitors with AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ may be at increased risk for angioedema.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M79" type="Trigger" span="84 14" str="increased risk"/>
<Mention id="M80" type="Precipitant" span="28 14" str="ACE inhibitors" code="N0000000181 | N0000175562 | N0000029130"/>
<Mention id="M81" type="SpecificInteraction" span="103 10" str="angioedema" code="41291007: Angioedema (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I40" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M79" precipitant="M80" effect="M81" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5390" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Avoid the concomitant use of ACE inhibitors with AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M82" type="Trigger" span="0 5" str="Avoid"/>
<Mention id="M83" type="Precipitant" span="29 14" str="ACE inhibitors" code="N0000000181 | N0000175562 | N0000029130"/>
<Interaction id="I41" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M82" precipitant="M83"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5391" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Non-Infectious Pneumonitis: Monitor for clinical symptoms or radiological changes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5392" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Withhold or permanently discontinue based on severity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5393" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Infections: Monitor for signs and symptoms of infection.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5394" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Severe Hypersensitivity Reactions: Permanently discontinue for clinically significant hypersensitivity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5395" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Angioedema: Patients taking concomitant ACE inhibitors may be at increased risk for angioedema.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M84" type="Trigger" span="65 14" str="increased risk"/>
<Mention id="M85" type="Precipitant" span="40 14" str="ACE inhibitors" code="N0000000181 | N0000175562 | N0000029130"/>
<Mention id="M86" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 10" str="angioedema" code="41291007: Angioedema (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I42" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M84" precipitant="M85" effect="M86" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5396" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Stomatitis: Initiate dexamethasone alcohol-free mouthwash when starting treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5397" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Renal Failure: Monitor renal function prior to treatment and periodically thereafter.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5398" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Impaired Wound Healing: Exercise caution in the peri-surgical period.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5399" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Geriatric Patients: Monitor and adjust dose for adverse reactions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5400" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Metabolic Disorders: Monitor serum glucose and lipids prior to treatment and periodically thereafter.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5401" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Withhold or permanently discontinue based on severity (2.9, 5.9) Myelosuppression: Monitor hematologic parameters prior to treatment and periodically thereafter.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5402" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Risk of Infection or Reduced Immune Response with Vaccination: Avoid live vaccines and close contact with those who have received live vaccines.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M90" type="Trigger" span="0 7" str="Risk of"/>
<Mention id="M91" type="Precipitant" span="69 13" str="live vaccines" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M89" type="SpecificInteraction" span="8 9" str="Infection" code="40733004: Infectious disease (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M92" type="SpecificInteraction" span="21 23" str="Reduced Immune Response" code="71922006: Immune defect (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I43" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M90" precipitant="M91" effect="M89" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I44" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M90" precipitant="M91" effect="M92" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5403" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Complete recommended childhood vaccinations prior to starting treatment.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M93" type="Trigger" span="0 8;44 8" str="Complete | prior to"/>
<Mention id="M94" type="Precipitant" span="9 34" str="recommended childhood vaccinations" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I45" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M93" precipitant="M94"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5404" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Embryo-Fetal Toxicity: Can cause fetal harm.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5405" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Advise patients of reproductive potential of the potential risk to a fetus and to use effective contraception.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5406" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Non-infectious pneumonitis is a class effect of rapamycin derivatives.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5407" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Non-infectious pneumonitis was reported in up to 19% of patients treated with AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ in clinical trials, some cases were reported with pulmonary hypertension (including pulmonary arterial hypertension) as a secondary event.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5408" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The incidence of Grade 3 and 4 non-infectious pneumonitis was up to 4% and up to 0.2%, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5409" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Consider a diagnosis of non-infectious pneumonitis in patients presenting with non-specific respiratory signs and symptoms.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5410" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Consider opportunistic infections such as pneumocystis jiroveci pneumonia (PJP) in the differential diagnosis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5411" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Advise patients to report promptly any new or worsening respiratory symptoms.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5412" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Continue AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ without dose alteration in patients who develop radiological changes suggestive of non-infectious pneumonitis and have few or no symptoms.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5413" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Imaging appears to overestimate the incidence of clinical pneumonitis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5414" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>For Grade 2 to 4 non-infectious pneumonitis, withhold or permanently discontinue AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ based on severity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5415" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Corticosteroids may be indicated until clinical symptoms resolve.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5416" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Administer prophylaxis for PJP when concomitant use of corticosteroids or other immunosuppressive agents are required.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M98" type="Trigger" span="11 15;109 8" str="prophylaxis for | required"/>
<Mention id="M96" type="Precipitant" span="55 15" str="corticosteroids" code="N0000011309 | N0000175576"/>
<Mention id="M100" type="SpecificInteraction" span="27 3" str="PJP" code="415125002: Pneumocystosis jirovecii pneumonia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M99" type="Precipitant" span="80 24" str="immunosuppressive agents" code="N0000175550"/>
<Interaction id="I46" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M98" precipitant="M96" effect="M100" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I47" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M98" precipitant="M99" effect="M100" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5417" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The development of pneumonitis has been reported even at a reduced dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5418" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ has immunosuppressive properties and may predispose patients to bacterial, fungal, viral, or protozoal infections, including infections with opportunistic pathogens.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5419" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Localized and systemic infections, including pneumonia, mycobacterial infections, other bacterial infections, invasive fungal infections (e.g., aspergillosis, candidiasis, or PJP) and viral infections (e.g., reactivation of hepatitis B virus) have occurred.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5420" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Some of these infections have been severe (e.g., sepsis, septic shock, or resulting in multisystem organ failure) or fatal.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5421" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The incidence of Grade 3 and 4 infections was up to 10% and up to 3%, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5422" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The incidence of serious infections was reported at a higher frequency in patients &lt; 6 years of age.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5423" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Complete treatment of preexisting invasive fungal infections prior to starting treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5424" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor for signs and symptoms of infection.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5425" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Withhold or permanently discontinue AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ based on severity of infection.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5426" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hypersensitivity reactions to AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ have been observed and include anaphylaxis, dyspnea, flushing, chest pain, and angioedema (e.g., swelling of the airways or tongue, with or without respiratory impairment).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5427" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The incidence of Grade 3 hypersensitivity reactions was up to 1%.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5428" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Permanently discontinue AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ for the development of clinically significant hypersensitivity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5429" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients taking concomitant ACE inhibitors with AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ may be at increased risk for angioedema (e.g., swelling of the airways or tongue, with or without respiratory impairment).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M101" type="Trigger" span="84 14" str="increased risk"/>
<Mention id="M102" type="Precipitant" span="28 14" str="ACE inhibitors" code="N0000000181 | N0000175562 | N0000029130"/>
<Mention id="M103" type="SpecificInteraction" span="103 10" str="angioedema" code="41291007: Angioedema (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I48" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M101" precipitant="M102" effect="M103" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5430" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In a pooled analysis of randomized double-blind oncology clinical trials, the incidence of angioedema in patients taking AFINITOR with an ACE inhibitor was 6.8% compared to 1.3% in the control arm with an ACE inhibitor.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M104" type="Trigger" span="78 9" str="incidence"/>
<Mention id="M105" type="Precipitant" span="138 13" str="ACE inhibitor" code="N0000000181 | N0000175562"/>
<Mention id="M106" type="SpecificInteraction" span="91 10" str="angioedema" code="41291007: Angioedema (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I49" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M104" precipitant="M105" effect="M106" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5431" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Permanently discontinue AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ for angioedema.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5432" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Stomatitis, including mouth ulcers and oral mucositis, has occurred in patients treated with AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ at an incidence ranging from 44% to 78% across clinical trials.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5433" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Grades 3-4 stomatitis was reported in 4% to 9% of patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5434" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Stomatitis most often occurs within the first 8 weeks of treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5435" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>When starting AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ, initiating dexamethasone alcohol-free oral solution as a swish and spit mouthwash reduces the incidence and severity of stomatitis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5436" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If stomatitis does occur, mouthwashes and/or other topical treatments are recommended.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5437" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Avoid alcohol-, hydrogen peroxide-, iodine-, or thyme- containing products, as they may exacerbate the condition.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M128" type="Trigger" span="0 5" str="Avoid "/>
<Mention id="M129" type="Trigger" span="88 10" str=" exacerbate"/>
<Mention id="M109" type="Precipitant" span="6 7" str="alcohol" code="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M"/>
<Mention id="M112" type="Precipitant" span="6 7;55 19" str="alcohol | containing products" code="3K9958V90M"/>
<Mention id="M115" type="Precipitant" span="16 17" str="hydrogen peroxide" code="BBX060AN9V"/>
<Mention id="M118" type="Precipitant" span="16 17;55 19" str="hydrogen peroxide | containing products" code="BBX060AN9V"/>
<Mention id="M121" type="Precipitant" span="36 6" str="iodine" code="9679TC07X4"/>
<Mention id="M124" type="Precipitant" span="36 6;55 19" str="iodine | containing products" code="9679TC07X4"/>
<Mention id="M127" type="Precipitant" span="48 5" str="thyme" code="CW657OBU4N"/>
<Mention id="M130" type="Precipitant" span="48 5;55 19" str="thyme | containing products" code="CW657OBU4N"/>
<Interaction id="I50" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M128;M129" precipitant="M109"/>
<Interaction id="I51" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M128;M129" precipitant="M112"/>
<Interaction id="I52" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M128;M129" precipitant="M115"/>
<Interaction id="I53" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M128;M129" precipitant="M118"/>
<Interaction id="I54" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M128;M129" precipitant="M121"/>
<Interaction id="I55" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M128;M129" precipitant="M124"/>
<Interaction id="I56" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M128;M129" precipitant="M127"/>
<Interaction id="I57" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M128;M129" precipitant="M130"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5438" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Do not administer antifungal agents, unless fungal infection has been diagnosed.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M131" type="Trigger" span="0 17" str="Do not administer"/>
<Mention id="M132" type="Precipitant" span="18 17" str="antifungal agents" code="N0000178297"/>
<Interaction id="I58" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M131" precipitant="M132"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5439" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Cases of renal failure (including acute renal failure), some with a fatal outcome, have occurred in patients taking AFINITOR.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5440" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Elevations of serum creatinine and proteinuria have been reported in patients taking AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5441" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The incidence of Grade 3 and 4 elevations of serum creatinine was up to 2% and up to 1%, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5442" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The incidence of Grade 3 and 4 proteinuria was up to 1% and up to 0.5%, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5443" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor renal function prior to starting AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ and annually thereafter.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5444" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor renal function at least every 6 months in patients who have additional risk factors for renal failure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5445" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ delays wound healing and increases the occurrence of wound-related complications like wound dehiscence, wound infection, incisional hernia, lymphocele, and seroma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5446" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>These wound-related complications may require surgical intervention.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5447" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Exercise caution with the use of AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ in the peri-surgical period.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5448" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In the randomized hormone receptor-positive, HER2-negative breast cancer study (BOLERO-2), the incidence of deaths due to any cause within 28 days of the last AFINITOR dose was 6% in patients ≥ 65 years of age compared to 2% in patients &lt; 65 years of age.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5449" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Adverse reactions leading to permanent treatment discontinuation occurred in 33% of patients ≥ 65 years of age compared to 17% in patients &lt; 65 years of age.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5450" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Careful monitoring and appropriate dose adjustments for adverse reactions are recommended.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5451" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hyperglycemia, hypercholesterolemia, and hypertriglyceridemia have been reported in patients taking AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ at an incidence up to 75%, 86%, and 73%, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5452" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The incidence of these Grade 3 and 4 laboratory abnormalities was up to 15% and up to 0.4%, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5453" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In non-diabetic patients, monitor fasting serum glucose prior to starting AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ and annually thereafter.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5454" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In diabetic patients, monitor fasting serum glucose more frequently as clinically indicated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5455" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor lipid profile prior to starting AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ and annually thereafter.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5456" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>When possible, achieve optimal glucose and lipid control prior to starting AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5457" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>For Grade 3 to 4 metabolic events, withhold or permanently discontinue AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ based on severity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5458" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Anemia, lymphopenia, neutropenia, and thrombocytopenia have been reported in patients taking AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5459" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The incidence of these Grade 3 and 4 laboratory abnormalities was up to 16% and up to 2%, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5460" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor complete blood count prior to starting AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ every 6 months for the first year of treatment and annually thereafter.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5461" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Withhold or permanently discontinue AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ based on severity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5462" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The safety of immunization with live vaccines during AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ therapy has not been studied.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5463" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Due to the potential increased risk of infection, avoid the use of live vaccines and close contact with individuals who have received live vaccines during treatment with AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M133" type="Trigger" span="21 14" str="increased risk"/>
<Mention id="M134" type="Precipitant" span="67 13" str="live vaccines" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M135" type="SpecificInteraction" span="39 9" str="infection" code="40733004: Infectious disease (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I59" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M133" precipitant="M134" effect="M135" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5464" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Due to the potential increased risk of infection or reduced immune response with vaccination, complete the recommended childhood series of vaccinations according to American Council on Immunization Practices (ACIP) guidelines prior to the start of therapy.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M139" type="Trigger" span="21 14" str="increased risk"/>
<Mention id="M140" type="Precipitant" span="81 11" str="vaccination" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M138" type="SpecificInteraction" span="39 9" str="Infection" code="40733004: Infectious disease (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M141" type="SpecificInteraction" span="52 23" str="Reduced Immune Response" code="71922006: Immune defect (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M142" type="Trigger" span="94 8;226 8" str="complete | prior to"/>
<Mention id="M143" type="Precipitant" span="107 21;139 12" str="recommended childhood | vaccinations" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I60" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M139" precipitant="M140" effect="M138" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I61" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M139" precipitant="M140" effect="M141" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I62" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M142" precipitant="M143"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5465" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>An accelerated vaccination schedule may be appropriate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5466" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Based on animal studies and the mechanism of action, AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5467" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In animal studies, everolimus caused embryo-fetal toxicities in rats when administered during the period of organogenesis at maternal exposures that were lower than human exposures at the clinical dose of 10 mg once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5468" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Advise pregnant women of the potential risk to a fetus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5469" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Advise female patients of reproductive potential to avoid becoming pregnant and to use effective contraception during treatment with AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ and for 8 weeks after the last dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5470" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Advise male patients with female partners of reproductive potential to use effective contraception during treatment with AFINITOR/AFINITOR DISPERZ and for 4 weeks after the last dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5471" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Everolimus is an inhibitor of mammalian target of rapamycin (mTOR), a serine-threonine kinase, downstream of the PI3K/AKT pathway.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5472" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mTOR pathway is dysregulated in several human cancers and in tuberous sclerosis complex (TSC).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5473" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Everolimus binds to an intracellular protein, FKBP-12, resulting in an inhibitory complex formation with mTOR complex 1 (mTORC1) and thus inhibition of mTOR kinase activity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5474" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Everolimus reduced the activity of S6 ribosomal protein kinase (S6K1) and eukaryotic initiation factor 4E-binding protein (4E-BP1), downstream effectors of mTOR, involved in protein synthesis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5475" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>S6K1 is a substrate of mTORC1 and phosphorylates the activation domain 1 of the estrogen receptor which results in ligand-independent activation of the receptor.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5476" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In addition, everolimus inhibited the expression of hypoxia-inducible factor (e.g., HIF-1) and reduced the expression of vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5477" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Inhibition of mTOR by everolimus has been shown to reduce cell proliferation, angiogenesis, and glucose uptake in in vitro and/or in vivo studies.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5478" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Constitutive activation of the PI3K/Akt/mTOR pathway can contribute to endocrine resistance in breast cancer.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5479" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In vitro studies show that estrogen-dependent and HER2+ breast cancer cells are sensitive to the inhibitory effects of everolimus, and that combination treatment with everolimus and Akt, HER2, or aromatase inhibitors enhances the anti-tumor activity of everolimus in a synergistic manner.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5480" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Two regulators of mTORC1 signaling are the oncogene suppressors tuberin-sclerosis complexes 1 and 2 (TSC1, TSC2).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5481" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Loss or inactivation of either TSC1 or TSC2 leads to activation of downstream signaling.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5482" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In TSC, a genetic disorder, inactivating mutations in either the TSC1 or the TSC2 gene lead to hamartoma formation throughout the body as well as seizures and epileptogenesis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5483" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Overactivation of mTOR results in neuronal dysplasia, aberrant axonogenesis and dendrite formation, increased excitatory synaptic currents, reduced myelination, and disruption of the cortical laminar structure causing abnormalities in neuronal development and function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5484" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Treatment with an mTOR inhibitor in animal models of mTOR dysregulation in the brain resulted in seizure suppression, prevention of the development of new-onset seizures, and prevention of premature death.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5485" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Exposure-Response Relationship In patients with TSC-associated subependymal giant cell astrocytoma (SEGA), the magnitude of the reduction in SEGA volume was correlated with the everolimus trough concentration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5486" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In patients with TSC-associated partial-onset seizures, the magnitude of the reduction in absolute seizure frequency was correlated with the everolimus trough concentration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5487" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Cardiac Electrophysiology In a randomized, placebo-controlled, cross-over study, 59 healthy subjects were administered a single oral dose of AFINITOR (20 mg and 50 mg) and placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5488" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>AFINITOR at single doses up to 50 mg did not prolong the QT/QTc interval.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5489" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Absorption After administration of AFINITOR in patients with advanced solid tumors, peak everolimus concentrations are reached 1 to 2 hours after administration of oral doses ranging from 5 mg to 70 mg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5490" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following single doses, Cmax is dose-proportional with daily dosing between 5 mg and 10 mg. With single doses of 20 mg and higher, the increase in Cmax is less than dose-proportional; however, AUC shows dose-proportionality over the 5 mg to 70 mg dose range.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5491" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Steady-state was achieved within 2 weeks following once-daily dosing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5492" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In patients with TSC-associated SEGA, everolimus Cmin was approximately dose-proportional within the dose range from 1.35 mg/m2 to 14.4 mg/m2.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5493" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Effect of Food: In healthy subjects, a high-fat meal (containing approximately 1000 calories and 55 grams of fat) reduced systemic exposure to AFINITOR 10 mg (as measured by AUC) by 22% and the peak blood concentration Cmax by 54%.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M158" type="Trigger" span="114 7;174 3" str="reduced | AUC"/>
<Mention id="M151" type="Precipitant" span="10 4" str="Food" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M156" type="Trigger" span="114 7;219 4" str="reduced | Cmax"/>
<Mention id="M154" type="Trigger" span="114 25" str="reduced systemic exposure"/>
<Mention id="M152" type="Trigger" span="114 7;194 24" str="reduced | peak blood concentration"/>
<Mention id="M159" type="Precipitant" span="39 13" str="high-fat meal" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I63" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M158" precipitant="M151" effect="C54609"/>
<Interaction id="I64" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M156" precipitant="M151" effect="C54606"/>
<Interaction id="I65" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M154" precipitant="M151" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I66" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M152" precipitant="M151" effect="C54606"/>
<Interaction id="I67" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M152" precipitant="M159" effect="C54606"/>
<Interaction id="I68" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M154" precipitant="M159" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I69" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M156" precipitant="M159" effect="C54606"/>
<Interaction id="I70" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M158" precipitant="M159" effect="C54609"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5494" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Light-fat meals (containing approximately 500 calories and 20 grams of fat) reduced AUC by 32% and Cmax by 42%.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M160" type="Trigger" span="76 7;99 4" str="reduced | Cmax"/>
<Mention id="M163" type="Precipitant" span="0 15" str="Light-fat meals" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M162" type="Trigger" span="76 11" str="reduced AUC"/>
<Interaction id="I71" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M160" precipitant="M163" effect="C54606"/>
<Interaction id="I72" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M162" precipitant="M163" effect="C54609"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5495" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In healthy subjects who received 9 mg of AFINITOR DISPERZ, high-fat meals (containing approximately 1000 calories and 55 grams of fat) reduced everolimus AUC by 12% and Cmax by 60% and low-fat meals (containing approximately 500 calories and 20 grams of fat) reduced everolimus AUC by 30% and Cmax by 50%.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M170" type="Trigger" span="135 7;154 3" str="reduced | AUC"/>
<Mention id="M167" type="Precipitant" span="59 14" str="high-fat meals" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M168" type="Trigger" span="135 7;169 4" str="reduced | Cmax"/>
<Mention id="M171" type="Precipitant" span="185 13" str="low-fat meals" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I73" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M170" precipitant="M167" effect="C54609"/>
<Interaction id="I74" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M168" precipitant="M167" effect="C54606"/>
<Interaction id="I75" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M168" precipitant="M171" effect="C54606"/>
<Interaction id="I76" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M170" precipitant="M171" effect="C54609"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5496" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Relative Bioavailability: The AUCinf of everolimus was equivalent between AFINITOR DISPERZ and AFINITOR; the Cmax of everolimus in the AFINITOR DISPERZ dosage form was 20% to 36% lower than that of AFINITOR.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5497" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The predicted trough concentrations at steady-state were similar after daily administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5498" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Distribution The blood-to-plasma ratio of everolimus, which is concentration-dependent over the range of 5 to 5000 ng/mL, is 17% to 73%.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5499" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The amount of everolimus confined to the plasma is approximately 20% at blood concentrations observed in cancer patients given AFINITOR 10 mg orally once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5500" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Plasma protein binding is approximately 74% both in healthy subjects and in patients with moderate hepatic impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5501" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Elimination The mean elimination half-life of everolimus is approximately 30 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5502" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Metabolism: Everolimus is a substrate of CYP3A4.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5503" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following oral administration, everolimus is the main circulating component in human blood.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5504" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Six main metabolites of everolimus have been detected in human blood, including three monohydroxylated metabolites, two hydrolytic ring-opened products, and a phosphatidylcholine conjugate of everolimus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5505" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>These metabolites were also identified in animal species used in toxicity studies, and showed approximately 100-times less activity than everolimus itself.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5506" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Excretion: No specific elimination studies have been undertaken in cancer patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5507" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following the administration of a 3 mg single dose of radiolabeled everolimus in patients who were receiving cyclosporine, 80% of the radioactivity was recovered from the feces, while 5% was excreted in the urine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5508" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The parent substance was not detected in urine or feces.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5509" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Specific Populations No relationship was apparent between oral clearance and age or sex in patients with cancer.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5510" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Patients with Renal Impairment: No significant influence of creatinine clearance (25 to 178 mL/min) was detected on oral clearance (CL/F) of everolimus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5511" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Patients with Hepatic Impairment: Compared to normal subjects, there was a 1.8-fold, 3.2-fold, and 3.6-fold increase in AUC for subjects with mild (Child-Pugh class A), moderate (Child-Pugh class B), and severe (Child-Pugh class C) hepatic impairment, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5512" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In another study, the average AUC of everolimus in subjects with moderate hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh class B) was twice that found in subjects with normal hepatic function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5513" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Pediatric Patients: In patients with TSC-associated SEGA or TSC-associated partial-onset seizures, the mean Cmin values normalized to mg/m2 dose in pediatric patients (&lt; 18 years of age) were lower than those observed in adults, suggesting that everolimus clearance adjusted to body surface area was higher in pediatric patients as compared to adults.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5514" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Race or Ethnicity: Based on a cross-study comparison, Japanese patients had on average exposures that were higher than non-Japanese patients receiving the same dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5515" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Oral clearance (CL/F) is on average 20% higher in Black patients than in White patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5516" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Drug Interaction Studies Effect of CYP3A4 and P-glycoprotein (P-gp) Inhibitors on Everolimus: Everolimus exposure increased when AFINITOR was coadministered with: ketoconazole (a P-gp and strong CYP3A4 inhibitor) - Cmax and AUC increased by 3.9- and 15-fold, respectively. erythromycin (a P-gp and moderate CYP3A4 inhibitor) - Cmax and AUC increased by 2- and 4.4-fold, respectively. verapamil (a P-gp and moderate CYP3A4 inhibitor) - Cmax and AUC increased by 2.3- and 3.5-fold, respectively.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M192" type="Trigger" span="224 13" str="AUC increased"/>
<Mention id="M175" type="Precipitant" span="273 12" str="erythromycin" code="N0000007133 | 63937KV33D"/>
<Mention id="M190" type="Trigger" span="215 4;114 9" str="Cmax | increased"/>
<Mention id="M188" type="Trigger" span="105 18" str="exposure increased"/>
<Mention id="M177" type="Precipitant" span="163 12" str="ketoconazole" code="N0000007319 | R9400W927I"/>
<Mention id="M181" type="Precipitant" span="298 25" str="moderate CYP3A4 inhibitor" code="N0000182141"/>
<Mention id="M187" type="Precipitant" span="62 4;68 9" str="P-gp | inhibitor" code="N0000185503"/>
<Mention id="M189" type="Precipitant" span="188 23" str="strong CYP3A4 inhibitor" code="N0000182141"/>
<Mention id="M193" type="Precipitant" span="384 9" str="verapamil" code="N0000007093 | CJ0O37KU29"/>
<Mention id="M196" type="Trigger" span="0 16" str="Drug Interaction"/>
<Mention id="M195" type="Precipitant" span="35 6;68 10" str="CYP3A4 | Inhibitors" code="N0000182141"/>
<Mention id="M197" type="Precipitant" span="46 14;68 10" str="P-glycoprotein | Inhibitors" code="N0000185503"/>
<Interaction id="I77" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M192" precipitant="M175" effect="C54605"/>
<Interaction id="I78" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M190" precipitant="M175" effect="C54602"/>
<Interaction id="I79" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M188" precipitant="M177" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I80" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M190" precipitant="M181" effect="C54602"/>
<Interaction id="I81" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M192" precipitant="M181" effect="C54605"/>
<Interaction id="I82" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M192" precipitant="M187" effect="C54605"/>
<Interaction id="I83" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M190" precipitant="M187" effect="C54602"/>
<Interaction id="I84" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M188" precipitant="M187" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I85" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M188" precipitant="M189" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I86" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M190" precipitant="M193" effect="C54602"/>
<Interaction id="I87" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M192" precipitant="M193" effect="C54605"/>
<Interaction id="I88" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M196" precipitant="M195"/>
<Interaction id="I89" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M196" precipitant="M197"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5517" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Effect of CYP3A4 and P-gp Inducers on Everolimus: The coadministration of AFINITOR with rifampin, a P-gp and strong inducer of CYP3A4, decreased everolimus AUC by 63% and Cmax by 58% compared to AFINITOR alone.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M206" type="Trigger" span="135 9;156 3" str="decreased | AUC"/>
<Mention id="M201" type="Precipitant" span="21 4;26 7" str="P-gp | inducer" code="N0000191264"/>
<Mention id="M208" type="Trigger" span="135 9;171 4" str="decreased | Cmax"/>
<Mention id="M205" type="Precipitant" span="88 8" str="rifampin" code="VJT6J7R4TR | N0000006026"/>
<Mention id="M209" type="Precipitant" span="109 24" str="strong inducer of CYP3A4" code="N0000185506"/>
<Mention id="M212" type="Trigger" span="0 6" str="Effect"/>
<Mention id="M211" type="Precipitant" span="10 6;26 8" str="CYP3A4 | Inducers" code="N0000185506"/>
<Mention id="M213" type="Precipitant" span="21 13" str="P-gp Inducers" code="N0000191264"/>
<Interaction id="I90" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M206" precipitant="M201" effect="C54609"/>
<Interaction id="I91" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M208" precipitant="M201" effect="C54606"/>
<Interaction id="I92" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M208" precipitant="M205" effect="C54606"/>
<Interaction id="I93" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M206" precipitant="M205" effect="C54609"/>
<Interaction id="I94" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M206" precipitant="M209" effect="C54609"/>
<Interaction id="I95" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M208" precipitant="M209" effect="C54606"/>
<Interaction id="I96" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M212" precipitant="M211"/>
<Interaction id="I97" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M212" precipitant="M213"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5518" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Effect of Everolimus on CYP3A4 Substrates: No clinically significant pharmacokinetic interactions were observed between AFINITOR and the HMG-CoA reductase inhibitors atorvastatin (a CYP3A4 substrate), pravastatin (a non-CYP3A4 substrate), and simvastatin (a CYP3A4 substrate).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5519" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The coadministration of an oral dose of midazolam (sensitive CYP3A4 substrate) with AFINITOR resulted in a 25% increase in midazolam Cmax and a 30% increase in midazolam AUC0-inf.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M220" type="Trigger" span="111 8;170 3" str="increase | AUC"/>
<Mention id="M217" type="Precipitant" span="40 9" str="midazolam" code="R60L0SM5BC"/>
<Mention id="M218" type="Trigger" span="111 8;133 4" str="increase | Cmax"/>
<Mention id="M221" type="Precipitant" span="51 26" str="sensitive CYP3A4 substrate" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I98" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M220" precipitant="M217" effect="C54613"/>
<Interaction id="I99" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M218" precipitant="M217" effect="C54610"/>
<Interaction id="I100" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M218" precipitant="M221" effect="C54610"/>
<Interaction id="I101" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M220" precipitant="M221" effect="C54613"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5520" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The coadministration of AFINITOR with exemestane increased exemestane Cmin by 45% and C2h by 64%; however, the corresponding estradiol levels at steady state (4 weeks) were not different between the 2 treatment arms.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M222" type="Trigger" span="49 9;70 4" str="increased | Cmin"/>
<Mention id="M223" type="Precipitant" span="38 10" str="exemestane" code="NY22HMQ4BX"/>
<Interaction id="I102" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M222" precipitant="M223" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5521" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No increase in adverse reactions related to exemestane was observed in patients with hormone receptor-positive, HER2-negative advanced breast cancer receiving the combination.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5522" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The coadministration of AFINITOR with long acting octreotide increased octreotide Cmin by approximately 50%.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M224" type="Trigger" span="61 9;82 4" str="increased | Cmin"/>
<Mention id="M225" type="Precipitant" span="50 10" str="octreotide" code="RWM8CCW8GP"/>
<Interaction id="I103" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M224" precipitant="M225" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5523" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Effect of Everolimus on Antiepileptic drugs (AEDs): Everolimus increased pre-dose concentrations of the carbamazepine, clobazam, oxcarbazepine, and clobazam’s metabolite N-desmethylclobazam by about 10%.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M232" type="Trigger" span="63 33" str="increased pre-dose concentrations"/>
<Mention id="M227" type="Precipitant" span="104 13" str="carbamazepine" code="33CM23913M | N0000007470"/>
<Mention id="M229" type="Precipitant" span="119 8" str="clobazam" code="2MRO291B4U"/>
<Mention id="M231" type="Precipitant" span="170 19" str="N-desmethylclobazam" code="MZ4L647O2H"/>
<Mention id="M233" type="Precipitant" span="129 13" str="oxcarbazepine" code="VZI5B1W380"/>
<Interaction id="I104" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M232" precipitant="M227" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I105" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M232" precipitant="M229" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I106" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M232" precipitant="M231" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I107" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M232" precipitant="M233" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5524" LabelDrug="Afinitor" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Everolimus had no impact on pre-dose concentrations of AEDs that are substrates of CYP3A4 (e.g., clonazepam and zonisamide) or other AEDs, including valproic acid, topiramate, phenobarbital, and phenytoin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="drugs that | induce | cyp3a4" precipitantCode="N0000185506"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="drugs that | induce | p-gp" precipitantCode="N0000191264"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="drugs that | induce p-glycoprotein" precipitantCode="N0000191264"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="drugs that inhibit | cyp3a4" precipitantCode="N0000182141"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="drugs that inhibit | p-glycoprotein" precipitantCode="N0000185503"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="drugs that inhibit | p-gp" precipitantCode="N0000185503"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="p-gp | inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000185503" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="p-gp | inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000185503"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="strong cyp3a4 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000182141"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="grapefruit" precipitantCode="O82C39RR8C"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="grapefruit juice" precipitantCode="n0000164879 | JQ9EK2H6BG"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="moderate cyp3a4 inhibitor" precipitantCode="N0000182141" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="moderate cyp3a4 inhibitor" precipitantCode="N0000182141" effect="C54602"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="moderate cyp3a4 inhibitor" precipitantCode="N0000182141" effect="C54605"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="p-gp | inhibitor" precipitantCode="N0000185503" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="p-gp | inhibitor" precipitantCode="N0000185503" effect="C54602"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="p-gp | inhibitor" precipitantCode="N0000185503" effect="C54605"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="hypericum perforatum" precipitantCode="XK4IUX8MNB"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="st. john’s wort" precipitantCode="N0000022261 | UFH8805FKA"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="p-gp | inducer" precipitantCode="N0000191264" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="p-gp | inducer" precipitantCode="N0000191264" effect="C54606"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="p-gp | inducer" precipitantCode="N0000191264" effect="C54609"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="strong cyp3a4 inducer" precipitantCode="N0000185506" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="strong cyp3a4 inducer" precipitantCode="N0000185506"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="p-gp | inducers" precipitantCode="N0000191264" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="p-gp | inducers" precipitantCode="N0000191264"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="strong cyp3a4 inducers" precipitantCode="N0000185506" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="strong cyp3a4 inducers" precipitantCode="N0000185506"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="moderate cyp3a4 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000182141" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ace inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000000181 | N0000175562 | N0000029130" effect="41291007: Angioedema (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="ace inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000000181 | N0000175562 | N0000029130"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="live vaccines" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="40733004: Infectious disease (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="live vaccines" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="71922006: Immune defect (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="recommended childhood vaccinations" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="corticosteroids" precipitantCode="N0000011309 | N0000175576" effect="415125002: Pneumocystosis jirovecii pneumonia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="immunosuppressive agents" precipitantCode="N0000175550" effect="415125002: Pneumocystosis jirovecii pneumonia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ace inhibitor" precipitantCode="N0000000181 | N0000175562" effect="41291007: Angioedema (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="alcohol" precipitantCode="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="alcohol | containing products" precipitantCode="3K9958V90M"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="hydrogen peroxide" precipitantCode="BBX060AN9V"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="hydrogen peroxide | containing products" precipitantCode="BBX060AN9V"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="iodine" precipitantCode="9679TC07X4"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="iodine | containing products" precipitantCode="9679TC07X4"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="thyme" precipitantCode="CW657OBU4N"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="thyme | containing products" precipitantCode="CW657OBU4N"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="antifungal agents" precipitantCode="N0000178297"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="vaccination" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="40733004: Infectious disease (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="vaccination" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="71922006: Immune defect (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="recommended childhood | vaccinations" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="food" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="food" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54606"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="food" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54609"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="high-fat meal" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="high-fat meal" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54606"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="high-fat meal" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54609"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="light-fat meals" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54606"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="light-fat meals" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54609"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="high-fat meals" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54606"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="high-fat meals" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54609"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="low-fat meals" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54606"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="low-fat meals" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54609"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="erythromycin" precipitantCode="N0000007133 | 63937KV33D" effect="C54602"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="erythromycin" precipitantCode="N0000007133 | 63937KV33D" effect="C54605"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="ketoconazole" precipitantCode="N0000007319 | R9400W927I" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="strong cyp3a4 inhibitor" precipitantCode="N0000182141" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="verapamil" precipitantCode="N0000007093 | CJ0O37KU29" effect="C54602"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="verapamil" precipitantCode="N0000007093 | CJ0O37KU29" effect="C54605"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="cyp3a4 | inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000182141"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="p-glycoprotein | inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000185503"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="rifampin" precipitantCode="VJT6J7R4TR | N0000006026" effect="C54606"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="rifampin" precipitantCode="VJT6J7R4TR | N0000006026" effect="C54609"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="strong inducer of cyp3a4" precipitantCode="N0000185506" effect="C54606"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="strong inducer of cyp3a4" precipitantCode="N0000185506" effect="C54609"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="cyp3a4 | inducers" precipitantCode="N0000185506"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="p-gp inducers" precipitantCode="N0000191264"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="midazolam" precipitantCode="R60L0SM5BC" effect="C54610"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="midazolam" precipitantCode="R60L0SM5BC" effect="C54613"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="sensitive cyp3a4 substrate" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54610"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="sensitive cyp3a4 substrate" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54613"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="exemestane" precipitantCode="NY22HMQ4BX" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="octreotide" precipitantCode="RWM8CCW8GP" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="carbamazepine" precipitantCode="33CM23913M | N0000007470" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="clobazam" precipitantCode="2MRO291B4U" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="n-desmethylclobazam" precipitantCode="MZ4L647O2H" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="oxcarbazepine" precipitantCode="VZI5B1W380" effect="C54357"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>