<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Uceris" setid="230e4596-2a9b-4d55-b0a0-0cabbcff5289">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
UCERIS rectal foam is contraindicated in patients with a history of a known hypersensitivity to budesonide or any of the ingredients of UCERIS rectal foam. Reactions have included anaphylaxis [see Adverse Reactions ( 6.2 )] . Known hypersensitivity to budesonide or any of the ingredients in UCERIS rectal foam. ( 4 )</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
• The recommended dosage is 1 metered dose administered twice daily for 2 weeks followed by 1 metered dose administered once daily for 4 weeks. ( 2.1 )  • For rectal administration only. ( 2.2 ) • Warm the canister in the hands while shaking it vigorously for 10 to 15 seconds prior to use. ( 2.2 ) The recommended dosage regimen is 1 metered dose administered rectally twice daily for 2 weeks followed by 1 metered dose administered rectally once daily for 4 weeks. Advise patients: • UCERIS rectal foam is only to be applied rectally. It is not for oral use. • Before using UCERIS rectal foam, use the bathroom to empty your bowels. • Each applicator is coated with a lubricant. If additional lubrication is needed, petrolatum or petroleum jelly can also be used. • Warm the canister in the hands while shaking it vigorously for 10 to 15 seconds prior to use. • UCERIS rectal foam can be used in a standing, lying or sitting position (e.g., while using the toilet). • Apply UCERIS rectal foam in the morning and the evening for the first 2 weeks of treatment; then once daily in the evening for the next 4 weeks. When applied in the evening, use immediately prior to bedtime. Try not to empty your bowels again until the next morning. • Avoid concomitant use of CYP3A4 inhibitors (e.g., ketoconazole, grapefruit juice) during treatment with UCERIS rectal foam.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
CYP3A4 Inhibitors (e.g., ketoconazole, grapefruit juice) : May cause increased systemic corticosteroid effects; avoid concomitant use. ( 7.1 ) The active ingredient of UCERIS rectal foam, budesonide, is metabolized by CYP3A4. Inhibitors of CYP3A4 activity (such as ketoconazole, itraconazole, ritonavir, indinavir, saquinavir, erythromycin, cyclosporine and grapefruit juice) can increase systemic budesonide concentrations. Avoid concomitant use of CYP3A4 inhibitors with UCERIS rectal foam [see Clinical Pharmacology ( 12.3 )] .</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
• Hypercorticism and adrenal suppression : Follow general warnings concerning glucocorticosteroids. ( 5.1 ) • Impaired Adrenal Function in Patients Transferred from Other Glucocorticoids : Taper slowly from glucocorticosteroids with high systemic effects; monitor for withdrawal symptoms and unmasking of allergies (rhinitis, eczema). ( 5.2 ) • Increased Risk of Infection, including serious and fatal chicken pox and measles: Monitor patients with active or quiescent tuberculosis infection, untreated fungal, bacterial, systemic viral or parasitic infections, or ocular herpes simplex. ( 5.3 ) • Other Glucocorticosteroid Effects: Monitor patients with other conditions where glucocorticoids may have unwanted effects. ( 5.4 ) • Flammable Contents : The contents of UCERIS rectal foam are flammable. Instruct the patient to avoid fire, flame and smoking during and immediately following administration. ( 5.5 ) When glucocorticosteroids are used chronically, systemic effects such as hypercorticism and adrenal suppression may occur. Glucocorticosteroids can reduce the response of the hypothalamus-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis to stress. In situations where patients are subject to surgery or other stress situations, supplementation with a systemic glucocorticosteroid is recommended. Since UCERIS rectal foam contains a glucocorticosteroid, general warnings concerning glucocorticoids should be followed [see Clinical Pharmacology ( 12.2 )]. Reduced liver function affects the elimination of glucocorticosteroids, and increased systemic availability of oral budesonide has been demonstrated in patients with liver cirrhosis [see Use in Specific Populations ( 8.6 )] . Monitor patients who are transferred from glucocorticosteroid treatment with higher systemic effects to glucocorticosteroids with lower systemic effects, such as UCERIS rectal foam, since symptoms attributed to withdrawal of steroid therapy, including those of acute adrenal suppression or benign intracranial hypertension, may develop. Adrenocortical function monitoring may be required in these patients and the dose of glucocorticosteroid treatment with high systemic effects should be reduced cautiously. Replacement of systemic glucocorticosteroids with UCERIS rectal foam may unmask allergies (e.g., rhinitis and eczema), which were previously controlled by the systemic drug. Patients who are on drugs that suppress the immune system are more susceptible to infection than healthy individuals. Chicken pox and measles, for example, can have a more serious or even fatal course in susceptible patients or patients on immunosuppressant doses of glucocorticosteroids. In patients who have not had these diseases, particular care should be taken to avoid exposure. How the dose, route and duration of glucocorticosteroid administration affect the risk of developing a disseminated infection is not known. The contribution of the underlying disease and/or prior glucocorticosteroid treatment to the risk is also not known. If exposed, therapy with varicella zoster immune globulin (VZIG) or pooled intravenous immunoglobulin (IVIG), as appropriate, may be indicated. If exposed to measles, prophylaxis with pooled intramuscular immunoglobulin (IG) may be indicated (see prescribing information for VZIG and IG). If chicken pox develops, treatment with antiviral agents may be considered. Glucocorticosteroids should be used with caution, if at all, in patients with active or quiescent tuberculosis infection, untreated fungal, bacterial, systemic viral or parasitic infections, or ocular herpes simplex. Monitor patients with hypertension, diabetes mellitus, osteoporosis, peptic ulcer, glaucoma or cataracts, or with a family history of diabetes or glaucoma, or with any other condition where glucocorticosteroids may have unwanted effects. The contents of UCERIS rectal foam include n-butane, isobutane and propane as propellants which are flammable. Instruct the patient to avoid fire, flame, and smoking during and immediately following administration. Patients should temporarily discontinue use of UCERIS rectal foam before initiation of bowel preparation for colonoscopy and consult their healthcare provider before resuming therapy.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Budesonide has glucocorticosteroid (GCS) activity. Treatment with glucocorticosteroids, including UCERIS rectal foam, is associated with a suppression of endogenous cortisol concentrations and an impairment of the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis function. These effects were measured by determination of plasma cortisol concentrations and responses to adrenocorticotropin challenge (i.e., ACTH stimulation test) in 2 placebo-controlled, 6-week trials in patients with active disease [see Clinical Studies (14)] . These trials enrolled subjects with post-ACTH stimulation cortisol levels of &amp;gt;18 mcg/dL at baseline. Subjects received UCERIS rectal foam 2 mg or a placebo twice daily for 2 weeks followed by once daily for 4 weeks. Normal morning serum cortisol levels &amp;gt;5 mcg/dL were maintained in 85% and 84% of UCERIS rectal foam treated subjects during Weeks 1 and 2 (twice daily treatment) and 93% and 94% during Weeks 4 and 6 (once daily treatment), respectively (see Table 3). At baseline (predose), 84% of subjects in the UCERIS rectal foam group had a normal response to the ACTH challenge and at Week 6, 63% of subjects had a normal response to the ACTH challenge; in the placebo group, these values were 86% and 76%, respectively (see Table 3). ACTH stimulation test was not performed routinely during the twice daily treatment period (Weeks 1 and 2). Table 3: Proportion of Subjects with Normal Endogenous Cortisol Levels (&amp;gt;5 mcg/dL) During the Study and Proportion of Subjects with Normal Response to ACTH Challenge Cortisol Parameter UCERIS Rectal Foam 2 mg/25 mL N=268 n (%) Placebo N=278 n (%) Total cortisol ˃5 mcg/dL (lower limit of normal range) Baseline 259/268 (96.6) 275/278 (98.9) Week 1 224/263 (85.2) 264/269 (98.1) Week 2 216/257 (84.0) 263/266 (98.9) Week 4 218/235 (92.8) 243/249 (97.6) Week 6 211/224 (94.2) 234/241 (97.1) Normal response to ACTH challenge The normal response to ACTH challenge included 3 criteria, as defined in the cosyntropin label: 1) morning cortisol level &amp;gt; 5 mcg/dL; 2) increase in cortisol level by ≥ 7 mcg/dL above the morning (pre-challenge) level following ACTH challenge; and cortisol level of &amp;gt; 18 mcg/dL following ACTH challenge. Baseline 222/266 (83.5) 238/278 (85.6) Week 6 Denominator includes 20 subjects in the UCERIS rectal foam arm and 2 subjects in the placebo arm who discontinued prior to week 6 due to adverse events related to low cortisol or abnormal response to ACTH challenge. 148/236 (62.7) 180/237 (75.9) Absorption Distal Ulcerative Colitis Patients Based on population pharmacokinetic analysis from sparse PK samples from phase 3 studies, the estimated AUC 0-12 following administration of UCERIS rectal foam 2 mg twice a day was 4.31 ng*hr/mL with a CV of 64% in the target patient population. Distribution The volume of distribution (V SS ) of budesonide varies between 2.2 and 3.9 L/kg in healthy subjects and in patients. Plasma protein binding is estimated to be 85 to 90% in the concentration range of 1 to 230 nmol/L, independent of gender. The erythrocyte/plasma partition ratio at clinically relevant concentrations is approximately 0.8. Metabolism Following absorption, budesonide is subject to first-pass metabolism. In vitro experiments in human liver microsomes demonstrate that budesonide is rapidly and extensively biotransformed, mainly by CYP3A4, to its 2 major metabolites, 6β-hydroxy budesonide and 16α-hydroxy prednisolone. The glucocorticoid activity of these metabolites is negligible (&amp;lt;1/100) in relation to that of the parent compound. In vivo investigations with intravenous doses in healthy subjects demonstrate that budesonide has a plasma clearance of 0.9-1.8 L/min. These plasma clearance values approach the estimated liver blood flow, suggesting that budesonide is a high hepatic clearance drug. Excretion Budesonide is excreted in urine and feces in the form of metabolites. After oral as well as intravenous administration of micronized [ 3 H]-budesonide, approximately 60% of the recovered radioactivity is found in urine. The major metabolites, including 6β-hydroxybudesonide and 16α-hydroxyprednisolone, are mainly renally excreted, intact or in conjugated forms. No unchanged budesonide is detected in urine. Specific Populations Hepatic Impairment The effect of hepatic impairment on the pharmacokinetics of UCERIS rectal foam has not been studied. In a study in patients with mild to moderate hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh Class A and Child-Pugh Class B) dosed with budesonide 4 mg oral capsules, systemic exposure was similar between patients with mild hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh Class A; n=4) and healthy subjects (n=8), and 3.5-fold higher in patients with moderate hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh Class B; n=4) than in healthy subjects. For the intravenous dose, no significant differences in CL or V SS are observed. Patients with severe liver dysfunction (Child-Pugh Class C) were not studied [see Use in Specific Population (8.6)]. Renal Impairment The pharmacokinetics of budesonide in patients with renal impairment has not been studied. Intact budesonide is not renally excreted, but metabolites are to a large extent, and might therefore reach higher levels in patients with impaired renal function. However, these metabolites have negligible corticosteroid activity as compared with budesonide. Drug-Drug Interactions Budesonide is metabolized via CYP3A4. Potent inhibitors of CYP3A4 can increase the plasma concentrations of budesonide. Co-administration of ketoconazole (inhibitor of CYP3A4) results in an 8-fold increase in AUC of oral budesonide, compared to budesonide alone. Grapefruit juice, an inhibitor of gut mucosal CYP3A, approximately doubles the systemic exposure of oral budesonide. Conversely, induction of CYP3A4 can result in the lowering of budesonide plasma concentrations. The effect of CYP3A4 inhibitors and inducers on the pharmacokinetics of UCERIS rectal foam have not been studied [ see Dosage and Administration ( 2 ) and Drug Interactions ( 7 ) ]. Oral contraceptives containing ethinyl estradiol, which are also metabolized by CYP3A4, do not affect the pharmacokinetics of oral budesonide. Budesonide does not affect the plasma concentrations of oral contraceptives (i.e., ethinyl estradiol). In vitro interactions studies performed with budesonide showed that budesonide did not inhibit human cytochrome P450 isoenzymes CYP1A2, CYP2B6, CYP2C9, CYP2D6, or CYP2E1 at concentrations ranging from 0.11 to 1130 ng/mL. Isoenzyme CYP3A4 was inhibited at the highest concentration tested but the IC 50 was &amp;gt;1130 ng/mL. UCERIS rectal foam is not expected to inhibit these enzymes in clinical use. No significant induction of CYP1A2, CYP2B6, CYP2C9 or CYP3A4/5 expression was observed in human hepatocytes in vitro at budesonide concentrations up to 9000 nM (3.88 mcg/mL). In an in vitro study, budesonide was not a substrate of human transporters OATP1B3 and may be a weak substrate of OATP1B1. Budesonide at concentrations up to 300 nM (129 ng/mL) did not inhibit OATP1B1 or OATP1B3. Budesonide was not a substrate of BCRP and was a weak substrate of P-glycoprotein. Budesonide was a weak inhibitor of P-glycoprotein (IC 50 9.78 µM or 4.21 mcg/mL) and BCRP (IC 50 43.1 µM or 18.6 mcg/mL). UCERIS rectal foam is not expected to inhibit these transporters in clinical use.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="1837" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>UCERIS rectal foam is contraindicated in patients with a history of a known hypersensitivity to budesonide or any of the ingredients of UCERIS rectal foam.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1838" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Reactions have included anaphylaxis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1839" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Known hypersensitivity to budesonide or any of the ingredients in UCERIS rectal foam.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1840" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommended dosage is 1 metered dose administered twice daily for 2 weeks followed by 1 metered dose administered once daily for 4 weeks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1841" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For rectal administration only.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1842" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Warm the canister in the hands while shaking it vigorously for 10 to 15 seconds prior to use.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1843" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommended dosage regimen is 1 metered dose administered rectally twice daily for 2 weeks followed by 1 metered dose administered rectally once daily for 4 weeks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1844" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Advise patients: UCERIS rectal foam is only to be applied rectally.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1845" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Before using UCERIS rectal foam, use the bathroom to empty your bowels.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1846" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Each applicator is coated with a lubricant.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1847" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If additional lubrication is needed, petrolatum or petroleum jelly can also be used.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1848" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>UCERIS rectal foam can be used in a standing, lying or sitting position (e.g., while using the toilet).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1849" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Apply UCERIS rectal foam in the morning and the evening for the first 2 weeks of treatment; then once daily in the evening for the next 4 weeks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1850" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>When applied in the evening, use immediately prior to bedtime.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1851" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Try not to empty your bowels again until the next morning.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1852" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Avoid concomitant use of CYP3A4 inhibitors (e.g., ketoconazole, grapefruit juice) during treatment with UCERIS rectal foam.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M5" type="Trigger" span="0 5" str="Avoid"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="25 17" str="CYP3A4 inhibitors" code="N0000182141"/>
<Mention id="M4" type="Precipitant" span="64 16" str="grapefruit juice" code="n0000164879 | JQ9EK2H6BG"/>
<Mention id="M6" type="Precipitant" span="50 12" str="ketoconazole" code="N0000007319 | R9400W927I"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M5" precipitant="M2"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M5" precipitant="M4"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M5" precipitant="M6"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1853" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>CYP3A4 Inhibitors (e.g., ketoconazole, grapefruit juice): May cause increased systemic corticosteroid effects; avoid concomitant use.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M15" type="Trigger" span="62 5" str="cause "/>
<Mention id="M16" type="Trigger" span="68 9;102 7" str=" increased | effects"/>
<Mention id="M9" type="Precipitant" span="0 17" str="CYP3A4 Inhibitors" code="N0000182141"/>
<Mention id="M18" type="SpecificInteraction" span="68 41" str="increased systemic corticosteroid effects" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M13" type="Precipitant" span="39 16" str="grapefruit juice" code="n0000164879 | JQ9EK2H6BG"/>
<Mention id="M17" type="Precipitant" span="25 12" str="ketoconazole" code="N0000007319 | R9400W927I"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M15;M16" precipitant="M9" effect="M18" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M15;M16" precipitant="M13" effect="M18" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M15;M16" precipitant="M17" effect="M18" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1854" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The active ingredient of UCERIS rectal foam, budesonide, is metabolized by CYP3A4.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1855" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Inhibitors of CYP3A4 activity (such as ketoconazole, itraconazole, ritonavir, indinavir, saquinavir, erythromycin, cyclosporine and grapefruit juice) can increase systemic budesonide concentrations.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M35" type="Trigger" span="154 17;183 14" str="increase systemic | concentrations"/>
<Mention id="M20" type="Precipitant" span="115 12" str="cyclosporine" code="83HN0GTJ6D | N0000007346"/>
<Mention id="M22" type="Precipitant" span="101 12" str="erythromycin" code="N0000007133 | 63937KV33D"/>
<Mention id="M24" type="Precipitant" span="132 16" str="grapefruit juice" code="n0000164879 | JQ9EK2H6BG"/>
<Mention id="M26" type="Precipitant" span="78 9" str="indinavir" code="N0000005722 | 5W6YA9PKKH"/>
<Mention id="M28" type="Precipitant" span="0 20" str="Inhibitors of CYP3A4" code="N0000182141"/>
<Mention id="M30" type="Precipitant" span="53 12" str="itraconazole" code="304NUG5GF4 | N0000006753"/>
<Mention id="M32" type="Precipitant" span="39 12" str="ketoconazole" code="N0000007319 | R9400W927I"/>
<Mention id="M34" type="Precipitant" span="67 9" str="ritonavir" code="O3J8G9O825 | N0000007423"/>
<Mention id="M36" type="Precipitant" span="89 10" str="saquinavir" code="N0000007376 | L3JE09KZ2F"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M20" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M22" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M24" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M26" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M28" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M30" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M32" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M34" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M36" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1856" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Avoid concomitant use of CYP3A4 inhibitors with UCERIS rectal foam.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M37" type="Trigger" span="0 5" str="Avoid"/>
<Mention id="M38" type="Precipitant" span="25 17" str="CYP3A4 inhibitors" code="N0000182141"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M37" precipitant="M38"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1857" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hypercorticism and adrenal suppression: Follow general warnings concerning glucocorticosteroids.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1858" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Impaired Adrenal Function in Patients Transferred from Other Glucocorticoids: Taper slowly from glucocorticosteroids with high systemic effects; monitor for withdrawal symptoms and unmasking of allergies (rhinitis, eczema).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M51" type="Trigger" span="78 12" str="Taper slowly "/>
<Mention id="M52" type="Trigger" span="145 7" str=" monitor"/>
<Mention id="M53" type="Precipitant" span="96 47" str="glucocorticosteroids with high systemic effects" code="N0000175576"/>
<Mention id="M42" type="SpecificInteraction" span="215 6" str="eczema" code="43116000: Eczema (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M46" type="SpecificInteraction" span="205 8" str="rhinitis" code="70076002: Rhinitis (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M50" type="SpecificInteraction" span="181 22" str="unmasking of allergies" code="473011001: Allergic condition (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M54" type="SpecificInteraction" span="157 19" str="withdrawal symptoms" code="363101005: Drug withdrawal (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M51;M52" precipitant="M53" effect="M42" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M51;M52" precipitant="M53" effect="M46" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M51;M52" precipitant="M53" effect="M50" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M51;M52" precipitant="M53" effect="M54" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1859" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Increased Risk of Infection, including serious and fatal chicken pox and measles: Monitor patients with active or quiescent tuberculosis infection, untreated fungal, bacterial, systemic viral or parasitic infections, or ocular herpes simplex.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1860" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Other Glucocorticosteroid Effects: Monitor patients with other conditions where glucocorticoids may have unwanted effects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1861" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Flammable Contents: The contents of UCERIS rectal foam are flammable.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1862" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Instruct the patient to avoid fire, flame and smoking during and immediately following administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1863" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>When glucocorticosteroids are used chronically, systemic effects such as hypercorticism and adrenal suppression may occur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1864" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Glucocorticosteroids can reduce the response of the hypothalamus-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis to stress.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1865" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In situations where patients are subject to surgery or other stress situations, supplementation with a systemic glucocorticosteroid is recommended.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1866" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Since UCERIS rectal foam contains a glucocorticosteroid, general warnings concerning glucocorticoids should be followed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1867" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Reduced liver function affects the elimination of glucocorticosteroids, and increased systemic availability of oral budesonide has been demonstrated in patients with liver cirrhosis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1868" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor patients who are transferred from glucocorticosteroid treatment with higher systemic effects to glucocorticosteroids with lower systemic effects, such as UCERIS rectal foam, since symptoms attributed to withdrawal of steroid therapy, including those of acute adrenal suppression or benign intracranial hypertension, may develop.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M61" type="Trigger" span="0 7" str="Monitor"/>
<Mention id="M62" type="Precipitant" span="42 58" str="glucocorticosteroid treatment with higher systemic effects" code="N0000175576"/>
<Mention id="M57" type="SpecificInteraction" span="261 25" str="acute adrenal suppression" code="386584007: Adrenal cortical hypofunction (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M60" type="SpecificInteraction" span="290 32" str="benign intracranial hypertension" code="68267002: Benign intracranial hypertension (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M63" type="SpecificInteraction" span="188 52" str="symptoms attributed to withdrawal of steroid therapy" code="84584008: Steroid withdrawal syndrome (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M61" precipitant="M62" effect="M57" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M61" precipitant="M62" effect="M60" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M61" precipitant="M62" effect="M63" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1869" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Adrenocortical function monitoring may be required in these patients and the dose of glucocorticosteroid treatment with high systemic effects should be reduced cautiously.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M64" type="Trigger" span="24 10" str="monitoring "/>
<Mention id="M65" type="Trigger" span="160 10" str=" cautiously"/>
<Mention id="M66" type="Precipitant" span="85 56" str="glucocorticosteroid treatment with high systemic effects" code="N0000175576"/>
<Mention id="M67" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 23" str="Adrenocortical function" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M64;M65" precipitant="M66" effect="M67" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1870" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Replacement of systemic glucocorticosteroids with UCERIS rectal foam may unmask allergies (e.g., rhinitis and eczema), which were previously controlled by the systemic drug.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M74" type="Trigger" span="0 11;73 6" str="Replacement | unmask"/>
<Mention id="M75" type="Precipitant" span="15 29" str="systemic glucocorticosteroids" code="N0000175576"/>
<Mention id="M70" type="SpecificInteraction" span="80 9" str="allergies" code="473011001: Allergic condition (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M73" type="SpecificInteraction" span="110 6" str="eczema" code="43116000: Eczema (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M76" type="SpecificInteraction" span="97 8" str="rhinitis" code="70076002: Rhinitis (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M74" precipitant="M75" effect="M70" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M74" precipitant="M75" effect="M73" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M74" precipitant="M75" effect="M76" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1871" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients who are on drugs that suppress the immune system are more susceptible to infection than healthy individuals.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1872" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Chicken pox and measles, for example, can have a more serious or even fatal course in susceptible patients or patients on immunosuppressant doses of glucocorticosteroids.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1873" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In patients who have not had these diseases, particular care should be taken to avoid exposure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1874" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>How the dose, route and duration of glucocorticosteroid administration affect the risk of developing a disseminated infection is not known.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1875" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The contribution of the underlying disease and/or prior glucocorticosteroid treatment to the risk is also not known.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1876" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If exposed, therapy with varicella zoster immune globulin (VZIG) or pooled intravenous immunoglobulin (IVIG), as appropriate, may be indicated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1877" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If exposed to measles, prophylaxis with pooled intramuscular immunoglobulin (IG) may be indicated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1878" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If chicken pox develops, treatment with antiviral agents may be considered.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1879" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Glucocorticosteroids should be used with caution, if at all, in patients with active or quiescent tuberculosis infection, untreated fungal, bacterial, systemic viral or parasitic infections, or ocular herpes simplex.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1880" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor patients with hypertension, diabetes mellitus, osteoporosis, peptic ulcer, glaucoma or cataracts, or with a family history of diabetes or glaucoma, or with any other condition where glucocorticosteroids may have unwanted effects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1881" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The contents of UCERIS rectal foam include n-butane, isobutane and propane as propellants which are flammable.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1882" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Instruct the patient to avoid fire, flame, and smoking during and immediately following administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1883" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients should temporarily discontinue use of UCERIS rectal foam before initiation of bowel preparation for colonoscopy and consult their healthcare provider before resuming therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1884" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Budesonide has glucocorticosteroid (GCS) activity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1885" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Treatment with glucocorticosteroids, including UCERIS rectal foam, is associated with a suppression of endogenous cortisol concentrations and an impairment of the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1886" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>These effects were measured by determination of plasma cortisol concentrations and responses to adrenocorticotropin challenge (i.e., ACTH stimulation test) in 2 placebo-controlled, 6-week trials in patients with active disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1887" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>These trials enrolled subjects with post-ACTH stimulation cortisol levels of &gt;18 mcg/dL at baseline.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1888" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Subjects received UCERIS rectal foam 2 mg or a placebo twice daily for 2 weeks followed by once daily for 4 weeks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1889" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Normal morning serum cortisol levels &gt;5 mcg/dL were maintained in 85% and 84% of UCERIS rectal foam treated subjects during Weeks 1 and 2 (twice daily treatment) and 93% and 94% during Weeks 4 and 6 (once daily treatment), respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1890" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>At baseline (predose), 84% of subjects in the UCERIS rectal foam group had a normal response to the ACTH challenge and at Week 6, 63% of subjects had a normal response to the ACTH challenge; in the placebo group, these values were 86% and 76%, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1891" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>ACTH stimulation test was not performed routinely during the twice daily treatment period (Weeks 1 and 2).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1892" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Table 3: Proportion of Subjects with Normal Endogenous Cortisol Levels (&gt;5 mcg/dL) During the Study and Proportion of Subjects with Normal Response to ACTH Challenge Cortisol Parameter UCERIS Rectal Foam 2 mg/25 mL N=268 n (%) Placebo N=278 n (%) Total cortisol ˃5 mcg/dL (lower limit of normal range) Baseline 259/268 (96.6) 275/278 (98.9) Week 1 224/263 (85.2) 264/269 (98.1) Week 2 216/257 (84.0) 263/266 (98.9) Week 4 218/235 (92.8) 243/249 (97.6) Week 6 211/224 (94.2) 234/241 (97.1) Normal response to ACTH challenge The normal response to ACTH challenge included 3 criteria, as defined in the cosyntropin label: 1) morning cortisol level &gt; 5 mcg/dL; 2) increase in cortisol level by ≥ 7 mcg/dL above the morning (pre-challenge) level following ACTH challenge; and cortisol level of &gt; 18 mcg/dL following ACTH challenge.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1893" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Baseline 222/266 (83.5) 238/278 (85.6) Week 6Denominator includes 20 subjects in the UCERIS rectal foam arm and 2 subjects in the placebo arm who discontinued prior to week 6 due to adverse events related to low cortisol or abnormal response to ACTH challenge.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1894" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>148/236 (62.7) 180/237 (75.9) Absorption Distal Ulcerative Colitis Patients Based on population pharmacokinetic analysis from sparse PK samples from phase 3 studies, the estimated AUC0-12 following administration of UCERIS rectal foam 2 mg twice a day was 4.31 ng*hr/mL with a CV of 64% in the target patient population.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1895" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Distribution The volume of distribution (VSS) of budesonide varies between 2.2 and 3.9 L/kg in healthy subjects and in patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1896" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Plasma protein binding is estimated to be 85 to 90% in the concentration range of 1 to 230 nmol/L, independent of gender.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1897" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The erythrocyte/plasma partition ratio at clinically relevant concentrations is approximately 0.8.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1898" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Metabolism Following absorption, budesonide is subject to first-pass metabolism.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1899" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In vitro experiments in human liver microsomes demonstrate that budesonide is rapidly and extensively biotransformed, mainly by CYP3A4, to its 2 major metabolites, 6β-hydroxy budesonide and 16α-hydroxy prednisolone.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1900" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The glucocorticoid activity of these metabolites is negligible (&lt;1/100) in relation to that of the parent compound.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1901" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In vivo investigations with intravenous doses in healthy subjects demonstrate that budesonide has a plasma clearance of 0.9-1.8 L/min.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1902" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>These plasma clearance values approach the estimated liver blood flow, suggesting that budesonide is a high hepatic clearance drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1903" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Excretion Budesonide is excreted in urine and feces in the form of metabolites.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1904" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>After oral as well as intravenous administration of micronized [3H]-budesonide, approximately 60% of the recovered radioactivity is found in urine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1905" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The major metabolites, including 6β-hydroxybudesonide and 16α-hydroxyprednisolone, are mainly renally excreted, intact or in conjugated forms.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1906" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No unchanged budesonide is detected in urine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1907" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Specific Populations Hepatic Impairment The effect of hepatic impairment on the pharmacokinetics of UCERIS rectal foam has not been studied.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1908" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In a study in patients with mild to moderate hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh Class A and Child-Pugh Class B) dosed with budesonide 4 mg oral capsules, systemic exposure was similar between patients with mild hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh Class A; n=4) and healthy subjects (n=8), and 3.5-fold higher in patients with moderate hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh Class B; n=4) than in healthy subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1909" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>For the intravenous dose, no significant differences in CL or VSS are observed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1910" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Patients with severe liver dysfunction (Child-Pugh Class C) were not studied.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1911" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Renal Impairment The pharmacokinetics of budesonide in patients with renal impairment has not been studied.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1912" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Intact budesonide is not renally excreted, but metabolites are to a large extent, and might therefore reach higher levels in patients with impaired renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1913" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>However, these metabolites have negligible corticosteroid activity as compared with budesonide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1914" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Drug-Drug Interactions Budesonide is metabolized via CYP3A4.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1915" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Potent inhibitors of CYP3A4 can increase the plasma concentrations of budesonide.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M77" type="Trigger" span="32 34" str="increase the plasma concentrations"/>
<Mention id="M78" type="Precipitant" span="0 27" str="Potent inhibitors of CYP3A4" code="N0000182141"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M77" precipitant="M78" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1916" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Co-administration of ketoconazole (inhibitor of CYP3A4) results in an 8-fold increase in AUC of oral budesonide, compared to budesonide alone.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M81" type="Trigger" span="77 15" str="increase in AUC"/>
<Mention id="M80" type="Precipitant" span="35 19" str="inhibitor of CYP3A4" code="N0000182141"/>
<Mention id="M82" type="Precipitant" span="21 12" str="ketoconazole" code="N0000007319 | R9400W927I"/>
<Interaction id="I29" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M81" precipitant="M80" effect="C54605"/>
<Interaction id="I30" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M81" precipitant="M82" effect="C54605"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1917" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Grapefruit juice, an inhibitor of gut mucosal CYP3A, approximately doubles the systemic exposure of oral budesonide.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M85" type="Trigger" span="67 29" str="doubles the systemic exposure"/>
<Mention id="M84" type="Precipitant" span="0 16" str="Grapefruit juice" code="n0000164879 | JQ9EK2H6BG"/>
<Mention id="M86" type="Precipitant" span="21 30" str="inhibitor of gut mucosal CYP3A" code="N0000190114"/>
<Interaction id="I31" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M85" precipitant="M84" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I32" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M85" precipitant="M86" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1918" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Conversely, induction of CYP3A4 can result in the lowering of budesonide plasma concentrations.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M87" type="Trigger" span="50 8;73 21" str="lowering | plasma concentrations"/>
<Mention id="M88" type="Precipitant" span="12 19" str="induction of CYP3A4" code="N0000185506"/>
<Interaction id="I33" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M87" precipitant="M88" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1919" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The effect of CYP3A4 inhibitors and inducers on the pharmacokinetics of UCERIS rectal foam have not been studied.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1920" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Oral contraceptives containing ethinyl estradiol, which are also metabolized by CYP3A4, do not affect the pharmacokinetics of oral budesonide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1921" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Budesonide does not affect the plasma concentrations of oral contraceptives (i.e., ethinyl estradiol).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1922" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In vitro interactions studies performed with budesonide showed that budesonide did not inhibit human cytochrome P450 isoenzymes CYP1A2, CYP2B6, CYP2C9, CYP2D6, or CYP2E1 at concentrations ranging from 0.11 to 1130 ng/mL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1923" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Isoenzyme CYP3A4 was inhibited at the highest concentration tested but the IC50 was &gt;1130 ng/mL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1924" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>UCERIS rectal foam is not expected to inhibit these enzymes in clinical use.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1925" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No significant induction of CYP1A2, CYP2B6, CYP2C9 or CYP3A4/5 expression was observed in human hepatocytes in vitro at budesonide concentrations up to 9000 nM (3.88 mcg/mL).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1926" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In an in vitro study, budesonide was not a substrate of human transporters OATP1B3 and may be a weak substrate of OATP1B1.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1927" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Budesonide at concentrations up to 300 nM (129 ng/mL) did not inhibit OATP1B1 or OATP1B3.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1928" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Budesonide was not a substrate of BCRP and was a weak substrate of P-glycoprotein.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1929" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Budesonide was a weak inhibitor of P-glycoprotein (IC50 9.78 µM or 4.21 mcg/mL) and BCRP (IC50 43.1 µM or 18.6 mcg/mL).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1930" LabelDrug="Uceris" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>UCERIS rectal foam is not expected to inhibit these transporters in clinical use.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cyp3a4 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000182141" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="cyp3a4 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000182141"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="grapefruit juice" precipitantCode="n0000164879 | JQ9EK2H6BG" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="grapefruit juice" precipitantCode="n0000164879 | JQ9EK2H6BG" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="grapefruit juice" precipitantCode="n0000164879 | JQ9EK2H6BG"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ketoconazole" precipitantCode="N0000007319 | R9400W927I" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="ketoconazole" precipitantCode="N0000007319 | R9400W927I" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="ketoconazole" precipitantCode="N0000007319 | R9400W927I" effect="C54605"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="ketoconazole" precipitantCode="N0000007319 | R9400W927I"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cyclosporine" precipitantCode="83HN0GTJ6D | N0000007346" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="erythromycin" precipitantCode="N0000007133 | 63937KV33D" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="indinavir" precipitantCode="N0000005722 | 5W6YA9PKKH" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="inhibitors of cyp3a4" precipitantCode="N0000182141" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="itraconazole" precipitantCode="304NUG5GF4 | N0000006753" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="ritonavir" precipitantCode="O3J8G9O825 | N0000007423" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="saquinavir" precipitantCode="N0000007376 | L3JE09KZ2F" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="glucocorticosteroids with high systemic effects" precipitantCode="N0000175576" effect="363101005: Drug withdrawal (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="glucocorticosteroids with high systemic effects" precipitantCode="N0000175576" effect="43116000: Eczema (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="glucocorticosteroids with high systemic effects" precipitantCode="N0000175576" effect="473011001: Allergic condition (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="glucocorticosteroids with high systemic effects" precipitantCode="N0000175576" effect="70076002: Rhinitis (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="glucocorticosteroid treatment with higher systemic effects" precipitantCode="N0000175576" effect="386584007: Adrenal cortical hypofunction (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="glucocorticosteroid treatment with higher systemic effects" precipitantCode="N0000175576" effect="68267002: Benign intracranial hypertension (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="glucocorticosteroid treatment with higher systemic effects" precipitantCode="N0000175576" effect="84584008: Steroid withdrawal syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="glucocorticosteroid treatment with high systemic effects" precipitantCode="N0000175576" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="systemic glucocorticosteroids" precipitantCode="N0000175576" effect="43116000: Eczema (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="systemic glucocorticosteroids" precipitantCode="N0000175576" effect="473011001: Allergic condition (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="systemic glucocorticosteroids" precipitantCode="N0000175576" effect="70076002: Rhinitis (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="potent inhibitors of cyp3a4" precipitantCode="N0000182141" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="inhibitor of cyp3a4" precipitantCode="N0000182141" effect="C54605"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="inhibitor of gut mucosal cyp3a" precipitantCode="N0000190114" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="induction of cyp3a4" precipitantCode="N0000185506" effect="C54356"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>