<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Premarin" setid="258e1602-a3cf-4ccc-ca80-73dbbfb812ff">
<Text><Section name="BOXED WARNING SECTION" id="34066-1">
WARNING: ENDOMETRIAL CANCER, CARDIOVASCULAR DISORDERS, BREAST CANCER AND PROBABLE DEMENTIA See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning. Estrogen-Alone Therapy There is an increased risk of endometrial cancer in a woman with a uterus who uses unopposed estrogens ( 5.2 ) Estrogen-alone therapy should not be used for the prevention of cardiovascular disease or dementia ( 5.1 , 5.3 ) Women's Health Initiative (WHI) estrogen-alone substudy reported increased risks of stroke and deep vein thrombosis (DVT) ( 5.1 ) The WHI Memory Study (WHIMS) estrogen-alone ancillary study of WHI reported an increased risk of probable dementia in postmenopausal women 65 years of age and older ( 5.3 ) Estrogen Plus Progestin Therapy Estrogen plus progestin therapy should not be used for the prevention of cardiovascular disease or dementia ( 5.1 , 5.3 ) The WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy reported increased risks of stroke, DVT, pulmonary embolism (PE), and myocardial infarction (MI) ( 5.1 ) The WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy reported increased risks of invasive breast cancer ( 5.2 ) The WHIMS estrogen plus progestin ancillary study of WHI reported an increased risk of probable dementia in postmenopausal women 65 years of age and older ( 5.3 ) Estrogen-Alone Therapy Endometrial Cancer There is an increased risk of endometrial cancer in a woman with a uterus who uses unopposed estrogens. Adding a progestin to estrogen therapy has been shown to reduce the risk of endometrial hyperplasia, which may be a precursor to endometrial cancer. Adequate diagnostic measures, including directed or random endometrial sampling when indicated, should be undertaken to rule out malignancy in postmenopausal women with undiagnosed persistent or recurring abnormal genital bleeding [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2) ]. Cardiovascular Disorders and Probable Dementia Estrogen-alone therapy should not be used for the prevention of cardiovascular disease or dementia [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1, 5.3) , and Clinical Studies (14.5, 14.6) ] . The Women's Health Initiative (WHI) estrogen-alone substudy reported increased risks of stroke and deep vein thrombosis (DVT) in postmenopausal women (50 to 79 years of age) during 7.1 years of treatment with daily oral conjugated estrogens (CE) [0.625 mg]-alone, relative to placebo [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1) , and Clinical Studies (14.5) ]. The WHI Memory Study (WHIMS) estrogen-alone ancillary study of WHI reported an increased risk of developing probable dementia in postmenopausal women 65 years of age or older during 5.2 years of treatment with daily CE (0.625 mg)-alone, relative to placebo. It is unknown whether this finding applies to younger postmenopausal women [see Warnings and Precautions (5.3) , Use in Specific Populations (8.5) , and Clinical Studies (14.6) ] . In the absence of comparable data, these risks should be assumed to be similar for other doses of CE and other dosage forms of estrogens. Estrogens with or without progestins should be prescribed at the lowest effective doses and for the shortest duration consistent with treatment goals and risks for the individual woman. Estrogen Plus Progestin Therapy Cardiovascular Disorders and Probable Dementia Estrogen plus progestin therapy should not be used for the prevention of cardiovascular disease or dementia [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1, 5.3) , and Clinical Studies (14.5 , 14.6) ]. The WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy reported increased risks of DVT, pulmonary embolism (PE), stroke and myocardial infarction (MI) in postmenopausal women (50 to 79 years of age) during 5.6 years of treatment with daily oral CE (0.625 mg) combined with medroxyprogesterone acetate (MPA) [2.5 mg], relative to placebo [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1), and Clinical Studies (14.5) ] . The WHIMS estrogen plus progestin ancillary study of the WHI, reported an increased risk of developing probable dementia in postmenopausal women 65 years of age or older during 4 years of treatment with daily CE (0.625 mg) combined with MPA (2.5 mg), relative to placebo. It is unknown whether this finding applies to younger postmenopausal women [see Warnings and Precautions (5.3) , Use in Specific Populations (8.5) , and Clinical Studies (14.6) ] . Breast Cancer The WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy also demonstrated an increased risk of invasive breast cancer [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2) , and Clinical Studies (14.5) ]. In the absence of comparable data, these risks should be assumed to be similar for other doses of CE and MPA, and other combinations and dosage forms of estrogens and progestins. Estrogens with or without progestins should be prescribed at the lowest effective doses and for the shortest duration consistent with treatment goals and risks for the individual woman. Using estrogen-alone may increase your chance of getting cancer of the uterus (womb) Report any unusual vaginal bleeding right away while you are using PREMARIN. Vaginal bleeding after menopause may be a warning sign of cancer of the uterus (womb). Your healthcare provider should check any unusual vaginal bleeding to find the cause. Do not use estrogen-alone to prevent heart disease, heart attacks, or dementia (decline of brain function) Using estrogen-alone may increase your chances of getting strokes or blood clots Using estrogen-alone may increase your chance of getting dementia, based on a study of women 65 years of age or older Do not use estrogens with progestins to prevent heart disease, heart attacks, strokes, or dementia Using estrogens with progestins may increase your chances of getting heart attacks, strokes, breast cancer, or blood clots Using estrogens with progestins may increase your chance of getting dementia, based on a study of women 65 years of age or older You and your healthcare provider should talk regularly about whether you still need treatment with PREMARIN</Section>
<Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
PREMARIN therapy is contraindicated in individuals with any of the following conditions: Undiagnosed abnormal genital bleeding Known, suspected, or history of breast cancer except in appropriately selected patients being treated for metastatic disease Known or suspected estrogen-dependent neoplasia Active DVT, PE, or a history of these conditions Active arterial thromboembolic disease (for example stroke and MI), or a history of these conditions Known anaphylactic reaction or angioedema with Premarin Known liver impairment or disease Known protein C, protein S or antithrombin deficiency, or other known thrombophilic disorders. Known or suspected pregnancy Undiagnosed abnormal genital bleeding ( 4 ) Known, suspected, or history of breast cancer except in appropriately selected patients being treated for metastatic diseases ( 4 , 5.2 ) Known or suspected estrogen-dependent neoplasia ( 4 , 5.2 ) Active DVT, PE, or a history of these conditions ( 4 , 5.1 ) Active arterial thromboembolic disease (for example, stroke and MI), or a history of these conditions ( 4 , 5.1 ) Known anaphylactic reaction or angioedema with PREMARIN ( 5.7 ) Known liver impairment or disease ( 4 , 5.12 ) Known protein C, protein S, or antithrombin deficiency, or other known thrombophilic disorders ( 4 ) Known or suspected pregnancy ( 4 , 8.1 )</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
Generally, when estrogen therapy is prescribed for a postmenopausal woman with a uterus, a progestin should be considered to reduce the risk of endometrial cancer [see Boxed Warning ]. A woman without a uterus does not need progestin. In some cases, however, hysterectomized women with a history of endometriosis may need a progestin [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2, 5.16) ] . Use of estrogen-alone, or in combination with a progestin, should be with the lowest effective dose and for the shortest duration consistent with treatment goals and risks for the individual woman. Postmenopausal women should be re-evaluated periodically as clinically appropriate to determine if treatment is still necessary. PREMARIN may be taken without regard to meals. Daily administration of 0.3, 0.45, 0.625, 0.9, and 1.25 mg ( 2.1 , 2.2 , 2.3 , 2.5 , 2.6 ) Cyclic administration of 0.3, 0.625, and 1.25 mg ( 2.1 , 2.2 , 2.3 ) Patients should be treated with the lowest effective dose. Generally, women should be started at 0.3 mg PREMARIN daily. Subsequent dosage adjustment may be made based upon the individual patient response. This dose should be periodically reassessed by the healthcare provider. PREMARIN therapy may be given continuously, with no interruption in therapy, or in cyclical regimens (regimens such as 25 days on drug followed by 5 days off drug), as is medically appropriate on an individual basis. Patients should be treated with the lowest effective dose. Generally, women should be started at 0.3 mg PREMARIN daily. Subsequent dosage adjustment may be made based upon the individual patient response. This dose should be periodically reassessed by the healthcare provider. PREMARIN therapy may be given continuously, with no interruption in therapy, or in cyclical regimens (regimens such as 25 days on drug followed by 5 days off drug), as is medically appropriate on an individual basis. PREMARIN therapy should be initiated and maintained with the lowest effective dose to achieve clinical goals. Female hypogonadism: 0.3 mg or 0.625 mg daily, administered cyclically (e.g., three weeks on and one week off). Doses are adjusted depending on the severity of symptoms and responsiveness of the endometrium [ see Clinical Studies (14.4) ]. Female castration or primary ovarian failure: 1.25 mg daily, cyclically. Adjust dosage, upward or downward, according to severity of symptoms and response of the patient. For maintenance, adjust dosage to lowest level that will provide effective control. Suggested dosage is 10 mg three times daily, for a period of at least three months. 1.25 mg to 2 × 1.25 mg three times daily. The effectiveness of therapy can be judged by phosphatase determinations as well as by symptomatic improvement of the patient. PREMARIN therapy may be given continuously, with no interruption in therapy, or in cyclical regimens (regimens such as 25 days on drug followed by 5 days off drug), as is medically appropriate on an individual basis. Patients should be treated with the lowest effective dose. Generally, women should be started at 0.3 mg PREMARIN daily. Subsequent dosage adjustment may be made based upon the individual clinical and bone mineral density responses. This dose should be periodically reassessed by the healthcare provider.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG &amp;amp; OR LABORATORY TEST INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34074-5">
Accelerated prothrombin time, partial thromboplastin time, and platelet aggregation time; increased platelet count; increased factors II, VII antigen, VIII antigen, VIII coagulant activity, IX, X, XII, VII-X complex, II-VII-X complex, and beta-thromboglobulin; decreased levels of antifactor Xa and antithrombin III, decreased antithrombin III activity; increased levels of fibrinogen and fibrinogen activity; increased plasminogen antigen and activity. Increased thyroid-binding globulin (TBG) levels leading to increased circulating total thyroid hormone levels as measured by protein-bound iodine (PBI), T 4 levels (by column or by radioimmunoassay) or T 3 levels by radioimmunoassay. T 3 resin uptake is decreased, reflecting the elevated TBG. Free T 4 and free T 3 concentrations are unaltered. Women on thyroid replacement therapy may require higher doses of thyroid hormone. Other binding proteins may be elevated in serum, for example, corticosteroid binding globulin (CBG), sex hormone-binding globulin (SHBG), leading to increased total circulating corticosteroids and sex steroids, respectively. Free hormone concentrations, such as testosterone and estradiol, may be decreased. Other plasma proteins may be increased (angiotensinogen/renin substrate, alpha-1-antitrypsin, ceruloplasmin). Increased plasma high-density lipoprotein (HDL) and HDL 2 cholesterol subfraction concentrations, reduced low-density lipoprotein (LDL) cholesterol concentrations, increased triglyceride levels. Impaired glucose tolerance.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
Data from a single-dose drug-drug interaction study involving conjugated estrogens and medroxyprogesterone acetate indicate that the pharmacokinetic disposition of both drugs is not altered when the drugs are coadministered. No other clinical drug-drug interaction studies have been conducted with conjugated estrogens. Inducers and/or inhibitors of CYP3A4 may affect estrogen drug metabolism ( 7.1 ) In vitro and in vivo studies have shown that estrogens are metabolized partially by cytochrome P450 3A4 (CYP3A4). Therefore, inducers or inhibitors of CYP3A4 may affect estrogen drug metabolism. Inducers of CYP3A4, such as St. John's Wort ( Hypericum perforatum ) preparations, phenobarbital, carbamazepine, and rifampin, may reduce plasma concentrations of estrogens, possibly resulting in a decrease in therapeutic effects and/or changes in the uterine bleeding profile. Inhibitors of CYP3A4, such as erythromycin, clarithromycin, ketoconazole, itraconazole, ritonavir and grapefruit juice, may increase plasma concentrations of estrogens and may result in side effects.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
Estrogens increase the risk of gallbladder disease ( 5.4 ) Discontinue estrogen if severe hypercalcemia, loss of vision, severe hypertriglyceridemia or cholestatic jaundice occurs ( 5.5 , 5.6 , 5.11 , 5.12 ) Monitor thyroid function in women on thyroid replacement therapy ( 5.13 , 5.18 ) An increased risk of stroke and DVT has been reported with estrogen-alone therapy. An increased risk of PE, DVT, stroke and MI has been reported with estrogen plus progestin therapy. Should any of these events occur or be suspected, estrogen with or without progestin therapy should be discontinued immediately. Risk factors for arterial vascular disease (for example, hypertension, diabetes mellitus, tobacco use, hypercholesterolemia, and obesity) and/or venous thromboembolism (VTE) (for example, personal or family history of VTE, obesity, and systemic lupus erythematosus) should be managed appropriately. Stroke In the WHI estrogen-alone substudy, a statistically significant increased risk of stroke was reported in women 50 to 79 years of age receiving daily CE (0.625 mg)-alone compared to women in the same age group receiving placebo (45 versus 33 per 10,000 women-years). The increase in risk was demonstrated in year 1 and persisted [see Clinical Studies (14.5) ] . Should a stroke occur or be suspected, estrogen-alone therapy should be discontinued immediately. Subgroup analyses of women 50 to 59 years of age suggest no increased risk of stroke for those women receiving CE (0.625 mg)-alone versus those receiving placebo (18 versus 21 per 10,000 women-years). 1 In the WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy, a statistically significant increased risk of stroke was reported in women 50 to 79 years of age receiving daily CE (0.625 mg) plus MPA (2.5 mg) compared to women in the same age group receiving placebo (33 versus 25 per 10,000 women-years) [see Clinical Studies (14.5) ] . The increase in risk was demonstrated after the first year and persisted. 1 Should a stroke occur or be suspected, estrogen plus progestin therapy should be discontinued immediately. Coronary Heart Disease In the WHI estrogen-alone substudy, no overall effect on coronary heart disease (CHD) events (defined as nonfatal MI, silent MI, or CHD death) was reported in women receiving estrogen-alone compared to placebo 2 [see Clinical Studies (14.5)] . Subgroup analyses of women 50 to 59 years of age suggest a statistically non-significant reduction in CHD events (CE [0.625 mg]-alone compared to placebo) in women with less than 10 years since menopause (8 versus 16 per 10,000 women-years). 1 In the WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy, there was a statistically non-significant increased risk of CHD events reported in women receiving daily CE (0.625 mg) plus MPA (2.5 mg) compared to women receiving placebo (41 versus 34 per 10,000 women-years). 1 An increase in relative risk was demonstrated in year 1, and a trend toward decreasing relative risk was reported in years 2 through 5 [see Clinical Studies (14.5) ] . In postmenopausal women with documented heart disease (n = 2,763, average 66.7 years of age), in a controlled clinical trial of secondary prevention of cardiovascular disease (Heart and Estrogen/Progestin Replacement Study; HERS), treatment with daily CE (0.625 mg) plus MPA (2.5 mg) demonstrated no cardiovascular benefit. During an average follow-up of 4.1 years, treatment with CE plus MPA did not reduce the overall rate of CHD events in postmenopausal women with established CHD. There were more CHD events in the CE plus MPA-treated group than in the placebo group in year 1, but not during the subsequent years. Two thousand, three hundred and twenty-one (2,321) women from the original HERS trial agreed to participate in an open label extension of HERS, HERS II. Average follow-up in HERS II was an additional 2.7 years, for a total of 6.8 years overall. Rates of CHD events were comparable among women in the CE (0.625 mg) plus MPA (2.5 mg) group and the placebo group in HERS, HERS II, and overall. Venous Thromboembolism (VTE) In the WHI estrogen-alone substudy, the risk of VTE (DVT and PE), was increased for women receiving daily CE (0.625 mg)-alone compared to placebo (30 versus 22 per 10,000 women-years), although only the increased risk of DVT reached statistical significance (23 versus 15 per 10,000 women-years). The increase in VTE risk was demonstrated during the first 2 years 3 [see Clinical Studies (14.5) ] . Should a VTE occur or be suspected, estrogen-alone therapy should be discontinued immediately. In the WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy, a statistically significant 2-fold greater rate of VTE was reported in women receiving daily CE (0.625 mg) plus MPA (2.5 mg) compared to women receiving placebo (35 versus 17 per 10,000 women-years). Statistically significant increases in risk for both DVT (26 versus 13 per 10,000 women-years) and PE (18 versus 8 per 10,000 women-years) were also demonstrated. The increase in VTE risk was demonstrated during the first year and persisted 4 [see Clinical Studies (14.5) ] . Should a VTE occur or be suspected, estrogen plus progestin therapy should be discontinued immediately. If feasible, estrogens should be discontinued at least 4 to 6 weeks before surgery of the type associated with an increased risk of thromboembolism, or during periods of prolonged immobilization. Endometrial Cancer An increased risk of endometrial cancer has been reported with the use of unopposed estrogen therapy in a woman with a uterus. The reported endometrial cancer risk among unopposed estrogen users is about 2 to 12 times greater than in non-users, and appears dependent on duration of treatment and on estrogen dose. Most studies show no significant increased risk associated with use of estrogens for less than 1 year. The greatest risk appears associated with prolonged use, with increased risks of 15- to 24-fold for 5 to 10 years or more, and this risk has been shown to persist for at least 8 to 15 years after estrogen therapy is discontinued. Clinical surveillance of all women using estrogen-alone or estrogen plus progestin therapy is important. Adequate diagnostic measures, including directed or random endometrial sampling when indicated, should be undertaken to rule out malignancy in postmenopausal women with undiagnosed persistent or recurring abnormal genital bleeding. There is no evidence that the use of natural estrogens results in a different endometrial risk profile than synthetic estrogens of equivalent estrogen dose. Adding a progestin to postmenopausal estrogen therapy has been shown to reduce the risk of endometrial hyperplasia, which may be a precursor to endometrial cancer. Breast Cancer The most important randomized clinical trial providing information about breast cancer in estrogen-alone users is the WHI substudy of daily CE (0.625 mg)-alone. In the WHI estrogen-alone substudy, after an average follow-up of 7.1 years, daily CE (0.625 mg)-alone was not associated with an increased risk of invasive breast cancer [relative risk (RR) 0.80] 5 [see Clinical Studies (14.5) ] . The most important randomized clinical trial providing information about breast cancer in estrogen plus progestin users is the WHI substudy of daily CE (0.625 mg) plus MPA (2.5 mg). After a mean follow-up of 5.6 years, the estrogen plus progestin substudy reported an increased risk of invasive breast cancer in women who took daily CE plus MPA. In this substudy, prior use of estrogen-alone or estrogen plus progestin therapy was reported by 26 percent of the women. The relative risk of invasive breast cancer was 1.24, and the absolute risk was 41 versus 33 cases per 10,000 women-years, for CE plus MPA compared with placebo. 6 Among women who reported prior use of hormone therapy, the relative risk of invasive breast cancer was 1.86, and the absolute risk was 46 versus 25 cases per 10,000 women-years for CE plus MPA compared with placebo. Among women who reported no prior use of hormone therapy, the relative risk of invasive breast cancer was 1.09, and the absolute risk was 40 versus 36 cases per 10,000 women-years for CE plus MPA compared with placebo. In the same substudy, invasive breast cancers were larger, were more likely to be node positive, and were diagnosed at a more advanced stage in the CE (0.625 mg) plus MPA (2.5 mg) group compared with the placebo group. Metastatic disease was rare, with no apparent difference between the two groups. Other prognostic factors, such as histologic subtype, grade and hormone receptor status did not differ between the groups [see Clinical Studies (14.5) ] . Consistent with the WHI clinical trial, observational studies have also reported an increased risk of breast cancer for estrogen plus progestin therapy, and a smaller increased risk for estrogen-alone therapy, after several years of use. The risk increased with duration of use, and appeared to return to baseline over about 5 years after stopping treatment (only the observational studies have substantial data on risk after stopping). Observational studies also suggest that the risk of breast cancer was greater, and became apparent earlier, with estrogen plus progestin therapy as compared to estrogen-alone therapy. However, these studies have not found significant variation in the risk of breast cancer among different estrogen plus progestin combinations, doses, or routes of administration. The use of estrogen-alone and estrogen plus progestin has been reported to result in an increase in abnormal mammograms, requiring further evaluation. All women should receive yearly breast examinations by a healthcare provider and perform monthly breast self-examinations. In addition, mammography examinations should be scheduled based on patient age, risk factors, and prior mammogram results. Ovarian Cancer The WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy reported a statistically non-significant increased risk of ovarian cancer. After an average follow-up of 5.6 years, the relative risk for ovarian cancer for CE plus MPA versus placebo was 1.58 (95 percent CI 0.77–3.24). The absolute risk for CE plus MPA versus placebo was 4 versus 3 cases per 10,000 women-years. 7 A meta-analysis of 17 prospective and 35 retrospective epidemiology studies found that women who used hormonal therapy for menopausal symptoms had an increased risk for ovarian cancer. The primary analysis, using case-control comparisons, included 12,110 cancer cases from the 17 prospective studies. The relative risks associated with current use of hormonal therapy was 1.41 (95% confidence interval [CI] 1.32 to 1.50); there was no difference in the risk estimates by duration of the exposure (less than 5 years [median of 3 years] vs. greater than 5 years [median of 10 years] of use before the cancer diagnosis). The relative risk associated with combined current and recent use (discontinued use within 5 years before cancer diagnosis) was 1.37 (95% CI 1.27–1.48), and the elevated risk was significant for both estrogen-alone and estrogen plus progestin products. The exact duration of hormone therapy use associated with an increased risk of ovarian cancer, however, is unknown. In the WHIMS estrogen-alone ancillary study of WHI, a population of 2,947 hysterectomized women 65 to 79 years of age was randomized to daily CE (0.625 mg)-alone or placebo. After an average follow-up of 5.2 years, 28 women in the estrogen-alone group and 19 women in the placebo group were diagnosed with probable dementia. The relative risk of probable dementia for CE-alone versus placebo was 1.49 (95 percent CI 0.83–2.66). The absolute risk of probable dementia for CE-alone versus placebo was 37 versus 25 cases per 10,000 women-years 8 [see Use in Specific Populations (8.5) , and Clinical Studies (14.6) ] . In the WHIMS estrogen plus progestin ancillary study of WHI, a population of 4,532 postmenopausal women 65 to 79 years of age was randomized to daily CE (0.625 mg) plus MPA (2.5 mg) or placebo. After an average follow-up of 4 years, 40 women in the CE plus MPA group and 21 women in the placebo group were diagnosed with probable dementia. The relative risk of probable dementia for CE plus MPA versus placebo was 2.05 (95 percent CI 1.21–3.48). The absolute risk of probable dementia for CE plus MPA versus placebo was 45 versus 22 cases per 10,000 women-years 8 [see Use in Specific Populations (8.5) , and Clinical Studies (14.6) ]. When data from the two populations in the WHIMS estrogen-alone and estrogen plus progestin ancillary studies were pooled as planned in the WHIMS protocol, the reported overall relative risk for probable dementia was 1.76 (95 percent CI 1.19–2.60). Since both ancillary studies were conducted in women 65 to 79 years of age, it is unknown whether these findings apply to younger postmenopausal women 8 [see Use in Specific Populations (8.5) , and Clinical Studies (14.6) ] . A 2- to 4-fold increase in the risk of gallbladder disease requiring surgery in postmenopausal women receiving estrogens has been reported. Estrogen administration may lead to severe hypercalcemia in patients with breast cancer and bone metastases. If hypercalcemia occurs, use of the drug should be stopped and appropriate measures taken to reduce the serum calcium level. Retinal vascular thrombosis has been reported in patients receiving estrogens. Discontinue medication pending examination if there is sudden partial or complete loss of vision, or a sudden onset of proptosis, diplopia, or migraine. If examination reveals papilledema or retinal vascular lesions, estrogens should be permanently discontinued. Cases of anaphylaxis, which developed within minutes to hours after taking PREMARIN and require emergency medical management, have been reported in the postmarketing setting. Skin (hives, pruritis, swollen lips-tongue-face) and either respiratory tract (respiratory compromise) or gastrointestinal tract (abdominal pain, vomiting) involvement has been noted. Angioedema involving the tongue, larynx, face, hands, and feet requiring medical intervention has occurred postmarketing in patients taking PREMARIN. If angioedema involves the tongue, glottis, or larynx, airway obstruction may occur. Patients who develop an anaphylactic reaction with or without angioedema after treatment with PREMARIN should not receive PREMARIN again. Studies of the addition of a progestin for 10 or more days of a cycle of estrogen administration or daily with estrogen in a continuous regimen, have reported a lowered incidence of endometrial hyperplasia than would be induced by estrogen treatment alone. Endometrial hyperplasia may be a precursor to endometrial cancer. There are, however, possible risks that may be associated with the use of progestins with estrogens compared to estrogen-alone regimens. These include an increased risk of breast cancer. In a small number of case reports, substantial increases in blood pressure have been attributed to idiosyncratic reactions to estrogens. In a large, randomized, placebo-controlled clinical trial, a generalized effect of estrogen therapy on blood pressure was not seen. In women with pre-existing hypertriglyceridemia, estrogen therapy may be associated with elevations of plasma triglycerides leading to pancreatitis. Consider discontinuation of treatment if pancreatitis occurs. Estrogens may be poorly metabolized in patients with impaired liver function. For women with a history of cholestatic jaundice associated with past estrogen use or with pregnancy, caution should be exercised, and in the case of recurrence, medication should be discontinued. Estrogen administration leads to increased thyroid-binding globulin (TBG) levels. Women with normal thyroid function can compensate for the increased TBG by making more thyroid hormone, thus maintaining free T 4 and T 3 serum concentrations in the normal range. Women dependent on thyroid hormone replacement therapy who are also receiving estrogens may require increased doses of their thyroid replacement therapy. These women should have their thyroid function monitored in order to maintain their free thyroid hormone levels in an acceptable range. Estrogens may cause some degree of fluid retention. Women with conditions that might be influenced by this factor, such as cardiac or renal dysfunction, warrant careful observation when estrogen alone is prescribed. Estrogen therapy should be used with caution in individuals with hypoparathyroidism as estrogen-induced hypocalcemia may occur. Exogenous estrogens may exacerbate symptoms of angioedema in women with hereditary angioedema. A few cases of malignant transformation of residual endometrial implants have been reported in women treated post-hysterectomy with estrogen-alone therapy. For women known to have residual endometriosis post-hysterectomy, the addition of progestin should be considered. Estrogen therapy may cause an exacerbation of asthma, diabetes mellitus, epilepsy, migraine, porphyria, systemic lupus erythematosus, and hepatic hemangiomas and should be used with caution in women with these conditions. Serum follicle stimulating hormone (FSH) and estradiol levels have not been shown to be useful in the management of moderate to severe vasomotor symptoms and moderate to severe symptoms of vulvar and vaginal atrophy. Laboratory parameters may be useful in guiding dosage for the treatment of hypoestrogenism due to hypogonadism, castration and primary ovarian failure. Accelerated prothrombin time, partial thromboplastin time, and platelet aggregation time; increased platelet count; increased factors II, VII antigen, VIII antigen, VIII coagulant activity, IX, X, XII, VII-X complex, II-VII-X complex, and beta-thromboglobulin; decreased levels of antifactor Xa and antithrombin III, decreased antithrombin III activity; increased levels of fibrinogen and fibrinogen activity; increased plasminogen antigen and activity. Increased thyroid-binding globulin (TBG) levels leading to increased circulating total thyroid hormone levels as measured by protein-bound iodine (PBI), T 4 levels (by column or by radioimmunoassay) or T 3 levels by radioimmunoassay. T 3 resin uptake is decreased, reflecting the elevated TBG. Free T 4 and free T 3 concentrations are unaltered. Women on thyroid replacement therapy may require higher doses of thyroid hormone. Other binding proteins may be elevated in serum, for example, corticosteroid binding globulin (CBG), sex hormone-binding globulin (SHBG), leading to increased total circulating corticosteroids and sex steroids, respectively. Free hormone concentrations, such as testosterone and estradiol, may be decreased. Other plasma proteins may be increased (angiotensinogen/renin substrate, alpha-1-antitrypsin, ceruloplasmin). Increased plasma high-density lipoprotein (HDL) and HDL 2 cholesterol subfraction concentrations, reduced low-density lipoprotein (LDL) cholesterol concentrations, increased triglyceride levels. Impaired glucose tolerance.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Endogenous estrogens are largely responsible for the development and maintenance of the female reproductive system and secondary sexual characteristics. Although circulating estrogens exist in a dynamic equilibrium of metabolic interconversions, estradiol is the principal intracellular human estrogen and is substantially more potent than its metabolites, estrone and estriol, at the receptor level. The primary source of estrogen in normally cycling adult women is the ovarian follicle, which secretes 70 to 500 mcg of estradiol daily, depending on the phase of the menstrual cycle. After menopause, most endogenous estrogen is produced by conversion of androstenedione, secreted by the adrenal cortex, to estrone in the peripheral tissues. Thus, estrone and the sulfate-conjugated form, estrone sulfate, are the most abundant circulating estrogens in postmenopausal women. Estrogens act through binding to nuclear receptors in estrogen-responsive tissues. To date, two estrogen receptors have been identified. These vary in proportion from tissue to tissue. Circulating estrogens modulate the pituitary secretion of the gonadotropins, luteinizing hormone (LH) and FSH, through a negative feedback mechanism. Estrogens act to reduce the elevated levels of these gonadotropins seen in postmenopausal women. There are no pharmacodynamic data for PREMARIN. Absorption Conjugated estrogens are water-soluble and are absorbed from the gastrointestinal tract after release from the drug formulation. The PREMARIN tablet releases conjugated estrogens slowly over several hours. Table 2 summarizes the mean pharmacokinetic parameters for unconjugated and conjugated estrogens following administration of 1 × 0.625 mg and 1 × 1.25 mg tablets to healthy postmenopausal women. Food effect: The pharmacokinetics of PREMARIN 0.45 mg and 1.25 mg tablets were assessed following a single dose with a high-fat breakfast and with fasting administration. The C max and AUC of estrogens were altered approximately 3–13%. The changes to C max and AUC are not considered clinically meaningful, therefore PREMARIN may be taken without regard to meals. TABLE 2: PHARMACOKINETIC PARAMETERS FOR PREMARIN Pharmacokinetic Profile of Unconjugated Estrogens Following a Dose of 1 × 0.625 mg PK Parameter Arithmetic Mean (%CV) C max (pg/mL) t max (h) t 1/2 (h) AUC (pg∙h/mL) Estrone 87 (33) 9.6 (33) 50.7 (35) 5557 (59) Baseline-adjusted estrone 64 (42) 9.6 (33) 20.2 (40) 1723 (52) Equilin 31 (38) 7.9 (32) 12.9 (112) 602 (54) Pharmacokinetic Profile of Conjugated Estrogens Following a Dose of 1 × 0.625 mg PK Parameter Arithmetic Mean (%CV) C max (ng/mL) t max (h) t 1/2 (h) AUC (ng∙h/mL) Total Estrone 2.7 (43) 6.9 (25) 26.7 (33) 75 (52) Baseline-adjusted total estrone 2.5 (45) 6.9 (25) 14.8 (35) 46 (48) Total Equilin 1.8 (56) 5.6 (45) 11.4 (31) 27 (56) Pharmacokinetic Profile of Unconjugated Estrogens Following a Dose of 1 × 1.25 mg PK Parameter Arithmetic Mean (%CV) C max (pg/mL) t max (h) t 1/2 (h) AUC (pg∙h/mL) Estrone 124 (30) 10.0 (32) 38.1 (37) 6332 (44) Baseline-adjusted estrone 102 (35) 10.0 (32) 19.7 (48) 3159 (53) Equilin 59 (43) 8.8 (36) 10.9 (47) 1182 (42) Pharmacokinetic Profile of Conjugated Estrogens Following a Dose of 1 × 1.25 mg PK Parameter Arithmetic Mean (%CV) C max (ng/mL) t max (h) t 1/2 (h) AUC (ng∙h/mL) Total Estrone 4.5 (39) 8.2 (58) 26.5 (40) 109 (46) Baseline-adjusted total estrone 4.3 (41) 8.2 (58) 17.5 (41) 87 (44) Total equilin 2.9 (42) 6.8 (49) 12.5 (34) 48 (51) Distribution The distribution of exogenous estrogens is similar to that of endogenous estrogens. Estrogens are widely distributed in the body and are generally found in higher concentration in the sex hormone target organs. Estrogens circulate in the blood largely bound to sex hormone-binding globulin (SHBG) and albumin. Metabolism Exogenous estrogens are metabolized in the same manner as endogenous estrogens. Circulating estrogens exist in a dynamic equilibrium of metabolic interconversions. These transformations take place mainly in the liver. Estradiol is converted reversibly to estrone, and both can be converted to estriol, which is a major urinary metabolite. Estrogens also undergo enterohepatic recirculation via sulfate and glucuronide conjugation in the liver, biliary secretion of conjugates into the intestine, and hydrolysis in the intestine followed by reabsorption. In postmenopausal women, a significant portion of the circulating estrogens exists as sulfate conjugates, especially estrone sulfate, which serves as a circulating reservoir for the formation of more active estrogens. Excretion Estradiol, estrone, and estriol are excreted in the urine, along with glucuronide and sulfate conjugates. Use in Specific Populations No pharmacokinetic studies were conducted with Premarin in specific populations, including patients with renal or hepatic impairment.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="1353" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>WARNING: ENDOMETRIAL CANCER, CARDIOVASCULAR DISORDERS, BREAST CANCER AND PROBABLE DEMENTIA See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1354" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Estrogen-Alone Therapy There is an increased risk of endometrial cancer in a woman with a uterus who uses unopposed estrogens (5.2) Estrogen-alone therapy should not be used for the prevention of cardiovascular disease or dementia (5.1, 5.3 ) Women's Health Initiative (WHI) estrogen-alone substudy reported increased risks of stroke and deep vein thrombosis (DVT) (5.1) The WHI Memory Study (WHIMS) estrogen-alone ancillary study of WHI reported an increased risk of probable dementia in postmenopausal women 65 years of age and older (5.3) Estrogen Plus Progestin Therapy Estrogen plus progestin therapy should not be used for the prevention of cardiovascular disease or dementia (5.1, 5.3) The WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy reported increased risks of stroke, DVT, pulmonary embolism (PE), and myocardial infarction (MI) (5.1) The WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy reported increased risks of invasive breast cancer (5.2) The WHIMS estrogen plus progestin ancillary study of WHI reported an increased risk of probable dementia in postmenopausal women 65 years of age and older (5.3) Estrogen-Alone Therapy Endometrial Cancer There is an increased risk of endometrial cancer in a woman with a uterus who uses unopposed estrogens.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1355" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Adding a progestin to estrogen therapy has been shown to reduce the risk of endometrial hyperplasia, which may be a precursor to endometrial cancer.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1356" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Adequate diagnostic measures, including directed or random endometrial sampling when indicated, should be undertaken to rule out malignancy in postmenopausal women with undiagnosed persistent or recurring abnormal genital bleeding.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1357" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Cardiovascular Disorders and Probable Dementia Estrogen-alone therapy should not be used for the prevention of cardiovascular disease or dementia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1358" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>The Women's Health Initiative (WHI) estrogen-alone substudy reported increased risks of stroke and deep vein thrombosis (DVT) in postmenopausal women (50 to 79 years of age) during 7.1 years of treatment with daily oral conjugated estrogens (CE) [0.625 mg]-alone, relative to placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1359" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>The WHI Memory Study (WHIMS) estrogen-alone ancillary study of WHI reported an increased risk of developing probable dementia in postmenopausal women 65 years of age or older during 5.2 years of treatment with daily CE (0.625 mg)-alone, relative to placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1360" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>It is unknown whether this finding applies to younger postmenopausal women.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1361" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>In the absence of comparable data, these risks should be assumed to be similar for other doses of CE and other dosage forms of estrogens.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1362" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Estrogens with or without progestins should be prescribed at the lowest effective doses and for the shortest duration consistent with treatment goals and risks for the individual woman.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1363" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Estrogen Plus Progestin Therapy Cardiovascular Disorders and Probable Dementia Estrogen plus progestin therapy should not be used for the prevention of cardiovascular disease or dementia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1364" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>The WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy reported increased risks of DVT, pulmonary embolism (PE), stroke and myocardial infarction (MI) in postmenopausal women (50 to 79 years of age) during 5.6 years of treatment with daily oral CE (0.625 mg) combined with medroxyprogesterone acetate (MPA) [2.5 mg], relative to placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1365" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>The WHIMS estrogen plus progestin ancillary study of the WHI, reported an increased risk of developing probable dementia in postmenopausal women 65 years of age or older during 4 years of treatment with daily CE (0.625 mg) combined with MPA (2.5 mg), relative to placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1366" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Breast Cancer The WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy also demonstrated an increased risk of invasive breast cancer.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1367" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>In the absence of comparable data, these risks should be assumed to be similar for other doses of CE and MPA, and other combinations and dosage forms of estrogens and progestins.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1368" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Using estrogen-alone may increase your chance of getting cancer of the uterus (womb)Report any unusual vaginal bleeding right away while you are using PREMARIN.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1369" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Vaginal bleeding after menopause may be a warning sign of cancer of the uterus (womb).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1370" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Your healthcare provider should check any unusual vaginal bleeding to find the cause.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1371" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Do not use estrogen-alone to prevent heart disease, heart attacks, or dementia (decline of brain function) Using estrogen-alone may increase your chances of getting strokes or blood clots Using estrogen-alone may increase your chance of getting dementia, based on a study of women 65 years of age or older Do not use estrogens with progestins to prevent heart disease, heart attacks, strokes, or dementia Using estrogens with progestins may increase your chances of getting heart attacks, strokes, breast cancer, or blood clots Using estrogens with progestins may increase your chance of getting dementia, based on a study of women 65 years of age or older You and your healthcare provider should talk regularly about whether you still need treatment with PREMARIN</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1372" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>PREMARIN therapy is contraindicated in individuals with any of the following conditions: Undiagnosed abnormal genital bleeding Known, suspected, or history of breast cancer except in appropriately selected patients being treated for metastatic disease Known or suspected estrogen-dependent neoplasia Active DVT, PE, or a history of these conditions Active arterial thromboembolic disease (for example stroke and MI), or a history of these conditions Known anaphylactic reaction or angioedema with Premarin Known liver impairment or disease Known protein C, protein S or antithrombin deficiency, or other known thrombophilic disorders.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1373" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Known or suspected pregnancy Undiagnosed abnormal genital bleeding (4) Known, suspected, or history of breast cancer except in appropriately selected patients being treated for metastatic diseases (4, 5.2) Known or suspected estrogen-dependent neoplasia (4, 5.2) Active DVT, PE, or a history of these conditions (4, 5.1) Active arterial thromboembolic disease (for example, stroke and MI), or a history of these conditions (4, 5.1) Known anaphylactic reaction or angioedema with PREMARIN (5.7) Known liver impairment or disease (4, 5.12) Known protein C, protein S, or antithrombin deficiency, or other known thrombophilic disorders (4) Known or suspected pregnancy (4, 8.1)</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1374" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Generally, when estrogen therapy is prescribed for a postmenopausal woman with a uterus, a progestin should be considered to reduce the risk of endometrial cancer.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1375" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>A woman without a uterus does not need progestin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1376" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In some cases, however, hysterectomized women with a history of endometriosis may need a progestin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1377" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Use of estrogen-alone, or in combination with a progestin, should be with the lowest effective dose and for the shortest duration consistent with treatment goals and risks for the individual woman.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1378" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Postmenopausal women should be re-evaluated periodically as clinically appropriate to determine if treatment is still necessary.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1379" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>PREMARIN may be taken without regard to meals.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1380" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Daily administration of 0.3, 0.45, 0.625, 0.9, and 1.25 mg (2.1, 2.2, 2.3, 2.5, 2.6) Cyclic administration of 0.3, 0.625, and 1.25 mg (2.1, 2.2, 2.3) Patients should be treated with the lowest effective dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1381" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Generally, women should be started at 0.3 mg PREMARIN daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1382" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Subsequent dosage adjustment may be made based upon the individual patient response.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1383" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>This dose should be periodically reassessed by the healthcare provider.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1384" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>PREMARIN therapy may be given continuously, with no interruption in therapy, or in cyclical regimens (regimens such as 25 days on drug followed by 5 days off drug), as is medically appropriate on an individual basis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1385" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Patients should be treated with the lowest effective dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1386" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>PREMARIN therapy should be initiated and maintained with the lowest effective dose to achieve clinical goals.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1387" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Female hypogonadism: 0.3 mg or 0.625 mg daily, administered cyclically (e.g., three weeks on and one week off).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1388" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Doses are adjusted depending on the severity of symptoms and responsiveness of the endometrium.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1389" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Female castration or primary ovarian failure: 1.25 mg daily, cyclically.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1390" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Adjust dosage, upward or downward, according to severity of symptoms and response of the patient.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1391" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For maintenance, adjust dosage to lowest level that will provide effective control.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1392" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Suggested dosage is 10 mg three times daily, for a period of at least three months.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1393" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>1.25 mg to 2 Ã— 1.25 mg three times daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1394" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The effectiveness of therapy can be judged by phosphatase determinations as well as by symptomatic improvement of the patient.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1395" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Subsequent dosage adjustment may be made based upon the individual clinical and bone mineral density responses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1396" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34074-5">
<SentenceText>Accelerated prothrombin time, partial thromboplastin time, and platelet aggregation time; increased platelet count; increased factors II, VII antigen, VIII antigen, VIII coagulant activity, IX, X, XII, VII-X complex, II-VII-X complex, and beta-thromboglobulin; decreased levels of antifactor Xa and antithrombin III, decreased antithrombin III activity; increased levels of fibrinogen and fibrinogen activity; increased plasminogen antigen and activity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1397" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34074-5">
<SentenceText>Increased thyroid-binding globulin (TBG) levels leading to increased circulating total thyroid hormone levels as measured by protein-bound iodine (PBI), T4 levels (by column or by radioimmunoassay) or T3 levels by radioimmunoassay.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1398" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34074-5">
<SentenceText>T3 resin uptake is decreased, reflecting the elevated TBG.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1399" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34074-5">
<SentenceText>Free T4 and free T3 concentrations are unaltered.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1400" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34074-5">
<SentenceText>Women on thyroid replacement therapy may require higher doses of thyroid hormone.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M1" type="Trigger" span="49 12" str="higher doses"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="65 15" str="thyroid hormone" code="0B4FDL9I6P"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M1" precipitant="M2"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1401" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34074-5">
<SentenceText>Other binding proteins may be elevated in serum, for example, corticosteroid binding globulin (CBG), sex hormone-binding globulin (SHBG), leading to increased total circulating corticosteroids and sex steroids, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1402" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34074-5">
<SentenceText>Free hormone concentrations, such as testosterone and estradiol, may be decreased.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1403" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34074-5">
<SentenceText>Other plasma proteins may be increased (angiotensinogen/renin substrate, alpha-1-antitrypsin, ceruloplasmin).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1404" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34074-5">
<SentenceText>Increased plasma high-density lipoprotein (HDL) and HDL2 cholesterol subfraction concentrations, reduced low-density lipoprotein (LDL) cholesterol concentrations, increased triglyceride levels.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1405" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Data from a single-dose drug-drug interaction study involving conjugated estrogens and medroxyprogesterone acetate indicate that the pharmacokinetic disposition of both drugs is not altered when the drugs are coadministered.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1406" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>No other clinical drug-drug interaction studies have been conducted with conjugated estrogens.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1407" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Inducers and/or inhibitors of CYP3A4 may affect estrogen drug metabolism (7.1) In vitro and in vivo studies have shown that estrogens are metabolized partially by cytochrome P450 3A4 (CYP3A4).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M6" type="Trigger" span="41 6;62 10" str="affect | metabolism"/>
<Mention id="M4" type="Precipitant" span="0 8;27 9" str="Inducers | of CYP3A4" code="N0000185506"/>
<Mention id="M8" type="SpecificInteraction" span="41 31" str="affect estrogen drug metabolism" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M7" type="Precipitant" span="16 20" str="inhibitors of CYP3A4" code="N0000182141"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M6" precipitant="M4" effect="M8" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M6" precipitant="M7" effect="M8" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1408" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Therefore, inducers or inhibitors of CYP3A4 may affect estrogen drug metabolism.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M12" type="Trigger" span="48 6;69 10" str="affect | metabolism"/>
<Mention id="M10" type="Precipitant" span="11 8;34 9" str="inducers | of CYP3A4" code="N0000185506"/>
<Mention id="M14" type="SpecificInteraction" span="48 31" str="affect estrogen drug metabolism" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M13" type="Precipitant" span="23 20" str="inhibitors of CYP3A4" code="N0000182141"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M12" precipitant="M10" effect="M14" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M12" precipitant="M13" effect="M14" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1409" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Inducers of CYP3A4, such as St. John's Wort (Hypericum perforatum) preparations, phenobarbital, carbamazepine, and rifampin, may reduce plasma concentrations of estrogens, possibly resulting in a decrease in therapeutic effects and/or changes in the uterine bleeding profile.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M48" type="Trigger" span="181 12" str="resulting in"/>
<Mention id="M52" type="Precipitant" span="96 13" str="carbamazepine" code="33CM23913M | N0000007470"/>
<Mention id="M47" type="SpecificInteraction" span="235 39" str="changes in the uterine bleeding profile" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M50" type="SpecificInteraction" span="196 31" str="decrease in therapeutic effects" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M54" type="Precipitant" span="45 20" str="Hypericum perforatum" code="XK4IUX8MNB"/>
<Mention id="M56" type="Precipitant" span="0 18" str="Inducers of CYP3A4" code="N0000185506"/>
<Mention id="M58" type="Precipitant" span="81 13" str="phenobarbital" code="YQE403BP4D | N0000005893"/>
<Mention id="M60" type="Precipitant" span="115 8" str="rifampin" code="VJT6J7R4TR | N0000006026"/>
<Mention id="M62" type="Precipitant" span="28 15" str="St. John's Wort" code="N0000022261 | UFH8805FKA"/>
<Mention id="M61" type="Trigger" span="129 28" str="reduce plasma concentrations"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M48" precipitant="M52" effect="M47" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M48" precipitant="M52" effect="M50" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M48" precipitant="M54" effect="M47" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M48" precipitant="M54" effect="M50" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M48" precipitant="M56" effect="M47" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M48" precipitant="M56" effect="M50" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M48" precipitant="M58" effect="M47" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M48" precipitant="M58" effect="M50" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M48" precipitant="M60" effect="M47" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M48" precipitant="M60" effect="M50" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M48" precipitant="M62" effect="M47" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M48" precipitant="M62" effect="M50" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M61" precipitant="M52" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M61" precipitant="M54" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M61" precipitant="M56" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M61" precipitant="M58" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M61" precipitant="M60" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M61" precipitant="M62" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1410" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Inhibitors of CYP3A4, such as erythromycin, clarithromycin, ketoconazole, itraconazole, ritonavir and grapefruit juice, may increase plasma concentrations of estrogens and may result in side effects.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M75" type="Trigger" span="124 30" str="increase plasma concentrations"/>
<Mention id="M64" type="Precipitant" span="44 14" str="clarithromycin" code="H1250JIK0A | N0000007316"/>
<Mention id="M66" type="Precipitant" span="30 12" str="erythromycin" code="N0000007133 | 63937KV33D"/>
<Mention id="M68" type="Precipitant" span="102 16" str="grapefruit juice" code="n0000164879 | JQ9EK2H6BG"/>
<Mention id="M70" type="Precipitant" span="0 20" str="Inhibitors of CYP3A4" code="N0000182141"/>
<Mention id="M72" type="Precipitant" span="74 12" str="itraconazole" code="304NUG5GF4 | N0000006753"/>
<Mention id="M74" type="Precipitant" span="60 12" str="ketoconazole" code="N0000007319 | R9400W927I"/>
<Mention id="M76" type="Precipitant" span="88 9" str="ritonavir" code="O3J8G9O825 | N0000007423"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M75" precipitant="M64" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M75" precipitant="M66" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M75" precipitant="M68" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M75" precipitant="M70" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M75" precipitant="M72" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I29" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M75" precipitant="M74" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I30" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M75" precipitant="M76" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1411" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Estrogens increase the risk of gallbladder disease (5.4) Discontinue estrogen if severe hypercalcemia, loss of vision, severe hypertriglyceridemia or cholestatic jaundice occurs (5.5, 5.6, 5.11, 5.12) Monitor thyroid function in women on thyroid replacement therapy (5.13, 5.18) An increased risk of stroke and DVT has been reported with estrogen-alone therapy.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M77" type="Trigger" span="201 7" str="Monitor"/>
<Mention id="M78" type="Precipitant" span="238 27" str="thyroid replacement therapy" code="0B4FDL9I6P"/>
<Mention id="M79" type="SpecificInteraction" span="209 16" str="thyroid function" code="312399001: Thyroid function tests abnormal (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I31" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M77" precipitant="M78" effect="M79" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1412" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>An increased risk of PE, DVT, stroke and MI has been reported with estrogen plus progestin therapy.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M89" type="Trigger" span="3 14" str="increased risk"/>
<Mention id="M90" type="Precipitant" span="81 9" str="progestin" code="N0000175602"/>
<Mention id="M82" type="SpecificInteraction" span="25 3" str="DVT" code="128053003: Deep venous thrombosis (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M85" type="SpecificInteraction" span="41 2" str="MI" code="22298006: Myocardial infarction (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M88" type="SpecificInteraction" span="21 2" str="PE" code="59282003: Pulmonary embolism (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M91" type="SpecificInteraction" span="30 6" str="stroke" code="230690007: Cerebrovascular accident (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I32" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M89" precipitant="M90" effect="M82" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I33" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M89" precipitant="M90" effect="M85" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I34" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M89" precipitant="M90" effect="M88" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I35" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M89" precipitant="M90" effect="M91" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1413" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Should any of these events occur or be suspected, estrogen with or without progestin therapy should be discontinued immediately.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1414" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Risk factors for arterial vascular disease (for example, hypertension, diabetes mellitus, tobacco use, hypercholesterolemia, and obesity) and/or venous thromboembolism (VTE) (for example, personal or family history of VTE, obesity, and systemic lupus erythematosus) should be managed appropriately.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1415" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Stroke In the WHI estrogen-alone substudy, a statistically significant increased risk of stroke was reported in women 50 to 79 years of age receiving daily CE (0.625 mg)-alone compared to women in the same age group receiving placebo (45 versus 33 per 10,000 women-years).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1416" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The increase in risk was demonstrated in year 1 and persisted.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1417" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Should a stroke occur or be suspected, estrogen-alone therapy should be discontinued immediately.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1418" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Subgroup analyses of women 50 to 59 years of age suggest no increased risk of stroke for those women receiving CE (0.625 mg)-alone versus those receiving placebo (18 versus 21 per 10,000 women-years).1 In the WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy, a statistically significant increased risk of stroke was reported in women 50 to 79 years of age receiving daily CE (0.625 mg) plus MPA (2.5 mg) compared to women in the same age group receiving placebo (33 versus 25 per 10,000 women-years).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1419" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The increase in risk was demonstrated after the first year and persisted.1 Should a stroke occur or be suspected, estrogen plus progestin therapy should be discontinued immediately.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1420" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Coronary Heart Disease In the WHI estrogen-alone substudy, no overall effect on coronary heart disease (CHD) events (defined as nonfatal MI, silent MI, or CHD death) was reported in women receiving estrogen-alone compared to placebo2.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1421" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Subgroup analyses of women 50 to 59 years of age suggest a statistically non-significant reduction in CHD events (CE [0.625 mg]-alone compared to placebo) in women with less than 10 years since menopause (8 versus 16 per 10,000 women-years).1 In the WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy, there was a statistically non-significant increased risk of CHD events reported in women receiving daily CE (0.625 mg) plus MPA (2.5 mg) compared to women receiving placebo (41 versus 34 per 10,000 women-years).1 An increase in relative risk was demonstrated in year 1, and a trend toward decreasing relative risk was reported in years 2 through 5.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1422" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In postmenopausal women with documented heart disease (n = 2,763, average 66.7 years of age), in a controlled clinical trial of secondary prevention of cardiovascular disease (Heart and Estrogen/Progestin Replacement Study; HERS), treatment with daily CE (0.625 mg) plus MPA (2.5 mg) demonstrated no cardiovascular benefit.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1423" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>During an average follow-up of 4.1 years, treatment with CE plus MPA did not reduce the overall rate of CHD events in postmenopausal women with established CHD.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1424" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There were more CHD events in the CE plus MPA-treated group than in the placebo group in year 1, but not during the subsequent years.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1425" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Two thousand, three hundred and twenty-one (2,321) women from the original HERS trial agreed to participate in an open label extension of HERS, HERS II.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1426" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Average follow-up in HERS II was an additional 2.7 years, for a total of 6.8 years overall.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1427" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Rates of CHD events were comparable among women in the CE (0.625 mg) plus MPA (2.5 mg) group and the placebo group in HERS, HERS II, and overall.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1428" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Venous Thromboembolism (VTE) In the WHI estrogen-alone substudy, the risk of VTE (DVT and PE), was increased for women receiving daily CE (0.625 mg)-alone compared to placebo (30 versus 22 per 10,000 women-years), although only the increased risk of DVT reached statistical significance (23 versus 15 per 10,000 women-years).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1429" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The increase in VTE risk was demonstrated during the first 2 years3.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1430" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Should a VTE occur or be suspected, estrogen-alone therapy should be discontinued immediately.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1431" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In the WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy, a statistically significant 2-fold greater rate of VTE was reported in women receiving daily CE (0.625 mg) plus MPA (2.5 mg) compared to women receiving placebo (35 versus 17 per 10,000 women-years).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1432" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Statistically significant increases in risk for both DVT (26 versus 13 per 10,000 women-years) and PE (18 versus 8 per 10,000 women-years) were also demonstrated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1433" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The increase in VTE risk was demonstrated during the first year and persisted4.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1434" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Should a VTE occur or be suspected, estrogen plus progestin therapy should be discontinued immediately.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1435" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If feasible, estrogens should be discontinued at least 4 to 6 weeks before surgery of the type associated with an increased risk of thromboembolism, or during periods of prolonged immobilization.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1436" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Endometrial Cancer An increased risk of endometrial cancer has been reported with the use of unopposed estrogen therapy in a woman with a uterus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1437" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The reported endometrial cancer risk among unopposed estrogen users is about 2 to 12 times greater than in non-users, and appears dependent on duration of treatment and on estrogen dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1438" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Most studies show no significant increased risk associated with use of estrogens for less than 1 year.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1439" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The greatest risk appears associated with prolonged use, with increased risks of 15- to 24-fold for 5 to 10 years or more, and this risk has been shown to persist for at least 8 to 15 years after estrogen therapy is discontinued.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1440" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Clinical surveillance of all women using estrogen-alone or estrogen plus progestin therapy is important.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1441" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There is no evidence that the use of natural estrogens results in a different endometrial risk profile than synthetic estrogens of equivalent estrogen dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1442" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Adding a progestin to postmenopausal estrogen therapy has been shown to reduce the risk of endometrial hyperplasia, which may be a precursor to endometrial cancer.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1443" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Breast Cancer The most important randomized clinical trial providing information about breast cancer in estrogen-alone users is the WHI substudy of daily CE (0.625 mg)-alone.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1444" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In the WHI estrogen-alone substudy, after an average follow-up of 7.1 years, daily CE (0.625 mg)-alone was not associated with an increased risk of invasive breast cancer [relative risk (RR) 0.80] 5.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1445" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The most important randomized clinical trial providing information about breast cancer in estrogen plus progestin users is the WHI substudy of daily CE (0.625 mg) plus MPA (2.5 mg).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1446" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>After a mean follow-up of 5.6 years, the estrogen plus progestin substudy reported an increased risk of invasive breast cancer in women who took daily CE plus MPA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1447" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In this substudy, prior use of estrogen-alone or estrogen plus progestin therapy was reported by 26 percent of the women.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1448" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The relative risk of invasive breast cancer was 1.24, and the absolute risk was 41 versus 33 cases per 10,000 women-years, for CE plus MPA compared with placebo.6 Among women who reported prior use of hormone therapy, the relative risk of invasive breast cancer was 1.86, and the absolute risk was 46 versus 25 cases per 10,000 women-years for CE plus MPA compared with placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1449" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Among women who reported no prior use of hormone therapy, the relative risk of invasive breast cancer was 1.09, and the absolute risk was 40 versus 36 cases per 10,000 women-years for CE plus MPA compared with placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1450" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In the same substudy, invasive breast cancers were larger, were more likely to be node positive, and were diagnosed at a more advanced stage in the CE (0.625 mg) plus MPA (2.5 mg) group compared with the placebo group.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1451" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Metastatic disease was rare, with no apparent difference between the two groups.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1452" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Other prognostic factors, such as histologic subtype, grade and hormone receptor status did not differ between the groups.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1453" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Consistent with the WHI clinical trial, observational studies have also reported an increased risk of breast cancer for estrogen plus progestin therapy, and a smaller increased risk for estrogen-alone therapy, after several years of use.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M92" type="Trigger" span="84 14" str="increased risk"/>
<Mention id="M93" type="Precipitant" span="134 9" str="progestin" code="N0000175602"/>
<Mention id="M94" type="SpecificInteraction" span="102 13" str="breast cancer" code="254837009: Malignant neoplasm of breast (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I36" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M92" precipitant="M93" effect="M94" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1454" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The risk increased with duration of use, and appeared to return to baseline over about 5 years after stopping treatment (only the observational studies have substantial data on risk after stopping).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1455" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Observational studies also suggest that the risk of breast cancer was greater, and became apparent earlier, with estrogen plus progestin therapy as compared to estrogen-alone therapy.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M95" type="Trigger" span="44 4;70 7" str="risk | greater"/>
<Mention id="M96" type="Precipitant" span="127 9" str="progestin" code="N0000175602"/>
<Mention id="M97" type="SpecificInteraction" span="52 13" str="breast cancer" code="254837009: Malignant neoplasm of breast (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I37" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M95" precipitant="M96" effect="M97" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1456" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>However, these studies have not found significant variation in the risk of breast cancer among different estrogen plus progestin combinations, doses, or routes of administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1457" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The use of estrogen-alone and estrogen plus progestin has been reported to result in an increase in abnormal mammograms, requiring further evaluation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1458" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>All women should receive yearly breast examinations by a healthcare provider and perform monthly breast self-examinations.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1459" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In addition, mammography examinations should be scheduled based on patient age, risk factors, and prior mammogram results.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1460" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Ovarian Cancer The WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy reported a statistically non-significant increased risk of ovarian cancer.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1461" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>After an average follow-up of 5.6 years, the relative risk for ovarian cancer for CE plus MPA versus placebo was 1.58 (95 percent CI 0.77–3.24).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1462" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The absolute risk for CE plus MPA versus placebo was 4 versus 3 cases per 10,000 women-years.7 A meta-analysis of 17 prospective and 35 retrospective epidemiology studies found that women who used hormonal therapy for menopausal symptoms had an increased risk for ovarian cancer.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1463" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The primary analysis, using case-control comparisons, included 12,110 cancer cases from the 17 prospective studies.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1464" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The relative risks associated with current use of hormonal therapy was 1.41 (95% confidence interval [CI] 1.32 to 1.50); there was no difference in the risk estimates by duration of the exposure (less than 5 years [median of 3 years] vs. greater than 5 years [median of 10 years] of use before the cancer diagnosis).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1465" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The relative risk associated with combined current and recent use (discontinued use within 5 years before cancer diagnosis) was 1.37 (95% CI 1.27–1.48), and the elevated risk was significant for both estrogen-alone and estrogen plus progestin products.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1466" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The exact duration of hormone therapy use associated with an increased risk of ovarian cancer, however, is unknown.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1467" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In the WHIMS estrogen-alone ancillary study of WHI, a population of 2,947 hysterectomized women 65 to 79 years of age was randomized to daily CE (0.625 mg)-alone or placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1468" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>After an average follow-up of 5.2 years, 28 women in the estrogen-alone group and 19 women in the placebo group were diagnosed with probable dementia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1469" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The relative risk of probable dementia for CE-alone versus placebo was 1.49 (95 percent CI 0.83–2.66).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1470" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The absolute risk of probable dementia for CE-alone versus placebo was 37 versus 25 cases per 10,000 women-years8.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1471" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In the WHIMS estrogen plus progestin ancillary study of WHI, a population of 4,532 postmenopausal women 65 to 79 years of age was randomized to daily CE (0.625 mg) plus MPA (2.5 mg) or placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1472" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>After an average follow-up of 4 years, 40 women in the CE plus MPA group and 21 women in the placebo group were diagnosed with probable dementia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1473" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The relative risk of probable dementia for CE plus MPA versus placebo was 2.05 (95 percent CI 1.21–3.48).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1474" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The absolute risk of probable dementia for CE plus MPA versus placebo was 45 versus 22 cases per 10,000 women-years8.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1475" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>When data from the two populations in the WHIMS estrogen-alone and estrogen plus progestin ancillary studies were pooled as planned in the WHIMS protocol, the reported overall relative risk for probable dementia was 1.76 (95 percent CI 1.19–2.60).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1476" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Since both ancillary studies were conducted in women 65 to 79 years of age, it is unknown whether these findings apply to younger postmenopausal women8.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1477" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>A 2- to 4-fold increase in the risk of gallbladder disease requiring surgery in postmenopausal women receiving estrogens has been reported.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1478" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Estrogen administration may lead to severe hypercalcemia in patients with breast cancer and bone metastases.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1479" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If hypercalcemia occurs, use of the drug should be stopped and appropriate measures taken to reduce the serum calcium level.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1480" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Retinal vascular thrombosis has been reported in patients receiving estrogens.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1481" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Discontinue medication pending examination if there is sudden partial or complete loss of vision, or a sudden onset of proptosis, diplopia, or migraine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1482" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If examination reveals papilledema or retinal vascular lesions, estrogens should be permanently discontinued.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1483" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Cases of anaphylaxis, which developed within minutes to hours after taking PREMARIN and require emergency medical management, have been reported in the postmarketing setting.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1484" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Skin (hives, pruritis, swollen lips-tongue-face) and either respiratory tract (respiratory compromise) or gastrointestinal tract (abdominal pain, vomiting) involvement has been noted.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1485" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Angioedema involving the tongue, larynx, face, hands, and feet requiring medical intervention has occurred postmarketing in patients taking PREMARIN.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1486" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If angioedema involves the tongue, glottis, or larynx, airway obstruction may occur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1487" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients who develop an anaphylactic reaction with or without angioedema after treatment with PREMARIN should not receive PREMARIN again.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1488" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Studies of the addition of a progestin for 10 or more days of a cycle of estrogen administration or daily with estrogen in a continuous regimen, have reported a lowered incidence of endometrial hyperplasia than would be induced by estrogen treatment alone.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1489" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Endometrial hyperplasia may be a precursor to endometrial cancer.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1490" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There are, however, possible risks that may be associated with the use of progestins with estrogens compared to estrogen-alone regimens.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M98" type="Trigger" span="29 5" str="risks "/>
<Mention id="M99" type="Trigger" span="47 15" str=" associated with"/>
<Mention id="M100" type="Precipitant" span="74 10" str="progestins" code="N0000029189 | N0000175602"/>
<Interaction id="I38" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M98;M99" precipitant="M100"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1491" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>These include an increased risk of breast cancer.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1492" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In a small number of case reports, substantial increases in blood pressure have been attributed to idiosyncratic reactions to estrogens.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1493" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In a large, randomized, placebo-controlled clinical trial, a generalized effect of estrogen therapy on blood pressure was not seen.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1494" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In women with pre-existing hypertriglyceridemia, estrogen therapy may be associated with elevations of plasma triglycerides leading to pancreatitis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1495" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Consider discontinuation of treatment if pancreatitis occurs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1496" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Estrogens may be poorly metabolized in patients with impaired liver function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1497" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>For women with a history of cholestatic jaundice associated with past estrogen use or with pregnancy, caution should be exercised, and in the case of recurrence, medication should be discontinued.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1498" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Estrogen administration leads to increased thyroid-binding globulin (TBG) levels.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1499" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Women with normal thyroid function can compensate for the increased TBG by making more thyroid hormone, thus maintaining free T4 and T3 serum concentrations in the normal range.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1500" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Women dependent on thyroid hormone replacement therapy who are also receiving estrogens may require increased doses of their thyroid replacement therapy.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M101" type="Trigger" span="100 15" str="increased doses"/>
<Mention id="M102" type="Precipitant" span="125 27" str="thyroid replacement therapy" code="0B4FDL9I6P"/>
<Interaction id="I39" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M101" precipitant="M102"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1501" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>These women should have their thyroid function monitored in order to maintain their free thyroid hormone levels in an acceptable range.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1502" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Estrogens may cause some degree of fluid retention.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1503" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Women with conditions that might be influenced by this factor, such as cardiac or renal dysfunction, warrant careful observation when estrogen alone is prescribed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1504" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Estrogen therapy should be used with caution in individuals with hypoparathyroidism as estrogen-induced hypocalcemia may occur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1505" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Exogenous estrogens may exacerbate symptoms of angioedema in women with hereditary angioedema.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1506" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>A few cases of malignant transformation of residual endometrial implants have been reported in women treated post-hysterectomy with estrogen-alone therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1507" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>For women known to have residual endometriosis post-hysterectomy, the addition of progestin should be considered.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1508" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Estrogen therapy may cause an exacerbation of asthma, diabetes mellitus, epilepsy, migraine, porphyria, systemic lupus erythematosus, and hepatic hemangiomas and should be used with caution in women with these conditions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1509" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Serum follicle stimulating hormone (FSH) and estradiol levels have not been shown to be useful in the management of moderate to severe vasomotor symptoms and moderate to severe symptoms of vulvar and vaginal atrophy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1510" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Laboratory parameters may be useful in guiding dosage for the treatment of hypoestrogenism due to hypogonadism, castration and primary ovarian failure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1511" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Endogenous estrogens are largely responsible for the development and maintenance of the female reproductive system and secondary sexual characteristics.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1512" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Although circulating estrogens exist in a dynamic equilibrium of metabolic interconversions, estradiol is the principal intracellular human estrogen and is substantially more potent than its metabolites, estrone and estriol, at the receptor level.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1513" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The primary source of estrogen in normally cycling adult women is the ovarian follicle, which secretes 70 to 500 mcg of estradiol daily, depending on the phase of the menstrual cycle.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1514" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>After menopause, most endogenous estrogen is produced by conversion of androstenedione, secreted by the adrenal cortex, to estrone in the peripheral tissues.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1515" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Thus, estrone and the sulfate-conjugated form, estrone sulfate, are the most abundant circulating estrogens in postmenopausal women.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1516" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Estrogens act through binding to nuclear receptors in estrogen-responsive tissues.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1517" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>To date, two estrogen receptors have been identified.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1518" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>These vary in proportion from tissue to tissue.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1519" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Circulating estrogens modulate the pituitary secretion of the gonadotropins, luteinizing hormone (LH) and FSH, through a negative feedback mechanism.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1520" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Estrogens act to reduce the elevated levels of these gonadotropins seen in postmenopausal women.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1521" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There are no pharmacodynamic data for PREMARIN.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1522" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Absorption Conjugated estrogens are water-soluble and are absorbed from the gastrointestinal tract after release from the drug formulation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1523" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The PREMARIN tablet releases conjugated estrogens slowly over several hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1524" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Table 2 summarizes the mean pharmacokinetic parameters for unconjugated and conjugated estrogens following administration of 1 Ã— 0.625 mg and 1 Ã— 1.25 mg tablets to healthy postmenopausal women.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1525" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Food effect: The pharmacokinetics of PREMARIN 0.45 mg and 1.25 mg tablets were assessed following a single dose with a high-fat breakfast and with fasting administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1526" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The Cmax and AUC of estrogens were altered approximately 3–13%.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1527" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The changes to Cmax and AUC are not considered clinically meaningful, therefore PREMARIN may be taken without regard to meals.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1528" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>TABLE 2: PHARMACOKINETIC PARAMETERS FOR PREMARIN Pharmacokinetic Profile of Unconjugated Estrogens Following a Dose of 1 Ã— 0.625 mg PK Parameter Arithmetic Mean (%CV) Cmax (pg/mL) tmax (h) t1/2 (h) AUC (pg∙h/mL) Estrone 87 (33) 9.6 (33) 50.7 (35) 5557 (59) Baseline-adjusted estrone 64 (42) 9.6 (33) 20.2 (40) 1723 (52) Equilin 31 (38) 7.9 (32) 12.9 (112) 602 (54) Pharmacokinetic Profile of Conjugated Estrogens Following a Dose of 1 Ã— 0.625 mg PK Parameter Arithmetic Mean (%CV) Cmax (ng/mL) tmax (h) t1/2 (h) AUC (ng∙h/mL) Total Estrone 2.7 (43) 6.9 (25) 26.7 (33) 75 (52) Baseline-adjusted total estrone 2.5 (45) 6.9 (25) 14.8 (35) 46 (48) Total Equilin 1.8 (56) 5.6 (45) 11.4 (31) 27 (56) Pharmacokinetic Profile of Unconjugated Estrogens Following a Dose of 1 Ã— 1.25 mg PK Parameter Arithmetic Mean (%CV) Cmax (pg/mL) tmax (h) t1/2 (h) AUC (pg∙h/mL) Estrone 124 (30) 10.0 (32) 38.1 (37) 6332 (44) Baseline-adjusted estrone 102 (35) 10.0 (32) 19.7 (48) 3159 (53) Equilin 59 (43) 8.8 (36) 10.9 (47) 1182 (42) Pharmacokinetic Profile of Conjugated Estrogens Following a Dose of 1 Ã— 1.25 mg PK Parameter Arithmetic Mean (%CV) Cmax (ng/mL) tmax (h) t1/2 (h) AUC (ng∙h/mL) Total Estrone 4.5 (39) 8.2 (58) 26.5 (40) 109 (46) Baseline-adjusted total estrone 4.3 (41) 8.2 (58) 17.5 (41) 87 (44) Total equilin 2.9 (42) 6.8 (49) 12.5 (34) 48 (51) Distribution The distribution of exogenous estrogens is similar to that of endogenous estrogens.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1529" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Estrogens are widely distributed in the body and are generally found in higher concentration in the sex hormone target organs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1530" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Estrogens circulate in the blood largely bound to sex hormone-binding globulin (SHBG) and albumin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1531" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Metabolism Exogenous estrogens are metabolized in the same manner as endogenous estrogens.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1532" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Circulating estrogens exist in a dynamic equilibrium of metabolic interconversions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1533" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>These transformations take place mainly in the liver.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1534" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Estradiol is converted reversibly to estrone, and both can be converted to estriol, which is a major urinary metabolite.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1535" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Estrogens also undergo enterohepatic recirculation via sulfate and glucuronide conjugation in the liver, biliary secretion of conjugates into the intestine, and hydrolysis in the intestine followed by reabsorption.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1536" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In postmenopausal women, a significant portion of the circulating estrogens exists as sulfate conjugates, especially estrone sulfate, which serves as a circulating reservoir for the formation of more active estrogens.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1537" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Excretion Estradiol, estrone, and estriol are excreted in the urine, along with glucuronide and sulfate conjugates.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1538" LabelDrug="Premarin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Use in Specific Populations No pharmacokinetic studies were conducted with Premarin in specific populations, including patients with renal or hepatic impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="thyroid hormone" precipitantCode="0B4FDL9I6P"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="inducers | of cyp3a4" precipitantCode="N0000185506" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="inhibitors of cyp3a4" precipitantCode="N0000182141" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="inhibitors of cyp3a4" precipitantCode="N0000182141" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="carbamazepine" precipitantCode="33CM23913M | N0000007470" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="carbamazepine" precipitantCode="33CM23913M | N0000007470" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="hypericum perforatum" precipitantCode="XK4IUX8MNB" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="hypericum perforatum" precipitantCode="XK4IUX8MNB" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="inducers of cyp3a4" precipitantCode="N0000185506" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="inducers of cyp3a4" precipitantCode="N0000185506" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="phenobarbital" precipitantCode="YQE403BP4D | N0000005893" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="phenobarbital" precipitantCode="YQE403BP4D | N0000005893" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="rifampin" precipitantCode="VJT6J7R4TR | N0000006026" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="rifampin" precipitantCode="VJT6J7R4TR | N0000006026" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="st. john's wort" precipitantCode="N0000022261 | UFH8805FKA" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="st. john's wort" precipitantCode="N0000022261 | UFH8805FKA" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="clarithromycin" precipitantCode="H1250JIK0A | N0000007316" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="erythromycin" precipitantCode="N0000007133 | 63937KV33D" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="grapefruit juice" precipitantCode="n0000164879 | JQ9EK2H6BG" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="itraconazole" precipitantCode="304NUG5GF4 | N0000006753" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="ketoconazole" precipitantCode="N0000007319 | R9400W927I" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="ritonavir" precipitantCode="O3J8G9O825 | N0000007423" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="thyroid replacement therapy" precipitantCode="0B4FDL9I6P" effect="312399001: Thyroid function tests abnormal (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="thyroid replacement therapy" precipitantCode="0B4FDL9I6P"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="progestin" precipitantCode="N0000175602" effect="128053003: Deep venous thrombosis (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="progestin" precipitantCode="N0000175602" effect="22298006: Myocardial infarction (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="progestin" precipitantCode="N0000175602" effect="230690007: Cerebrovascular accident (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="progestin" precipitantCode="N0000175602" effect="254837009: Malignant neoplasm of breast (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="progestin" precipitantCode="N0000175602" effect="59282003: Pulmonary embolism (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="progestins" precipitantCode="N0000029189 | N0000175602"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>