<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Precose" setid="29a6f213-bc93-4dbd-bab0-744722b6f0b8">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
PRECOSE is contraindicated in patients with known hypersensitivity to the drug. Precose is contraindicated in patients with diabetic ketoacidosis or cirrhosis. PRECOSE is also contraindicated in patients with inflammatory bowel disease, colonic ulceration, partial intestinal obstruction or in patients predisposed to intestinal obstruction. In addition, PRECOSE is contraindicated in patients who have chronic intestinal diseases associated with marked disorders of digestion or absorption and in patients who have conditions that may deteriorate as a result of increased gas formation in the intestine.</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
There is no fixed dosage regimen for the management of diabetes mellitus with PRECOSE or any other pharmacologic agent. Dosage of PRECOSE must be individualized on the basis of both effectiveness and tolerance while not exceeding the maximum recommended dose of 100 mg t.i.d. PRECOSE should be taken three times daily at the start (with the first bite) of each main meal. PRECOSE should be started at a low dose, with gradual dose escalation as described below, both to reduce gastrointestinal side effects and to permit identification of the minimum dose required for adequate glycemic control of the patient. If the prescribed diet is not observed, the intestinal side effects may be intensified. If strongly distressing symptoms develop in spite of adherence to the diabetic diet prescribed, the doctor must be consulted and the dose temporarily or permanently reduced. During treatment initiation and dose titration (see below), one-hour postprandial plasma glucose may be used to determine the therapeutic response to PRECOSE and identify the minimum effective dose for the patient. Thereafter, glycosylated hemoglobin should be measured at intervals of approximately three months. The therapeutic goal should be to decrease both postprandial plasma glucose and glycosylated hemoglobin levels to normal or near normal by using the lowest effective dose of PRECOSE, either as monotherapy or in combination with sulfonylureas, insulin or metformin. The recommended starting dosage of PRECOSE is 25 mg given orally three times daily at the start (with the first bite) of each main meal. However, some patients may benefit from more gradual dose titration to minimize gastrointestinal side effects. This may be achieved by initiating treatment at 25 mg once per day and subsequently increasing the frequency of administration to achieve 25 mg t.i.d. Once a 25 mg t.i.d. dosage regimen is reached, dosage of PRECOSE should be adjusted at 4–8 week intervals based on one-hour postprandial glucose or glycosylated hemoglobin levels, and on tolerance. The dosage can be increased from 25 mg t.i.d. to 50 mg t.i.d. Some patients may benefit from further increasing the dosage to 100 mg t.i.d. The maintenance dose ranges from 50 mg t.i.d. to 100 mg t.i.d. However, since patients with low body weight may be at increased risk for elevated serum transaminases, only patients with body weight &amp;gt; 60 kg should be considered for dose titration above 50 mg t.i.d. (see PRECAUTIONS ).  If no further reduction in postprandial glucose or glycosylated hemoglobin levels is observed with titration to 100 mg t.i.d., consideration should be given to lowering the dose. Once an effective and tolerated dosage is established, it should be maintained. The maximum recommended dose for patients ≤ 60 kg is 50 mg t.i.d. The maximum recommended dose for patients &amp;gt; 60 kg is 100 mg t.i.d. Sulfonylurea agents or insulin may cause hypoglycemia. PRECOSE given in combination with a sulfonylurea or insulin will cause a further lowering of blood glucose and may increase the potential for hypoglycemia. If hypoglycemia occurs, appropriate adjustments in the dosage of these agents should be made.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
Certain drugs tend to produce hyperglycemia and may lead to loss of blood glucose control. These drugs include the thiazides and other diuretics, corticosteroids, phenothiazines, thyroid products, estrogens, oral contraceptives, phenytoin, nicotinic acid, sympathomimetics, calcium channel-blocking drugs, and isoniazid. When such drugs are administered to a patient receiving PRECOSE, the patient should be closely observed for loss of blood glucose control. When such drugs are withdrawn from patients receiving PRECOSE in combination with sulfonylureas or insulin, patients should be observed closely for any evidence of hypoglycemia. Patients Receiving Sulfonylureas or Insulin:  Sulfonylurea agents or insulin may cause hypoglycemia. PRECOSE given in combination with a sulfonylurea or insulin may cause a further lowering of blood glucose and may increase the potential for hypoglycemia. If hypoglycemia occurs, appropriate adjustments in the dosage of these agents should be made. Very rarely, individual cases of hypoglycemic shock have been reported in patients receiving PRECOSE therapy in combination with sulfonylureas and/or insulin. Intestinal adsorbents (for example, charcoal) and digestive enzyme preparations containing carbohydrate-splitting enzymes (for example, amylase, pancreatin) may reduce the effect of PRECOSE and should not be taken concomitantly. PRECOSE has been shown to change the bioavailability of digoxin when they are coadministered, which may require digoxin dose adjustment. (See CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY, Drug-Drug Interactions .</Section>
<Section name="PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="42232-9">
There have been no clinical studies establishing conclusive evidence of macrovascular risk reduction with PRECOSE or any other anti-diabetic drug. Hypoglycemia Because of its mechanism of action, PRECOSE when administered alone should not cause hypoglycemia in the fasted or postprandial state. Sulfonylurea agents or insulin may cause hypoglycemia. Because PRECOSE given in combination with a sulfonylurea or insulin will cause a further lowering of blood glucose, it may increase the potential for hypoglycemia. Hypoglycemia does not occur in patients receiving metformin alone under usual circumstances of use, and no increased incidence of hypoglycemia was observed in patients when PRECOSE was added to metformin therapy. Oral glucose (dextrose), whose absorption is not inhibited by PRECOSE, should be used instead of sucrose (cane sugar) in the treatment of mild to moderate hypoglycemia. Sucrose, whose hydrolysis to glucose and fructose is inhibited by PRECOSE, is unsuitable for the rapid correction of hypoglycemia. Severe hypoglycemia may require the use of either intravenous glucose infusion or glucagon injection. In long-term studies (up to 12 months, and including PRECOSE doses up to 300 mg t.i.d.) conducted in the United States, treatment-emergent elevations of serum transaminases (AST and/or ALT) above the upper limit of normal (ULN), greater than 1.8 times the ULN, and greater than 3 times the ULN occurred in 14%, 6%, and 3%, respectively, of PRECOSE-treated patients as compared to 7%, 2%, and 1%, respectively, of placebo-treated patients. Although these differences between treatments were statistically significant, these elevations were asymptomatic, reversible, more common in females, and, in general, were not associated with other evidence of liver dysfunction. In addition, these serum transaminase elevations appeared to be dose related. In US studies including PRECOSE doses up to the maximum approved dose of 100 mg t.i.d., treatment-emergent elevations of AST and/or ALT at any level of severity were similar between PRECOSE-treated patients and placebo-treated patients (p ≥ 0.496). In approximately 3 million patient-years of international postmarketing experience with PRECOSE, 62 cases of serum transaminase elevations &amp;gt; 500 IU/L (29 of which were associated with jaundice) have been reported. Forty-one of these 62 patients received treatment with 100 mg t.i.d. or greater and 33 of 45 patients for whom weight was reported weighed &amp;lt; 60 kg. In the 59 cases where follow-up was recorded, hepatic abnormalities improved or resolved upon discontinuation of PRECOSE in 55 and were unchanged in two. Cases of fulminant hepatitis with fatal outcome have been reported; the relationship to acarbose is unclear. When diabetic patients are exposed to stress such as fever, trauma, infection, or surgery, a temporary loss of control of blood glucose may occur. At such times, temporary insulin therapy may be necessary. Patients should be told to take PRECOSE orally three times a day at the start (with the first bite) of each main meal. It is important that patients continue to adhere to dietary instructions, a regular exercise program, and regular testing of urine and/or blood glucose. PRECOSE itself does not cause hypoglycemia even when administered to patients in the fasted state. Sulfonylurea drugs and insulin, however, can lower blood sugar levels enough to cause symptoms or sometimes life-threatening hypoglycemia. Because PRECOSE given in combination with a sulfonylurea or insulin will cause a further lowering of blood sugar, it may increase the hypoglycemic potential of these agents. Hypoglycemia does not occur in patients receiving metformin alone under usual circumstances of use, and no increased incidence of hypoglycemia was observed in patients when PRECOSE was added to metformin therapy. The risk of hypoglycemia, its symptoms and treatment, and conditions that predispose to its development should be well understood by patients and responsible family members. Because PRECOSE prevents the breakdown of table sugar, patients should have a readily available source of glucose (dextrose, D-glucose) to treat symptoms of low blood sugar when taking PRECOSE in combination with a sulfonylurea or insulin. If side effects occur with PRECOSE, they usually develop during the first few weeks of therapy. They are most commonly mild-to-moderate gastrointestinal effects, such as flatulence, diarrhea, or abdominal discomfort, and generally diminish in frequency and intensity with time. Therapeutic response to PRECOSE should be monitored by periodic blood glucose tests. Measurement of glycosylated hemoglobin levels is recommended for the monitoring of long-term glycemic control. PRECOSE, particularly at doses in excess of 50 mg t.i.d., may give rise to elevations of serum transaminases and, in rare instances, hyperbilirubinemia. It is recommended that serum transaminase levels be checked every 3 months during the first year of treatment with PRECOSE and periodically thereafter. If elevated transaminases are observed, a reduction in dosage or withdrawal of therapy may be indicated, particularly if the elevations persist. Monitoring glycemic control with 1,5-AG assay is not recommended as measurements of 1,5-AG are unreliable in assessing glycemic control in patients taking acarbose. Use alternative methods to monitor for glycemic control. Plasma concentrations of PRECOSE in renally impaired volunteers were proportionally increased relative to the degree of renal dysfunction. Long-term clinical trials in diabetic patients with significant renal dysfunction (serum creatinine &amp;gt; 2.0 mg/dL) have not been conducted. Therefore, treatment of these patients with PRECOSE is not recommended. Certain drugs tend to produce hyperglycemia and may lead to loss of blood glucose control. These drugs include the thiazides and other diuretics, corticosteroids, phenothiazines, thyroid products, estrogens, oral contraceptives, phenytoin, nicotinic acid, sympathomimetics, calcium channel-blocking drugs, and isoniazid. When such drugs are administered to a patient receiving PRECOSE, the patient should be closely observed for loss of blood glucose control. When such drugs are withdrawn from patients receiving PRECOSE in combination with sulfonylureas or insulin, patients should be observed closely for any evidence of hypoglycemia. Patients Receiving Sulfonylureas or Insulin:  Sulfonylurea agents or insulin may cause hypoglycemia. PRECOSE given in combination with a sulfonylurea or insulin may cause a further lowering of blood glucose and may increase the potential for hypoglycemia. If hypoglycemia occurs, appropriate adjustments in the dosage of these agents should be made. Very rarely, individual cases of hypoglycemic shock have been reported in patients receiving PRECOSE therapy in combination with sulfonylureas and/or insulin. Intestinal adsorbents (for example, charcoal) and digestive enzyme preparations containing carbohydrate-splitting enzymes (for example, amylase, pancreatin) may reduce the effect of PRECOSE and should not be taken concomitantly. PRECOSE has been shown to change the bioavailability of digoxin when they are coadministered, which may require digoxin dose adjustment. (See CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY, Drug-Drug Interactions . Eight carcinogenicity studies were conducted with acarbose. Six studies were performed in rats (two strains, Sprague-Dawley and Wistar) and two studies were performed in hamsters. In the first rat study, Sprague-Dawley rats received acarbose in feed at high doses (up to approximately 500 mg/kg body weight) for 104 weeks. Acarbose treatment resulted in a significant increase in the incidence of renal tumors (adenomas and adenocarcinomas) and benign Leydig cell tumors. This study was repeated with a similar outcome. Further studies were performed to separate direct carcinogenic effects of acarbose from indirect effects resulting from the carbohydrate malnutrition induced by the large doses of acarbose employed in the studies. In one study using Sprague-Dawley rats, acarbose was mixed with feed but carbohydrate deprivation was prevented by the addition of glucose to the diet. In a 26-month study of Sprague-Dawley rats, acarbose was administered by daily postprandial gavage so as to avoid the pharmacologic effects of the drug. In both of these studies, the increased incidence of renal tumors found in the original studies did not occur. Acarbose was also given in food and by postprandial gavage in two separate studies in Wistar rats. No increased incidence of renal tumors was found in either of these Wistar rat studies. In two feeding studies of hamsters, with and without glucose supplementation, there was also no evidence of carcinogenicity. Acarbose did not induce any DNA damage in vitro in the CHO chromosomal aberration assay, bacterial mutagenesis (Ames) assay, or a DNA binding assay. In vivo, no DNA damage was detected in the dominant lethal test in male mice, or the mouse micronucleus test. Fertility studies conducted in rats after oral administration produced no untoward effect on fertility or on the overall capability to reproduce. The safety of PRECOSE in pregnant women has not been established. Reproduction studies have been performed in rats at doses up to 480 mg/kg (corresponding to 9 times the exposure in humans, based on drug blood levels) and have revealed no evidence of impaired fertility or harm to the fetus due to acarbose. In rabbits, reduced maternal body weight gain, probably the result of the pharmacodynamic activity of high doses of acarbose in the intestines, may have been responsible for a slight increase in the number of embryonic losses. However, rabbits given 160 mg/kg acarbose (corresponding to 10 times the dose in man, based on body surface area) showed no evidence of embryotoxicity and there was no evidence of teratogenicity at a dose 32 times the dose in man (based on body surface area). There are, however, no adequate and well-controlled studies of PRECOSE in pregnant women. Because animal reproduction studies are not always predictive of the human response, this drug should be used during pregnancy only if clearly needed. Because current information strongly suggests that abnormal blood glucose levels during pregnancy are associated with a higher incidence of congenital anomalies as well as increased neonatal morbidity and mortality, most experts recommend that insulin be used during pregnancy to maintain blood glucose levels as close to normal as possible. A small amount of radioactivity has been found in the milk of lactating rats after administration of radiolabeled acarbose. It is not known whether this drug is excreted in human milk. Because many drugs are excreted in human milk, PRECOSE should not be administered to a nursing woman. Safety and effectiveness of PRECOSE in pediatric patients have not been established. Of the total number of subjects in clinical studies of PRECOSE in the United States, 27% were 65 and over, while 4% were 75 and over. No overall differences in safety and effectiveness were observed between these subjects and younger subjects. The mean steady-state area under the curve (AUC) and maximum concentrations of acarbose were approximately 1.5 times higher in elderly compared to young volunteers; however, these differences were not statistically significant.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Acarbose is a complex oligosaccharide that delays the digestion of ingested carbohydrates, thereby resulting in a smaller rise in blood glucose concentration following meals. As a consequence of plasma glucose reduction, PRECOSE reduces levels of glycosylated hemoglobin in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus. Systemic non-enzymatic protein glycosylation, as reflected by levels of glycosylated hemoglobin, is a function of average blood glucose concentration over time. In contrast to sulfonylureas, PRECOSE does not enhance insulin secretion. The antihyperglycemic action of acarbose results from a competitive, reversible inhibition of pancreatic alpha-amylase and membrane-bound intestinal alpha-glucoside hydrolase enzymes. Pancreatic alpha-amylase hydrolyzes complex starches to oligosaccharides in the lumen of the small intestine, while the membrane-bound intestinal alpha-glucosidases hydrolyze oligosaccharides, trisaccharides, and disaccharides to glucose and other monosaccharides in the brush border of the small intestine. In diabetic patients, this enzyme inhibition results in a delayed glucose absorption and a lowering of postprandial hyperglycemia. Because its mechanism of action is different, the effect of PRECOSE to enhance glycemic control is additive to that of sulfonylureas, insulin or metformin when used in combination. In addition, PRECOSE diminishes the insulinotropic and weight-increasing effects of sulfonylureas. Acarbose has no inhibitory activity against lactase and consequently would not be expected to induce lactose intolerance. In a study of 6 healthy men, less than 2% of an oral dose of acarbose was absorbed as active drug, while approximately 35% of total radioactivity from a 14 C-labeled oral dose was absorbed. An average of 51% of an oral dose was excreted in the feces as unabsorbed drug-related radioactivity within 96 hours of ingestion. Because acarbose acts locally within the gastrointestinal tract, this low systemic bioavailability of parent compound is therapeutically desired. Following oral dosing of healthy volunteers with 14 C-labeled acarbose, peak plasma concentrations of radioactivity were attained 14–24 hours after dosing, while peak plasma concentrations of active drug were attained at approximately 1 hour. The delayed absorption of acarbose-related radioactivity reflects the absorption of metabolites that may be formed by either intestinal bacteria or intestinal enzymatic hydrolysis. Acarbose is metabolized exclusively within the gastrointestinal tract, principally by intestinal bacteria, but also by digestive enzymes. A fraction of these metabolites (approximately 34% of the dose) was absorbed and subsequently excreted in the urine. At least 13 metabolites have been separated chromatographically from urine specimens. The major metabolites have been identified as 4-methylpyrogallol derivatives (that is, sulfate, methyl, and glucuronide conjugates). One metabolite (formed by cleavage of a glucose molecule from acarbose) also has alpha-glucosidase inhibitory activity. This metabolite, together with the parent compound, recovered from the urine, accounts for less than 2% of the total administered dose. The fraction of acarbose that is absorbed as intact drug is almost completely excreted by the kidneys. When acarbose was given intravenously, 89% of the dose was recovered in the urine as active drug within 48 hours. In contrast, less than 2% of an oral dose was recovered in the urine as active (that is, parent compound and active metabolite) drug. This is consistent with the low bioavailability of the parent drug. The plasma elimination half-life of acarbose activity is approximately 2 hours in healthy volunteers. Consequently, drug accumulation does not occur with three times a day (t.i.d.) oral dosing. The mean steady-state area under the curve (AUC) and maximum concentrations of acarbose were approximately 1.5 times higher in elderly compared to young volunteers; however, these differences were not statistically significant. Patients with severe renal impairment (Clcr &amp;lt; 25 mL/min/1.73m 2 ) attained about 5 times higher peak plasma concentrations of acarbose and 6 times larger AUCs than volunteers with normal renal function. No studies of acarbose pharmacokinetic parameters according to race have been performed. In U.S. controlled clinical studies of PRECOSE in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus, reductions in glycosylated hemoglobin levels were similar in Caucasians (n=478) and African-Americans (n=167), with a trend toward a better response in Latinos (n=132). Studies in healthy volunteers have shown that PRECOSE has no effect on either the pharmacokinetics or pharmacodynamics of nifedipine, propranolol, or ranitidine. PRECOSE did not interfere with the absorption or disposition of the sulfonylurea glyburide in diabetic patients. PRECOSE may affect digoxin bioavailability and may require dose adjustment of digoxin by 16% (90% confidence interval: 8-23%), decrease mean C max of digoxin by 26% (90% confidence interval: 16–34%) and decreases mean trough concentrations of digoxin by 9% (90% confidence limit: 19% decrease to 2% increase). (See PRECAUTIONS, Drug Interactions . ) The amount of metformin absorbed while taking PRECOSE was bioequivalent to the amount absorbed when taking placebo, as indicated by the plasma AUC values. However, the peak plasma level of metformin was reduced by approximately 20% when taking PRECOSE  due to a slight delay in the absorption of metformin. There is little if any clinically significant interaction between PRECOSE and metformin.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="8474" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>PRECOSE is contraindicated in patients with known hypersensitivity to the drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8475" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Precose is contraindicated in patients with diabetic ketoacidosis or cirrhosis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8476" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>PRECOSE is also contraindicated in patients with inflammatory bowel disease, colonic ulceration, partial intestinal obstruction or in patients predisposed to intestinal obstruction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8477" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>In addition, PRECOSE is contraindicated in patients who have chronic intestinal diseases associated with marked disorders of digestion or absorption and in patients who have conditions that may deteriorate as a result of increased gas formation in the intestine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8478" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>There is no fixed dosage regimen for the management of diabetes mellitus with PRECOSE or any other pharmacologic agent.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8479" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dosage of PRECOSE must be individualized on the basis of both effectiveness and tolerance while not exceeding the maximum recommended dose of 100 mg t.i.d.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8480" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>PRECOSE should be taken three times daily at the start (with the first bite) of each main meal.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8481" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>PRECOSE should be started at a low dose, with gradual dose escalation as described below, both to reduce gastrointestinal side effects and to permit identification of the minimum dose required for adequate glycemic control of the patient.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8482" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If the prescribed diet is not observed, the intestinal side effects may be intensified.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8483" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If strongly distressing symptoms develop in spite of adherence to the diabetic diet prescribed, the doctor must be consulted and the dose temporarily or permanently reduced.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8484" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>During treatment initiation and dose titration, one-hour postprandial plasma glucose may be used to determine the therapeutic response to PRECOSE and identify the minimum effective dose for the patient.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8485" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Thereafter, glycosylated hemoglobin should be measured at intervals of approximately three months.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8486" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The therapeutic goal should be to decrease both postprandial plasma glucose and glycosylated hemoglobin levels to normal or near normal by using the lowest effective dose of PRECOSE, either as monotherapy or in combination with sulfonylureas, insulin or metformin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8487" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommended starting dosage of PRECOSE is 25 mg given orally three times daily at the start (with the first bite) of each main meal.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8488" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>However, some patients may benefit from more gradual dose titration to minimize gastrointestinal side effects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8489" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>This may be achieved by initiating treatment at 25 mg once per day and subsequently increasing the frequency of administration to achieve 25 mg t.i.d.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8490" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Once a 25 mg t.i.d. dosage regimen is reached, dosage of PRECOSE should be adjusted at 4–8 week intervals based on one-hour postprandial glucose or glycosylated hemoglobin levels, and on tolerance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8491" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The dosage can be increased from 25 mg t.i.d. to 50 mg t.i.d.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8492" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Some patients may benefit from further increasing the dosage to 100 mg t.i.d.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8493" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The maintenance dose ranges from 50 mg t.i.d. to 100 mg t.i.d.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8494" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>However, since patients with low body weight may be at increased risk for elevated serum transaminases, only patients with body weight &gt; 60 kg should be considered for dose titration above 50 mg t.i.d.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8495" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If no further reduction in postprandial glucose or glycosylated hemoglobin levels is observed with titration to 100 mg t.i.d., consideration should be given to lowering the dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8496" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Once an effective and tolerated dosage is established, it should be maintained.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8497" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The maximum recommended dose for patients ≤ 60 kg is 50 mg t.i.d.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8498" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The maximum recommended dose for patients &gt; 60 kg is 100 mg t.i.d.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8499" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Sulfonylurea agents or insulin may cause hypoglycemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8500" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>PRECOSE given in combination with a sulfonylurea or insulin will cause a further lowering of blood glucose and may increase the potential for hypoglycemia.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M7" type="Trigger" span="115 22" str="increase the potential"/>
<Mention id="M5" type="Precipitant" span="52 7" str="insulin" code="N0000004931 | N0000175944"/>
<Mention id="M9" type="SpecificInteraction" span="142 12" str="hypoglycemia" code="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M10" type="Trigger" span="65 5" str="cause"/>
<Mention id="M12" type="SpecificInteraction" span="81 25" str="lowering of blood glucose" code="51798006: Decreased glucose level (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M11" type="Precipitant" span="36 12" str="sulfonylurea" code="N0000175608 | N0000008054"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M7" precipitant="M5" effect="M9" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M10" precipitant="M5" effect="M12" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M7" precipitant="M11" effect="M9" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M10" precipitant="M11" effect="M12" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8501" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If hypoglycemia occurs, appropriate adjustments in the dosage of these agents should be made.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8502" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Certain drugs tend to produce hyperglycemia and may lead to loss of blood glucose control.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8503" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>These drugs include the thiazides and other diuretics, corticosteroids, phenothiazines, thyroid products, estrogens, oral contraceptives, phenytoin, nicotinic acid, sympathomimetics, calcium channel-blocking drugs, and isoniazid.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8504" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>When such drugs are administered to a patient receiving PRECOSE, the patient should be closely observed for loss of blood glucose control.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8505" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>When such drugs are withdrawn from patients receiving PRECOSE in combination with sulfonylureas or insulin, patients should be observed closely for any evidence of hypoglycemia.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M16" type="Trigger" span="117 18" str="should be observed"/>
<Mention id="M14" type="Precipitant" span="99 7" str="insulin" code="N0000004931 | N0000175944"/>
<Mention id="M18" type="SpecificInteraction" span="164 12" str="hypoglycemia" code="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M17" type="Precipitant" span="82 13" str="sulfonylureas" code="N0000175608 | N0000008054"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M16" precipitant="M14" effect="M18" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M16" precipitant="M17" effect="M18" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8506" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Patients Receiving Sulfonylureas or Insulin: Sulfonylurea agents or insulin may cause hypoglycemia.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M25" type="Trigger" span="80 5" str="cause"/>
<Mention id="M20" type="Precipitant" span="36 7" str="insulin" code="N0000004931 | N0000175944"/>
<Mention id="M27" type="SpecificInteraction" span="86 12" str="hypoglycemia" code="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M23" type="Precipitant" span="45 19" str="Sulfonylurea agents" code="N0000175608"/>
<Mention id="M26" type="Precipitant" span="19 13" str="Sulfonylureas" code="N0000175608 | N0000008054"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M25" precipitant="M20" effect="M27" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M25" precipitant="M23" effect="M27" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M25" precipitant="M26" effect="M27" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8507" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>PRECOSE given in combination with a sulfonylurea or insulin may cause a further lowering of blood glucose and may increase the potential for hypoglycemia.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M34" type="Trigger" span="114 22" str="increase the potential"/>
<Mention id="M32" type="Precipitant" span="52 7" str="insulin" code="N0000004931 | N0000175944"/>
<Mention id="M36" type="SpecificInteraction" span="141 12" str="hypoglycemia" code="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M37" type="Trigger" span="64 5" str="cause"/>
<Mention id="M39" type="SpecificInteraction" span="80 25" str="lowering of blood glucose" code="51798006: Decreased glucose level (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M38" type="Precipitant" span="36 12" str="sulfonylurea" code="N0000175608 | N0000008054"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M34" precipitant="M32" effect="M36" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M37" precipitant="M32" effect="M39" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M34" precipitant="M38" effect="M36" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M37" precipitant="M38" effect="M39" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8508" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Very rarely, individual cases of hypoglycemic shock have been reported in patients receiving PRECOSE therapy in combination with sulfonylureas and/or insulin.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M45" type="SpecificInteraction" span="33 18" str="hypoglycemic shock" code="360546002: Hypoglycemic shock (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M41" type="Precipitant" span="150 7" str="insulin" code="N0000004931 | N0000175944"/>
<Mention id="M44" type="Precipitant" span="129 13" str="sulfonylureas" code="N0000175608 | N0000008054"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M45" precipitant="M41" effect="M45" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M45" precipitant="M44" effect="M45" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8509" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Intestinal adsorbents (for example, charcoal) and digestive enzyme preparations containing carbohydrate-splitting enzymes (for example, amylase, pancreatin) may reduce the effect of PRECOSE and should not be taken concomitantly.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M61" type="Trigger" span="161 17" str="reduce the effect"/>
<Mention id="M47" type="Precipitant" span="136 7" str="amylase" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M63" type="SpecificInteraction" span="161 28" str="reduce the effect of PRECOSE" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M50" type="Precipitant" span="91 30" str="carbohydrate-splitting enzymes" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M53" type="Precipitant" span="36 8" str="charcoal" code="2P3VWU3H10"/>
<Mention id="M56" type="Precipitant" span="50 29" str="digestive enzyme preparations" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M59" type="Precipitant" span="0 21" str="Intestinal adsorbents" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M62" type="Precipitant" span="145 10" str="pancreatin" code="FQ3DRG0N5K"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M61" precipitant="M47" effect="M63" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M61" precipitant="M50" effect="M63" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M61" precipitant="M53" effect="M63" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M61" precipitant="M56" effect="M63" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M61" precipitant="M59" effect="M63" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M61" precipitant="M62" effect="M63" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8510" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>PRECOSE has been shown to change the bioavailability of digoxin when they are coadministered, which may require digoxin dose adjustment.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M64" type="Trigger" span="26 26" str="change the bioavailability "/>
<Mention id="M65" type="Trigger" span="120 15" str=" dose adjustment"/>
<Mention id="M66" type="Precipitant" span="56 7" str="digoxin" code="73K4184T59 | N0000005903"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M64;M65" precipitant="M66"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8511" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>(See CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY, Drug-Drug Interactions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8512" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>There have been no clinical studies establishing conclusive evidence of macrovascular risk reduction with PRECOSE or any other anti-diabetic drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8513" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Hypoglycemia Because of its mechanism of action, PRECOSE when administered alone should not cause hypoglycemia in the fasted or postprandial state.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8514" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because PRECOSE given in combination with a sulfonylurea or insulin will cause a further lowering of blood glucose, it may increase the potential for hypoglycemia.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M73" type="Trigger" span="123 22" str="increase the potential"/>
<Mention id="M71" type="Precipitant" span="60 7" str="insulin" code="N0000004931 | N0000175944"/>
<Mention id="M75" type="SpecificInteraction" span="150 12" str="hypoglycemia" code="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M76" type="Trigger" span="2 5" str="cause"/>
<Mention id="M78" type="SpecificInteraction" span="89 25" str="lowering of blood glucose" code="51798006: Decreased glucose level (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M77" type="Precipitant" span="44 12" str="sulfonylurea" code="N0000175608 | N0000008054"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M73" precipitant="M71" effect="M75" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M76" precipitant="M71" effect="M78" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M73" precipitant="M77" effect="M75" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M76" precipitant="M77" effect="M78" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8515" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Hypoglycemia does not occur in patients receiving metformin alone under usual circumstances of use, and no increased incidence of hypoglycemia was observed in patients when PRECOSE was added to metformin therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8516" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Oral glucose (dextrose), whose absorption is not inhibited by PRECOSE, should be used instead of sucrose (cane sugar) in the treatment of mild to moderate hypoglycemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8517" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Sucrose, whose hydrolysis to glucose and fructose is inhibited by PRECOSE, is unsuitable for the rapid correction of hypoglycemia.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M79" type="Trigger" span="53 9" str="inhibited"/>
<Mention id="M80" type="Precipitant" span="0 7" str="Sucrose" code="C151H8M554"/>
<Mention id="M81" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 7;15 10;53 9" str="Sucrose | hydrolysis | inhibited" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M79" precipitant="M80" effect="M81" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8518" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Severe hypoglycemia may require the use of either intravenous glucose infusion or glucagon injection.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8519" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In long-term studies (up to 12 months, and including PRECOSE doses up to 300 mg t.i.d.) conducted in the United States, treatment-emergent elevations of serum transaminases (AST and/or ALT) above the upper limit of normal (ULN), greater than 1.8 times the ULN, and greater than 3 times the ULN occurred in 14%, 6%, and 3%, respectively, of PRECOSE-treated patients as compared to 7%, 2%, and 1%, respectively, of placebo-treated patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8520" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Although these differences between treatments were statistically significant, these elevations were asymptomatic, reversible, more common in females, and, in general, were not associated with other evidence of liver dysfunction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8521" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In addition, these serum transaminase elevations appeared to be dose related.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8522" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In US studies including PRECOSE doses up to the maximum approved dose of 100 mg t.i.d., treatment-emergent elevations of AST and/or ALT at any level of severity were similar between PRECOSE-treated patients and placebo-treated patients (p ≥ 0.496).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8523" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In approximately 3 million patient-years of international postmarketing experience with PRECOSE, 62 cases of serum transaminase elevations &gt; 500 IU/L (29 of which were associated with jaundice) have been reported.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8524" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Forty-one of these 62 patients received treatment with 100 mg t.i.d. or greater and 33 of 45 patients for whom weight was reported weighed &lt; 60 kg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8525" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In the 59 cases where follow-up was recorded, hepatic abnormalities improved or resolved upon discontinuation of PRECOSE in 55 and were unchanged in two.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8526" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Cases of fulminant hepatitis with fatal outcome have been reported; the relationship to acarbose is unclear.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8527" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>When diabetic patients are exposed to stress such as fever, trauma, infection, or surgery, a temporary loss of control of blood glucose may occur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8528" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>At such times, temporary insulin therapy may be necessary.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8529" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Patients should be told to take PRECOSE orally three times a day at the start (with the first bite) of each main meal.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8530" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>It is important that patients continue to adhere to dietary instructions, a regular exercise program, and regular testing of urine and/or blood glucose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8531" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>PRECOSE itself does not cause hypoglycemia even when administered to patients in the fasted state.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8532" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Sulfonylurea drugs and insulin, however, can lower blood sugar levels enough to cause symptoms or sometimes life-threatening hypoglycemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8533" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because PRECOSE given in combination with a sulfonylurea or insulin will cause a further lowering of blood sugar, it may increase the hypoglycemic potential of these agents.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M88" type="Trigger" span="121 8;147 9" str="increase | potential"/>
<Mention id="M86" type="Precipitant" span="60 7" str="insulin" code="N0000004931 | N0000175944"/>
<Mention id="M90" type="SpecificInteraction" span="121 35" str="increase the hypoglycemic potential" code="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M91" type="Trigger" span="2 5" str="cause"/>
<Mention id="M93" type="SpecificInteraction" span="89 23" str="lowering of blood sugar" code="51798006: Decreased glucose level (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M92" type="Precipitant" span="44 12" str="sulfonylurea" code="N0000175608 | N0000008054"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M88" precipitant="M86" effect="M90" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I29" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M91" precipitant="M86" effect="M93" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I30" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M88" precipitant="M92" effect="M90" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I31" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M91" precipitant="M92" effect="M93" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8534" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The risk of hypoglycemia, its symptoms and treatment, and conditions that predispose to its development should be well understood by patients and responsible family members.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8535" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because PRECOSE prevents the breakdown of table sugar, patients should have a readily available source of glucose (dextrose, D-glucose) to treat symptoms of low blood sugar when taking PRECOSE in combination with a sulfonylurea or insulin.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M97" type="Trigger" span="145 8" str="symptoms"/>
<Mention id="M95" type="Precipitant" span="231 7" str="insulin" code="N0000004931 | N0000175944"/>
<Mention id="M99" type="SpecificInteraction" span="157 15" str="low blood sugar" code="51798006: Decreased glucose level (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M98" type="Precipitant" span="215 12" str="sulfonylurea" code="N0000175608 | N0000008054"/>
<Interaction id="I32" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M97" precipitant="M95" effect="M99" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I33" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M97" precipitant="M98" effect="M99" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8536" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>If side effects occur with PRECOSE, they usually develop during the first few weeks of therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8537" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>They are most commonly mild-to-moderate gastrointestinal effects, such as flatulence, diarrhea, or abdominal discomfort, and generally diminish in frequency and intensity with time.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8538" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Therapeutic response to PRECOSE should be monitored by periodic blood glucose tests.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8539" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Measurement of glycosylated hemoglobin levels is recommended for the monitoring of long-term glycemic control.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8540" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>PRECOSE, particularly at doses in excess of 50 mg t.i.d., may give rise to elevations of serum transaminases and, in rare instances, hyperbilirubinemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8541" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>It is recommended that serum transaminase levels be checked every 3 months during the first year of treatment with PRECOSE and periodically thereafter.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8542" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>If elevated transaminases are observed, a reduction in dosage or withdrawal of therapy may be indicated, particularly if the elevations persist.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8543" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Monitoring glycemic control with 1,5-AG assay is not recommended as measurements of 1,5-AG are unreliable in assessing glycemic control in patients taking acarbose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8544" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Use alternative methods to monitor for glycemic control.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8545" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Plasma concentrations of PRECOSE in renally impaired volunteers were proportionally increased relative to the degree of renal dysfunction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8546" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Long-term clinical trials in diabetic patients with significant renal dysfunction (serum creatinine &gt; 2.0 mg/dL) have not been conducted.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8547" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Therefore, treatment of these patients with PRECOSE is not recommended.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8548" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Eight carcinogenicity studies were conducted with acarbose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8549" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Six studies were performed in rats (two strains, Sprague-Dawley and Wistar) and two studies were performed in hamsters.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8550" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In the first rat study, Sprague-Dawley rats received acarbose in feed at high doses (up to approximately 500 mg/kg body weight) for 104 weeks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8551" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Acarbose treatment resulted in a significant increase in the incidence of renal tumors (adenomas and adenocarcinomas) and benign Leydig cell tumors.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8552" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>This study was repeated with a similar outcome.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8553" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Further studies were performed to separate direct carcinogenic effects of acarbose from indirect effects resulting from the carbohydrate malnutrition induced by the large doses of acarbose employed in the studies.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8554" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In one study using Sprague-Dawley rats, acarbose was mixed with feed but carbohydrate deprivation was prevented by the addition of glucose to the diet.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8555" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In a 26-month study of Sprague-Dawley rats, acarbose was administered by daily postprandial gavage so as to avoid the pharmacologic effects of the drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8556" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In both of these studies, the increased incidence of renal tumors found in the original studies did not occur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8557" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Acarbose was also given in food and by postprandial gavage in two separate studies in Wistar rats.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8558" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>No increased incidence of renal tumors was found in either of these Wistar rat studies.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8559" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In two feeding studies of hamsters, with and without glucose supplementation, there was also no evidence of carcinogenicity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8560" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Acarbose did not induce any DNA damage in vitro in the CHO chromosomal aberration assay, bacterial mutagenesis (Ames) assay, or a DNA binding assay.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8561" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In vivo, no DNA damage was detected in the dominant lethal test in male mice, or the mouse micronucleus test.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8562" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Fertility studies conducted in rats after oral administration produced no untoward effect on fertility or on the overall capability to reproduce.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8563" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The safety of PRECOSE in pregnant women has not been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8564" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Reproduction studies have been performed in rats at doses up to 480 mg/kg (corresponding to 9 times the exposure in humans, based on drug blood levels) and have revealed no evidence of impaired fertility or harm to the fetus due to acarbose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8565" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In rabbits, reduced maternal body weight gain, probably the result of the pharmacodynamic activity of high doses of acarbose in the intestines, may have been responsible for a slight increase in the number of embryonic losses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8566" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>However, rabbits given 160 mg/kg acarbose (corresponding to 10 times the dose in man, based on body surface area) showed no evidence of embryotoxicity and there was no evidence of teratogenicity at a dose 32 times the dose in man (based on body surface area).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8567" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>There are, however, no adequate and well-controlled studies of PRECOSE in pregnant women.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8568" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because animal reproduction studies are not always predictive of the human response, this drug should be used during pregnancy only if clearly needed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8569" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because current information strongly suggests that abnormal blood glucose levels during pregnancy are associated with a higher incidence of congenital anomalies as well as increased neonatal morbidity and mortality, most experts recommend that insulin be used during pregnancy to maintain blood glucose levels as close to normal as possible.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8570" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>A small amount of radioactivity has been found in the milk of lactating rats after administration of radiolabeled acarbose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8571" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>It is not known whether this drug is excreted in human milk.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8572" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because many drugs are excreted in human milk, PRECOSE should not be administered to a nursing woman.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8573" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Safety and effectiveness of PRECOSE in pediatric patients have not been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8574" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Of the total number of subjects in clinical studies of PRECOSE in the United States, 27% were 65 and over, while 4% were 75 and over.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8575" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>No overall differences in safety and effectiveness were observed between these subjects and younger subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8576" LabelDrug="Precose" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The mean steady-state area under the curve (AUC) and maximum concentrations of acarbose were approximately 1.5 times higher in elderly compared to young volunteers; however, these differences were not statistically significant.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8577" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Acarbose is a complex oligosaccharide that delays the digestion of ingested carbohydrates,thereby resulting in a smaller rise in blood glucose concentration following meals.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8578" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>As a consequence of plasma glucose reduction, PRECOSE reduces levels of glycosylated hemoglobin in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8579" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Systemic non-enzymatic protein glycosylation, as reflected by levels of glycosylated hemoglobin, is a function of average blood glucose concentration over time.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8580" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In contrast to sulfonylureas, PRECOSE does not enhance insulin secretion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8581" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The antihyperglycemic action of acarbose results from a competitive, reversible inhibition of pancreatic alpha-amylase and membrane-bound intestinal alpha-glucoside hydrolase enzymes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8582" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Pancreatic alpha-amylase hydrolyzes complex starches to oligosaccharides in the lumen of the small intestine, while the membrane-bound intestinal alpha-glucosidases hydrolyze oligosaccharides, trisaccharides, and disaccharides to glucose and other monosaccharides in the brush border of the small intestine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8583" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In diabetic patients, this enzyme inhibition results in a delayed glucose absorption and a lowering of postprandial hyperglycemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8584" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Because its mechanism of action is different, the effect of PRECOSE to enhance glycemic control is additive to that of sulfonylureas, insulin or metformin when used in combination.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8585" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In addition, PRECOSE diminishes the insulinotropic and weight-increasing effects of sulfonylureas.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M103" type="Trigger" span="21 10;73 7" str="diminishes | effects"/>
<Mention id="M104" type="Precipitant" span="84 13" str="sulfonylureas" code="N0000175608 | N0000008054"/>
<Mention id="M102" type="SpecificInteraction" span="21 10;55 25" str="diminishes | weight-increasing effects" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M105" type="SpecificInteraction" span="21 29;73 7" str="diminishes the insulinotropic | effects" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I34" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M103" precipitant="M104" effect="M102" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I35" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M103" precipitant="M104" effect="M105" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8586" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Acarbose has no inhibitory activity against lactase and consequently would not be expected to induce lactose intolerance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8587" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In a study of 6 healthy men, less than 2% of an oral dose of acarbose was absorbed as active drug, while approximately 35% of total radioactivity from a 14C-labeled oral dose was absorbed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8588" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>An average of 51% of an oral dose was excreted in the feces as unabsorbed drug-related radioactivity within 96 hours of ingestion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8589" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Because acarbose acts locally within the gastrointestinal tract, this low systemic bioavailability of parent compound is therapeutically desired.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8590" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following oral dosing of healthy volunteers with 14C-labeled acarbose, peak plasma concentrations of radioactivity were attained 14–24 hours after dosing, while peak plasma concentrations of active drug were attained at approximately 1 hour.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8591" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The delayed absorption of acarbose-related radioactivity reflects the absorption of metabolites that may be formed by either intestinal bacteria or intestinal enzymatic hydrolysis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8592" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Acarbose is metabolized exclusively within the gastrointestinal tract, principally by intestinal bacteria, but also by digestive enzymes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8593" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A fraction of these metabolites (approximately 34% of the dose) was absorbed and subsequently excreted in the urine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8594" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>At least 13 metabolites have been separated chromatographically from urine specimens.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8595" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The major metabolites have been identified as 4-methylpyrogallol derivatives (that is, sulfate, methyl, and glucuronide conjugates).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8596" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>One metabolite (formed by cleavage of a glucose molecule from acarbose) also has alpha-glucosidase inhibitory activity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8597" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This metabolite, together with the parent compound, recovered from the urine, accounts for less than 2% of the total administered dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8598" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The fraction of acarbose that is absorbed as intact drug is almost completely excreted by the kidneys.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8599" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>When acarbose was given intravenously, 89% of the dose was recovered in the urine as active drug within 48 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8600" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In contrast, less than 2% of an oral dose was recovered in the urine as active (that is, parent compound and active metabolite) drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8601" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This is consistent with the low bioavailability of the parent drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8602" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The plasma elimination half-life of acarbose activity is approximately 2 hours in healthy volunteers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8603" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Consequently, drug accumulation does not occur with three times a day (t.i.d.)</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8604" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Patients with severe renal impairment (Clcr &lt; 25 mL/min/1.73m2) attained about 5 times higher peak plasma concentrations of acarbose and 6 times larger AUCs than volunteers with normal renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8605" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No studies of acarbose pharmacokinetic parameters according to race have been performed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8606" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In U.S. controlled clinical studies of PRECOSE in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus, reductions in glycosylated hemoglobin levels were similar in Caucasians (n=478) and African-Americans (n=167), with a trend toward a better response in Latinos (n=132).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8607" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Studies in healthy volunteers have shown that PRECOSE has no effect on either the pharmacokinetics or pharmacodynamics of nifedipine, propranolol, or ranitidine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8608" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>PRECOSE did not interfere with the absorption or disposition of the sulfonylurea glyburide in diabetic patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8609" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>PRECOSE may affect digoxin bioavailability and may require dose adjustment of digoxin by 16% (90% confidence interval: 8-23%), decrease mean Cmax of digoxin by 26% (90% confidence interval: 16–34%) and decreases mean trough concentrations of digoxin by 9% (90% confidence limit: 19% decrease to 2% increase).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M106" type="Trigger" span="127 8;141 4" str="decrease | Cmax"/>
<Mention id="M112" type="Precipitant" span="19 7" str="digoxin" code="73K4184T59 | N0000005903"/>
<Mention id="M108" type="Trigger" span="202 9;217 21" str="decreases | trough concentrations"/>
<Mention id="M110" type="Trigger" span="12 6;27 15" str="affect | bioavailability "/>
<Mention id="M111" type="Trigger" span="59 15" str=" dose adjustment"/>
<Interaction id="I36" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M106" precipitant="M112" effect="C54615"/>
<Interaction id="I37" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M108" precipitant="M112" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I38" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M110;M111" precipitant="M112"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8610" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The amount of metformin absorbed while taking PRECOSE was bioequivalent to the amount absorbed when taking placebo, as indicated by the plasma AUC values.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8611" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>However, the peak plasma level of metformin was reduced by approximately 20% when taking PRECOSE due to a slight delay in the absorption of metformin.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M113" type="Trigger" span="113 23" str="delay in the absorption"/>
<Mention id="M116" type="Precipitant" span="34 9" str="metformin" code="9100L32L2N"/>
<Mention id="M115" type="Trigger" span="13 17;48 7" str="peak plasma level | reduced"/>
<Interaction id="I39" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M113" precipitant="M116" effect="C54612"/>
<Interaction id="I40" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M115" precipitant="M116" effect="C54615"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8612" LabelDrug="Precose" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There is little if any clinically significant interaction between PRECOSE and metformin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="insulin" precipitantCode="N0000004931 | N0000175944" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="insulin" precipitantCode="N0000004931 | N0000175944" effect="360546002: Hypoglycemic shock (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="insulin" precipitantCode="N0000004931 | N0000175944" effect="51798006: Decreased glucose level (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sulfonylurea" precipitantCode="N0000175608 | N0000008054" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sulfonylurea" precipitantCode="N0000175608 | N0000008054" effect="51798006: Decreased glucose level (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sulfonylureas" precipitantCode="N0000175608 | N0000008054" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sulfonylureas" precipitantCode="N0000175608 | N0000008054" effect="360546002: Hypoglycemic shock (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sulfonylureas" precipitantCode="N0000175608 | N0000008054" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sulfonylurea agents" precipitantCode="N0000175608" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="amylase" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="carbohydrate-splitting enzymes" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="charcoal" precipitantCode="2P3VWU3H10" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="digestive enzyme preparations" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="intestinal adsorbents" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="pancreatin" precipitantCode="FQ3DRG0N5K" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="digoxin" precipitantCode="73K4184T59 | N0000005903" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="digoxin" precipitantCode="73K4184T59 | N0000005903" effect="C54615"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="digoxin" precipitantCode="73K4184T59 | N0000005903"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sucrose" precipitantCode="C151H8M554" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="metformin" precipitantCode="9100L32L2N" effect="C54612"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="metformin" precipitantCode="9100L32L2N" effect="C54615"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>