<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Osmolex ER" setid="2bced627-51e3-4e5c-a23c-30deb86ff37b">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
OSMOLEX ER is contraindicated in patients with end-stage renal disease (i.e., creatinine clearance below 15 mL/min/1.73 m 2 ) [see Clinical Pharmacology ( 12.3 )]. OSMOLEX ER is contraindicated in patients with end-stage renal disease ( 4 )</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
The initial dosage is 129 mg orally once daily in the morning ( 2.1 ) The dosage may be increased in weekly intervals to a maximum daily dose of 322 mg once daily in the morning ( 2.1 ) Swallow tablets whole; do not chew, crush, or divide ( 2.2 ) Dosing frequency reduction and monitoring required for renal impairment ( 2.3 , 8.6 ) The recommended initial dosage of OSMOLEX ER is 129 mg administered orally once daily in the morning. The dosage may be increased in weekly intervals to a maximum daily dose of 322 mg (administered as a 129 mg and 193 mg tablet), taken in the morning.  OSMOLEX ER is not interchangeable with other amantadine immediate- or extended-release products. For patients unable to tolerate more than 100 mg per day of immediate-release amantadine, there is no equivalent dose or dosing regimen of OSMOLEX ER. OSMOLEX ER should be swallowed whole. Do not chew, crush, or divide tablets.  OSMOLEX ER can be administered without regard to food.  There are no modifications for the recommended initial and maximum dosage in patients with renal impairment; however, modifications are recommended for the titration interval and frequency of dosing in patients with moderate and severe renal impairment (see Table 1).  Table 1: Recommended Titration and Frequency of OSMOLEX ER Dosing in Patients with Renal Impairment Renal Function/Estimated GFR (mL/min/1.73 m 2 ) * Minimum Titration Interval Frequency of Dosing Regimen Mild renal impairment (60 to 89) Increase every week One dose every 24 hours Moderate renal impairment (30 to 59) Increase every 3 weeks One dose every 48 hours Severe renal impairment (15 to 29) Increase every 4 weeks One dose every 96 hours End-Stage Renal Disease (below 15) Contraindicated * estimated by Modification of Diet in Renal Disease (MDRD) method Monitor patients with renal impairment for change in renal function, especially in those with severe renal impairment receiving the maximum daily dosage of 322 mg [see Use in Specific Populations ( 8.6 )]. OSMOLEX ER should not be discontinued abruptly . The dose should be reduced gradually from higher doses to 129 mg daily for 1 to 2 weeks before discontinuing [see Warnings and Precautions ( 5.5 )]. If a dose of OSMOLEX ER is missed, the next dose should be taken as scheduled.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
Anticholinergic Drugs: Increased risk of anticholinergic effects; the dose of anticholinergic drugs or OSMOLEX ER may require reduction ( 7.1 ) Drugs Affecting Urinary pH: Excretion increases with acidic urine; possible accumulation with urine change towards alkaline ( 7.2 ) Live Attenuated Influenza Vaccines: Not recommended during use ( 7.3 ) Alcohol: Concomitant use is not recommended; increased potential for CNS effects ( 7.4 ) Products with anticholinergic properties may potentiate the anticholinergic-like side effects of amantadine. The dose of anticholinergic drugs or of OSMOLEX ER should be reduced if atropine-like effects appear when these drugs are used concurrently [see Warnings and Precautions ( 5.4 )] .  The pH of the urine has been reported to influence the excretion rate of amantadine. Urine pH is altered by diet, drugs (e.g., carbonic anhydrase inhibitors, sodium bicarbonate), and clinical state of the patient (e.g., renal tubular acidosis or severe infections of the urinary tract). Since the excretion rate of amantadine increases rapidly when the urine is acidic, the administration of urine acidifying drugs may increase the elimination of the drug from the body. Alterations of urine pH towards the alkaline condition may lead to an accumulation of the drug with a possible increase in adverse reactions.  Monitor for efficacy or adverse reactions under conditions that alter the urine pH to more acidic or alkaline, respectively. Because of its antiviral properties, amantadine may interfere with the efficacy of live attenuated influenza vaccines. Therefore, live vaccines are not recommended during treatment with OSMOLEX ER.  Inactivated influenza vaccines may be used, as appropriate. Concomitant use with alcohol is not recommended, as it may increase the potential for central nervous system effects such as somnolence, dizziness, confusion, lightheadedness, and orthostatic hypotension [see Warnings and Precautions ( 5.1 , 5.4 ].</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
Falling Asleep During Activities of Daily Living and Somnolence: Advise patients prior to treatment; ordinarily discontinue if occurs ( 5.1 ) Suicidality and Depression: Monitor patients for depressed mood, depression, or suicidal ideation or behavior ( 5.2 ) Hallucinations/Psychotic Behavior: Patients with major psychotic disorder should ordinarily not be treated with OSMOLEX ER; observe patients for the occurrence of hallucinations throughout treatment, especially at initiation and after dose increases ( 5.3 ) Dizziness and Orthostatic Hypotension: Monitor patients for dizziness and orthostatic hypotension, especially after starting OSMOLEX ER or increasing the dose ( 5.4 ) Withdrawal-Emergent Hyperpyrexia and Confusion: Avoid sudden discontinuation ( 5.5 ) Impulse Control/Compulsive Behaviors: Ask patients about increased gambling urges, sexual urges, uncontrolled spending or other urges; consider dose reduction or discontinuation if occurs ( 5.6 ) Patients treated with amantadine have reported falling asleep while engaged in activities of daily living, including the operation of motor vehicles, which sometimes has resulted in accidents. Patients may not perceive warning signs, such as excessive drowsiness, or they may report feeling alert immediately prior to the event. Before initiating treatment with OSMOLEX ER, advise patients of the potential to develop drowsiness and specifically ask about factors that may increase the risk for somnolence with OSMOLEX ER, such as concomitant sedating medications, alcohol, or the presence of a sleep disorder.  If a patient develops daytime sleepiness or episodes of falling asleep during activities that require full attention (e.g., driving a motor vehicle, conversations, eating), OSMOLEX ER should ordinarily be discontinued. If a decision is made to continue OSMOLEX ER, advise patients not to drive and to avoid other potentially dangerous activities that might result in harm if they become somnolent. There is insufficient information to establish that dose reduction will eliminate episodes of falling asleep while engaged in activities of daily living or daytime somnolence. Suicide, suicide attempts, and suicidal ideation have been reported in patients with and without prior history of psychiatric illness while treated with amantadine. Amantadine can exacerbate psychiatric symptoms in patients with a history of psychiatric disorders or substance abuse. Monitor patients for depression, including suicidal ideation or behavior. Prescribers should consider whether the benefits outweigh the risks of treatment with OSMOLEX ER in patients with a history of suicidality or depression. Patients with a major psychotic disorder should ordinarily not be treated with OSMOLEX ER because of the risk of exacerbating psychosis.  Treatment with amantadine or abrupt withdrawal can cause confusion, psychosis, personality changes, agitation, aggressive behavior, hallucinations, paranoia, other psychotic or paranoia reactions [see Warnings and Precautions ( 5.5 )] . Monitor patients for hallucinations throughout treatment but especially after initiation and after the dose of OSMOLEX ER is increased or decreased. Dizziness and orthostatic hypotension can occur with OSMOLEX ER.  Patients should be monitored for these adverse reactions, especially after starting OSMOLEX ER or increasing the dose. Concomitant use of alcohol when using OSMOLEX ER is not recommended [see Drug Interactions ( 7.4 )]. A symptom complex resembling neuroleptic malignant syndrome (characterized by elevated temperature, muscular rigidity, altered consciousness, and autonomic instability), with no other obvious etiology, has been reported in association with rapid dose reduction, withdrawal of, or changes in drugs that increase central dopaminergic tone. Abrupt discontinuation of OSMOLEX ER may cause an increase in the symptoms of Parkinson’s disease or cause delirium, agitation, delusions, hallucinations, paranoid reaction, stupor, anxiety, depression, or slurred speech.  It is recommended to avoid sudden discontinuation of OSMOLEX ER [see Dosage and Administration ( 2.4 )]. Patients can experience intense urges to gamble, increased sexual urges, intense urges to spend money, binge eating, and/or other intense urges, and the inability to control these urges while taking one or more of the medications that increase central dopaminergic tone, including OSMOLEX ER. In some cases, these urges were reported to have stopped when the dose was reduced or the medication was stopped. Because patients may not recognize these behaviors as abnormal, it is important for prescribers to specifically ask patients or their caregivers about the development of new or increased gambling urges, sexual urges, uncontrolled spending, or other urges while being treated with OSMOLEX ER. Consider dose reduction or stopping the medication if a patient develops such urges while taking OSMOLEX ER.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
The mechanism by which amantadine exerts efficacy in the treatment of Parkinson’s disease and drug-induced extrapyramidal reactions is unknown. Amantadine is a weak uncompetitive antagonist of the NMDA receptor; however, it exhibits anticholinergic-like side effects such as dry mouth, urinary retention, and constipation in humans. Amantadine may have direct and indirect effects on dopamine neurons; it exerts dopaminergic-like side effects such as hallucinations and dizziness in humans.  The effect of amantadine on QT prolongation was not studied in a dedicated thorough QT study. Alcohol consumption may increase the potential for CNS effects, such as somnolence, dizziness, confusion, lightheadedness, and orthostatic hypotension [see Drug Interactions ( 7.4 )] . OSMOLEX ER tablet consists of an immediate-release outer layer and an extended-release core. The pharmacokinetics of amantadine from OSMOLEX ER is dose proportional across the dose range of 129 mg to 322 mg. Absorption Following oral administration of OSMOLEX ER, peak concentration of amantadine was observed in a median time of 7.5 hours (range 5.5 to 12 hours). After a single oral administration of the 129 mg dose, the mean (CV%) Cmax and AUC were 328 ng/ml (18%) and 8263 ng . h/ml (18%) respectively. Cmax and AUC with other dose levels of OSMOLEX ER increase proportionally.  Effect of Food Food does not affect the rate or the extent of absorption of OSMOLEX ER. Distribution Amantadine is 67% bound to plasma proteins over a concentration range of 0.1 to 2.0 μg/mL. The volume of distribution after intravenous administration is 3-8 L/kg, suggesting potential extravascular distribution. Elimination Amantadine is mainly eliminated renally, and approximately 85% of the administered dose is excreted unchanged in urine. After oral administration of a single 129 mg OSMOLEX ER tablet, the apparent oral clearance was approximately11 L/h. The half-life was approximately 16 hours. Metabolism Metabolism accounts for only 5-15% of the total clearance for amantadine. Eight metabolites of amantadine have been identified in human urine. One metabolite, an N-acetylated compound, was quantified in human urine and accounted for 0-15% of the administered dose in multiple studies. The contribution of this metabolite to efficacy or toxicity is not known. Excretion Amantadine is primarily excreted by glomerular filtration and tubular secretion. The pH of the urine has been reported to influence the excretion rate of amantadine [see Drug Interactions ( 7.2 )]. Specific Populations Geriatric Patients Amantadine is known to be substantially excreted by the kidney, and the risk of adverse reactions to this drug may be greater in patients with impaired renal function [see Use in Specific Populations ( 8.5 )] . Patients with  Renal Impairment The renal clearance of amantadine is significantly lower in patients with moderate or severe renal impairment, compared to healthy subjects with normal renal function. Therefore, a reduction in dosing frequency is required for patients with moderate or severe renal impairment [see Dosage and Administration ( 2.3 )] . OSMOLEX ER is contraindicated in patients with end-stage renal disease (i.e., creatinine clearance below 15 mL/min/1.73 m 2 ) [see Contraindications ( 4 )]. Male and Female Patients In a study of young healthy subjects (n=20), mean renal clearance of amantadine, normalized for body mass index, was 1.5 fold higher in males compared to females. No dose adjustment by gender is warranted. Drug Interaction Studies Coadministration of quinine or quinidine with amantadine was shown to reduce the renal clearance of amantadine by about 30%.  The clinical significance of this effect is unknown.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="7702" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>OSMOLEX ER is contraindicated in patients with end-stage renal disease (i.e., creatinine clearance below 15 mL/min/1.73 m2).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7703" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>OSMOLEX ER is contraindicated in patients with end-stage renal disease (4)</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7704" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The initial dosage is 129 mg orally once daily in the morning (2.1) The dosage may be increased in weekly intervals to a maximum daily dose of 322 mg once daily in the morning (2.1) Swallow tablets whole; do not chew, crush, or divide (2.2) Dosing frequency reduction and monitoring required for renal impairment (2.3, 8.6) The recommended initial dosage of OSMOLEX ER is 129 mg administered orally once daily in the morning.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7705" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The dosage may be increased in weekly intervals to a maximum daily dose of 322 mg (administered as a 129 mg and 193 mg tablet), taken in the morning.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7706" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>OSMOLEX ER is not interchangeable with other amantadine immediate- or extended-release products.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7707" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For patients unable to tolerate more than 100 mg per day of immediate-release amantadine, there is no equivalent dose or dosing regimen of OSMOLEX ER.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7708" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>OSMOLEX ER can be administered without regard to food.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7709" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>There are no modifications for the recommended initial and maximum dosage in patients with renal impairment; however, modifications are recommended for the titration interval and frequency of dosing in patients with moderate and severe renal impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7710" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Table 1: Recommended Titration and Frequency of OSMOLEX ER Dosing in Patients with Renal Impairment Renal Function/Estimated GFR (mL/min/1.73 m2)* Minimum Titration Interval Frequency of Dosing Regimen Mild renal impairment (60 to 89) Increase every week One dose every 24 hours Moderate renal impairment (30 to 59) Increase every 3 weeks One dose every 48 hours Severe renal impairment (15 to 29) Increase every 4 weeks One dose every 96 hours End-Stage Renal Disease (below 15) Contraindicated * estimated by Modification of Diet in Renal Disease (MDRD) method Monitor patients with renal impairment for change in renal function, especially in those with severe renal impairment receiving the maximum daily dosage of 322 mg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7711" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>OSMOLEX ER should not be discontinued abruptly.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7712" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The dose should be reduced gradually from higher doses to 129 mg daily for 1 to 2 weeks before discontinuing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7713" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If a dose of OSMOLEX ER is missed, the next dose should be taken as scheduled.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7714" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Anticholinergic Drugs: Increased risk of anticholinergic effects; the dose of anticholinergic drugs or OSMOLEX ER may require reduction (7.1) Drugs Affecting Urinary pH: Excretion increases with acidic urine; possible accumulation with urine change towards alkaline (7.2) Live Attenuated Influenza Vaccines: Not recommended during use (7.3) Alcohol: Concomitant use is not recommended; increased potential for CNS effects (7.4) Products with anticholinergic properties may potentiate the anticholinergic-like side effects of amantadine.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M1" type="Trigger" span="23 9;57 7" str="increased | effects"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="341 7" str="Alcohol" code="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M"/>
<Mention id="M3" type="SpecificInteraction" span="410 11" str="CNS effects" code="246557006: Central nervous system symptom (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M4" type="Trigger" span="23 14" str="Increased risk "/>
<Mention id="M5" type="Trigger" span="70 4;126 9" str=" dose | reduction"/>
<Mention id="M6" type="Precipitant" span="0 21" str="anticholinergic drugs" code="N0000175574"/>
<Mention id="M7" type="SpecificInteraction" span="41 23" str="anticholinergic effects" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M8" type="Trigger" span="473 10" str="potentiate"/>
<Mention id="M9" type="Precipitant" span="428 40" str="Products with anticholinergic properties" code="N0000175574"/>
<Mention id="M10" type="SpecificInteraction" span="488 33" str="anticholinergic-like side effects" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M11" type="Trigger" span="218 12" str="accumulation"/>
<Mention id="M14" type="Precipitant" span="142 26" str="Drugs Affecting Urinary pH" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M13" type="Trigger" span="170 19" str="Excretion increases"/>
<Mention id="M15" type="Trigger" span="308 15" str="Not recommended"/>
<Mention id="M16" type="Precipitant" span="272 34" str="Live Attenuated Influenza Vaccines" code="N0000184007"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M1" precipitant="M2" effect="M3" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M4;M5" precipitant="M6" effect="M7" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M8" precipitant="M9" effect="M10" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M11" precipitant="M14" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M13" precipitant="M14" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M15" precipitant="M16"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7715" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The dose of anticholinergic drugs or of OSMOLEX ER should be reduced if atropine-like effects appear when these drugs are used concurrently.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M17" type="Trigger" span="4 4;61 7" str="dose | reduced "/>
<Mention id="M18" type="Trigger" span="69 2;94 6" str=" if | appear"/>
<Mention id="M19" type="Precipitant" span="12 21" str="anticholinergic drugs" code="N0000175574"/>
<Mention id="M20" type="SpecificInteraction" span="72 21" str="atropine-like effects" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M17;M18" precipitant="M19" effect="M20" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7716" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The pH of the urine has been reported to influence the excretion rate of amantadine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7717" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Urine pH is altered by diet, drugs (e.g., carbonic anhydrase inhibitors, sodium bicarbonate), and clinical state of the patient (e.g., renal tubular acidosis or severe infections of the urinary tract).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M24" type="Trigger" span="12 7" str="altered"/>
<Mention id="M22" type="Precipitant" span="42 29" str="carbonic anhydrase inhibitors" code="N0000000235"/>
<Mention id="M26" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 19" str="Urine pH is altered" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M25" type="Precipitant" span="73 18" str="sodium bicarbonate" code="8MDF5V39QO | N0000005741"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M24" precipitant="M22" effect="M26" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M24" precipitant="M25" effect="M26" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7718" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Since the excretion rate of amantadine increases rapidly when the urine is acidic, the administration of urine acidifying drugs may increase the elimination of the drug from the body.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M27" type="Trigger" span="10 9;39 9" str="excretion | increases "/>
<Mention id="M28" type="Trigger" span="132 24" str=" increase the elimination"/>
<Mention id="M29" type="Precipitant" span="105 22" str="urine acidifying drugs" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M27;M28" precipitant="M29" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7719" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Alterations of urine pH towards the alkaline condition may lead to an accumulation of the drug with a possible increase in adverse reactions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7720" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor for efficacy or adverse reactions under conditions that alter the urine pH to more acidic or alkaline, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7721" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Because of its antiviral properties, amantadine may interfere with the efficacy of live attenuated influenza vaccines.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M30" type="Trigger" span="52 27" str="interfere with the efficacy"/>
<Mention id="M31" type="Precipitant" span="83 34" str="live attenuated influenza vaccines" code="N0000184007"/>
<Mention id="M32" type="SpecificInteraction" span="52 65" str="interfere with the efficacy of live attenuated influenza vaccines" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M30" precipitant="M31" effect="M32" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7722" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Therefore, live vaccines are not recommended during treatment with OSMOLEX ER.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M33" type="Trigger" span="29 15" str="not recommended"/>
<Mention id="M34" type="Precipitant" span="11 13" str="live vaccines" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M33" precipitant="M34"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7723" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Inactivated influenza vaccines may be used, as appropriate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7724" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant use with alcohol is not recommended, as it may increase the potential for central nervous system effects such as somnolence, dizziness, confusion, lightheadedness, and orthostatic hypotension.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M50" type="Trigger" span="59 22" str="increase the potential"/>
<Mention id="M51" type="Precipitant" span="21 7" str="alcohol" code="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M"/>
<Mention id="M37" type="SpecificInteraction" span="86 29" str="central nervous system effect" code="246557006: Central nervous system symptom (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M40" type="SpecificInteraction" span="148 9" str="confusion" code="40917007: Clouded consciousness (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M43" type="SpecificInteraction" span="137 9" str="dizziness" code="404640003: Dizziness (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M46" type="SpecificInteraction" span="159 15" str="lightheadedness" code="386705008: Lightheadedness (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M49" type="SpecificInteraction" span="180 23" str="orthostatic hypotension" code="28651003: Orthostatic hypotension (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M52" type="SpecificInteraction" span="125 10" str="somnolence" code="271782001: Drowsy (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M50" precipitant="M51" effect="M37" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M50" precipitant="M51" effect="M40" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M50" precipitant="M51" effect="M43" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M50" precipitant="M51" effect="M46" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M50" precipitant="M51" effect="M49" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M50" precipitant="M51" effect="M52" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7725" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Falling Asleep During Activities of Daily Living and Somnolence: Advise patients prior to treatment; ordinarily discontinue if occurs (5.1) Suicidality and Depression: Monitor patients for depressed mood, depression, or suicidal ideation or behavior (5.2) Hallucinations/Psychotic Behavior: Patients with major psychotic disorder should ordinarily not be treated with OSMOLEX ER; observe patients for the occurrence of hallucinations throughout treatment, especially at initiation and after dose increases (5.3) Dizziness and Orthostatic Hypotension: Monitor patients for dizziness and orthostatic hypotension, especially after starting OSMOLEX ER or increasing the dose (5.4) Withdrawal-Emergent Hyperpyrexia and Confusion: Avoid sudden discontinuation (5.5) Impulse Control/Compulsive Behaviors: Ask patients about increased gambling urges, sexual urges, uncontrolled spending or other urges; consider dose reduction or discontinuation if occurs (5.6) Patients treated with amantadine have reported falling asleep while engaged in activities of daily living, including the operation of motor vehicles, which sometimes has resulted in accidents.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7726" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients may not perceive warning signs, such as excessive drowsiness, or they may report feeling alert immediately prior to the event.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7727" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Before initiating treatment with OSMOLEX ER, advise patients of the potential to develop drowsiness and specifically ask about factors that may increase the risk for somnolence with OSMOLEX ER, such as concomitant sedating medications, alcohol, or the presence of a sleep disorder.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M56" type="Trigger" span="144 17" str="increase the risk"/>
<Mention id="M54" type="Precipitant" span="236 7" str="alcohol" code="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M"/>
<Mention id="M58" type="SpecificInteraction" span="166 10" str="somnolence" code="271782001: Drowsy (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M57" type="Precipitant" span="214 20" str="sedating medications" code="N0000193842"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M56" precipitant="M54" effect="M58" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M56" precipitant="M57" effect="M58" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7728" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If a patient develops daytime sleepiness or episodes of falling asleep during activities that require full attention (e.g., driving a motor vehicle, conversations, eating), OSMOLEX ER should ordinarily be discontinued.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7729" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If a decision is made to continue OSMOLEX ER, advise patients not to drive and to avoid other potentially dangerous activities that might result in harm if they become somnolent.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7730" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There is insufficient information to establish that dose reduction will eliminate episodes of falling asleep while engaged in activities of daily living or daytime somnolence.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7731" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Suicide, suicide attempts, and suicidal ideation have been reported in patients with and without prior history of psychiatric illness while treated with amantadine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7732" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Amantadine can exacerbate psychiatric symptoms in patients with a history of psychiatric disorders or substance abuse.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7733" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor patients for depression, including suicidal ideation or behavior.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7734" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Prescribers should consider whether the benefits outweigh the risks of treatment with OSMOLEX ER in patients with a history of suicidality or depression.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7735" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients with a major psychotic disorder should ordinarily not be treated with OSMOLEX ER because of the risk of exacerbating psychosis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7736" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Treatment with amantadine or abrupt withdrawal can cause confusion, psychosis, personality changes, agitation, aggressive behavior, hallucinations, paranoia, other psychotic or paranoia reactions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7737" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor patients for hallucinations throughout treatment but especially after initiation and after the dose of OSMOLEX ER is increased or decreased.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7738" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Dizziness and orthostatic hypotension can occur with OSMOLEX ER.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7739" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients should be monitored for these adverse reactions, especially after starting OSMOLEX ER or increasing the dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7740" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant use of alcohol when using OSMOLEX ER is not recommended.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M59" type="Trigger" span="52 15" str="not recommended"/>
<Mention id="M60" type="Precipitant" span="19 7" str="alcohol" code="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M59" precipitant="M60"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7741" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>A symptom complex resembling neuroleptic malignant syndrome (characterized by elevated temperature, muscular rigidity, altered consciousness, and autonomic instability), with no other obvious etiology, has been reported in association with rapid dose reduction, withdrawal of, or changes in drugs that increase central dopaminergic tone.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7742" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Abrupt discontinuation of OSMOLEX ER may cause an increase in the symptoms of Parkinson’s disease or cause delirium, agitation, delusions, hallucinations, paranoid reaction, stupor, anxiety, depression, or slurred speech.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7743" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>It is recommended to avoid sudden discontinuation of OSMOLEX ER.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7744" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients can experience intense urges to gamble, increased sexual urges, intense urges to spend money, binge eating, and/or other intense urges, and the inability to control these urges while taking one or more of the medications that increase central dopaminergic tone, including OSMOLEX ER.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7745" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In some cases, these urges were reported to have stopped when the dose was reduced or the medication was stopped.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7746" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Because patients may not recognize these behaviors as abnormal, it is important for prescribers to specifically ask patients or their caregivers about the development of new or increased gambling urges, sexual urges, uncontrolled spending, or other urges while being treated with OSMOLEX ER.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7747" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Consider dose reduction or stopping the medication if a patient develops such urges while taking OSMOLEX ER.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7748" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mechanism by which amantadine exerts efficacy in the treatment of Parkinson’s disease and drug-induced extrapyramidal reactions is unknown.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7749" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Amantadine is a weak uncompetitive antagonist of the NMDA receptor; however, it exhibits anticholinergic-like side effects such as dry mouth, urinary retention, and constipation in humans.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7750" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Amantadine may have direct and indirect effects on dopamine neurons; it exerts dopaminergic-like side effects such as hallucinations and dizziness in humans.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7751" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The effect of amantadine on QT prolongation was not studied in a dedicated thorough QT study.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7752" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Alcohol consumption may increase the potential for CNS effects, such as somnolence, dizziness, confusion, lightheadedness, and orthostatic hypotension.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M76" type="Trigger" span="24 22" str="increase the potential"/>
<Mention id="M77" type="Precipitant" span="0 7" str="Alcohol" code="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M"/>
<Mention id="M63" type="SpecificInteraction" span="51 11" str="CNS effects" code="246557006: Central nervous system symptom (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M66" type="SpecificInteraction" span="95 9" str="confusion" code="40917007: Clouded consciousness (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M69" type="SpecificInteraction" span="84 9" str="dizziness" code="404640003: Dizziness (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M72" type="SpecificInteraction" span="106 15" str="lightheadedness" code="386705008: Lightheadedness (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M75" type="SpecificInteraction" span="127 23" str="orthostatic hypotension" code="28651003: Orthostatic hypotension (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M78" type="SpecificInteraction" span="72 10" str="somnolence" code="271782001: Drowsy (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M76" precipitant="M77" effect="M63" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M76" precipitant="M77" effect="M66" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M76" precipitant="M77" effect="M69" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M76" precipitant="M77" effect="M72" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M76" precipitant="M77" effect="M75" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M76" precipitant="M77" effect="M78" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7753" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>OSMOLEX ER tablet consists of an immediate-release outer layer and an extended-release core.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7754" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacokinetics of amantadine from OSMOLEX ER is dose proportional across the dose range of 129 mg to 322 mg. Absorption Following oral administration of OSMOLEX ER, peak concentration of amantadine was observed in a median time of 7.5 hours (range 5.5 to 12 hours).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7755" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>After a single oral administration of the 129 mg dose, the mean (CV%) Cmax and AUC were 328 ng/ml (18%) and 8263 ng.h/ml (18%) respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7756" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Cmax and AUC with other dose levels of OSMOLEX ER increase proportionally.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7757" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Effect of Food Food does not affect the rate or the extent of absorption of OSMOLEX ER.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7758" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Distribution Amantadine is 67% bound to plasma proteins over a concentration range of 0.1 to 2.0 μg/mL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7759" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The volume of distribution after intravenous administration is 3-8 L/kg, suggesting potential extravascular distribution.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7760" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Elimination Amantadine is mainly eliminated renally, and approximately 85% of the administered dose is excreted unchanged in urine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7761" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>After oral administration of a single 129 mg OSMOLEX ER tablet, the apparent oral clearance was approximately11 L/h.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7762" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The half-life was approximately 16 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7763" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Metabolism Metabolism accounts for only 5-15% of the total clearance for amantadine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7764" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Eight metabolites of amantadine have been identified in human urine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7765" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>One metabolite, an N-acetylated compound, was quantified in human urine and accounted for 0-15% of the administered dose in multiple studies.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7766" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The contribution of this metabolite to efficacy or toxicity is not known.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7767" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Excretion Amantadine is primarily excreted by glomerular filtration and tubular secretion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7768" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Specific Populations Geriatric Patients Amantadine is known to be substantially excreted by the kidney, and the risk of adverse reactions to this drug may be greater in patients with impaired renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7769" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Patients with Renal Impairment The renal clearance of amantadine is significantly lower in patients with moderate or severe renal impairment, compared to healthy subjects with normal renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7770" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Therefore, a reduction in dosing frequency is required for patients with moderate or severe renal impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7771" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Male and Female Patients In a study of young healthy subjects (n=20), mean renal clearance of amantadine, normalized for body mass index, was 1.5 fold higher in males compared to females.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7772" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No dose adjustment by gender is warranted.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7773" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Drug Interaction Studies Coadministration of quinine or quinidine with amantadine was shown to reduce the renal clearance of amantadine by about 30%.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M81" type="Trigger" span="95 26" str="reduce the renal clearance"/>
<Mention id="M80" type="Precipitant" span="56 9" str="quinidine" code="N0000007728 | ITX08688JL"/>
<Mention id="M82" type="Precipitant" span="45 7" str="quinine" code="A7V27PHC7A"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M81" precipitant="M80" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I29" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M81" precipitant="M82" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7774" LabelDrug="Osmolex ER" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The clinical significance of this effect is unknown.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="alcohol" precipitantCode="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M" effect="246557006: Central nervous system symptom (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="alcohol" precipitantCode="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M" effect="271782001: Drowsy (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="alcohol" precipitantCode="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M" effect="28651003: Orthostatic hypotension (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="alcohol" precipitantCode="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M" effect="386705008: Lightheadedness (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="alcohol" precipitantCode="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M" effect="404640003: Dizziness (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="alcohol" precipitantCode="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M" effect="40917007: Clouded consciousness (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="alcohol" precipitantCode="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="anticholinergic drugs" precipitantCode="N0000175574" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="products with anticholinergic properties" precipitantCode="N0000175574" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="drugs affecting urinary ph" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="drugs affecting urinary ph" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="live attenuated influenza vaccines" precipitantCode="N0000184007" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="live attenuated influenza vaccines" precipitantCode="N0000184007"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="carbonic anhydrase inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000000235" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sodium bicarbonate" precipitantCode="8MDF5V39QO | N0000005741" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="urine acidifying drugs" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="live vaccines" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sedating medications" precipitantCode="N0000193842" effect="271782001: Drowsy (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="quinidine" precipitantCode="N0000007728 | ITX08688JL" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="quinine" precipitantCode="A7V27PHC7A" effect="C54355"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>