<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Thalomid" setid="2eda833b-1357-4ed4-a093-194524fcb061">
<Text><Section name="BOXED WARNING SECTION" id="34066-1">
WARNING: EMBRYO-FETAL TOXICITY AND VENOUS THROMBOEMBOLISM EMBRYO-FETAL TOXICITY If thalidomide is taken during pregnancy, it can cause severe birth defects or embryo-fetal death. Thalidomide should never be used by females who are pregnant or who could become pregnant while taking the drug. Even a single dose [1 capsule (regardless of strength)] taken by a pregnant woman during her pregnancy can cause severe birth defects. Because of this toxicity and in an effort to make the chance of embryo-fetal exposure to THALOMID ® (thalidomide) as negligible as possible, THALOMID ® (thalidomide) is approved for marketing only through a special restricted distribution program: THALOMID REMS ® program, approved by the Food and Drug Administration. You can get the information about THALOMID and the THALOMID REMS program on the Internet at www.celgeneriskmanagement.com or by calling the manufacturer's toll-free number 1-888-423-5436. VENOUS THROMBOEMBOLISM The use of THALOMID ® (thalidomide) in multiple myeloma results in an increased risk of venous thromboembolism, such as deep venous thrombosis and pulmonary embolism.  This risk increases significantly when thalidomide is used in combination with standard chemotherapeutic agents including dexamethasone. In one controlled trial, the rate of venous thromboembolism was 22.5% in patients receiving thalidomide in combination with dexamethasone compared to 4.9% in patients receiving dexamethasone alone (p = 0.002). Patients and physicians are advised to be observant for the signs and symptoms of thromboembolism. Instruct patients to seek medical care if they develop symptoms such as shortness of breath, chest pain, or arm or leg swelling. Consider thromboprophylaxis based on an assessment of individual patients' underlying risk factors. WARNING: EMBRYO-FETAL TOXICITY AND VENOUS THROMBOEMBOLISM See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning. EMBRYO-FETAL TOXICITY If thalidomide is taken during pregnancy, it can cause severe birth defects or embryo-fetal death. Thalidomide should never be used by females who are pregnant or who could be pregnant while taking the drug. Even a single dose [1 capsule (regardless of strength)] taken by a pregnant woman during her pregnancy can cause severe birth defects. Pregnancy must be excluded before start of treatment. Prevent pregnancy thereafter by the use of two reliable methods of contraception. ( 5.1 , 8.3 ) THALOMID ® (thalidomide) is only available through a restricted distribution program, the THALOMID REMS ® program ( 5.2 ). VENOUS THROMBOEMBOLISM Significant increased risk of deep vein thrombosis (DVT) and pulmonary embolism (PE) in patients with multiple myeloma receiving THALOMID ® (thalidomide) with dexamethasone ( 5.3 ).</Section>
<Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
Pregnancy ( Boxed Warning , 4.1 , 5.1 , 5.2 , 8.1 , 17 ) Demonstrated hypersensitivity to the drug or its components ( 4.2 , 5.15 , 6.2 ) [see Boxed Warning ] THALOMID can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant female [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1) and Use in Specific Populations (8.1) ] . Thalidomide is contraindicated in females who are pregnant. Thalidomide is a powerful human teratogen, inducing a high frequency of severe and life-threatening birth defects, even after a single dose [see Boxed Warning ] . Mortality at or shortly after birth has been reported in about 40% of infants. If this drug is used during pregnancy, or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking this drug, the patient should be apprised of the potential risk to a fetus. If pregnancy occurs during thalidomide treatment, the drug should be discontinued immediately. THALOMID is contraindicated in patients who have demonstrated hypersensitivity to the drug or its components [see Warnings and Precautions (5.16) ] .</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
MM: 200 mg orally once daily. The recommended dose of dexamethasone is 40 mg/day on days 1-4, 9-12, and 17-20 every 28 days. ( 2.1 ) ENL: 100 to 300 mg/day for an episode of cutaneous ENL. Up to 400 mg/day for severe cutaneous ENL. ( 2.2 ) THALOMID (thalidomide) must only be administered in compliance with all of the terms outlined in the THALOMID REMS program. THALOMID (thalidomide) may only be prescribed by prescribers certified with the THALOMID REMS program and may only be dispensed by pharmacists certified with the THALOMID REMS program. Drug prescribing to females of reproductive potential is contingent upon initial and continued negative results of pregnancy testing [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1 and 5.2) ] . Consider dose reduction, delay, or discontinuation in patients who develop National Cancer Institute Common Toxicity Criteria (NCI CTC) Grade 3 or 4 adverse reactions and/or based on clinical judgment. THALOMID is administered in combination with dexamethasone in 28-day treatment cycles. The dose of THALOMID is 200 mg administered orally once daily with water, preferably at bedtime and at least 1 hour after the evening meal. The dose of dexamethasone is 40 mg daily administered orally on days 1-4, 9-12, and 17-20 every 28 days. Patients who develop adverse reactions such as constipation, somnolence, or peripheral neuropathy may benefit by either temporarily discontinuing the drug or continuing at a lower dose. With the abatement of these adverse reactions, the drug may be started at a lower dose or at the previous dose based on clinical judgment. For an episode of cutaneous ENL, THALOMID dosing should be initiated at 100 to 300 mg/day, administered once daily with water, preferably at bedtime and at least 1 hour after the evening meal. Patients weighing less than 50 kilograms should be started at the low end of the dose range. In patients with a severe cutaneous ENL reaction, or in those who have previously required higher doses to control the reaction, THALOMID dosing may be initiated at higher doses up to 400 mg/day once daily at bedtime or in divided doses with water, at least 1 hour after meals. In patients with moderate to severe neuritis associated with a severe ENL reaction, corticosteroids may be started concomitantly with THALOMID. Steroid usage can be tapered and discontinued when the neuritis has ameliorated. Dosing with THALOMID should usually continue until signs and symptoms of active reaction have subsided, usually a period of at least 2 weeks. Patients may then be tapered off medication in 50 mg decrements every 2 to 4 weeks. Patients who have a documented history of requiring prolonged maintenance treatment to prevent the recurrence of cutaneous ENL or who flare during tapering should be maintained on the minimum dose necessary to control the reaction. Tapering off medication should be attempted every 3 to 6 months, in decrements of 50 mg every 2 to 4 weeks.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
Use caution if other drugs which have sedative and hypnotic properties, slow cardiac conduction and/or cause peripheral neuropathy must be used. ( 7.1 , 7.2 , 7.3 ) It is not known whether concomitant use of hormonal contraceptives further increases the risk of thromboembolism with THALOMID. ( 5.14 , 7.4 ) Patients taking concomitant therapies such as erythropoietin stimulating agents or estrogen containing therapies may have an increased risk of thromboembolism. ( 7.7 ) The use of opioids, antihistamines, antipsychotics, anti-anxiety agents, or other CNS depressants concomitantly with THALOMID may cause an additive sedative effect and should be avoided. The use of drugs which slow cardiac conduction concomitantly with THALOMID may cause an additive bradycardic effect and should be used with caution.  Cardiovascular medications which may cause bradycardia include calcium channel blockers, beta blockers, alpha/beta-adrenergic blockers, and digoxin.  Non-cardiac drugs that may cause bradycardia include H2 blockers (e.g., famotidine, cimetidine), lithium, tricyclic antidepressants and neuromuscular blockers (succinylcholine). In 16 healthy men, the pharmacokinetic profile of a single 0.5 mg digoxin dose was similar with and without the coadministration of thalidomide 200 mg/day at steady state levels. The single dose of digoxin had no effect on the pharmacokinetic profile of thalidomide.  The safety of long-term concomitant use of THALOMID and digoxin has not been evaluated. The use of drugs which cause peripheral neuropathy (e.g., bortezomib, amiodarone, cisplatin, docetaxel, paclitaxel, vincristine, disulfiram, phenytoin, metronidazole, alcohol) can cause an additive effect and should be used with caution. Hormonal contraceptives increase the risk of thromboembolism. It is not known whether concomitant use of hormonal contraceptives further increases the risk of thromboembolism with THALOMID. In 10 healthy women, the pharmacokinetic profiles of norethindrone and ethinyl estradiol following administration of a single dose containing 1.0 mg of norethindrone acetate and 75 mcg of ethinyl estradiol were studied. The results were similar with and without coadministration of thalidomide 200 mg/day to steady-state levels. In 13 healthy men, the pharmacokinetic profile and international normalized ratio (INR) of prothrombin time for warfarin, following a single oral dose of 25 mg, were similar with and without the coadministration of thalidomide 200 mg/day at steady-state levels. The single dose of warfarin had no effect on the pharmacokinetic profile of thalidomide. Concomitant use of HIV-protease inhibitors, griseofulvin, modafinil, penicillins, rifampin, rifabutin, phenytoin, carbamazepine, or certain herbal supplements such as St. John's Wort with hormonal contraceptive agents may reduce the effectiveness of the contraception up to one month after discontinuation of these concomitant therapies. Therefore, females requiring treatment with one or more of these drugs must use two OTHER effective or highly effective methods of contraception while taking thalidomide. Erythropoietic agents, or other agents that may increase the risk of thromboembolism, such as estrogen containing therapies, should be used with caution in multiple myeloma patients receiving thalidomide with dexamethasone [see Warnings and Precautions (5.3) ] .</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
Ischemic heart disease (including myocardial infarction) and stroke have been observed in patients treated with THALOMID in combination with dexamethasone. ( 5.3 ) Increased Mortality: Observed in patients with MM when pembrolizumab was added to dexamethasone and a thalidomide analogue. ( 5.4 ) Drowsiness and Somnolence: Instruct patients to avoid situations where drowsiness may be a problem and not to take other medications that may cause drowsiness. ( 5.5 ) Peripheral Neuropathy: Examine patients at monthly intervals for the first 3 months of thalidomide therapy and periodically thereafter for signs or symptoms of peripheral neuropathy. Consider electrophysiological testing, consisting of measurement of sensory nerve action potential (SNAP) amplitudes at baseline and thereafter every 6 months in an effort to detect asymptomatic neuropathy. ( 5.6 ) Dizziness and Orthostatic Hypotension: Advise patients to sit upright for a few minutes prior to standing up from a recumbent position. ( 5.7 ) Neutropenia: Patients may require dose interruption and/or dose reduction. ( 5.8 ) Thrombocytopenia: Patients may require dose interruption and/or dose reduction. ( 5.9 ) Increased HIV Viral Load: Measure viral load after the first and third months of treatment and every 3 months thereafter. ( 5.10 ) Bradycardia: Monitor patients for bradycardia and possible syncope. Dose reduction or discontinuation may be required. ( 5.11 ) Stevens-Johnson Syndrome and Toxic Epidermal Necrolysis: Do not resume THALOMID following discontinuation for these reactions. ( 5.12 ) Seizures: Monitor patients with a history of seizures or at risk for the development of seizures closely for clinical changes that could precipitate acute seizure activity. ( 5.13 ) Tumor Lysis Syndrome: Monitor patients at risk (e.g., those with high tumor burden prior to treatment) and take appropriate precautions. ( 5.14 ) Hypersensitivity: Monitor patients for potential hypersensitivity to the drug and its components. ( 5.16 ) Thalidomide is a powerful human teratogen that induces a high frequency of severe and life-threatening birth defects, even after a single dose. Mortality at or shortly after birth has been reported in about 40% of infants. When there is no satisfactory alternative treatment, females of reproductive potential may be treated with thalidomide provided adequate precautions are taken to avoid pregnancy. THALOMID ® (thalidomide) is only available through the THALOMID REMS program [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2) ] . Oral ingestion is the only type of maternal thalidomide exposure known to result in drug-associated birth defects. There are no specific data available regarding the reproductive risks of cutaneous absorption or inhalation of thalidomide; however, females of reproductive potential should avoid contact with THALOMID ® (thalidomide) Capsules.  THALOMID Capsules should be stored in blister packs until ingestion. If there is contact with non-intact thalidomide capsules or the powder contents, the exposed area should be washed with soap and water. If healthcare providers or other care givers are exposed to body fluids from patients receiving THALOMID (thalidomide) the exposed area should be washed with soap and water.  Appropriate precautions should be utilized, such as wearing gloves to prevent the potential cutaneous exposure to THALOMID. Females of Reproductive Potential Females of reproductive potential must avoid pregnancy for at least 4 weeks before beginning THALOMID therapy, during therapy, during dose interruptions and for at least 4 weeks after completing therapy. Females must commit either to abstain continuously from heterosexual sexual intercourse or to use two methods of reliable birth control, beginning 4 weeks prior to initiating treatment with THALOMID, during therapy, during dose interruptions and continuing for 4 weeks following discontinuation of THALOMID therapy. Two negative pregnancy tests must be obtained prior to initiating therapy. The first test should be performed within 10-14 days and the second test within 24 hours prior to prescribing THALOMID therapy and then weekly during the first month, then monthly thereafter in females with regular menstrual cycles or every 2 weeks in females with irregular menstrual cycles [see Use in Specific Populations (8.3) ] . Males Thalidomide is present in the semen of patients receiving the drug. Therefore, males must always use a latex or synthetic condom during any sexual contact with females of reproductive potential while taking THALOMID and for up to 4 weeks after discontinuing THALOMID, even if they have undergone a successful vasectomy.   Male patients taking THALOMID must not donate sperm [see Use in Specific Populations (8.3) ] . Blood Donation Patients must not donate blood during treatment with THALOMID and for 4 weeks following discontinuation of the drug because the blood might be given to a pregnant female patient whose fetus must not be exposed to THALOMID. Because of the embryo-fetal risk [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1) ] , THALOMID is available only through a restricted program under a Risk Evaluation and Mitigation Strategy (REMS), the THALOMID REMS program. Required components of the THALOMID REMS program include the following: Prescribers must be certified with the THALOMID REMS program by enrolling and complying with the REMS requirements. Patients must sign a Patient-Physician Agreement Form and comply with the REMS requirements. In particular, female patients of reproductive potential who are not pregnant must comply with the pregnancy testing and contraception requirements [see Use in Specific Populations (8.3) ] and males must comply with contraception requirements [see Use in Specific Populations (8.3) ] . Pharmacies must be certified with the THALOMID REMS program, must only dispense to patients who are authorized to receive THALOMID and comply with REMS requirements. Further information about the THALOMID REMS program is available at www.celgeneriskmanagement.com or by telephone at 1-888-423-5436. The use of THALOMID in patients with MM results in an increased risk of venous thromboembolism, such as deep venous thrombosis and pulmonary embolism. This risk increases significantly when thalidomide is used in combination with standard chemotherapeutic agents including dexamethasone. In one controlled trial, the rate of venous thromboembolism was 22.5% in patients receiving thalidomide in combination with dexamethasone compared to 4.9% in patients receiving dexamethasone alone (p = 0.002). Ischemic heart disease (11.1%), including myocardial infarction (1.3%), and stroke (cerebrovascular accident, 2.6%) have also occurred in patients with previously untreated MM treated with THALOMID and dexamethasone compared to placebo and dexamethasone (4.7%, 1.7%, and 0.9%, respectively) in one clinical trial [see Adverse Reactions (6.1) ] . Consider thromboprophylaxis based on an assessment of individual patients' underlying risk factors. Patients and physicians should be observant for the signs and symptoms of thromboembolism. Advise patients to seek immediate medical care if they develop symptoms such as shortness of breath, chest pain, or arm or leg swelling [see Boxed Warning ] . Agents that also may increase the risk of thromboembolism should be used with caution in patients receiving THALOMID [see Drug Interactions (7.7) ] . In two randomized clinical trials in patients with MM, the addition of pembrolizumab to a thalidomide analogue plus dexamethasone, a use for which no PD-1 or PD-L1 blocking antibody is indicated, resulted in increased mortality. Treatment of patients with MM with a PD-1 or PD-L1 blocking antibody in combination with a thalidomide analogue plus dexamethasone is not recommended outside of controlled clinical trials. Thalidomide frequently causes drowsiness and somnolence. Patients should be instructed to avoid situations where drowsiness may be a problem and not to take other medications that may cause drowsiness without adequate medical advice [see Drug Interactions (7.1) ]. Advise patients as to the possible impairment of mental and/or physical abilities required for the performance of hazardous tasks, such as driving a car or operating other complex or dangerous machinery. Dose reductions may be required. Thalidomide is known to cause nerve damage that may be permanent. Peripheral neuropathy is a common (≥10%) and potentially severe adverse reaction of treatment with thalidomide that may be irreversible. Peripheral neuropathy generally occurs following chronic use over a period of months; however, peripheral neuropathy following relatively short-term use has been reported. The correlation with cumulative dose is unclear. Symptoms may occur some time after thalidomide treatment has been stopped and may resolve slowly or not at all. Few reports of neuropathy have arisen in the treatment of ENL despite long-term thalidomide treatment. However, the inability clinically to differentiate thalidomide neuropathy from the neuropathy often seen in Hansen's disease makes it difficult to determine accurately the incidence of thalidomide-related neuropathy in ENL patients treated with thalidomide. Patients should be examined at monthly intervals for the first 3 months of thalidomide therapy to enable the clinician to detect early signs of neuropathy, which include numbness, tingling or pain in the hands and feet. Patients should be evaluated periodically thereafter during treatment. Patients should be regularly counseled, questioned, and evaluated for signs or symptoms of peripheral neuropathy. Consideration should be given to electrophysiological testing, consisting of measurement of sensory nerve action potential (SNAP) amplitudes at baseline and thereafter every 6 months in an effort to detect asymptomatic neuropathy. If symptoms of drug-induced neuropathy develop, thalidomide should be discontinued immediately to limit further damage, if clinically appropriate. Usually, treatment with thalidomide should only be reinitiated if the neuropathy returns to baseline status. Medications known to be associated with neuropathy should be used with caution in patients receiving thalidomide [see Drug Interactions (7.3) ] . Patients should also be advised that thalidomide may cause dizziness and orthostatic hypotension and that, therefore, they should sit upright for a few minutes prior to standing up from a recumbent position. Decreased white blood cell counts, including neutropenia, have been reported in association with the clinical use of thalidomide. Treatment should not be initiated with an absolute neutrophil count (ANC) of &amp;lt;750/mm 3 . White blood cell count and differential should be monitored on an ongoing basis, especially in patients who may be more prone to neutropenia, such as patients who are HIV-seropositive. If ANC decreases to below 750/mm 3 while on treatment, the patient's medication regimen should be re-evaluated and, if the neutropenia persists, consideration should be given to withholding thalidomide if clinically appropriate. Thrombocytopenia, including Grade 3 or 4 occurrences, has been reported in association with the clinical use of thalidomide. Monitor blood counts, including platelet counts. Dose reduction, delay, or discontinuation may be required. Monitor for signs and symptoms of bleeding including petechiae, epistaxis, and gastrointestinal bleeding, especially if concomitant medication may increase the risk of bleeding. In a randomized, placebo-controlled trial of thalidomide in an HIV-seropositive patient population, plasma HIV RNA levels were found to increase (median change = 0.42 log 10 copies HIV RNA/mL, p = 0.04 compared to placebo). A similar trend was observed in a second, unpublished study conducted in patients who were HIV-seropositive. The clinical significance of this increase is unknown. Both studies were conducted prior to availability of highly active antiretroviral therapy. Until the clinical significance of this finding is further understood, in HIV-seropositive patients, viral load should be measured after the first and third months of treatment and every 3 months thereafter. Bradycardia in association with thalidomide use has been reported. Cases of bradycardia have been reported, some required medical interventions. The clinical significance and underlying etiology of the bradycardia noted in some thalidomide-treated patients are presently unknown.  Monitor patients for bradycardia and syncope. Dose reduction or discontinuation may be required. Medications known to decrease heart rate should be used with caution in patients receiving thalidomide [see Drug Interactions (7.2) ] . Serious dermatologic reactions including Stevens-Johnson syndrome and toxic epidermal necrolysis, which may be fatal, have been reported. THALOMID should be discontinued if a skin rash occurs and only resumed following appropriate clinical evaluation. If the rash is exfoliative, purpuric, or bullous or if Stevens-Johnson syndrome or toxic epidermal necrolysis is suspected, use of THALOMID should not be resumed. Although not reported from pre-marketing controlled clinical trials, seizures, including grand mal convulsions, have been reported during post-approval use of THALOMID in clinical practice. Because these events are reported voluntarily from a population of unknown size, estimates of frequency cannot be made. Most patients had disorders that may have predisposed them to seizure activity, and it is not currently known whether thalidomide has any epileptogenic influence. During therapy with thalidomide, patients with a history of seizures or with other risk factors for the development of seizures should be monitored closely for clinical changes that could precipitate acute seizure activity. Monitor patients at risk of tumor lysis syndrome (e.g., patients with high tumor burden prior to treatment) and take appropriate precautions. Some contraceptive methods may pose a higher risk of adverse effects or may be medically contraindicated in some patients treated with THALOMID. Because some patients may develop sudden, severe neutropenia and/or thrombocytopenia, use of an intrauterine device (IUD) or implantable contraception in these patients may carry an increased risk for infection or bleeding either at insertion, removal or during use. Treatment with THALOMID, the presence of an underlying malignancy, and/or use of an estrogen-containing contraceptive can each increase the risk of thromboembolism. It is not known if these risks of thromboembolism are additive. However, they should be taken into consideration when choosing contraceptive methods. Hypersensitivity to THALOMID has been reported. Signs and symptoms have included the occurrence of erythematous macular rash, possibly associated with fever, tachycardia, and hypotension, and if severe, may necessitate interruption of therapy. If the reaction recurs when dosing is resumed, THALOMID should be discontinued.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
The mechanism of action of THALOMID is not fully understood. Cellular activities of thalidomide are mediated through its target cereblon, a component of a cullin ring E3 ubiquitin ligase enzyme complex. THALOMID possesses immunomodulatory, anti-inflammatory and antiangiogenic properties. Available data from in vitro studies and clinical trials suggest that the immunologic effects of this compound can vary substantially under different conditions, but may be related to suppression of excessive tumor necrosis factor-alpha (TNF-α) production and down-modulation of selected cell surface adhesion molecules involved in leukocyte migration. For example, administration of thalidomide has been reported to decrease circulating levels of TNF-α in patients with erythema nodosum leprosum (ENL); however, it has also been shown to increase plasma TNF-α levels in HIV-seropositive patients. Other anti-inflammatory and immunomodulatory properties of thalidomide may include suppression of macrophage involvement in prostaglandin synthesis, and modulation of interleukin-10 and interleukin-12 production by peripheral blood mononuclear cells. Thalidomide treatment of multiple myeloma patients is accompanied by an increase in the number of circulating natural killer cells, and an increase in plasma levels of interleukin-2 and interferon-gamma (T cell-derived cytokines associated with cytotoxic activity). Thalidomide was found to inhibit angiogenesis in a human umbilical artery explant model in vitro . The cellular processes of angiogenesis inhibited by thalidomide may include the proliferation of endothelial cells. Absorption Absorption of THALOMID is slow after oral administration. The maximum plasma concentrations are reached approximately 2-5 hours after administration. The absolute bioavailability of thalidomide from thalidomide capsules has not yet been characterized in human subjects due to its poor aqueous solubility. Based on the 14 C-radiolabel thalidomide study in human, greater than 90% of the total radioactivity is recovered in urine suggesting good oral absorption. While the extent of absorption (as measured by area under the curve [AUC]) is proportional to dose in healthy subjects, the observed peak concentration (C max ) increased in a less than proportional manner (see Table 5 below). This lack of C max dose proportionality, coupled with the observed increase in T max values, suggests that the poor solubility of thalidomide in aqueous media may be hindering the rate of absorption. Table 5: Pharmacokinetic Parameter Values for THALOMID Mean (%CV) Population/ Single Dose AUC 0-∞ mcg · hr/mL C max mcg/mL T max (hrs) Half‑life (hrs) Healthy Subjects (n=14) 50 mg 4.9 (16%) 0.62 (52%) 2.9 (66%) 5.52 (37%) 200 mg 18.9 (17%) 1.76 (30%) 3.5 (57%) 5.53 (25%) 400 mg 36.4 (26%) 2.82 (28%) 4.3 (37%) 7.29 (36%) Patients with Hansen’s Disease (n=6) 400 mg 46.4 (44.1%) 3.44 (52.6%) 5.7 (27%) 6.86 (17%) Coadministration of THALOMID ® (thalidomide) with a high-fat meal causes minor (&amp;lt;10%) changes in the observed AUC and C max values; however, it causes an increase in T max to approximately 6 hours. Distribution In human plasma, the geometric mean plasma protein binding was 55% and 66%, respectively, for (+)-(R)- and (-)-(S)-thalidomide. In a pharmacokinetic study of thalidomide in HIV-seropositive adult male subjects receiving thalidomide 100 mg/day, thalidomide was detectable in the semen. Metabolism In a 14 C-radiolabel ADME study in humans, unchanged drug is the predominant circulating component. Thalidomide is not a substrate of the cytochrome P450 system.   At therapeutic concentrations, thalidomide is not an inhibitor or inducer of human cytochrome P450 enzymes in vitro .  Pharmacokinetic drug-drug interactions with substrates, inhibitors or inducers of CYP450 are not anticipated. Elimination The mean elimination half-life of thalidomide in plasma following single oral doses between 50 mg and 400 mg was 5.5 to 7.3 hours. Following a single 400 mg oral dose of radiolabeled thalidomide, the total mean recovery was 93.6% of the administered dose by Day 8. The majority of the radioactive dose was excreted within 48 hours following dose administration. In humans, 14 C-thalidomide is primarily excreted in urine (91.9% of the radioactive dose) mainly as hydrolytic metabolites while fecal excretion is minor (&amp;lt;2% of the dose).  Unchanged thalidomide is not eliminated by the kidney to a notable degree (&amp;lt;3.5% of the dose). Effects of Weight There is a linear relationship between body weight and estimated thalidomide clearance.  In MM patients with body weight from 47-133 kg, thalidomide clearance ranged from approximately 6-12 L/h, representing an increase in thalidomide clearance of 0.605 L/h per 10 kg body weight increase. Effects of Age, Gender and Race Analysis of the data from pharmacokinetic studies in healthy volunteers and patients with Hansen's disease ranging in age from 20 to 69 years does not reveal any age-related changes. While a comparative trial of the effects of gender on thalidomide pharmacokinetics has not been conducted, examination of the data for thalidomide does not reveal any significant gender differences in pharmacokinetic parameter values. Pharmacokinetic differences due to race have not been studied. Pharmacokinetic Data in Special Populations HIV-seropositive Subjects: There is no apparent significant difference in measured pharmacokinetic parameter values between healthy human subjects and HIV-seropositive subjects following single-dose administration of THALOMID Capsules. Patients with Hansen's Disease: Analysis of data from a small study in Hansen's patients suggests that these patients, relative to healthy subjects, may have an increased bioavailability of THALOMID. The increase is reflected both in an increased area under the curve and in increased peak plasma levels. The clinical significance of this increase is unknown. Pediatric: No pharmacokinetic data are available in subjects below the age of 18 years.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="7927" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>WARNING: EMBRYO-FETAL TOXICITY AND VENOUS THROMBOEMBOLISM EMBRYO-FETAL TOXICITY If thalidomide is taken during pregnancy, it can cause severe birth defects or embryo-fetal death.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7928" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Thalidomide should never be used by females who are pregnant or who could become pregnant while taking the drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7929" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Even a single dose [1 capsule (regardless of strength)] taken by a pregnant woman during her pregnancy can cause severe birth defects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7930" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Because of this toxicity and in an effort to make the chance of embryo-fetal exposure to THALOMID® (thalidomide) as negligible as possible, THALOMID® (thalidomide) is approved for marketing only through a special restricted distribution program: THALOMID REMS® program, approved by the Food and Drug Administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7931" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>You can get the information about THALOMID and the THALOMID REMS program on the Internet at www.celgeneriskmanagement.com or by calling the manufacturer's toll-free number 1-888-423-5436.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7932" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>VENOUS THROMBOEMBOLISM The use of THALOMID® (thalidomide) in multiple myeloma results in an increased risk of venous thromboembolism, such as deep venous thrombosis and pulmonary embolism.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7933" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>This risk increases significantly when thalidomide is used in combination with standard chemotherapeutic agents including dexamethasone.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M3" type="Trigger" span="5 14" str="risk increases"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="122 13" str="dexamethasone" code="7S5I7G3JQL"/>
<Mention id="M4" type="Precipitant" span="79 32" str="standard chemotherapeutic agents" code="N0000178307"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M3" precipitant="M2"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M3" precipitant="M4"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7934" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>In one controlled trial, the rate of venous thromboembolism was 22.5% in patients receiving thalidomide in combination with dexamethasone compared to 4.9% in patients receiving dexamethasone alone (p = 0.002).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M7" type="SpecificInteraction" span="37 22" str="venous thromboembolism" code="429098002: Thromboembolism of vein (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M6" type="Precipitant" span="124 13" str="dexamethasone" code="7S5I7G3JQL"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M7" precipitant="M6" effect="M7" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7935" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Patients and physicians are advised to be observant for the signs and symptoms of thromboembolism.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7936" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Instruct patients to seek medical care if they develop symptoms such as shortness of breath, chest pain, or arm or leg swelling.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7937" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Consider thromboprophylaxis based on an assessment of individual patients' underlying risk factors.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7938" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>WARNING: EMBRYO-FETAL TOXICITY AND VENOUS THROMBOEMBOLISM See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7939" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>EMBRYO-FETAL TOXICITY If thalidomide is taken during pregnancy, it can cause severe birth defects or embryo-fetal death.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7940" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Thalidomide should never be used by females who are pregnant or who could be pregnant while taking the drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7941" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Pregnancy must be excluded before start of treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7942" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Prevent pregnancy thereafter by the use of two reliable methods of contraception.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7943" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>THALOMID® (thalidomide) is only available through a restricted distribution program, the THALOMID REMS® program (5.2).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7944" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>VENOUS THROMBOEMBOLISM Significant increased risk of deep vein thrombosis (DVT) and pulmonary embolism (PE) in patients with multiple myeloma receiving THALOMID® (thalidomide) with dexamethasone (5.3).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M20" type="Trigger" span="35 14" str="increased risk"/>
<Mention id="M21" type="Precipitant" span="181 13" str="dexamethasone" code="7S5I7G3JQL"/>
<Mention id="M10" type="SpecificInteraction" span="53 20" str="deep vein thrombosis" code="128053003: Deep venous thrombosis (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M13" type="SpecificInteraction" span="75 3" str="DVT" code="128053003: Deep venous thrombosis (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M16" type="SpecificInteraction" span="104 2" str="PE" code="59282003: Pulmonary embolism (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M19" type="SpecificInteraction" span="84 18" str="pulmonary embolism" code="59282003: Pulmonary embolism (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M22" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 22" str="VENOUS THROMBOEMBOLISM" code="429098002: Thromboembolism of vein (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M20" precipitant="M21" effect="M10" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M20" precipitant="M21" effect="M13" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M20" precipitant="M21" effect="M16" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M20" precipitant="M21" effect="M19" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M20" precipitant="M21" effect="M22" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7945" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Pregnancy (Boxed Warning, 4.1, 5.1, 5.2, 8.1, 17) Demonstrated hypersensitivity to the drug or its components (4.2, 5.15, 6.2) THALOMID can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant female.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7946" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Thalidomide is contraindicated in females who are pregnant.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7947" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Thalidomide is a powerful human teratogen, inducing a high frequency of severe and life-threatening birth defects, even after a single dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7948" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Mortality at or shortly after birth has been reported in about 40% of infants.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7949" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>If this drug is used during pregnancy, or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking this drug, the patient should be apprised of the potential risk to a fetus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7950" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>If pregnancy occurs during thalidomide treatment, the drug should be discontinued immediately.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7951" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>THALOMID is contraindicated in patients who have demonstrated hypersensitivity to the drug or its components.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7952" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommended dose of dexamethasone is 40 mg/day on days 1-4, 9-12, and 17-20 every 28 days.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7953" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>ENL: 100 to 300 mg/day for an episode of cutaneous ENL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7954" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Up to 400 mg/day for severe cutaneous ENL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7955" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>THALOMID (thalidomide) must only be administered in compliance with all of the terms outlined in the THALOMID REMS program.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7956" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>THALOMID (thalidomide) may only be prescribed by prescribers certified with the THALOMID REMS program and may only be dispensed by pharmacists certified with the THALOMID REMS program.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7957" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Drug prescribing to females of reproductive potential is contingent upon initial and continued negative results of pregnancy testing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7958" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Consider dose reduction, delay, or discontinuation in patients who develop National Cancer Institute Common Toxicity Criteria (NCI CTC) Grade 3 or 4 adverse reactions and/or based on clinical judgment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7959" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>THALOMID is administered in combination with dexamethasone in 28-day treatment cycles.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7960" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The dose of THALOMID is 200 mg administered orally once daily with water, preferably at bedtime and at least 1 hour after the evening meal.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7961" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The dose of dexamethasone is 40 mg daily administered orally on days 1-4, 9-12, and 17-20 every 28 days.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7962" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Patients who develop adverse reactions such as constipation, somnolence, or peripheral neuropathy may benefit by either temporarily discontinuing the drug or continuing at a lower dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7963" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>With the abatement of these adverse reactions, the drug may be started at a lower dose or at the previous dose based on clinical judgment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7964" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For an episode of cutaneous ENL, THALOMID dosing should be initiated at 100 to 300 mg/day, administered once daily with water, preferably at bedtime and at least 1 hour after the evening meal.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7965" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Patients weighing less than 50 kilograms should be started at the low end of the dose range.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7966" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In patients with a severe cutaneous ENL reaction, or in those who have previously required higher doses to control the reaction, THALOMID dosing may be initiated at higher doses up to 400 mg/day once daily at bedtime or in divided doses with water, at least 1 hour after meals.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7967" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In patients with moderate to severe neuritis associated with a severe ENL reaction, corticosteroids may be started concomitantly with THALOMID.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7968" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Steroid usage can be tapered and discontinued when the neuritis has ameliorated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7969" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dosing with THALOMID should usually continue until signs and symptoms of active reaction have subsided, usually a period of at least 2 weeks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7970" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Patients may then be tapered off medication in 50 mg decrements every 2 to 4 weeks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7971" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Patients who have a documented history of requiring prolonged maintenance treatment to prevent the recurrence of cutaneous ENL or who flare during tapering should be maintained on the minimum dose necessary to control the reaction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7972" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Tapering off medication should be attempted every 3 to 6 months, in decrements of 50 mg every 2 to 4 weeks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7973" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Use caution if other drugs which have sedative and hypnotic properties, slow cardiac conduction and/or cause peripheral neuropathy must be used.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M27" type="Trigger" span="4 7" str="caution "/>
<Mention id="M24" type="Trigger" span="103 5" str=" cause"/>
<Mention id="M25" type="Precipitant" span="21 11;103 27" str="drugs which | cause peripheral neuropathy" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M26" type="SpecificInteraction" span="109 21" str="peripheral neuropathy" code="302226006: Peripheral nerve disease (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M28" type="Trigger" span="72 4" str=" slow"/>
<Mention id="M29" type="Precipitant" span="21 11;72 23" str="drugs which | slow cardiac conduction" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M30" type="SpecificInteraction" span="72 23" str="slow cardiac conduction" code="36358004: Abnormal cardiac conduction (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M31" type="Trigger" span="4 7" str="caution"/>
<Mention id="M32" type="Precipitant" span="21 49" str="drugs which have sedative and hypnotic properties" code="N0000193842"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M27;M24" precipitant="M25" effect="M26" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M27;M28" precipitant="M29" effect="M30" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M31" precipitant="M32"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7974" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>It is not known whether concomitant use of hormonal contraceptives further increases the risk of thromboembolism with THALOMID.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7975" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Patients taking concomitant therapies such as erythropoietin stimulating agents or estrogen containing therapies may have an increased risk of thromboembolism.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M39" type="Trigger" span="125 14" str="increased risk"/>
<Mention id="M34" type="Precipitant" span="46 33" str="erythropoietin stimulating agents" code="N0000175665"/>
<Mention id="M41" type="SpecificInteraction" span="143 15" str="thromboembolism" code="371039008: Thromboembolic disorder (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M37" type="Precipitant" span="83 8" str="estrogen" code="N0000175825 | N0000011402"/>
<Mention id="M40" type="Precipitant" span="83 29" str="estrogen containing therapies" code="N0000175825"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M39" precipitant="M34" effect="M41" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M39" precipitant="M37" effect="M41" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M39" precipitant="M40" effect="M41" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7976" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The use of opioids, antihistamines, antipsychotics, anti-anxiety agents, or other CNS depressants concomitantly with THALOMID may cause an additive sedative effect and should be avoided.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M54" type="Trigger" span="139 8;157 6" str="additive | effect"/>
<Mention id="M43" type="Precipitant" span="52 19" str="anti-anxiety agents" code="N0000193818"/>
<Mention id="M56" type="SpecificInteraction" span="139 24" str="additive sedative effect" code="17971005: Sedated (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M46" type="Precipitant" span="20 14" str="antihistamines" code="N0000175750 | N0000029071"/>
<Mention id="M49" type="Precipitant" span="36 14" str="antipsychotics" code="N0000029150 | N0000178316"/>
<Mention id="M52" type="Precipitant" span="82 15" str="CNS depressants" code="N0000175758"/>
<Mention id="M55" type="Precipitant" span="11 7" str="opioids" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M54" precipitant="M43" effect="M56" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M54" precipitant="M46" effect="M56" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M54" precipitant="M49" effect="M56" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M54" precipitant="M52" effect="M56" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M54" precipitant="M55" effect="M56" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7977" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The use of drugs which slow cardiac conduction concomitantly with THALOMID may cause an additive bradycardic effect and should be used with caution.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M57" type="Trigger" span="88 8;109 6" str="additive | effect"/>
<Mention id="M58" type="Precipitant" span="11 35" str="drugs which slow cardiac conduction" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M59" type="SpecificInteraction" span="88 27" str="additive bradycardic effect" code="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M57" precipitant="M58" effect="M59" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7978" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Cardiovascular medications which may cause bradycardia include calcium channel blockers, beta blockers, alpha/beta-adrenergic blockers, and digoxin.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M72" type="Trigger" span="37 5" str="cause"/>
<Mention id="M61" type="Precipitant" span="104 30" str="alpha/beta-adrenergic blockers" code="N0000175953"/>
<Mention id="M74" type="SpecificInteraction" span="43 11" str="bradycardia" code="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M64" type="Precipitant" span="89 13" str="beta blockers" code="N0000000161 | N0000175556"/>
<Mention id="M67" type="Precipitant" span="63 24" str="calcium channel blockers" code="N0000175566 | N0000000069 | N0000029119"/>
<Mention id="M70" type="Precipitant" span="0 54" str="Cardiovascular medications which may cause bradycardia" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M73" type="Precipitant" span="140 7" str="digoxin" code="73K4184T59 | N0000005903"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M72" precipitant="M61" effect="M74" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M72" precipitant="M64" effect="M74" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M72" precipitant="M67" effect="M74" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M72" precipitant="M70" effect="M74" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M72" precipitant="M73" effect="M74" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7979" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Non-cardiac drugs that may cause bradycardia include H2 blockers (e.g., famotidine, cimetidine), lithium, tricyclic antidepressants and neuromuscular blockers (succinylcholine).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M96" type="Trigger" span="27 5" str="cause"/>
<Mention id="M76" type="Precipitant" span="84 10" str="cimetidine" code="80061L1WGD"/>
<Mention id="M98" type="SpecificInteraction" span="33 11" str="bradycardia" code="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M79" type="Precipitant" span="72 10" str="famotidine" code="5QZO15J2Z8"/>
<Mention id="M82" type="Precipitant" span="53 11" str="H2 blockers" code="N0000000151"/>
<Mention id="M85" type="Precipitant" span="97 7" str="lithium" code="9FN79X2M3F | N0000147892"/>
<Mention id="M88" type="Precipitant" span="136 22" str="neuromuscular blockers" code="N0000175731"/>
<Mention id="M91" type="Precipitant" span="0 44" str="Non-cardiac drugs that may cause bradycardia" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M94" type="Precipitant" span="160 15" str="succinylcholine" code="N0000006153 | J2R869A8YF"/>
<Mention id="M97" type="Precipitant" span="106 25" str="tricyclic antidepressants" code="N0000029148 | N0000175752"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M96" precipitant="M76" effect="M98" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M96" precipitant="M79" effect="M98" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M96" precipitant="M82" effect="M98" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I29" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M96" precipitant="M85" effect="M98" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I30" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M96" precipitant="M88" effect="M98" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I31" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M96" precipitant="M91" effect="M98" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I32" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M96" precipitant="M94" effect="M98" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I33" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M96" precipitant="M97" effect="M98" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7980" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>In 16 healthy men, the pharmacokinetic profile of a single 0.5 mg digoxin dose was similar with and without the coadministration of thalidomide 200 mg/day at steady state levels.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7981" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The single dose of digoxin had no effect on the pharmacokinetic profile of thalidomide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7982" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The safety of long-term concomitant use of THALOMID and digoxin has not been evaluated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7983" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The use of drugs which cause peripheral neuropathy (e.g., bortezomib, amiodarone, cisplatin, docetaxel, paclitaxel, vincristine, disulfiram, phenytoin, metronidazole, alcohol) can cause an additive effect and should be used with caution.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M129" type="Trigger" span="189 15" str="additive effect"/>
<Mention id="M100" type="Precipitant" span="167 7" str="alcohol" code="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M"/>
<Mention id="M131" type="SpecificInteraction" span="29 21" str="peripheral neuropathy" code="302226006: Peripheral nerve disease (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M103" type="Precipitant" span="70 10" str="amiodarone" code="N0000005761 | N3RQ532IUT"/>
<Mention id="M106" type="Precipitant" span="58 10" str="bortezomib" code="69G8BD63PP"/>
<Mention id="M109" type="Precipitant" span="82 9" str="cisplatin" code="N0000007062 | Q20Q21Q62J"/>
<Mention id="M112" type="Precipitant" span="129 10" str="disulfiram" code="TR3MLJ1UAI"/>
<Mention id="M115" type="Precipitant" span="93 9" str="docetaxel" code="15H5577CQD"/>
<Mention id="M118" type="Precipitant" span="11 39" str="drugs which cause peripheral neuropathy" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M121" type="Precipitant" span="152 13" str="metronidazole" code="140QMO216E"/>
<Mention id="M124" type="Precipitant" span="104 10" str="paclitaxel" code="P88XT4IS4D"/>
<Mention id="M127" type="Precipitant" span="141 9" str="phenytoin" code="6158TKW0C5 | N0000006023"/>
<Mention id="M130" type="Precipitant" span="116 11" str="vincristine" code="5J49Q6B70F"/>
<Interaction id="I34" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M129" precipitant="M100" effect="M131" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I35" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M129" precipitant="M103" effect="M131" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I36" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M129" precipitant="M106" effect="M131" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I37" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M129" precipitant="M109" effect="M131" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I38" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M129" precipitant="M112" effect="M131" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I39" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M129" precipitant="M115" effect="M131" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I40" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M129" precipitant="M118" effect="M131" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I41" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M129" precipitant="M121" effect="M131" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I42" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M129" precipitant="M124" effect="M131" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I43" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M129" precipitant="M127" effect="M131" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I44" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M129" precipitant="M130" effect="M131" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7984" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Hormonal contraceptives increase the risk of thromboembolism.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M132" type="Trigger" span="24 17" str="increase the risk"/>
<Mention id="M133" type="Precipitant" span="0 23" str="Hormonal contraceptives" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M134" type="SpecificInteraction" span="45 15" str="thromboembolism" code="371039008: Thromboembolic disorder (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I45" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M132" precipitant="M133" effect="M134" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7985" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>In 10 healthy women, the pharmacokinetic profiles of norethindrone and ethinyl estradiol following administration of a single dose containing 1.0 mg of norethindrone acetate and 75 mcg of ethinyl estradiol were studied.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7986" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The results were similar with and without coadministration of thalidomide 200 mg/day to steady-state levels.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7987" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>In 13 healthy men, the pharmacokinetic profile and international normalized ratio (INR) of prothrombin time for warfarin, following a single oral dose of 25 mg, were similar with and without the coadministration of thalidomide 200 mg/day at steady-state levels.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7988" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The single dose of warfarin had no effect on the pharmacokinetic profile of thalidomide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7989" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant use of HIV-protease inhibitors, griseofulvin, modafinil, penicillins, rifampin, rifabutin, phenytoin, carbamazepine, or certain herbal supplements such as St. John's Wort with hormonal contraceptive agents may reduce the effectiveness of the contraception up to one month after discontinuation of these concomitant therapies.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M159" type="Trigger" span="222 24" str="reduce the effectiveness"/>
<Mention id="M136" type="Precipitant" span="114 13" str="carbamazepine" code="33CM23913M | N0000007470"/>
<Mention id="M161" type="SpecificInteraction" span="222 45" str="reduce the effectiveness of the contraception" code="102955006: Contraception failure (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M139" type="Precipitant" span="44 12" str="griseofulvin" code="32HRV3E3D5"/>
<Mention id="M142" type="Precipitant" span="19 23" str="HIV-protease inhibitors" code="N0000175520 | N0000000246"/>
<Mention id="M145" type="Precipitant" span="58 9" str="modafinil" code="R3UK8X3U3D"/>
<Mention id="M148" type="Precipitant" span="69 11" str="penicillins" code="N0000175497"/>
<Mention id="M151" type="Precipitant" span="103 9" str="phenytoin" code="6158TKW0C5 | N0000006023"/>
<Mention id="M154" type="Precipitant" span="92 9" str="rifabutin" code="1W306TDA6S | N0000007464"/>
<Mention id="M157" type="Precipitant" span="82 8" str="rifampin" code="VJT6J7R4TR | N0000006026"/>
<Mention id="M160" type="Precipitant" span="167 15" str="St. John's Wort" code="N0000022261 | UFH8805FKA"/>
<Interaction id="I46" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M159" precipitant="M136" effect="M161" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I47" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M159" precipitant="M139" effect="M161" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I48" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M159" precipitant="M142" effect="M161" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I49" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M159" precipitant="M145" effect="M161" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I50" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M159" precipitant="M148" effect="M161" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I51" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M159" precipitant="M151" effect="M161" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I52" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M159" precipitant="M154" effect="M161" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I53" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M159" precipitant="M157" effect="M161" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I54" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M159" precipitant="M160" effect="M161" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7990" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Therefore, females requiring treatment with one or more of these drugs must use two OTHER effective or highly effective methods of contraception while taking thalidomide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7991" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Erythropoietic agents, or other agents that may increase the risk of thromboembolism, such as estrogen containing therapies, should be used with caution in multiple myeloma patients receiving thalidomide with dexamethasone.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M171" type="Trigger" span="48 17" str="increase the risk"/>
<Mention id="M163" type="Precipitant" span="32 52" str="agents that may increase the risk of thromboembolism" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M173" type="SpecificInteraction" span="69 15" str="thromboembolism" code="371039008: Thromboembolic disorder (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M166" type="Precipitant" span="0 21" str="Erythropoietic agents" code="N0000175665"/>
<Mention id="M169" type="Precipitant" span="94 8" str="estrogen" code="N0000175825 | N0000011402"/>
<Mention id="M172" type="Precipitant" span="94 29" str="estrogen containing therapies" code="N0000175825"/>
<Interaction id="I55" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M171" precipitant="M163" effect="M173" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I56" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M171" precipitant="M166" effect="M173" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I57" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M171" precipitant="M169" effect="M173" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I58" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M171" precipitant="M172" effect="M173" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7992" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Ischemic heart disease (including myocardial infarction) and stroke have been observed in patients treated with THALOMID in combination with dexamethasone.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M176" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 22" str="Ischemic heart disease" code="414545008: Ischemic heart disease (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M181" type="Precipitant" span="141 13" str="dexamethasone" code="7S5I7G3JQL"/>
<Mention id="M179" type="SpecificInteraction" span="34 21" str="myocardial infarction" code="22298006: Myocardial infarction (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M182" type="SpecificInteraction" span="61 6" str="stroke" code="230690007: Cerebrovascular accident (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I59" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M176" precipitant="M181" effect="M176" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I60" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M179" precipitant="M181" effect="M179" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I61" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M182" precipitant="M181" effect="M182" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7993" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Increased Mortality: Observed in patients with MM when pembrolizumab was added to dexamethasone and a thalidomide analogue.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M183" type="Trigger" span="0 9" str="Increased"/>
<Mention id="M184" type="Precipitant" span="55 13" str="pembrolizumab" code="DPT0O3T46P"/>
<Mention id="M185" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 19" str="Increased Mortality" code="419620001: Death (event)"/>
<Interaction id="I62" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M183" precipitant="M184" effect="M185" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7994" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Drowsiness and Somnolence: Instruct patients to avoid situations where drowsiness may be a problem and not to take other medications that may cause drowsiness.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M191" type="Trigger" span="48 5" str="avoid "/>
<Mention id="M192" type="Trigger" span="103 11" str=" not to take "/>
<Mention id="M193" type="Trigger" span="142 5" str=" cause"/>
<Mention id="M194" type="Precipitant" span="121 37" str="medications that may cause drowsiness" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M190" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 10" str="Drowsiness" code="271782001: Drowsy (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M195" type="SpecificInteraction" span="15 10" str="Somnolence" code="271782001: Drowsy (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I63" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M191;M192;M193" precipitant="M194" effect="M190" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I64" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M191;M192;M193" precipitant="M194" effect="M195" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7995" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Peripheral Neuropathy: Examine patients at monthly intervals for the first 3 months of thalidomide therapy and periodically thereafter for signs or symptoms of peripheral neuropathy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7996" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Consider electrophysiological testing, consisting of measurement of sensory nerve action potential (SNAP) amplitudes at baseline and thereafter every 6 months in an effort to detect asymptomatic neuropathy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7997" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Dizziness and Orthostatic Hypotension: Advise patients to sit upright for a few minutes prior to standing up from a recumbent position.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7998" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Neutropenia: Patients may require dose interruption and/or dose reduction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7999" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Thrombocytopenia: Patients may require dose interruption and/or dose reduction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8000" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Increased HIV Viral Load: Measure viral load after the first and third months of treatment and every 3 months thereafter.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8001" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Bradycardia: Monitor patients for bradycardia and possible syncope.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8002" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Dose reduction or discontinuation may be required.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8003" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Stevens-Johnson Syndrome and Toxic Epidermal Necrolysis: Do not resume THALOMID following discontinuation for these reactions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8004" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Seizures: Monitor patients with a history of seizures or at risk for the development of seizures closely for clinical changes that could precipitate acute seizure activity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8005" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Tumor Lysis Syndrome: Monitor patients at risk (e.g., those with high tumor burden prior to treatment) and take appropriate precautions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8006" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hypersensitivity: Monitor patients for potential hypersensitivity to the drug and its components.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8007" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Thalidomide is a powerful human teratogen that induces a high frequency of severe and life-threatening birth defects, even after a single dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8008" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>When there is no satisfactory alternative treatment, females of reproductive potential may be treated with thalidomide provided adequate precautions are taken to avoid pregnancy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8009" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>THALOMID® (thalidomide) is only available through the THALOMID REMS program.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8010" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Oral ingestion is the only type of maternal thalidomide exposure known to result in drug-associated birth defects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8011" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There are no specific data available regarding the reproductive risks of cutaneous absorption or inhalation of thalidomide; however, females of reproductive potential should avoid contact with THALOMID® (thalidomide) Capsules.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8012" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>THALOMID Capsules should be stored in blister packs until ingestion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8013" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If there is contact with non-intact thalidomide capsules or the powder contents, the exposed area should be washed with soap and water.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8014" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If healthcare providers or other care givers are exposed to body fluids from patients receiving THALOMID (thalidomide) the exposed area should be washed with soap and water.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8015" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Appropriate precautions should be utilized, such as wearing gloves to prevent the potential cutaneous exposure to THALOMID.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8016" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Females of Reproductive Potential Females of reproductive potential must avoid pregnancy for at least 4 weeks before beginning THALOMID therapy, during therapy, during dose interruptions and for at least 4 weeks after completing therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8017" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Females must commit either to abstain continuously from heterosexual sexual intercourse or to use two methods of reliable birth control, beginning 4 weeks prior to initiating treatment with THALOMID, during therapy, during dose interruptions and continuing for 4 weeks following discontinuation of THALOMID therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8018" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Two negative pregnancy tests must be obtained prior to initiating therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8019" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The first test should be performed within 10-14 days and the second test within 24 hours prior to prescribing THALOMID therapy and then weekly during the first month, then monthly thereafter in females with regular menstrual cycles or every 2 weeks in females with irregular menstrual cycles.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8020" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Males Thalidomide is present in the semen of patients receiving the drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8021" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Therefore, males must always use a latex or synthetic condom during any sexual contact with females of reproductive potential while taking THALOMID and for up to 4 weeks after discontinuing THALOMID, even if they have undergone a successful vasectomy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8022" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Male patients taking THALOMID must not donate sperm.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8023" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Blood Donation Patients must not donate blood during treatment with THALOMID and for 4 weeks following discontinuation of the drug because the blood might be given to a pregnant female patient whose fetus must not be exposed to THALOMID.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8024" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Because of the embryo-fetal risk, THALOMID is available only through a restricted program under a Risk Evaluation and Mitigation Strategy (REMS), the THALOMID REMS program.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8025" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Required components of the THALOMID REMS program include the following: Prescribers must be certified with the THALOMID REMS program by enrolling and complying with the REMS requirements.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8026" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients must sign a Patient-Physician Agreement Form and comply with the REMS requirements.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8027" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In particular, female patients of reproductive potential who are not pregnant must comply with the pregnancy testing and contraception requirements and males must comply with contraception requirements.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8028" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Pharmacies must be certified with the THALOMID REMS program, must only dispense to patients who are authorized to receive THALOMID and comply with REMS requirements.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8029" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Further information about the THALOMID REMS program is available at www.celgeneriskmanagement.com or by telephone at 1-888-423-5436.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8030" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The use of THALOMID in patients with MM results in an increased risk of venous thromboembolism, such as deep venous thrombosis and pulmonary embolism.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8031" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Ischemic heart disease (11.1%), including myocardial infarction (1.3%), and stroke (cerebrovascular accident, 2.6%) have also occurred in patients with previously untreated MM treated with THALOMID and dexamethasone compared to placebo and dexamethasone (4.7%, 1.7%, and 0.9%, respectively) in one clinical trial.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8032" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients and physicians should be observant for the signs and symptoms of thromboembolism.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8033" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Advise patients to seek immediate medical care if they develop symptoms such as shortness of breath, chest pain, or arm or leg swelling.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8034" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Agents that also may increase the risk of thromboembolism should be used with caution in patients receiving THALOMID.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M196" type="Trigger" span="21 17" str="increase the risk"/>
<Mention id="M197" type="Precipitant" span="0 57" str="Agents that also may increase the risk of thromboembolism" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M198" type="SpecificInteraction" span="42 15" str="thromboembolism" code="371039008: Thromboembolic disorder (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I65" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M196" precipitant="M197" effect="M198" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8035" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In two randomized clinical trials in patients with MM, the addition of pembrolizumab to a thalidomide analogue plus dexamethasone, a use for which no PD-1 or PD-L1 blocking antibody is indicated, resulted in increased mortality.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M199" type="Trigger" span="196 11" str="resulted in"/>
<Mention id="M200" type="Precipitant" span="71 13" str="pembrolizumab" code="DPT0O3T46P"/>
<Mention id="M201" type="SpecificInteraction" span="208 19" str="Increased Mortality" code="419620001: Death (event)"/>
<Mention id="M204" type="Trigger" span="147 2;185 9" str="no | indicated"/>
<Mention id="M203" type="Precipitant" span="150 4;164 17" str="PD-1 | blocking antibody" code="N0000191260"/>
<Mention id="M205" type="Precipitant" span="158 23" str="PD-L1 blocking antibody" code="N0000193338"/>
<Interaction id="I66" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M199" precipitant="M200" effect="M201" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I67" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M204" precipitant="M203"/>
<Interaction id="I68" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M204" precipitant="M205"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8036" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Treatment of patients with MM with a PD-1 or PD-L1 blocking antibody in combination with a thalidomide analogue plus dexamethasone is not recommended outside of controlled clinical trials.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M208" type="Trigger" span="134 15" str="not recommended"/>
<Mention id="M207" type="Precipitant" span="37 4;51 17" str="PD-1 | blocking antibody" code="N0000191260"/>
<Mention id="M209" type="Precipitant" span="45 23" str="PD-L1 blocking antibody" code="N0000193338"/>
<Interaction id="I69" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M208" precipitant="M207"/>
<Interaction id="I70" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M208" precipitant="M209"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8037" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Thalidomide frequently causes drowsiness and somnolence.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8038" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients should be instructed to avoid situations where drowsiness may be a problem and not to take other medications that may cause drowsiness without adequate medical advice.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M210" type="Trigger" span="33 5" str="avoid "/>
<Mention id="M211" type="Trigger" span="88 11" str=" not to take "/>
<Mention id="M212" type="Trigger" span="127 5" str=" cause"/>
<Mention id="M213" type="Precipitant" span="106 37" str="medications that may cause drowsiness" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M214" type="SpecificInteraction" span="56 10" str="drowsiness" code="271782001: Drowsy (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I71" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M210;M211;M212" precipitant="M213" effect="M214" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8039" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Advise patients as to the possible impairment of mental and/or physical abilities required for the performance of hazardous tasks, such as driving a car or operating other complex or dangerous machinery.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8040" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Thalidomide is known to cause nerve damage that may be permanent.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8041" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Peripheral neuropathy is a common (≥10%) and potentially severe adverse reaction of treatment with thalidomide that may be irreversible.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8042" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Peripheral neuropathy generally occurs following chronic use over a period of months; however, peripheral neuropathy following relatively short-term use has been reported.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8043" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The correlation with cumulative dose is unclear.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8044" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Symptoms may occur some time after thalidomide treatment has been stopped and may resolve slowly or not at all.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8045" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Few reports of neuropathy have arisen in the treatment of ENL despite long-term thalidomide treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8046" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>However, the inability clinically to differentiate thalidomide neuropathy from the neuropathy often seen in Hansen's disease makes it difficult to determine accurately the incidence of thalidomide-related neuropathy in ENL patients treated with thalidomide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8047" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients should be examined at monthly intervals for the first 3 months of thalidomide therapy to enable the clinician to detect early signs of neuropathy, which include numbness, tingling or pain in the hands and feet.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8048" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients should be evaluated periodically thereafter during treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8049" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients should be regularly counseled, questioned, and evaluated for signs or symptoms of peripheral neuropathy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8050" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Consideration should be given to electrophysiological testing, consisting of measurement of sensory nerve action potential (SNAP) amplitudes at baseline and thereafter every 6 months in an effort to detect asymptomatic neuropathy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8051" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If symptoms of drug-induced neuropathy develop, thalidomide should be discontinued immediately to limit further damage, if clinically appropriate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8052" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Usually, treatment with thalidomide should only be reinitiated if the neuropathy returns to baseline status.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8053" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Medications known to be associated with neuropathy should be used with caution in patients receiving thalidomide.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M215" type="Trigger" span="24 15" str="associated with"/>
<Mention id="M216" type="Precipitant" span="0 11;24 26" str="Medications | associated with neuropathy" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M217" type="SpecificInteraction" span="40 10" str="neuropathy" code="386033004: Neuropathy (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I72" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M215" precipitant="M216" effect="M217" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8054" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients should also be advised that thalidomide may cause dizziness and orthostatic hypotension and that, therefore, they should sit upright for a few minutes prior to standing up from a recumbent position.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8055" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Decreased white blood cell counts, including neutropenia, have been reported in association with the clinical use of thalidomide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8056" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Treatment should not be initiated with an absolute neutrophil count (ANC) of &lt;750/mm3.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8057" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>White blood cell count and differential should be monitored on an ongoing basis, especially in patients who may be more prone to neutropenia, such as patients who are HIV-seropositive.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8058" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If ANC decreases to below 750/mm3 while on treatment, the patient's medication regimen should be re-evaluated and, if the neutropenia persists, consideration should be given to withholding thalidomide if clinically appropriate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8059" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Thrombocytopenia, including Grade 3 or 4 occurrences, has been reported in association with the clinical use of thalidomide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8060" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor blood counts, including platelet counts.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8061" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Dose reduction, delay, or discontinuation may be required.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8062" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor for signs and symptoms of bleeding including petechiae, epistaxis, and gastrointestinal bleeding, especially if concomitant medication may increase the risk of bleeding.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M233" type="Trigger" span="0 7" str="Monitor "/>
<Mention id="M234" type="Trigger" span="12 18" str=" signs and symptoms "/>
<Mention id="M235" type="Trigger" span="147 17" str=" increase the risk"/>
<Mention id="M236" type="Precipitant" span="132 44" str="medication may increase the risk of bleeding" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M222" type="SpecificInteraction" span="34 8" str="bleeding" code="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M227" type="SpecificInteraction" span="64 9" str="epistaxis" code="249366005: Bleeding from nose (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M232" type="SpecificInteraction" span="79 25" str="gastrointestinal bleeding" code="61401005: Gastric hemorrhage (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M237" type="SpecificInteraction" span="53 9" str="petechiae" code="271813007: Petechiae (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I73" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M233;M234;M235" precipitant="M236" effect="M222" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I74" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M233;M234;M235" precipitant="M236" effect="M227" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I75" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M233;M234;M235" precipitant="M236" effect="M232" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I76" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M233;M234;M235" precipitant="M236" effect="M237" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8063" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In a randomized, placebo-controlled trial of thalidomide in an HIV-seropositive patient population, plasma HIV RNA levels were found to increase (median change = 0.42 log10 copies HIV RNA/mL, p = 0.04 compared to placebo).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8064" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>A similar trend was observed in a second, unpublished study conducted in patients who were HIV-seropositive.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8065" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The clinical significance of this increase is unknown.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8066" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Both studies were conducted prior to availability of highly active antiretroviral therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8067" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Until the clinical significance of this finding is further understood, in HIV-seropositive patients, viral load should be measured after the first and third months of treatment and every 3 months thereafter.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8068" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Bradycardia in association with thalidomide use has been reported.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8069" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Cases of bradycardia have been reported, some required medical interventions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8070" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The clinical significance and underlying etiology of the bradycardia noted in some thalidomide-treated patients are presently unknown.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8071" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor patients for bradycardia and syncope.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8072" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Medications known to decrease heart rate should be used with caution in patients receiving thalidomide.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M240" type="SpecificInteraction" span="21 19" str="decrease heart rate" code="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M239" type="Precipitant" span="0 40" str="Medications known to decrease heart rate" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I77" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M240" precipitant="M239" effect="M240" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8073" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Serious dermatologic reactions including Stevens-Johnson syndrome and toxic epidermal necrolysis, which may be fatal, have been reported.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8074" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>THALOMID should be discontinued if a skin rash occurs and only resumed following appropriate clinical evaluation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8075" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If the rash is exfoliative, purpuric, or bullous or if Stevens-Johnson syndrome or toxic epidermal necrolysis is suspected, use of THALOMID should not be resumed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8076" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Although not reported from pre-marketing controlled clinical trials, seizures, including grand mal convulsions, have been reported during post-approval use of THALOMID in clinical practice.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8077" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Because these events are reported voluntarily from a population of unknown size, estimates of frequency cannot be made.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8078" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Most patients had disorders that may have predisposed them to seizure activity, and it is not currently known whether thalidomide has any epileptogenic influence.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8079" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>During therapy with thalidomide, patients with a history of seizures or with other risk factors for the development of seizures should be monitored closely for clinical changes that could precipitate acute seizure activity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8080" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor patients at risk of tumor lysis syndrome (e.g., patients with high tumor burden prior to treatment) and take appropriate precautions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8081" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Some contraceptive methods may pose a higher risk of adverse effects or may be medically contraindicated in some patients treated with THALOMID.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M241" type="Trigger" span="38 11" str="higher risk "/>
<Mention id="M242" type="Trigger" span="53 15" str=" adverse effects "/>
<Mention id="M243" type="Trigger" span="89 15" str=" contraindicated"/>
<Mention id="M244" type="Precipitant" span="0 26" str="Some contraceptive methods" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I78" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M241;M242;M243" precipitant="M244"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8082" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Because some patients may develop sudden, severe neutropenia and/or thrombocytopenia, use of an intrauterine device (IUD) or implantable contraception in these patients may carry an increased risk for infection or bleeding either at insertion, removal or during use.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8083" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Treatment with THALOMID, the presence of an underlying malignancy, and/or use of an estrogen-containing contraceptive can each increase the risk of thromboembolism.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M248" type="Trigger" span="127 17" str="increase the risk"/>
<Mention id="M246" type="Precipitant" span="84 8" str="estrogen" code="N0000175825 | N0000011402"/>
<Mention id="M250" type="SpecificInteraction" span="148 15" str="thromboembolism" code="371039008: Thromboembolic disorder (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M249" type="Precipitant" span="84 33" str="estrogen-containing contraceptive" code="N0000175825"/>
<Interaction id="I79" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M248" precipitant="M246" effect="M250" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I80" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M248" precipitant="M249" effect="M250" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8084" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>It is not known if these risks of thromboembolism are additive.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8085" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>However, they should be taken into consideration when choosing contraceptive methods.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8086" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hypersensitivity to THALOMID has been reported.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8087" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Signs and symptoms have included the occurrence of erythematous macular rash, possibly associated with fever, tachycardia, and hypotension, and if severe, may necessitate interruption of therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8088" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If the reaction recurs when dosing is resumed, THALOMID should be discontinued.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8089" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mechanism of action of THALOMID is not fully understood.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8090" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Cellular activities of thalidomide are mediated through its target cereblon, a component of a cullin ring E3 ubiquitin ligase enzyme complex.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8091" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>THALOMID possesses immunomodulatory, anti-inflammatory and antiangiogenic properties.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8092" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Available data from in vitro studies and clinical trials suggest that the immunologic effects of this compound can vary substantially under different conditions, but may be related to suppression of excessive tumor necrosis factor-alpha (TNF-α) production and down-modulation of selected cell surface adhesion molecules involved in leukocyte migration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8093" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>For example, administration of thalidomide has been reported to decrease circulating levels of TNF-α in patients with erythema nodosum leprosum (ENL); however, it has also been shown to increase plasma TNF-α levels in HIV-seropositive patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8094" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Other anti-inflammatory and immunomodulatory properties of thalidomide may include suppression of macrophage involvement in prostaglandin synthesis, and modulation of interleukin-10 and interleukin-12 production by peripheral blood mononuclear cells.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8095" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Thalidomide treatment of multiple myeloma patients is accompanied by an increase in the number of circulating natural killer cells, and an increase in plasma levels of interleukin-2 and interferon-gamma (T cell-derived cytokines associated with cytotoxic activity).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8096" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Thalidomide was found to inhibit angiogenesis in a human umbilical artery explant model in vitro.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8097" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The cellular processes of angiogenesis inhibited by thalidomide may include the proliferation of endothelial cells.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8098" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Absorption Absorption of THALOMID is slow after oral administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8099" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The maximum plasma concentrations are reached approximately 2-5 hours after administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8100" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The absolute bioavailability of thalidomide from thalidomide capsules has not yet been characterized in human subjects due to its poor aqueous solubility.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8101" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Based on the 14C-radiolabel thalidomide study in human, greater than 90% of the total radioactivity is recovered in urine suggesting good oral absorption.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8102" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>While the extent of absorption (as measured by area under the curve [AUC]) is proportional to dose in healthy subjects, the observed peak concentration (Cmax) increased in a less than proportional manner.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8103" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This lack of Cmax dose proportionality, coupled with the observed increase in Tmax values, suggests that the poor solubility of thalidomide in aqueous media may be hindering the rate of absorption.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8104" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Table 5: Pharmacokinetic Parameter Values for THALOMID Mean (%CV) Population/Single Dose AUC0-∞ mcgg·hr/mL Cmax mcg/mL Tmax (hrs) Half‑life (hrs) Healthy Subjects (n=14) 50 mg 4.9 (16%) 0.62 (52%) 2.9 (66%) 5.52 (37%) 200 mg 18.9 (17%) 1.76 (30%) 3.5 (57%) 5.53 (25%) 400 mg 36.4 (26%) 2.82 (28%) 4.3 (37%) 7.29 (36%) Patients with Hansen’s Disease (n=6) 400 mg 46.4 (44.1%) 3.44 (52.6%) 5.7 (27%) 6.86 (17%) Coadministration of THALOMID® (thalidomide) with a high-fat meal causes minor (&lt;10%) changes in the observed AUC and Cmax values; however, it causes an increase in Tmax to approximately 6 hours.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M251" type="Trigger" span="561 16" str="increase in Tmax"/>
<Mention id="M252" type="Precipitant" span="460 13" str="high-fat meal" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I81" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M251" precipitant="M252" effect="C54604"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8105" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Distribution In human plasma, the geometric mean plasma protein binding was 55% and 66%, respectively, for (+)-(R)- and (-)-(S)-thalidomide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8106" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In a pharmacokinetic study of thalidomide in HIV-seropositive adult male subjects receiving thalidomide 100 mg/day, thalidomide was detectable in the semen.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8107" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Metabolism In a 14C-radiolabel ADME study in humans, unchanged drug is the predominant circulating component.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8108" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Thalidomide is not a substrate of the cytochrome P450 system.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8109" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>At therapeutic concentrations, thalidomide is not an inhibitor or inducer of human cytochrome P450 enzymes in vitro.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8110" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Pharmacokinetic drug-drug interactions with substrates, inhibitors or inducers of CYP450 are not anticipated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8111" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Elimination The mean elimination half-life of thalidomide in plasma following single oral doses between 50 mg and 400 mg was 5.5 to 7.3 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8112" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following a single 400 mg oral dose of radiolabeled thalidomide, the total mean recovery was 93.6% of the administered dose by Day 8.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8113" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The majority of the radioactive dose was excreted within 48 hours following dose administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8114" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In humans, 14C-thalidomide is primarily excreted in urine (91.9% of the radioactive dose) mainly as hydrolytic metabolites while fecal excretion is minor (&lt;2% of the dose).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8115" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Unchanged thalidomide is not eliminated by the kidney to a notable degree (&lt;3.5% of the dose).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8116" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Effects of Weight There is a linear relationship between body weight and estimated thalidomide clearance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8117" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In MM patients with body weight from 47-133 kg, thalidomide clearance ranged from approximately 6-12 L/h, representing an increase in thalidomide clearance of 0.605 L/h per 10 kg body weight increase.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8118" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Effects of Age, Gender and Race Analysis of the data from pharmacokinetic studies in healthy volunteers and patients with Hansen's disease ranging in age from 20 to 69 years does not reveal any age-related changes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8119" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>While a comparative trial of the effects of gender on thalidomide pharmacokinetics has not been conducted, examination of the data for thalidomide does not reveal any significant gender differences in pharmacokinetic parameter values.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8120" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Pharmacokinetic differences due to race have not been studied.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8121" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Pharmacokinetic Data in Special Populations HIV-seropositive Subjects: There is no apparent significant difference in measured pharmacokinetic parameter values between healthy human subjects and HIV-seropositive subjects following single-dose administration of THALOMID Capsules.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8122" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Patients with Hansen's Disease: Analysis of data from a small study in Hansen's patients suggests that these patients, relative to healthy subjects, may have an increased bioavailability of THALOMID.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8123" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The increase is reflected both in an increased area under the curve and in increased peak plasma levels.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8124" LabelDrug="Thalomid" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Pediatric: No pharmacokinetic data are available in subjects below the age of 18 years.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="dexamethasone" precipitantCode="7S5I7G3JQL" effect="128053003: Deep venous thrombosis (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="dexamethasone" precipitantCode="7S5I7G3JQL" effect="22298006: Myocardial infarction (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="dexamethasone" precipitantCode="7S5I7G3JQL" effect="230690007: Cerebrovascular accident (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="dexamethasone" precipitantCode="7S5I7G3JQL" effect="414545008: Ischemic heart disease (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="dexamethasone" precipitantCode="7S5I7G3JQL" effect="429098002: Thromboembolism of vein (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="dexamethasone" precipitantCode="7S5I7G3JQL" effect="59282003: Pulmonary embolism (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="dexamethasone" precipitantCode="7S5I7G3JQL"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="standard chemotherapeutic agents" precipitantCode="N0000178307"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="drugs which | cause peripheral neuropathy" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="302226006: Peripheral nerve disease (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="drugs which | slow cardiac conduction" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="36358004: Abnormal cardiac conduction (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="drugs which have sedative and hypnotic properties" precipitantCode="N0000193842"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="erythropoietin stimulating agents" precipitantCode="N0000175665" effect="371039008: Thromboembolic disorder (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="estrogen" precipitantCode="N0000175825 | N0000011402" effect="371039008: Thromboembolic disorder (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="estrogen containing therapies" precipitantCode="N0000175825" effect="371039008: Thromboembolic disorder (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="anti-anxiety agents" precipitantCode="N0000193818" effect="17971005: Sedated (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="antihistamines" precipitantCode="N0000175750 | N0000029071" effect="17971005: Sedated (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="antipsychotics" precipitantCode="N0000029150 | N0000178316" effect="17971005: Sedated (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cns depressants" precipitantCode="N0000175758" effect="17971005: Sedated (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="opioids" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="17971005: Sedated (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="drugs which slow cardiac conduction" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="alpha/beta-adrenergic blockers" precipitantCode="N0000175953" effect="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="beta blockers" precipitantCode="N0000000161 | N0000175556" effect="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="calcium channel blockers" precipitantCode="N0000175566 | N0000000069 | N0000029119" effect="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cardiovascular medications which may cause bradycardia" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="digoxin" precipitantCode="73K4184T59 | N0000005903" effect="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cimetidine" precipitantCode="80061L1WGD" effect="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="famotidine" precipitantCode="5QZO15J2Z8" effect="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="h2 blockers" precipitantCode="N0000000151" effect="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="lithium" precipitantCode="9FN79X2M3F | N0000147892" effect="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="neuromuscular blockers" precipitantCode="N0000175731" effect="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="non-cardiac drugs that may cause bradycardia" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="succinylcholine" precipitantCode="N0000006153 | J2R869A8YF" effect="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="tricyclic antidepressants" precipitantCode="N0000029148 | N0000175752" effect="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="alcohol" precipitantCode="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M" effect="302226006: Peripheral nerve disease (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="amiodarone" precipitantCode="N0000005761 | N3RQ532IUT" effect="302226006: Peripheral nerve disease (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="bortezomib" precipitantCode="69G8BD63PP" effect="302226006: Peripheral nerve disease (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cisplatin" precipitantCode="N0000007062 | Q20Q21Q62J" effect="302226006: Peripheral nerve disease (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="disulfiram" precipitantCode="TR3MLJ1UAI" effect="302226006: Peripheral nerve disease (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="docetaxel" precipitantCode="15H5577CQD" effect="302226006: Peripheral nerve disease (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="drugs which cause peripheral neuropathy" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="302226006: Peripheral nerve disease (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="metronidazole" precipitantCode="140QMO216E" effect="302226006: Peripheral nerve disease (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="paclitaxel" precipitantCode="P88XT4IS4D" effect="302226006: Peripheral nerve disease (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="phenytoin" precipitantCode="6158TKW0C5 | N0000006023" effect="102955006: Contraception failure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="phenytoin" precipitantCode="6158TKW0C5 | N0000006023" effect="302226006: Peripheral nerve disease (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="vincristine" precipitantCode="5J49Q6B70F" effect="302226006: Peripheral nerve disease (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="hormonal contraceptives" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="371039008: Thromboembolic disorder (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="carbamazepine" precipitantCode="33CM23913M | N0000007470" effect="102955006: Contraception failure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="griseofulvin" precipitantCode="32HRV3E3D5" effect="102955006: Contraception failure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="hiv-protease inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175520 | N0000000246" effect="102955006: Contraception failure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="modafinil" precipitantCode="R3UK8X3U3D" effect="102955006: Contraception failure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="penicillins" precipitantCode="N0000175497" effect="102955006: Contraception failure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="rifabutin" precipitantCode="1W306TDA6S | N0000007464" effect="102955006: Contraception failure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="rifampin" precipitantCode="VJT6J7R4TR | N0000006026" effect="102955006: Contraception failure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="st. john's wort" precipitantCode="N0000022261 | UFH8805FKA" effect="102955006: Contraception failure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="agents that may increase the risk of thromboembolism" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="371039008: Thromboembolic disorder (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="erythropoietic agents" precipitantCode="N0000175665" effect="371039008: Thromboembolic disorder (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="pembrolizumab" precipitantCode="DPT0O3T46P" effect="419620001: Death (event)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="medications that may cause drowsiness" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="271782001: Drowsy (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="agents that also may increase the risk of thromboembolism" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="371039008: Thromboembolic disorder (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="pd-1 | blocking antibody" precipitantCode="N0000191260"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="pd-l1 blocking antibody" precipitantCode="N0000193338"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="medications | associated with neuropathy" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="386033004: Neuropathy (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="medication may increase the risk of bleeding" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="medication may increase the risk of bleeding" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="249366005: Bleeding from nose (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="medication may increase the risk of bleeding" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="271813007: Petechiae (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="medication may increase the risk of bleeding" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="61401005: Gastric hemorrhage (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="medications known to decrease heart rate" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="48867003: Bradycardia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="some contraceptive methods" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="estrogen-containing contraceptive" precipitantCode="N0000175825" effect="371039008: Thromboembolic disorder (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="high-fat meal" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54604"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>