<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Lialda" setid="3098a080-be86-4265-9818-7fc4beab77b7">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
LIALDA is contraindicated in patients with known hypersensitivity to salicylates or aminosalicylates or to any of the ingredients of LIALDA [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3) ,  Description (11) ,  Adverse Reactions (6.2) ]. Patients with known hypersensitivity to salicylates or aminosalicylates or to any of the ingredients of LIALDA tablets. ( 4 )</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
The recommended dosage for the induction of remission in adult patients with active, mild to moderate ulcerative colitis is two to four 1.2 g tablets taken once daily with a meal for a total daily dose of 2.4 g or 4.8 g. The recommended dosage for the maintenance of remission is two 1.2 g tablets taken once daily with a meal for a total daily dose of 2.4 g. For induction of remission of active, mild to moderate ulcerative colitis, two to four 1.2 g tablets taken once daily with food. ( 1 , 2 ) For maintenance of remission of ulcerative colitis, two 1.2 g tablets taken once daily with food. ( 1 , 2 )</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
No investigations of interaction between LIALDA and other drugs except for certain antibiotics have been performed [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3) ] . However, the following drug-drug interactions have been reported for products containing mesalamine: Nephrotoxic agents including NSAIDs: renal reactions have been reported. ( 7.1 ) Azathioprine or 6-mercaptopurine: blood disorders have been reported. ( 7.2 ) The concurrent use of mesalamine with known nephrotoxic agents, including non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) may increase the risk of renal reactions. The concurrent use of mesalamine with azathioprine or 6-mercaptopurine may increase the risk for blood disorders.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
Renal impairment may occur. Assess renal function at the beginning of treatment and periodically during treatment. ( 5.1 ) Mesalamine-induced acute intolerance syndrome has been reported. Observe patients closely for worsening of these symptoms while on treatment. ( 5.2 ) Use caution when treating patients who are hypersensitive to sulfasalazine. ( 5.3 ) Mesalamine-induced cardiac hypersensitivity reactions (myocarditis and pericarditis) have been reported. ( 5.3 ) Hepatic failure has been reported in patients with pre-existing liver disease. Use caution when treating patients with liver disease. ( 5.4 ) Upper GI tract obstruction may delay onset of action. ( 5.5 ) Patients with pre-existing skin conditions have reported more severe photosensitivity reactions ( 5.6 ) Use of mesalamine may lead to spuriously elevated test results when measuring urinary normetanephrine by liquid chromatography with electrochemical detection. ( 5.7 ) Renal impairment, including minimal change nephropathy, acute and chronic interstitial nephritis, and, rarely, renal failure, has been reported in patients given products such as LIALDA that contain mesalamine or are converted to mesalamine. It is recommended that patients have an evaluation of renal function prior to initiation of LIALDA therapy and periodically while on therapy. Exercise caution when using LIALDA in patients with known renal dysfunction or a history of renal disease. In animal studies, the kidney was the principal organ for toxicity. [See Drug Interactions (7.1) and Nonclinical Toxicology (13.2) ] Mesalamine has been associated with an acute intolerance syndrome that may be difficult to distinguish from an exacerbation of ulcerative colitis. Although the exact frequency of occurrence has not been determined, it has occurred in 3% of patients in controlled clinical trials of mesalamine or sulfasalazine. Symptoms include cramping, acute abdominal pain and bloody diarrhea, and sometimes fever, headache, and rash. Observe patients closely for worsening of these symptoms while on treatment. If acute intolerance syndrome is suspected, promptly discontinue treatment with LIALDA. Some patients who have experienced a hypersensitivity reaction to sulfasalazine may have a similar reaction to LIALDA tablets or to other compounds that contain or are converted to mesalamine. Mesalamine-induced cardiac hypersensitivity reactions (myocarditis and pericarditis) have been reported with LIALDA and other mesalamine medications. Caution should be taken in prescribing this medicine to patients with conditions predisposing them to the development of myocarditis or pericarditis. There have been reports of hepatic failure in patients with pre-existing liver disease who have been administered mesalamine. Caution should be exercised when administering LIALDA to patients with liver disease. Pyloric stenosis or other organic or functional obstruction in the upper gastrointestinal tract may cause prolonged gastric retention of LIALDA which would delay mesalamine release in the colon. Patients with pre-existing skin conditions such as atopic dermatitis and atopic eczema have reported more severe photosensitivity reactions. Use of mesalamine may lead to spuriously elevated test results when measuring urinary normetanephrine by liquid chromatography with electrochemical detection because of the similarity in the chromatograms of normetanephrine and mesalamine's main metabolite, N-acetylaminosalicylic acid (N-Ac-5-ASA). An alternative, selective assay for normetanephrine should be considered.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
The mechanism of action of mesalamine is not fully understood, but appears to have a topical anti-inflammatory effect on the colonic epithelial cells. Mucosal production of arachidonic acid metabolites, both through the cyclooxygenase and lipoxygenase pathways, is increased in patients with chronic inflammatory bowel disease, and it is possible that mesalamine diminishes inflammation by blocking cyclooxygenase and inhibiting prostaglandin production in the colon. Mesalamine has the potential to inhibit the activation of nuclear factor kappa B (NFκB) and consequently the production of key pro-inflammatory cytokines. It has been proposed that reduced expression of PPARγ nuclear receptors (γ-form of peroxisome proliferator-activated receptors) may be implicated in ulcerative colitis. There is evidence that mesalamine produces pharmacodynamic effects through direct activation of PPARγ receptors in the colonic/rectal epithelium. The pharmacodynamic actions of mesalamine occur in the colonic/rectal mucosae local to the delivery of drug from LIALDA into the lumen. There is information suggesting that severity of colonic inflammation in ulcerative colitis patients treated with mesalamine is inversely correlated with mucosal concentrations of mesalamine. Plasma concentrations representing systemically absorbed mesalamine are not believed to contribute extensively to efficacy. Absorption The total absorption of mesalamine from LIALDA 2.4 g or 4.8 g given once daily for 14 days to healthy volunteers was found to be approximately 21-22% of the administered dose. Gamma-scintigraphy studies have shown that a single dose of LIALDA 1.2 g (one tablet) passed intact through the upper gastrointestinal tract of fasted healthy volunteers. Scintigraphic images showed a trail of radio-labeled tracer in the colon, suggesting that mesalamine had distributed through this region of the gastrointestinal tract. In a single dose study, LIALDA 1.2 g, 2.4 g and 4.8 g were administered in the fasted state to healthy subjects. Plasma concentrations of mesalamine were detectable after 2 hours and reached a maximum by 9-12 hours on average for the doses studied. The pharmacokinetic parameters are highly variable among subjects (Table 3). Mesalamine systemic exposure in terms of area under the plasma concentration-time curve (AUC) was slightly more than dose proportional between 1.2 g and 4.8 g LIALDA. Maximum plasma concentrations (C max ) of mesalamine increased approximately dose proportionately between 1.2 g and 2.4 g and sub-proportionately between 2.4 g and 4.8 g LIALDA, with the dose normalized value at 4.8 g representing, on average, 74% of that at 2.4 g based on geometric means. Table 3: Mean (SD) PK Parameters for Mesalamine Following Single Dose Administration of LIALDA Under Fasting Conditions Parameter 1 of Mesalamine LIALDA 1.2 g (N=47) LIALDA 2.4 g (N=48) LIALDA 4.8 g (N=48) AUC 0-t (ng.h/mL) 9039 + (5054) 20538 (12980) 41434 (26640) AUC 0-∞ (ng.h/mL) 9578 • (5214) 21084 (13185) 44775 # (30302) C max (ng/mL) 857 (638) 1595 (1484) 2154 (1140) T max * (h) 9.0** (4.0-32.1) 12.0 (4.0-34.1) 12.0 (4.0-34.0) T lag * (h) 2.0** (0-8.0) 2.0 (1.0-4.0) 2.0 (1.0-4.0) T 1/2 (h) (Terminal Phase) 8.56 • (6.38) 7.05 § (5.54) 7.25 # (8.32) 1 Arithmetic mean of parameter values are presented except for T max and T lag . *Median (min, max); + N=43, • N=27, § N=33, # N=36, **N=46 Administration of a single dose of LIALDA 4.8 g with a high fat meal resulted in further delay in absorption, and plasma concentrations of mesalamine were detectable 4 hours following dosing. However, a high fat meal increased systemic exposure of mesalamine (mean C max : ↑ 91%; mean AUC: ↑ 16%) compared to results in the fasted state. LIALDA was administered with food in the controlled clinical trials that supported its approval. In a single and multiple dose pharmacokinetic study of LIALDA, 2.4 g or 4.8 g was administered once daily with standard meals to 28 healthy volunteers per dose group. Plasma concentrations of mesalamine were detectable after 4 hours and were maximal by 8 hours after the single dose. Steady state was achieved generally by 2 days after dosing. Mean AUC at steady state was only modestly greater (1.1- to 1.4-fold) than predictable from single dose pharmacokinetics. In a single dose pharmacokinetic study of LIALDA, 4.8 g was administered in the fasted state to 71 healthy male and female volunteers (28 young (18-35yrs); 28 elderly (65-75yrs); 15 elderly (&amp;gt;75yrs)). Increased age resulted in increased systemic exposure (approximately 2-fold in C max ), to mesalamine and its metabolite N-acetyl-5-aminosalicylic acid. Increased age resulted in a slower apparent elimination of mesalamine, though there was high between-subject variability. Systemic exposures in individual subjects were inversely correlated with renal function as assessed by estimated creatinine clearance. Table 4: Mean (SD) PK Parameters for Mesalamine Following Single Dose Administration of LIALDA 4.8 g under Fasting Conditions to Young and Elderly Subjects Parameter of 5-ASA Young Subjects (18-35 yrs) (N=28) Elderly Subjects (65-75 yrs) (N=28) Elderly Subjects (&amp;gt;75 yrs) (N=15) AUC 0-t (ng.h/mL) 51570 (23870) 73001 (42608) 65820 (25283) AUC 0-∞ (ng.h/mL) 58057 b (22429) 89612 c (40596) 63067 d (22531) C max (ng/mL) 2243 (1410) 4999 (4381) 4832 (4383) t max a (h) 22.0 (5.98 - 48.0) 12.5 (4.00 - 36.0) 16.0 (4.00 - 26.0) t lag a (h) 2.00 (1.00 - 6.00) 2.00 (1.00 - 4.00) 2.00 (2.00 - 4.00) t 1/2 (h), terminal phase 5.68 b (2.83) 9.68 c (7.47) 8.67 d (5.84) Renal clearance (L/h) 2.05 (1.33) 2.04 (1.16) 2.13 (1.20) Arithmetic mean (SD) data are presented, N = Number of subjects a Median (min-max), b N=15, c N=16, d N=13 Distribution Mesalamine is approximately 43% bound to plasma proteins at the concentration of 2.5 μg/mL. Metabolism The only major metabolite of mesalamine (5-aminosalicylic acid) is N-acetyl-5-aminosalicylic acid. Its formation is brought about by N-acetyltransferase (NAT) activity in the liver and intestinal mucosa cells, principally by NAT-1. Elimination Elimination of mesalamine is mainly via the renal route following metabolism to N-acetyl-5-aminosalicylic acid (acetylation). However, there is also limited excretion of the parent drug in urine. Of the approximately 21-22% of the dose absorbed, less than 8% of the dose was excreted unchanged in the urine after 24 hours, compared with greater than 13% for N-acetyl-5-aminosalicylic acid. The apparent terminal half-lives for mesalamine and its major metabolite after administration of LIALDA 2.4 g and 4.8 g were, on average, 7-9 hours and 8-12 hours, respectively. Drug Interactions: The potential effect of LIALDA (4.8 g given once daily) on the pharmacokinetics of four commonly used antibiotics were evaluated in healthy subjects. The four antibiotics studied and their dosing regimens were as follows: amoxicillin (single 500 mg dose), ciprofloxacin XR (single 500 mg dose), metronidazole (750 mg twice daily for 3.5 days), and sulfamethoxazole/trimethoprim (800 mg/160 mg twice daily for 3.5 days). Coadministration of LIALDA did not result in clinically significant changes in the pharmacokinetics of any of the four antibiotics. The change in Cmax and AUC of amoxicillin, ciprofloxacin and metronidazole when they were co-administered with LIALDA were all ≤ 3%. There was an increase of 12% in Cmax and an increase of 15% in AUC of sulfamethoxazole when sulfamethoxazole/trimethoprim was coadministered with LIALDA [see Drug Interactions (7) ].</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="1052" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>LIALDA is contraindicated in patients with known hypersensitivity to salicylates or aminosalicylates or to any of the ingredients of LIALDA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1053" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Patients with known hypersensitivity to salicylates or aminosalicylates or to any of the ingredients of LIALDA tablets.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1054" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommended dosage for the induction of remission in adult patients with active, mild to moderate ulcerative colitis is two to four 1.2 g tablets taken once daily with a meal for a total daily dose of 2.4 g or 4.8 g. The recommended dosage for the maintenance of remission is two 1.2 g tablets taken once daily with a meal for a total daily dose of 2.4 g. For induction of remission of active, mild to moderate ulcerative colitis, two to four 1.2 g tablets taken once daily with food.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1055" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For maintenance of remission of ulcerative colitis, two 1.2 g tablets taken once daily with food.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1056" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>No investigations of interaction between LIALDA and other drugs except for certain antibiotics have been performed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1057" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>However, the following drug-drug interactions have been reported for products containing mesalamine: Nephrotoxic agents including NSAIDs: renal reactions have been reported.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M5" type="Trigger" span="23 22" str="drug-drug interactions "/>
<Mention id="M6" type="Trigger" span="144 9" str=" reactions"/>
<Mention id="M3" type="Precipitant" span="101 18" str="Nephrotoxic agents" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M8" type="SpecificInteraction" span="138 15" str="renal reactions" code="90708001: Kidney disease (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M7" type="Precipitant" span="130 6" str="NSAIDs" code="N0000175722"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M5;M6" precipitant="M3" effect="M8" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M5;M6" precipitant="M7" effect="M8" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1058" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Azathioprine or 6-mercaptopurine: blood disorders have been reported.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M14" type="SpecificInteraction" span="34 15" str="blood disorders" code="414027002: Disorder of hematopoietic structure (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M10" type="Precipitant" span="16 16" str="6-mercaptopurine" code="PKK6MUZ20G"/>
<Mention id="M13" type="Precipitant" span="0 12" str="Azathioprine" code="MRK240IY2L"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M14" precipitant="M10" effect="M14" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M14" precipitant="M13" effect="M14" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1059" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The concurrent use of mesalamine with known nephrotoxic agents, including non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) may increase the risk of renal reactions.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M21" type="Trigger" span="125 17" str="increase the risk"/>
<Mention id="M16" type="Precipitant" span="44 18" str="nephrotoxic agents" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M23" type="SpecificInteraction" span="146 15" str="renal reactions" code="90708001: Kidney disease (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M19" type="Precipitant" span="74 37" str="non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M22" type="Precipitant" span="113 6" str="NSAIDs" code="N0000175722"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M21" precipitant="M16" effect="M23" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M21" precipitant="M19" effect="M23" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M21" precipitant="M22" effect="M23" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1060" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The concurrent use of mesalamine with azathioprine or 6-mercaptopurine may increase the risk for blood disorders.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M27" type="Trigger" span="75 17" str="increase the risk"/>
<Mention id="M25" type="Precipitant" span="54 16" str="6-mercaptopurine" code="PKK6MUZ20G"/>
<Mention id="M29" type="SpecificInteraction" span="97 15" str="blood disorders" code="414027002: Disorder of hematopoietic structure (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M28" type="Precipitant" span="38 12" str="azathioprine" code="MRK240IY2L"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M27" precipitant="M25" effect="M29" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M27" precipitant="M28" effect="M29" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1061" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Assess renal function at the beginning of treatment and periodically during treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1062" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Mesalamine-induced acute intolerance syndrome has been reported.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1063" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Observe patients closely for worsening of these symptoms while on treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1064" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Use caution when treating patients who are hypersensitive to sulfasalazine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1065" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Mesalamine-induced cardiac hypersensitivity reactions (myocarditis and pericarditis) have been reported.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1066" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hepatic failure has been reported in patients with pre-existing liver disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1067" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Use caution when treating patients with liver disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1068" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Upper GI tract obstruction may delay onset of action.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1069" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients with pre-existing skin conditions have reported more severe photosensitivity reactions (5.6) Use of mesalamine may lead to spuriously elevated test results when measuring urinary normetanephrine by liquid chromatography with electrochemical detection.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1070" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Renal impairment, including minimal change nephropathy, acute and chronic interstitial nephritis, and, rarely, renal failure, has been reported in patients given products such as LIALDA that contain mesalamine or are converted to mesalamine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1071" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>It is recommended that patients have an evaluation of renal function prior to initiation of LIALDA therapy and periodically while on therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1072" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Exercise caution when using LIALDA in patients with known renal dysfunction or a history of renal disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1073" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In animal studies, the kidney was the principal organ for toxicity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1074" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Mesalamine has been associated with an acute intolerance syndrome that may be difficult to distinguish from an exacerbation of ulcerative colitis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1075" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Although the exact frequency of occurrence has not been determined, it has occurred in 3% of patients in controlled clinical trials of mesalamine or sulfasalazine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1076" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Symptoms include cramping, acute abdominal pain and bloody diarrhea, and sometimes fever, headache, and rash.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1077" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If acute intolerance syndrome is suspected, promptly discontinue treatment with LIALDA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1078" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Some patients who have experienced a hypersensitivity reaction to sulfasalazine may have a similar reaction to LIALDA tablets or to other compounds that contain or are converted to mesalamine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1079" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Mesalamine-induced cardiac hypersensitivity reactions (myocarditis and pericarditis) have been reported with LIALDA and other mesalamine medications.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1080" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Caution should be taken in prescribing this medicine to patients with conditions predisposing them to the development of myocarditis or pericarditis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1081" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There have been reports of hepatic failure in patients with pre-existing liver disease who have been administered mesalamine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1082" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Caution should be exercised when administering LIALDA to patients with liver disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1083" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Pyloric stenosis or other organic or functional obstruction in the upper gastrointestinal tract may cause prolonged gastric retention of LIALDA which would delay mesalamine release in the colon.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1084" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients with pre-existing skin conditions such as atopic dermatitis and atopic eczema have reported more severe photosensitivity reactions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1085" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Use of mesalamine may lead to spuriously elevated test results when measuring urinary normetanephrine by liquid chromatography with electrochemical detection because of the similarity in the chromatograms of normetanephrine and mesalamine's main metabolite, N-acetylaminosalicylic acid (N-Ac-5-ASA).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1086" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>An alternative, selective assay for normetanephrine should be considered.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1087" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mechanism of action of mesalamine is not fully understood, but appears to have a topical anti-inflammatory effect on the colonic epithelial cells.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1088" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Mucosal production of arachidonic acid metabolites, both through the cyclooxygenase and lipoxygenase pathways, is increased in patients with chronic inflammatory bowel disease, and it is possible that mesalamine diminishes inflammation by blocking cyclooxygenase and inhibiting prostaglandin production in the colon.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1089" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Mesalamine has the potential to inhibit the activation of nuclear factor kappa B (NFκB) and consequently the production of key pro-inflammatory cytokines.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1090" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>It has been proposed that reduced expression of PPARγ nuclear receptors (γ-form of peroxisome proliferator-activated receptors) may be implicated in ulcerative colitis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1091" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There is evidence that mesalamine produces pharmacodynamic effects through direct activation of PPARγ receptors in the colonic/rectal epithelium.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1092" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacodynamic actions of mesalamine occur in the colonic/rectal mucosae local to the delivery of drug from LIALDA into the lumen.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1093" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There is information suggesting that severity of colonic inflammation in ulcerative colitis patients treated with mesalamine is inversely correlated with mucosal concentrations of mesalamine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1094" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Plasma concentrations representing systemically absorbed mesalamine are not believed to contribute extensively to efficacy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1095" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Absorption The total absorption of mesalamine from LIALDA 2.4 g or 4.8 g given once daily for 14 days to healthy volunteers was found to be approximately 21-22% of the administered dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1096" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Gamma-scintigraphy studies have shown that a single dose of LIALDA 1.2 g (one tablet) passed intact through the upper gastrointestinal tract of fasted healthy volunteers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1097" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Scintigraphic images showed a trail of radio-labeled tracer in the colon, suggesting that mesalamine had distributed through this region of the gastrointestinal tract.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1098" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In a single dose study, LIALDA 1.2 g, 2.4 g and 4.8 g were administered in the fasted state to healthy subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1099" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Plasma concentrations of mesalamine were detectable after 2 hours and reached a maximum by 9-12 hours on average for the doses studied.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1100" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacokinetic parameters are highly variable among subjects (Table 3).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1101" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Mesalamine systemic exposure in terms of area under the plasma concentration-time curve (AUC) was slightly more than dose proportional between 1.2 g and 4.8 g LIALDA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1102" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Maximum plasma concentrations (Cmax) of mesalamine increased approximately dose proportionately between 1.2 g and 2.4 g and sub-proportionately between 2.4 g and 4.8 g LIALDA, with the dose normalized value at 4.8 g representing, on average, 74% of that at 2.4 g based on geometric means.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1103" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Table 3: Mean (SD) PK Parameters for Mesalamine Following Single Dose Administration of LIALDA Under Fasting Conditions Parameter1 of Mesalamine LIALDA 1.2 g(N=47) LIALDA 2.4 g(N=48) LIALDA 4.8 g(N=48) AUC0-t (ng.h/mL) 9039+ (5054) 20538 (12980) 41434 (26640) AUC0-∞ (ng.h/mL) 9578 (5214) 21084 (13185) 44775# (30302) Cmax (ng/mL) 857 (638) 1595 (1484) 2154 (1140) Tmax* (h) 9.0** (4.0-32.1) 12.0 (4.0-34.1) 12.0 (4.0-34.0) Tlag* (h) 2.0** (0-8.0) 2.0 (1.0-4.0) 2.0 (1.0-4.0) T1/2 (h) (Terminal Phase) 8.56 (6.38) 7.05§ (5.54) 7.25# (8.32) 1 Arithmetic mean of parameter values are presented except for Tmax and Tlag.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1104" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>*Median (min, max); +N=43, N=27, §N=33, #N=36, **N=46 Administration of a single dose of LIALDA 4.8 g with a high fat meal resulted in further delay in absorption, and plasma concentrations of mesalamine were detectable 4 hours following dosing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1105" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>However, a high fat meal increased systemic exposure of mesalamine (mean Cmax:↑ 91%; mean AUC: ↑ 16%) compared to results in the fasted state.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M30" type="Trigger" span="25 9;73 4" str="increased | Cmax"/>
<Mention id="M35" type="Precipitant" span="11 13" str="high fat meal" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M32" type="Trigger" span="25 27" str="increased systemic exposure"/>
<Mention id="M34" type="Trigger" span="25 9;90 3" str="increased | AUC"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M30" precipitant="M35" effect="C54602"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M32" precipitant="M35" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M34" precipitant="M35" effect="C54605"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1106" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>LIALDA was administered with food in the controlled clinical trials that supported its approval.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1107" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In a single and multiple dose pharmacokinetic study of LIALDA, 2.4 g or 4.8 g was administered once daily with standard meals to 28 healthy volunteers per dose group.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1108" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Plasma concentrations of mesalamine were detectable after 4 hours and were maximal by 8 hours after the single dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1109" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Steady state was achieved generally by 2 days after dosing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1110" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Mean AUC at steady state was only modestly greater (1.1- to 1.4-fold) than predictable from single dose pharmacokinetics.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1111" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In a single dose pharmacokinetic study of LIALDA, 4.8 g was administered in the fasted state to 71 healthy male and female volunteers (28 young (18-35yrs); 28 elderly (65-75yrs); 15 elderly (&gt;75yrs)).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1112" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Increased age resulted in increased systemic exposure (approximately 2-fold in Cmax), to mesalamine and its metabolite N-acetyl-5-aminosalicylic acid.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1113" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Increased age resulted in a slower apparent elimination of mesalamine, though there was high between-subject variability.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1114" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Systemic exposures in individual subjects were inversely correlated with renal function as assessed by estimated creatinine clearance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1115" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Table 4: Mean (SD) PK Parameters for Mesalamine Following Single Dose Administration of LIALDA 4.8 g under Fasting Conditions to Young and Elderly Subjects Parameter of 5-ASA Young Subjects(18-35 yrs)(N=28) Elderly Subjects(65-75 yrs)(N=28) Elderly Subjects(&gt;75 yrs)(N=15) AUC0-t (ng.h/mL) 51570 (23870) 73001 (42608) 65820 (25283) AUC0-∞ (ng.h/mL) 58057b (22429) 89612c (40596) 63067d (22531) Cmax (ng/mL) 2243 (1410) 4999 (4381) 4832 (4383) tmax a (h) 22.0 (5.98 - 48.0) 12.5 (4.00 - 36.0) 16.0 (4.00 - 26.0) tlag a (h) 2.00 (1.00 - 6.00) 2.00 (1.00 - 4.00) 2.00 (2.00 - 4.00) t1/2 (h), terminal phase 5.68b (2.83) 9.68c (7.47) 8.67d (5.84) Renal clearance (L/h) 2.05 (1.33) 2.04 (1.16) 2.13 (1.20) Arithmetic mean (SD) data are presented, N = Number of subjects a Median (min-max), bN=15, cN=16, dN=13 Distribution Mesalamine is approximately 43% bound to plasma proteins at the concentration of 2.5 μg/mL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1116" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Metabolism The only major metabolite of mesalamine (5-aminosalicylic acid) is N-acetyl-5-aminosalicylic acid.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1117" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Its formation is brought about by N-acetyltransferase (NAT) activity in the liver and intestinal mucosa cells, principally by NAT-1.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1118" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Elimination Elimination of mesalamine is mainly via the renal route following metabolism to N-acetyl-5-aminosalicylic acid (acetylation).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1119" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>However, there is also limited excretion of the parent drug in urine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1120" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Of the approximately 21-22% of the dose absorbed, less than 8% of the dose was excreted unchanged in the urine after 24 hours, compared with greater than 13% for N-acetyl-5-aminosalicylic acid.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1121" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The apparent terminal half-lives for mesalamine and its major metabolite after administration of LIALDA 2.4 g and 4.8 g were, on average, 7-9 hours and 8-12 hours, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1122" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Drug Interactions: The potential effect of LIALDA (4.8 g given once daily) on the pharmacokinetics of four commonly used antibiotics were evaluated in healthy subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1123" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The four antibiotics studied and their dosing regimens were as follows: amoxicillin (single 500 mg dose), ciprofloxacin XR (single 500 mg dose), metronidazole (750 mg twice daily for 3.5 days), and sulfamethoxazole/trimethoprim (800 mg/160 mg twice daily for 3.5 days).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1124" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Coadministration of LIALDA did not result in clinically significant changes in the pharmacokinetics of any of the four antibiotics.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1125" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The change in Cmax and AUC of amoxicillin, ciprofloxacin and metronidazole when they were co-administered with LIALDA were all ≤ 3%.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1126" LabelDrug="Lialda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There was an increase of 12% in Cmax and an increase of 15% in AUC of sulfamethoxazole when sulfamethoxazole/trimethoprim was coadministered with LIALDA.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M36" type="Trigger" span="13 8;63 3" str="increase | AUC"/>
<Mention id="M39" type="Precipitant" span="70 16" str="sulfamethoxazole" code="JE42381TNV"/>
<Mention id="M38" type="Trigger" span="13 8;32 4" str="increase | Cmax"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M36" precipitant="M39" effect="C54613"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M38" precipitant="M39" effect="C54610"/>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nephrotoxic agents" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="90708001: Kidney disease (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nsaids" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="90708001: Kidney disease (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="6-mercaptopurine" precipitantCode="PKK6MUZ20G" effect="414027002: Disorder of hematopoietic structure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="azathioprine" precipitantCode="MRK240IY2L" effect="414027002: Disorder of hematopoietic structure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="90708001: Kidney disease (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="high fat meal" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="high fat meal" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54602"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="high fat meal" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54605"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="sulfamethoxazole" precipitantCode="JE42381TNV" effect="C54610"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="sulfamethoxazole" precipitantCode="JE42381TNV" effect="C54613"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>