<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Saxenda" setid="3946d389-0926-4f77-a708-0acb8153b143">
<Text><Section name="Boxed Warning section" id="34066-1">
• Liraglutide causes dose-dependent and treatment-duration-dependent thyroid C-cell tumors at clinically relevant exposures in both genders of rats and mice. It is unknown whether Saxenda causes thyroid C-cell tumors, including medullary thyroid carcinoma (MTC), in humans, as the human relevance of liraglutide-induced rodent thyroid C-cell tumors has not been determined [see Warnings and Precautions ( 5.1 ) and Nonclinical Toxicology ( 13.1 )] . • Saxenda is contraindicated in patients with a personal or family history of MTC and in patients with Multiple Endocrine Neoplasia syndrome type 2 (MEN 2). Counsel patients regarding the potential risk of MTC with use of Saxenda and inform them of symptoms of thyroid tumors (e.g., a mass in the neck, dysphagia, dyspnea, persistent hoarseness). Routine monitoring of serum calcitonin or using thyroid ultrasound is of uncertain value for early detection of MTC in patients treated with Saxenda [see Contraindications ( 4 ), Warnings and Precautions ( 5.1 )]. WARNING: RISK OF THYROID C-CELL TUMORS See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning. • Liraglutide causes thyroid C-cell tumors at clinically relevant exposures in both genders of rats and mice. It is unknown whether Saxenda causes thyroid C-cell tumors, including medullary thyroid carcinoma (MTC), in humans, as the human relevance of liraglutide-induced rodent thyroid C-cell tumors has not been determined ( 5.1 ). • Saxenda is contraindicated in patients with a personal or family history of MTC or in patients with Multiple Endocrine Neoplasia syndrome type 2 (MEN 2). Counsel patients regarding the potential risk of MTC and the symptoms of thyroid tumors ( 4 , 5.1 , 13.1 ).</Section>
<Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
Saxenda is contraindicated in: • Patients with a personal or family history of medullary thyroid carcinoma (MTC) or patients with Multiple Endocrine Neoplasia syndrome type 2 (MEN 2) [see Warnings and Precautions ( 5.1 )]. • Patients with a prior serious hypersensitivity reaction to liraglutide or to any of the product components [see Warnings and Precautions ( 5.7 )]. • Pregnancy [see Use in Specific Populations ( 8.1 )]. • Personal or family history of medullary thyroid carcinoma or Multiple Endocrine Neoplasia syndrome type 2 ( 4 , 5.1 ). • Hypersensitivity to liraglutide or any product components ( 4 , 5.7 ). • Pregnancy ( 4 , 8.1 ).</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
The recommended dosage of Saxenda is 3 mg daily. The dose escalation schedule in Table 1 should be used to reduce the likelihood of gastrointestinal symptoms. If patients do not tolerate an increased dose during dose escalation, consider delaying dose escalation for approximately one additional week. Saxenda should be discontinued, however, if a patient cannot tolerate the 3 mg dose, as efficacy has not been established at lower doses (0.6, 1.2, 1.8, and 2.4 mg). Table 1. Dose Escalation Schedule Week Daily Dose 1 0.6 mg 2 1.2 mg 3 1.8 mg 4 2.4 mg 5 and onward 3 mg Saxenda should be taken once daily at any time of day, without regard to the timing of meals. Saxenda can be injected subcutaneously in the abdomen, thigh, or upper arm. The injection site and timing can be changed without dose adjustment. Saxenda must not be administered intravenously or intramuscularly. When initiating Saxenda in patients taking insulin secretagogues (such as sulfonylureas), consider reducing the dose of the insulin secretagogue (for example, by one-half) to reduce the risk for hypoglycemia, and monitor blood glucose. Saxenda and insulin should not be used together [see Warnings and Precautions ( 5.4 ) and Adverse Reactions ( 6.1 )]. Conversely, if discontinuing Saxenda in patients with type 2 diabetes, monitor for an increase in blood glucose. Evaluate the change in body weight 16 weeks after initiating Saxenda and discontinue Saxenda if the patient has not lost at least 4% of baseline body weight, since it is unlikely that the patient will achieve and sustain clinically meaningful weight loss with continued treatment. If a dose is missed, the once-daily regimen should be resumed as prescribed with the next scheduled dose. An extra dose or increase in dose should not be taken to make up for the missed dose. If more than 3 days have elapsed since the last Saxenda dose, patients should reinitiate Saxenda at 0.6 mg daily and follow the dose escalation schedule in Table 1, which may reduce the occurrence of gastrointestinal symptoms associated with reinitiation of treatment. Prior to initiation of Saxenda, patients should be trained by their healthcare professional on proper injection technique. Training reduces the risk of administration errors such as needle sticks and incomplete dosing. Refer to the accompanying Instructions for Use for complete administration instructions with illustrations. Saxenda solution should be inspected prior to each injection, and the solution should be used only if it is clear, colorless, and contains no particles. BMI is calculated by dividing weight in (kilograms) by height (in meters) squared. A chart for determining BMI based on height and weight is provided in Table 2. Table 2. BMI Conversion Chart • Recommended dose of Saxenda is 3 mg daily. Administer at any time of day, without regard to the timing of meals ( 2 ). • Initiate at 0.6 mg per day for one week. In weekly intervals, increase the dose until a dose of 3 mg is reached ( 2 ). • Inject subcutaneously in the abdomen, thigh or upper arm ( 2 ). • The injection site and timing can be changed without dose adjustment ( 2 ). Image 1</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
• Saxenda delays gastric emptying. May impact absorption of concomitantly administered oral medications. Use with caution ( 7 ). Saxenda causes a delay of gastric emptying, and thereby has the potential to impact the absorption of concomitantly administered oral medications. In clinical pharmacology trials, liraglutide did not affect the absorption of the tested orally administered medications to any clinically relevant degree. Nonetheless, monitor for potential consequences of delayed absorption of oral medications concomitantly administered with Saxenda.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
• Thyroid C-cell Tumors: See Boxed Warning ( 5.1 ). • Acute Pancreatitis: Discontinue promptly if pancreatitis is suspected. Do not restart if pancreatitis is confirmed ( 5.2 ). • Acute Gallbladder Disease: If cholelithiasis or cholecystitis are suspected, gallbladder studies are indicated ( 5.3 ). • Serious Hypoglycemia: Can occur when Saxenda is used with an insulin secretagogue (e.g. a sulfonylurea). Consider lowering the dose of anti-diabetic drugs to reduce the risk of hypoglycemia ( 2 , 5.4 ). • Heart Rate Increase: Monitor heart rate at regular intervals ( 5.5 ). • Renal Impairment: Has been reported post-marketing, usually in association with nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, or dehydration which may sometimes require hemodialysis. Use caution when initiating or escalating doses of Saxenda in patients with renal impairment ( 5.6 ). • Hypersensitivity Reactions: Post-marketing reports of serious hypersensitivity reactions (e.g., anaphylactic reactions and angioedema). Discontinue Saxenda and other suspect medications and promptly seek medical advice ( 5.7 ). • Suicidal Behavior and Ideation: Monitor for depression or suicidal thoughts. Discontinue Saxenda if symptoms develop ( 5.8 ). Liraglutide causes dose-dependent and treatment-duration-dependent thyroid C-cell tumors (adenomas and/or carcinomas) at clinically relevant exposures in both genders of rats and mice [see Nonclinical Toxicology ( 13.1 )] . Malignant thyroid C-cell carcinomas were detected in rats and mice. It is unknown whether Saxenda will cause thyroid C-cell tumors, including medullary thyroid carcinoma (MTC), in humans, as the human relevance of liraglutide-induced rodent thyroid C-cell tumors has not been determined. Cases of MTC in patients treated with liraglutide have been reported in the post-marketing period; the data in these reports are insufficient to establish or exclude a causal relationship between MTC and liraglutide use in humans. Saxenda is contraindicated in patients with a personal or family history of MTC or in patients with MEN 2. Counsel patients regarding the potential risk for MTC with the use of Saxenda and inform them of symptoms of thyroid tumors (e.g., a mass in the neck, dysphagia, dyspnea, persistent hoarseness). Routine monitoring of serum calcitonin or using thyroid ultrasound is of uncertain value for early detection of MTC in patients treated with Saxenda. Such monitoring may increase the risk of unnecessary procedures, due to low test specificity for serum calcitonin and a high background incidence of thyroid disease. Significantly elevated serum calcitonin may indicate MTC, and patients with MTC usually have calcitonin values greater than 50 ng/L. If serum calcitonin is measured and found to be elevated, the patient should be further evaluated. Patients with thyroid nodules noted on physical examination or neck imaging should also be further evaluated. Based on spontaneous post-marketing reports, acute pancreatitis, including fatal and non-fatal hemorrhagic or necrotizing pancreatitis, has been observed in patients treated with liraglutide. After initiation of Saxenda, observe patients carefully for signs and symptoms of pancreatitis (including persistent severe abdominal pain, sometimes radiating to the back and which may or may not be accompanied by vomiting). If pancreatitis is suspected, Saxenda should promptly be discontinued and appropriate management should be initiated. If pancreatitis is confirmed, Saxenda should not be restarted. In Saxenda clinical trials, acute pancreatitis was confirmed by adjudication in 9 (0.3%) of 3291 Saxenda-treated patients and 2 (0.1%) of 1843 placebo-treated patients. In addition, there were 2 cases of acute pancreatitis in Saxenda-treated patients who prematurely withdrew from these clinical trials, occurring 74 and 124 days after the last dose. There were 2 additional cases in Saxenda-treated patients, 1 during an off-treatment follow-up period within 2 weeks of discontinuing Saxenda, and 1 that occurred in a patient who completed treatment and was off-treatment for 106 days. Liraglutide has been studied in a limited number of patients with a history of pancreatitis. It is unknown if patients with a history of pancreatitis are at higher risk for development of pancreatitis on Saxenda. In Saxenda clinical trials, 2.2% of Saxenda-treated patients reported adverse events of cholelithiasis versus 0.8% of placebo-treated patients. The incidence of cholecystitis was 0.8% in Saxenda-treated patients versus 0.4% in placebo-treated patients. The majority of Saxenda-treated patients with adverse events of cholelithiasis and cholecystitis required cholecystectomy. Substantial or rapid weight loss can increase the risk of cholelithiasis; however, the incidence of acute gallbladder disease was greater in Saxenda-treated patients than in placebo-treated patients even after accounting for the degree of weight loss. If cholelithiasis is suspected, gallbladder studies and appropriate clinical follow-up are indicated. The risk for serious hypoglycemia is increased when Saxenda is used in combination with insulin secretagogues (for example, sulfonylureas) in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus. Therefore, patients may require a lower dose of sulfonylurea (or other concomitantly administered insulin secretagogues) in this setting [see Dosage and Administration ( 2 ) and Adverse Reactions ( 6.1 )] . Saxenda should not be used in patients taking insulin. Saxenda can lower blood glucose [see Clinical Pharmacology ( 12.2 )] . Monitor blood glucose parameters prior to starting Saxenda and during Saxenda treatment in patients with type 2 diabetes. If needed, adjust co-administered anti-diabetic drugs based on glucose monitoring results and risk of hypoglycemia. Mean increases in resting heart rate of 2 to 3 beats per minute (bpm) were observed with routine clinical monitoring in Saxenda-treated patients compared to placebo in clinical trials. More patients treated with Saxenda, compared with placebo, had changes from baseline at two consecutive visits of more than 10 bpm (34% versus 19%, respectively) and 20 bpm (5% versus 2%, respectively). At least one resting heart rate exceeding 100 bpm was recorded for 6% of Saxenda-treated patients compared with 4% of placebo-treated patients, with this occurring at two consecutive study visits for 0.9% and 0.3%, respectively. Tachycardia was reported as an adverse reaction in 0.6% of Saxenda-treated patients and in 0.1% of placebo-treated patients. In a clinical pharmacology trial that monitored heart rate continuously for 24 hours, Saxenda treatment was associated with a heart rate that was 4 to 9 bpm higher than that observed with placebo. Heart rate should be monitored at regular intervals consistent with usual clinical practice. Patients should inform health care providers of palpitations or feelings of a racing heartbeat while at rest during Saxenda treatment. For patients who experience a sustained increase in resting heart rate while taking Saxenda, Saxenda should be discontinued. In patients treated with GLP-1 receptor agonists, including Saxenda, there have been reports of acute renal failure and worsening of chronic renal failure, sometimes requiring hemodialysis [see Adverse Reactions ( 6.2 )] . Some of these events were reported in patients without known underlying renal disease. A majority of the reported events occurred in patients who had experienced nausea, vomiting, or diarrhea leading to volume depletion. Some of the reported events occurred in patients receiving one or more medications known to affect renal function or volume status. Altered renal function has been reversed in many of the reported cases with supportive treatment and discontinuation of potentially causative agents, including liraglutide. Use caution when initiating or escalating doses of Saxenda in patients with renal impairment [see Use in Specific Populations ( 8.6 )] . There have been reports of serious hypersensitivity reactions (e.g., anaphylactic reactions and angioedema) in patients treated with liraglutide [see Contraindications ( 4 ) and Adverse Reactions ( 6.1 , 6.2 )] . If a hypersensitivity reaction occurs, the patient should discontinue Saxenda and other suspect medications and promptly seek medical advice. Anaphylaxis and angioedema have been reported with other GLP-1 receptor agonists. Use caution in a patient with a history of anaphylaxis or angioedema with another GLP-1 receptor agonist because it is unknown whether such patients will be predisposed to these reactions with Saxenda. In Saxenda clinical trials, 9 (0.3%) of 3384 Saxenda-treated patients and 2 (0.1%) of the 1941 placebo-treated patients reported suicidal ideation; one of these Saxenda-treated patients attempted suicide. Patients treated with Saxenda should be monitored for the emergence or worsening of depression, suicidal thoughts or behavior, and/or any unusual changes in mood or behavior. Discontinue Saxenda in patients who experience suicidal thoughts or behaviors. Avoid Saxenda in patients with a history of suicidal attempts or active suicidal ideation.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Liraglutide is an acylated human glucagon-like peptide-1 (GLP-1) receptor agonist with 97% amino acid sequence homology to endogenous human GLP-1(7-37). Like endogenous GLP-1, liraglutide binds to and activates the GLP-1 receptor, a cell-surface receptor coupled to adenylyl cyclase activation through the stimulatory G-protein, Gs. Endogenous GLP-1 has a half-life of 1.5-2 minutes due to degradation by the ubiquitous endogenous enzymes, dipeptidyl peptidase 4 (DPP-4) and neutral endopeptidases (NEP). Unlike native GLP-1, liraglutide is stable against metabolic degradation by both peptidases and has a plasma half-life of 13 hours after subcutaneous administration. The pharmacokinetic profile of liraglutide, which makes it suitable for once-daily administration, is a result of self-association that delays absorption, plasma protein binding, and stability against metabolic degradation by DPP-4 and NEP. GLP-1 is a physiological regulator of appetite and calorie intake, and the GLP-1 receptor is present in several areas of the brain involved in appetite regulation. In animal studies, peripheral administration of liraglutide resulted in the presence of liraglutide in specific brain regions regulating appetite, including the hypothalamus. Although liraglutide activated neurons in brain regions known to regulate appetite, specific brain regions mediating the effects of liraglutide on appetite were not identified in rats. Liraglutide lowers body weight through decreased calorie intake. Liraglutide does not increase 24-hour energy expenditure. As with other GLP-1 receptor agonists, liraglutide stimulates insulin secretion and reduces glucagon secretion in a glucose-dependent manner. These effects can lead to a reduction of blood glucose. Cardiac Electrophysiology (QTc) in healthy volunteers The effect of liraglutide on cardiac repolarization was tested in a QTc study. Liraglutide at steady-state concentrations after daily doses up to 1.8 mg did not produce QTc prolongation. The maximum liraglutide plasma concentration (C max ) in overweight and obese subjects treated with liraglutide 3 mg is similar to the C max observed in the liraglutide QTc study in healthy volunteers. Absorption - Following subcutaneous administration, maximum concentrations of liraglutide are achieved at 11 hours post dosing. The average liraglutide steady state concentration (AUCτ /24 ) reached approximately 116 ng/mL in obese (BMI 30-40 kg/m 2 ) subjects following administration of Saxenda. Liraglutide exposure increased proportionally in the dose range of 0.6 mg to 3 mg. The intra-subject coefficient of variation for liraglutide AUC was 11% following single dose administration. Liraglutide exposures were considered similar among three subcutaneous injection sites (upper arm, abdomen, and thigh). Absolute bioavailability of liraglutide following subcutaneous administration is approximately 55%. Distribution - The mean apparent volume of distribution after subcutaneous administration of liraglutide 3 mg is 20-25 L (for a person weighing approximately 100 kg). The mean volume of distribution after intravenous administration of liraglutide is 0.07 L/kg. Liraglutide is extensively bound to plasma protein (greater than 98%). Metabolism - During the initial 24 hours following administration of a single [3H]-liraglutide dose to healthy subjects, the major component in plasma was intact liraglutide. Liraglutide is endogenously metabolized in a similar manner to large proteins without a specific organ as a major route of elimination. Elimination - Following a [3H]-liraglutide dose, intact liraglutide was not detected in urine or feces. Only a minor part of the administered radioactivity was excreted as liraglutide-related metabolites in urine or feces (6% and 5%, respectively). The majority of urine and feces radioactivity was excreted during the first 6-8 days. The mean apparent clearance following subcutaneous administration of a single dose of liraglutide is approximately 0.9-1.4 L/h with an elimination half-life of approximately 13 hours, making liraglutide suitable for once daily administration. Specific Populations Elderly - No dosage adjustment is required based on age. Age had no effect on the pharmacokinetics of liraglutide based on a pharmacokinetic study in healthy elderly subjects (65 to 83 years) and population pharmacokinetic analyses of data from overweight and obese patients 18 to 82 years of age [see Use in Specific Populations ( 8.5 )] . Gender - Based on the results of population pharmacokinetic analyses, females have 24% lower weight adjusted clearance of Saxenda compared to males. Based on the exposure response data, no dose adjustment is necessary based on gender. Race and Ethnicity - Race and ethnicity had no effect on the pharmacokinetics of liraglutide based on the results of population pharmacokinetic analyses that included overweight and obese patients of Caucasian, Black, Asian and Hispanic/Non-Hispanic groups. Body Weight - Body weight significantly affects the pharmacokinetics of liraglutide based on results of population pharmacokinetic analyses conducted in patients with body weight range of 60-234 kg. The exposure of liraglutide decreases as baseline body weight increases. Pediatric - Saxenda has not been studied in pediatric patients [see Use in Specific Populations ( 8.4 )] . Renal Impairment - The single-dose pharmacokinetics of liraglutide were evaluated in subjects with varying degrees of renal impairment. Subjects with mild (estimated creatinine clearance 50-80 mL/min) to severe (estimated creatinine clearance less than 30 mL/min) renal impairment and subjects with end-stage renal disease requiring dialysis were included in the trial. Compared to healthy subjects, liraglutide AUC in mild, moderate, and severe renal impairment and in end-stage renal disease was on average 35%, 19%, 29% and 30% lower, respectively [see Use in Specific Populations ( 8.6 )] . Hepatic Impairment - The single-dose pharmacokinetics of liraglutide were evaluated in subjects with varying degrees of hepatic impairment. Subjects with mild (Child Pugh score 5-6) to severe (Child Pugh score greater than 9) hepatic impairment were included in the trial. Compared to healthy subjects, liraglutide AUC in subjects with mild, moderate and severe hepatic impairment was on average 11%, 14% and 42% lower, respectively [see Use in Specific Populations ( 8.7)]. Drug Interactions In vitro assessment of drug−drug interactions Liraglutide has low potential for pharmacokinetic drug-drug interactions related to cytochrome P450 (CYP) and plasma protein binding. In vivo assessment of drug−drug interactions The drug-drug interaction studies were performed at steady state with liraglutide 1.8 mg/day. The effect on rate of gastric emptying was equivalent between liraglutide 1.8 mg and 3 mg (acetaminophen AUC 0-300min ). Administration of the interacting drugs was timed so that C max of liraglutide (8-12 h) would coincide with the absorption peak of the co-administered drugs. Oral Contraceptives A single dose of an oral contraceptive combination product containing 0.03 mg ethinylestradiol and 0.15 mg levonorgestrel was administered under fed conditions and 7 hours after the dose of liraglutide at steady state. Liraglutide lowered ethinylestradiol and levonorgestrel C max by 12% and 13%, respectively. There was no effect of liraglutide on the overall exposure (AUC) of ethinylestradiol. Liraglutide increased the levonorgestrel AUC 0-∞ by 18%. Liraglutide delayed T max for both ethinylestradiol and levonorgestrel by 1.5 h. Digoxin A single dose of digoxin 1 mg was administered 7 hours after the dose of liraglutide at steady state. The concomitant administration with liraglutide resulted in a reduction of digoxin AUC by 16%; C max decreased by 31%. Digoxin median time to maximal concentration (T max ) was delayed from 1 h to 1.5 h. Lisinopril A single dose of lisinopril 20 mg was administered 5 minutes after the dose of liraglutide at steady state. The co-administration with liraglutide resulted in a reduction of lisinopril AUC by 15%; C max decreased by 27%. Lisinopril median T max was delayed from 6 h to 8 h with liraglutide. Atorvastatin Liraglutide did not change the overall exposure (AUC) of atorvastatin following a single dose of atorvastatin 40 mg, administered 5 hours after the dose of liraglutide at steady state. Atorvastatin C max was decreased by 38% and median T max was delayed from 1 h to 3 h with liraglutide. Acetaminophen Liraglutide did not change the overall exposure (AUC) of acetaminophen following a single dose of acetaminophen 1000 mg, administered 8 hours after the dose of liraglutide at steady state. Acetaminophen C max was decreased by 31% and median T max was delayed up to 15 minutes. Griseofulvin Liraglutide did not change the overall exposure (AUC) of griseofulvin following co-administration of a single dose of griseofulvin 500 mg with liraglutide at steady state. Griseofulvin C max increased by 37% while median T max did not change. Insulin Detemir No pharmacokinetic interaction was observed between liraglutide and insulin detemir when separate subcutaneous injections of insulin detemir 0.5 Unit/kg (single-dose) and liraglutide 1.8 mg (steady state) were administered to patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="739" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Liraglutide causes dose-dependent and treatment-duration-dependent thyroid C-cell tumors at clinically relevant exposures in both genders of rats and mice.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="740" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>It is unknown whether Saxenda causes thyroid C-cell tumors, including medullary thyroid carcinoma (MTC), in humans, as the human relevance of liraglutide-induced rodent thyroid C-cell tumors has not been determined.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="741" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Saxenda is contraindicated in patients with a personal or family history of MTC and in patients with Multiple Endocrine Neoplasia syndrome type 2 (MEN 2).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="742" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Counsel patients regarding the potential risk of MTC with use of Saxenda and inform them of symptoms of thyroid tumors (e.g., a mass in the neck, dysphagia, dyspnea, persistent hoarseness).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="743" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Routine monitoring of serum calcitonin or using thyroid ultrasound is of uncertain value for early detection of MTC in patients treated with Saxenda.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="744" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>WARNING: RISK OF THYROID C-CELL TUMORS See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="745" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Liraglutide causes thyroid C-cell tumors at clinically relevant exposures in both genders of rats and mice.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="746" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>It is unknown whether Saxenda causes thyroid C-cell tumors, including medullary thyroid carcinoma (MTC), in humans, as the human relevance of liraglutide-induced rodent thyroid C-cell tumors has not been determined (5.1).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="747" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Saxenda is contraindicated in patients with a personal or family history of MTC or in patients with Multiple Endocrine Neoplasia syndrome type 2 (MEN 2).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="748" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Counsel patients regarding the potential risk of MTC and the symptoms of thyroid tumors (4, 5.1, 13.1).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="749" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Saxenda is contraindicated in: Patients with a personal or family history of medullary thyroid carcinoma (MTC) or patients with Multiple Endocrine Neoplasia syndrome type 2 (MEN 2).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="750" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Patients with a prior serious hypersensitivity reaction to liraglutide or to any of the product components.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="751" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Pregnancy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="752" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Personal or family history of medullary thyroid carcinoma or Multiple Endocrine Neoplasia syndrome type 2 (4, 5.1).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="753" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Hypersensitivity to liraglutide or any product components (4, 5.7).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="754" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommended dosage of Saxenda is 3 mg daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="755" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The dose escalation schedule in Table 1 should be used to reduce the likelihood of gastrointestinal symptoms.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="756" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If patients do not tolerate an increased dose during dose escalation, consider delaying dose escalation for approximately one additional week.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="757" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Saxenda should be discontinued, however, if a patient cannot tolerate the 3 mg dose, as efficacy has not been established at lower doses (0.6, 1.2, 1.8, and 2.4 mg).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="758" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dose Escalation Schedule Week Daily Dose 1 0.6 mg 2 1.2 mg 3 1.8 mg 4 2.4 mg 5 and onward 3 mg Saxenda should be taken once daily at any time of day, without regard to the timing of meals.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="759" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Saxenda can be injected subcutaneously in the abdomen, thigh, or upper arm.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="760" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The injection site and timing can be changed without dose adjustment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="761" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Saxenda must not be administered intravenously or intramuscularly.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="762" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>When initiating Saxenda in patients taking insulin secretagogues (such as sulfonylureas), consider reducing the dose of the insulin secretagogue (for example, by one-half) to reduce the risk for hypoglycemia, and monitor blood glucose.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M7" type="Trigger" span="213 7" str="monitor"/>
<Mention id="M5" type="Precipitant" span="43 20" str="insulin secretagogue" code="N0000009360"/>
<Mention id="M9" type="SpecificInteraction" span="221 13" str="blood glucose" code="166922008: Blood glucose abnormal (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M10" type="Trigger" span="186 8" str="risk for"/>
<Mention id="M12" type="SpecificInteraction" span="195 12" str="hypoglycemia" code="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M11" type="Precipitant" span="74 13" str="sulfonylureas" code="N0000175608 | N0000008054"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M7" precipitant="M5" effect="M9" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M10" precipitant="M5" effect="M12" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M7" precipitant="M11" effect="M9" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M10" precipitant="M11" effect="M12" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="763" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Saxenda and insulin should not be used together.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M13" type="Trigger" span="20 18" str="should not be used"/>
<Mention id="M14" type="Precipitant" span="12 7" str="insulin" code="N0000004931 | N0000175944"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M13" precipitant="M14"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="764" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Conversely, if discontinuing Saxenda in patients with type 2 diabetes, monitor for an increase in blood glucose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="765" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Evaluate the change in body weight 16 weeks after initiating Saxenda and discontinue Saxenda if the patient has not lost at least 4% of baseline body weight, since it is unlikely that the patient will achieve and sustain clinically meaningful weight loss with continued treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="766" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If a dose is missed, the once-daily regimen should be resumed as prescribed with the next scheduled dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="767" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>An extra dose or increase in dose should not be taken to make up for the missed dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="768" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If more than 3 days have elapsed since the last Saxenda dose, patients should reinitiate Saxenda at 0.6 mg daily and follow the dose escalation schedule in Table 1, which may reduce the occurrence of gastrointestinal symptoms associated with reinitiation of treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="769" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Prior to initiation of Saxenda, patients should be trained by their healthcare professional on proper injection technique.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="770" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Training reduces the risk of administration errors such as needle sticks and incomplete dosing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="771" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Refer to the accompanying Instructions for Use for complete administration instructions with illustrations.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="772" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Saxenda solution should be inspected prior to each injection, and the solution should be used only if it is clear, colorless, and contains no particles.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="773" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>BMI is calculated by dividing weight in (kilograms) by height (in meters) squared.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="774" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>A chart for determining BMI based on height and weight is provided in Table 2.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="775" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>BMI Conversion Chart Recommended dose of Saxenda is 3 mg daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="776" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Administer at any time of day, without regard to the timing of meals (2).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="777" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Initiate at 0.6 mg per day for one week.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="778" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In weekly intervals, increase the dose until a dose of 3 mg is reached (2).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="779" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Inject subcutaneously in the abdomen, thigh or upper arm (2).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="780" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The injection site and timing can be changed without dose adjustment (2).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="781" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>May impact absorption of concomitantly administered oral medications.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="782" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Saxenda causes a delay of gastric emptying, and thereby has the potential to impact the absorption of concomitantly administered oral medications.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="783" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>In clinical pharmacology trials, liraglutide did not affect the absorption of the tested orally administered medications to any clinically relevant degree.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="784" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Nonetheless, monitor for potential consequences of delayed absorption of oral medications concomitantly administered with Saxenda.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="785" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Thyroid C-cell Tumors: See Boxed Warning (5.1).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="786" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Acute Pancreatitis: Discontinue promptly if pancreatitis is suspected.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="787" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Do not restart if pancreatitis is confirmed (5.2).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="788" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Acute Gallbladder Disease: If cholelithiasis or cholecystitis are suspected, gallbladder studies are indicated (5.3).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="789" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Serious Hypoglycemia: Can occur when Saxenda is used with an insulin secretagogue (e.g. a sulfonylurea).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M18" type="Trigger" span="26 5" str="occur"/>
<Mention id="M16" type="Precipitant" span="61 20" str="insulin secretagogue" code="N0000009360"/>
<Mention id="M20" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 20" str="Serious Hypoglycemia" code="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M19" type="Precipitant" span="90 12" str="sulfonylurea" code="N0000175608 | N0000008054"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M18" precipitant="M16" effect="M20" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M18" precipitant="M19" effect="M20" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="790" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Consider lowering the dose of anti-diabetic drugs to reduce the risk of hypoglycemia (2, 5.4).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M21" type="Trigger" span="64 7" str="risk of"/>
<Mention id="M22" type="Precipitant" span="30 19" str="anti-diabetic drugs" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M23" type="SpecificInteraction" span="72 12" str="hypoglycemia" code="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M21" precipitant="M22" effect="M23" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="791" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Heart Rate Increase: Monitor heart rate at regular intervals (5.5).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="792" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Renal Impairment: Has been reported post-marketing, usually in association with nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, or dehydration which may sometimes require hemodialysis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="793" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Use caution when initiating or escalating doses of Saxenda in patients with renal impairment (5.6).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="794" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hypersensitivity Reactions: Post-marketing reports of serious hypersensitivity reactions (e.g., anaphylactic reactions and angioedema).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="795" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Discontinue Saxenda and other suspect medications and promptly seek medical advice (5.7).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="796" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Suicidal Behavior and Ideation: Monitor for depression or suicidal thoughts.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="797" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Discontinue Saxenda if symptoms develop (5.8).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="798" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Liraglutide causes dose-dependent and treatment-duration-dependent thyroid C-cell tumors (adenomas and/or carcinomas) at clinically relevant exposures in both genders of rats and mice.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="799" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Malignant thyroid C-cell carcinomas were detected in rats and mice.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="800" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>It is unknown whether Saxenda will cause thyroid C-cell tumors, including medullary thyroid carcinoma (MTC), in humans, as the human relevance of liraglutide-induced rodent thyroid C-cell tumors has not been determined.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="801" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Cases of MTC in patients treated with liraglutide have been reported in the post-marketing period; the data in these reports are insufficient to establish or exclude a causal relationship between MTC and liraglutide use in humans.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="802" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Saxenda is contraindicated in patients with a personal or family history of MTC or in patients with MEN 2.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="803" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Counsel patients regarding the potential risk for MTC with the use of Saxenda and inform them of symptoms of thyroid tumors (e.g., a mass in the neck, dysphagia, dyspnea, persistent hoarseness).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="804" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Such monitoring may increase the risk of unnecessary procedures, due to low test specificity for serum calcitonin and a high background incidence of thyroid disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="805" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Significantly elevated serum calcitonin may indicate MTC, and patients with MTC usually have calcitonin values greater than 50 ng/L.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="806" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If serum calcitonin is measured and found to be elevated, the patient should be further evaluated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="807" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients with thyroid nodules noted on physical examination or neck imaging should also be further evaluated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="808" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Based on spontaneous post-marketing reports, acute pancreatitis, including fatal and non-fatal hemorrhagic or necrotizing pancreatitis, has been observed in patients treated with liraglutide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="809" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>After initiation of Saxenda, observe patients carefully for signs and symptoms of pancreatitis (including persistent severe abdominal pain, sometimes radiating to the back and which may or may not be accompanied by vomiting).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="810" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If pancreatitis is suspected, Saxenda should promptly be discontinued and appropriate management should be initiated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="811" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If pancreatitis is confirmed, Saxenda should not be restarted.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="812" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In Saxenda clinical trials, acute pancreatitis was confirmed by adjudication in 9 (0.3%) of 3291 Saxenda-treated patients and 2 (0.1%) of 1843 placebo-treated patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="813" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In addition, there were 2 cases of acute pancreatitis in Saxenda-treated patients who prematurely withdrew from these clinical trials, occurring 74 and 124 days after the last dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="814" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There were 2 additional cases in Saxenda-treated patients, 1 during an off-treatment follow-up period within 2 weeks of discontinuing Saxenda, and 1 that occurred in a patient who completed treatment and was off-treatment for 106 days.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="815" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Liraglutide has been studied in a limited number of patients with a history of pancreatitis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="816" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>It is unknown if patients with a history of pancreatitis are at higher risk for development of pancreatitis on Saxenda.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="817" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In Saxenda clinical trials, 2.2% of Saxenda-treated patients reported adverse events of cholelithiasis versus 0.8% of placebo-treated patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="818" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The incidence of cholecystitis was 0.8% in Saxenda-treated patients versus 0.4% in placebo-treated patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="819" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The majority of Saxenda-treated patients with adverse events of cholelithiasis and cholecystitis required cholecystectomy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="820" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Substantial or rapid weight loss can increase the risk of cholelithiasis; however, the incidence of acute gallbladder disease was greater in Saxenda-treated patients than in placebo-treated patients even after accounting for the degree of weight loss.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="821" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If cholelithiasis is suspected, gallbladder studies and appropriate clinical follow-up are indicated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="822" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The risk for serious hypoglycemia is increased when Saxenda is used in combination with insulin secretagogues (for example, sulfonylureas) in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M27" type="Trigger" span="4 4;37 9" str="risk | increased"/>
<Mention id="M25" type="Precipitant" span="88 21" str="insulin secretagogues" code="N0000009360"/>
<Mention id="M29" type="SpecificInteraction" span="13 20" str="Serious Hypoglycemia" code="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M28" type="Precipitant" span="124 13" str="sulfonylureas" code="N0000175608 | N0000008054"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M27" precipitant="M25" effect="M29" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M27" precipitant="M28" effect="M29" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="823" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Therefore, patients may require a lower dose of sulfonylurea (or other concomitantly administered insulin secretagogues) in this setting.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M32" type="Trigger" span="34 10" str="lower dose"/>
<Mention id="M31" type="Precipitant" span="98 21" str="insulin secretagogues" code="N0000009360"/>
<Mention id="M33" type="Precipitant" span="48 12" str="sulfonylurea" code="N0000175608 | N0000008054"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M32" precipitant="M31"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M32" precipitant="M33"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="824" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Saxenda should not be used in patients taking insulin.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M34" type="Trigger" span="8 18" str="should not be used"/>
<Mention id="M35" type="Precipitant" span="46 7" str="insulin" code="N0000004931 | N0000175944"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M34" precipitant="M35"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="825" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Saxenda can lower blood glucose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="826" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor blood glucose parameters prior to starting Saxenda and during Saxenda treatment in patients with type 2 diabetes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="827" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If needed, adjust co-administered anti-diabetic drugs based on glucose monitoring results and risk of hypoglycemia.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M36" type="Trigger" span="94 7" str="risk of"/>
<Mention id="M37" type="Precipitant" span="34 19" str="anti-diabetic drugs" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M38" type="SpecificInteraction" span="102 12" str="hypoglycemia" code="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M36" precipitant="M37" effect="M38" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="828" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Mean increases in resting heart rate of 2 to 3 beats per minute (bpm) were observed with routine clinical monitoring in Saxenda-treated patients compared to placebo in clinical trials.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="829" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>More patients treated with Saxenda, compared with placebo, had changes from baseline at two consecutive visits of more than 10 bpm (34% versus 19%, respectively) and 20 bpm (5% versus 2%, respectively).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="830" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>At least one resting heart rate exceeding 100 bpm was recorded for 6% of Saxenda-treated patients compared with 4% of placebo-treated patients, with this occurring at two consecutive study visits for 0.9% and 0.3%, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="831" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Tachycardia was reported as an adverse reaction in 0.6% of Saxenda-treated patients and in 0.1% of placebo-treated patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="832" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In a clinical pharmacology trial that monitored heart rate continuously for 24 hours, Saxenda treatment was associated with a heart rate that was 4 to 9 bpm higher than that observed with placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="833" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Heart rate should be monitored at regular intervals consistent with usual clinical practice.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="834" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients should inform health care providers of palpitations or feelings of a racing heartbeat while at rest during Saxenda treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="835" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>For patients who experience a sustained increase in resting heart rate while taking Saxenda, Saxenda should be discontinued.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="836" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In patients treated with GLP-1 receptor agonists, including Saxenda, there have been reports of acute renal failure and worsening of chronic renal failure, sometimes requiring hemodialysis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="837" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Some of these events were reported in patients without known underlying renal disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="838" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>A majority of the reported events occurred in patients who had experienced nausea, vomiting, or diarrhea leading to volume depletion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="839" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Some of the reported events occurred in patients receiving one or more medications known to affect renal function or volume status.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M41" type="Trigger" span="21 15" str="events occurred"/>
<Mention id="M40" type="Precipitant" span="71 27;117 13" str="medications known to affect | volume status" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M42" type="Precipitant" span="71 42" str="medications known to affect renal function" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M41" precipitant="M40"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M41" precipitant="M42"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="840" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Altered renal function has been reversed in many of the reported cases with supportive treatment and discontinuation of potentially causative agents, including liraglutide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="841" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Use caution when initiating or escalating doses of Saxenda in patients with renal impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="842" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There have been reports of serious hypersensitivity reactions (e.g., anaphylactic reactions and angioedema) in patients treated with liraglutide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="843" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If a hypersensitivity reaction occurs, the patient should discontinue Saxenda and other suspect medications and promptly seek medical advice.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="844" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Anaphylaxis and angioedema have been reported with other GLP-1 receptor agonists.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="845" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Use caution in a patient with a history of anaphylaxis or angioedema with another GLP-1 receptor agonist because it is unknown whether such patients will be predisposed to these reactions with Saxenda.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="846" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In Saxenda clinical trials, 9 (0.3%) of 3384 Saxenda-treated patients and 2 (0.1%) of the 1941 placebo-treated patients reported suicidal ideation; one of these Saxenda-treated patients attempted suicide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="847" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients treated with Saxenda should be monitored for the emergence or worsening of depression, suicidal thoughts or behavior, and/or any unusual changes in mood or behavior.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="848" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Discontinue Saxenda in patients who experience suicidal thoughts or behaviors.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="849" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Avoid Saxenda in patients with a history of suicidal attempts or active suicidal ideation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="850" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Liraglutide is an acylated human glucagon-like peptide-1 (GLP-1) receptor agonist with 97% amino acid sequence homology to endogenous human GLP-1(7-37).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="851" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Like endogenous GLP-1, liraglutide binds to and activates the GLP-1 receptor, a cell-surface receptor coupled to adenylyl cyclase activation through the stimulatory G-protein, Gs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="852" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Endogenous GLP-1 has a half-life of 1.5-2 minutes due to degradation by the ubiquitous endogenous enzymes, dipeptidyl peptidase 4 (DPP-4) and neutral endopeptidases (NEP).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="853" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Unlike native GLP-1, liraglutide is stable against metabolic degradation by both peptidases and has a plasma half-life of 13 hours after subcutaneous administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="854" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacokinetic profile of liraglutide, which makes it suitable for once-daily administration, is a result of self-association that delays absorption, plasma protein binding, and stability against metabolic degradation by DPP-4 and NEP.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="855" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>GLP-1 is a physiological regulator of appetite and calorie intake, and the GLP-1 receptor is present in several areas of the brain involved in appetite regulation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="856" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In animal studies, peripheral administration of liraglutide resulted in the presence of liraglutide in specific brain regions regulating appetite, including the hypothalamus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="857" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Although liraglutide activated neurons in brain regions known to regulate appetite, specific brain regions mediating the effects of liraglutide on appetite were not identified in rats.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="858" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Liraglutide lowers body weight through decreased calorie intake.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="859" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Liraglutide does not increase 24-hour energy expenditure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="860" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>As with other GLP-1 receptor agonists, liraglutide stimulates insulin secretion and reduces glucagon secretion in a glucose-dependent manner.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="861" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>These effects can lead to a reduction of blood glucose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="862" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Cardiac Electrophysiology (QTc) in healthy volunteers The effect of liraglutide on cardiac repolarization was tested in a QTc study.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="863" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Liraglutide at steady-state concentrations after daily doses up to 1.8 mg did not produce QTc prolongation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="864" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The maximum liraglutide plasma concentration (Cmax) in overweight and obese subjects treated with liraglutide 3 mg is similar to the Cmax observed in the liraglutide QTc study in healthy volunteers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="865" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Absorption - Following subcutaneous administration, maximum concentrations of liraglutide are achieved at 11 hours post dosing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="866" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The average liraglutide steady state concentration (AUCτ/24) reached approximately 116 ng/mL in obese (BMI 30-40 kg/m2) subjects following administration of Saxenda.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="867" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Liraglutide exposure increased proportionally in the dose range of 0.6 mg to 3 mg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="868" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The intra-subject coefficient of variation for liraglutide AUC was 11% following single dose administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="869" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Liraglutide exposures were considered similar among three subcutaneous injection sites (upper arm, abdomen, and thigh).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="870" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Absolute bioavailability of liraglutide following subcutaneous administration is approximately 55%.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="871" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Distribution - The mean apparent volume of distribution after subcutaneous administration of liraglutide 3 mg is 20-25 L (for a person weighing approximately 100 kg).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="872" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mean volume of distribution after intravenous administration of liraglutide is 0.07 L/kg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="873" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Liraglutide is extensively bound to plasma protein (greater than 98%).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="874" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Metabolism - During the initial 24 hours following administration of a single [3H]-liraglutide dose to healthy subjects, the major component in plasma was intact liraglutide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="875" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Liraglutide is endogenously metabolized in a similar manner to large proteins without a specific organ as a major route of elimination.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="876" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Elimination - Following a [3H]-liraglutide dose, intact liraglutide was not detected in urine or feces.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="877" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Only a minor part of the administered radioactivity was excreted as liraglutide-related metabolites in urine or feces (6% and 5%, respectively).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="878" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The majority of urine and feces radioactivity was excreted during the first 6-8 days.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="879" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mean apparent clearance following subcutaneous administration of a single dose of liraglutide is approximately 0.9-1.4 L/h with an elimination half-life of approximately 13 hours, making liraglutide suitable for once daily administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="880" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Specific Populations Elderly - No dosage adjustment is required based on age.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="881" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Age had no effect on the pharmacokinetics of liraglutide based on a pharmacokinetic study in healthy elderly subjects (65 to 83 years) and population pharmacokinetic analyses of data from overweight and obese patients 18 to 82 years of age.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="882" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Gender - Based on the results of population pharmacokinetic analyses, females have 24% lower weight adjusted clearance of Saxenda compared to males.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="883" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Based on the exposure response data, no dose adjustment is necessary based on gender.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="884" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Race and Ethnicity - Race and ethnicity had no effect on the pharmacokinetics of liraglutide based on the results of population pharmacokinetic analyses that included overweight and obese patients of Caucasian, Black, Asian and Hispanic/Non-Hispanic groups.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="885" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Body Weight - Body weight significantly affects the pharmacokinetics of liraglutide based on results of population pharmacokinetic analyses conducted in patients with body weight range of 60-234 kg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="886" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The exposure of liraglutide decreases as baseline body weight increases.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="887" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Pediatric - Saxenda has not been studied in pediatric patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="888" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Renal Impairment - The single-dose pharmacokinetics of liraglutide were evaluated in subjects with varying degrees of renal impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="889" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Subjects with mild (estimated creatinine clearance 50-80 mL/min) to severe (estimated creatinine clearance less than 30 mL/min) renal impairment and subjects with end-stage renal disease requiring dialysis were included in the trial.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="890" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Compared to healthy subjects, liraglutide AUC in mild, moderate, and severe renal impairment and in end-stage renal disease was on average 35%, 19%, 29% and 30% lower, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="891" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Hepatic Impairment - The single-dose pharmacokinetics of liraglutide were evaluated in subjects with varying degrees of hepatic impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="892" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Subjects with mild (Child Pugh score 5-6) to severe (Child Pugh score greater than 9) hepatic impairment were included in the trial.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="893" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Compared to healthy subjects, liraglutide AUC in subjects with mild, moderate and severe hepatic impairment was on average 11%, 14% and 42% lower, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="894" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Drug Interactions In vitro assessment of drug−drug interactions Liraglutide has low potential for pharmacokinetic drug-drug interactions related to cytochrome P450 (CYP) and plasma protein binding.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="895" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In vivo assessment of drug−drug interactions The drug-drug interaction studies were performed at steady state with liraglutide 1.8 mg/day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="896" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The effect on rate of gastric emptying was equivalent between liraglutide 1.8 mg and 3 mg (acetaminophen AUC0-300min).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="897" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Administration of the interacting drugs was timed so that Cmax of liraglutide (8-12 h) would coincide with the absorption peak of the co-administered drugs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="898" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Oral Contraceptives A single dose of an oral contraceptive combination product containing 0.03 mg ethinylestradiol and 0.15 mg levonorgestrel was administered under fed conditions and 7 hours after the dose of liraglutide at steady state.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="899" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Liraglutide lowered ethinylestradiol and levonorgestrel Cmax by 12% and 13%, respectively.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M45" type="Trigger" span="12 7;56 4" str="lowered | Cmax"/>
<Mention id="M44" type="Precipitant" span="20 16" str="ethinylestradiol" code="423D2T571U"/>
<Mention id="M46" type="Precipitant" span="41 14" str="levonorgestrel" code="5W7SIA7YZW"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M45" precipitant="M44" effect="C54615"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M45" precipitant="M46" effect="C54615"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="900" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There was no effect of liraglutide on the overall exposure (AUC) of ethinylestradiol.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="901" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Liraglutide increased the levonorgestrel AUC0-∞ by 18%.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M47" type="Trigger" span="12 9;41 3" str="increased | AUC"/>
<Mention id="M48" type="Precipitant" span="26 14" str="levonorgestrel" code="5W7SIA7YZW"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M47" precipitant="M48" effect="C54613"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="902" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Liraglutide delayed Tmax for both ethinylestradiol and levonorgestrel by 1.5 h. Digoxin A single dose of digoxin 1 mg was administered 7 hours after the dose of liraglutide at steady state.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M51" type="Trigger" span="12 12" str="delayed Tmax"/>
<Mention id="M50" type="Precipitant" span="34 16" str="ethinylestradiol" code="423D2T571U"/>
<Mention id="M52" type="Precipitant" span="55 14" str="levonorgestrel" code="5W7SIA7YZW"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M51" precipitant="M50" effect="C54612"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M51" precipitant="M52" effect="C54612"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="903" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The concomitant administration with liraglutide resulted in a reduction of digoxin AUC by 16%; Cmax decreased by 31%.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M53" type="Trigger" span="95 14" str="Cmax decreased"/>
<Mention id="M56" type="Precipitant" span="75 7" str="digoxin" code="73K4184T59 | N0000005903"/>
<Mention id="M55" type="Trigger" span="62 9;83 3" str="reduction | AUC"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M53" precipitant="M56" effect="C54615"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M55" precipitant="M56" effect="C54614"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="904" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Digoxin median time to maximal concentration (Tmax) was delayed from 1 h to 1.5 h. Lisinopril A single dose of lisinopril 20 mg was administered 5 minutes after the dose of liraglutide at steady state.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M57" type="Trigger" span="15 29;56 7" str="time to maximal concentration | delayed"/>
<Mention id="M60" type="Precipitant" span="0 7" str="Digoxin" code="73K4184T59 | N0000005903"/>
<Mention id="M59" type="Trigger" span="46 4;56 7" str="Tmax | delayed"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M57" precipitant="M60" effect="C54612"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M59" precipitant="M60" effect="C54612"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="905" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The co-administration with liraglutide resulted in a reduction of lisinopril AUC by 15%; Cmax decreased by 27%.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M61" type="Trigger" span="89 14" str="Cmax decreased"/>
<Mention id="M64" type="Precipitant" span="66 10" str="lisinopril" code="E7199S1YWR"/>
<Mention id="M63" type="Trigger" span="53 9;77 3" str="reduction | AUC"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M61" precipitant="M64" effect="C54615"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M63" precipitant="M64" effect="C54614"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="906" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Lisinopril median Tmax was delayed from 6 h to 8 h with liraglutide.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M65" type="Trigger" span="18 16" str="Tmax was delayed"/>
<Mention id="M66" type="Precipitant" span="0 10" str="Lisinopril" code="E7199S1YWR"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M65" precipitant="M66" effect="C54612"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="907" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Atorvastatin Liraglutide did not change the overall exposure (AUC) of atorvastatin following a single dose of atorvastatin 40 mg, administered 5 hours after the dose of liraglutide at steady state.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="908" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Atorvastatin Cmax was decreased by 38% and median Tmax was delayed from 1 h to 3 h with liraglutide.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M67" type="Trigger" span="13 18" str="Cmax was decreased"/>
<Mention id="M70" type="Precipitant" span="0 12" str="Atorvastatin" code="A0JWA85V8F | N0000022046"/>
<Mention id="M69" type="Trigger" span="50 16" str="Tmax was delayed"/>
<Interaction id="I29" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M67" precipitant="M70" effect="C54615"/>
<Interaction id="I30" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M69" precipitant="M70" effect="C54612"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="909" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Acetaminophen Liraglutide did not change the overall exposure (AUC) of acetaminophen following a single dose of acetaminophen 1000 mg, administered 8 hours after the dose of liraglutide at steady state.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="910" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Acetaminophen Cmax was decreased by 31% and median Tmax was delayed up to 15 minutes.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M71" type="Trigger" span="14 18" str="Cmax was decreased"/>
<Mention id="M74" type="Precipitant" span="0 13" str="Acetaminophen" code="362O9ITL9D"/>
<Mention id="M73" type="Trigger" span="51 16" str="Tmax was delayed"/>
<Interaction id="I31" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M71" precipitant="M74" effect="C54615"/>
<Interaction id="I32" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M73" precipitant="M74" effect="C54612"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="911" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Griseofulvin Liraglutide did not change the overall exposure (AUC) of griseofulvin following co-administration of a single dose of griseofulvin 500 mg with liraglutide at steady state.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="912" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Griseofulvin Cmax increased by 37% while median Tmax did not change.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M75" type="Trigger" span="13 14" str="Cmax increased"/>
<Mention id="M76" type="Precipitant" span="0 12" str="Griseofulvin" code="32HRV3E3D5"/>
<Interaction id="I33" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M75" precipitant="M76" effect="C54610"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="913" LabelDrug="Saxenda" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Insulin Detemir No pharmacokinetic interaction was observed between liraglutide and insulin detemir when separate subcutaneous injections of insulin detemir 0.5 Unit/kg (single-dose) and liraglutide 1.8 mg (steady state) were administered to patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="insulin secretagogue" precipitantCode="N0000009360" effect="166922008: Blood glucose abnormal (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="insulin secretagogue" precipitantCode="N0000009360" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sulfonylureas" precipitantCode="N0000175608 | N0000008054" effect="166922008: Blood glucose abnormal (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sulfonylureas" precipitantCode="N0000175608 | N0000008054" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="insulin" precipitantCode="N0000004931 | N0000175944"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sulfonylurea" precipitantCode="N0000175608 | N0000008054" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="sulfonylurea" precipitantCode="N0000175608 | N0000008054"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="anti-diabetic drugs" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="insulin secretagogues" precipitantCode="N0000009360" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="insulin secretagogues" precipitantCode="N0000009360"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="medications known to affect | volume status" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="medications known to affect renal function" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="ethinylestradiol" precipitantCode="423D2T571U" effect="C54612"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="ethinylestradiol" precipitantCode="423D2T571U" effect="C54615"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="levonorgestrel" precipitantCode="5W7SIA7YZW" effect="C54612"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="levonorgestrel" precipitantCode="5W7SIA7YZW" effect="C54613"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="levonorgestrel" precipitantCode="5W7SIA7YZW" effect="C54615"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="digoxin" precipitantCode="73K4184T59 | N0000005903" effect="C54612"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="digoxin" precipitantCode="73K4184T59 | N0000005903" effect="C54614"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="digoxin" precipitantCode="73K4184T59 | N0000005903" effect="C54615"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="lisinopril" precipitantCode="E7199S1YWR" effect="C54612"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="lisinopril" precipitantCode="E7199S1YWR" effect="C54614"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="lisinopril" precipitantCode="E7199S1YWR" effect="C54615"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="atorvastatin" precipitantCode="A0JWA85V8F | N0000022046" effect="C54612"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="atorvastatin" precipitantCode="A0JWA85V8F | N0000022046" effect="C54615"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="acetaminophen" precipitantCode="362O9ITL9D" effect="C54612"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="acetaminophen" precipitantCode="362O9ITL9D" effect="C54615"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="griseofulvin" precipitantCode="32HRV3E3D5" effect="C54610"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>