<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Tolbutamide" setid="3995eed8-39ec-ce5e-8cc2-062f93445c8d">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
Tolbutamide tablets are contraindicated in patients with: • Known hypersensitivity or allergy to the drug. • Diabetic ketoacidosis, with or without coma. This condition should be treated with insulin. • Type I diabetes, as sole therapy.</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
There is no fixed dosage regimen for the management of diabetes mellitus with tolbutamide tablets or any other hypoglycemic agent. In addition to the usual monitoring of urinary glucose, the patient's blood glucose must also be monitored periodically to determine the minimum effective dose for the patient; to detect primary failure, i.e., inadequate lowering of blood glucose at the maximum recommended dose of medication; and to detect secondary failure, i.e., loss of an adequate blood glucose lowering response after an initial period of effectiveness. Glycosylated hemoglobin levels may also be of value in monitoring the patient's response to therapy. Short-term administration of tolbutamide tablets may be sufficient during periods of transient loss of control in patients usually controlled well on diet. The usual starting dose is 1 to 2 grams daily. This may be increased or decreased, depending on individual patient response. Failure to follow an appropriate dosage regimen may precipitate hypoglycemia. Patients who do not adhere to their prescribed dietary regimens are more prone to exhibit unsatisfactory response to drug therapy. Transfer of patients from other oral antidiabetes regimens to tolbutamide tablets should be done conservatively. When transferring patients from oral hypoglycemic agents other than chlorpropamide to tolbutamide, no transition period and no initial or priming doses are necessary. When transferring patients from chlorpropamide, however, particular care should be exercised during the first 2 weeks because of the prolonged retention of chlorpropamide, in the body and the possibility that subsequent overlapping drug effects might provoke hypoglycemia. Patients requiring 20 units or less of insulin daily may be placed directly on tolbutamide tablets and insulin abruptly discontinued. Patients whose insulin requirement is between 20 and 40 units daily may be started on therapy with tolbutamide tablets with a concurrent 30% to 50% reduction in insulin dose, with further daily reduction of the insulin when response to tolbutamide tablets is observed. In patients requiring more than 40 units of insulin daily, therapy with tolbutamide tablets may be initiated in conjunction with a 20% reduction in insulin dose the first day, with further careful reduction of insulin as response is observed. Occasionally, conversion to tolbutamide tablets in the hospital may be advisable in candidates who require more than 40 units of insulin daily. During this conversion period when both insulin and tolbutamide tablets are being used hypoglycemia may rarely occur. During insulin withdrawal, patients should test their urine for glucose and acetone at least 3 times daily and report results to their physician. The appearance of persistent acetonuria with glycosuria indicates that the patient is type I diabetic who requires insulin therapy. Daily doses of greater than 3 grams are not recommended. The maintenance dose is in the range of 0.25 to 3 grams daily. Maintenance doses above 2 grams are seldom required. The total daily dose may be taken either in the morning or in divided doses through the day. While either schedule is usually effective, the divided dose system is preferred by some clinicians from the standpoint of digestive tolerance. In elderly patients, debilitated or malnourished patients, and patients with impaired renal or hepatic function, the initial and maintenance dosing should be conservative to avoid hypoglycemic reactions (see PRECAUTIONS ).</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
The hypoglycemia action of sulfonylurea may be potentiated by certain drugs including non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agents and other drugs that are highly protein bound, salicylates, sulfonamides, chloramphenicol, probenecid, coumarins, monoamine oxidase inhibitors, and beta-adrenergic blocking agents. When such drugs are administered to a patient receiving tolbutamide, the patient should be observed closely for hypoglycemia. When such drugs are withdrawn from a patient receiving tolbutamide, the patient should be observed closely for loss of control. Certain drugs tend to produce hyperglycemia and may lead to loss of control. These drugs include the thiazides and other diuretics, corticosteroids, phenothiazines, thyroid products, estrogens, oral contraceptives, phenytoin, nicotinic acid, sympathomimetics, calcium channel blocking drugs, and isoniazid. When such drugs are administered to a patient receiving tolbutamide, the patient should be closely observed for loss of control. When such drugs are withdrawn from a patient receiving tolbutamide, the patient should be observed closely for hypoglycemia. A potential interaction between oral miconazole and oral hypoglycemic agents leading to severe hypoglycemia has been reported. Whether this interaction also occurs with the intravenous, topical or vaginal preparations of miconazole is not known.</Section>
<Section name="PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="42232-9">
All sulfonylurea drugs are capable of producing severe hypoglycemia. Proper patient selection, dosage, and instructions are important to avoid hypoglycemic episodes. Renal or hepatic insufficiency may cause elevated blood levels of tolbutamide and the latter may also diminish gluconeogenic capacity, both of which increase the risk of serious hypoglycemic reactions. Elderly, debilitated or malnourished patients, and those with adrenal or pituitary insufficiency are particularly susceptible to the hypoglycemic action of glucose-lowering drugs. Hypoglycemia may be difficult to recognize in the elderly, and in people who are taking beta-adrenergic blocking drugs. Hypoglycemia is more likely to occur when caloric intake is deficient, after severe or prolonged exercise, when alcohol is ingested, or when more than one glucose-lowering drug is used. When a patient stabilized on any diabetic regimen is exposed to stress such as fever, trauma, infection, or surgery, a loss of control may occur. At such times, it may be necessary to discontinue tolbutamide and administer insulin. The effectiveness of any oral hypoglycemic drug, including tolbutamide, in lowering blood glucose to a desired level decreases in many patients over a period of time, which may be due to progression of the severity of the diabetes or to diminished responsiveness to the drug. This phenomenon is known as a secondary failure, to distinguish it from primary failure in which the drug is ineffective in an individual patient when first given. Adequate adjustment of dose and adherence to diet should be assessed before classifying a patient as a secondary failure. Treatment of patients with glucose 6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PD) deficiency with sulfonylurea agents can lead to hemolytic anemia. Because tolbutamide belongs to the class of sulfonylurea agents, caution should be used in patients with G6PD deficiency and a non-sulfonylurea alternative should be considered. In post-marketing reports, hemolytic anemia has also been reported in patients who did not have known G6PD deficiency. Patients should be informed of the potential risks and advantages of tolbutamide and of alternative modes of therapy. They should also be informed about the importance of adherence to dietary instructions, of a regular exercise program, and of regular testing of urine and/or blood glucose. The risks of hypoglycemia, its symptoms and treatment, and conditions that predispose to its development should be explained to patients and responsible family members. Primary and secondary failure should also be explained. Blood and urine glucose should be monitored periodically. Measurement of glycosylated hemoglobin may be useful. A metabolite of tolbutamide in urine may give a false positive reaction for albumin if measured by the acidification-after-boiling test, which causes the metabolite to precipitate. There is no interference with the sulfosalicylic acid test. The hypoglycemia action of sulfonylurea may be potentiated by certain drugs including non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agents and other drugs that are highly protein bound, salicylates, sulfonamides, chloramphenicol, probenecid, coumarins, monoamine oxidase inhibitors, and beta-adrenergic blocking agents. When such drugs are administered to a patient receiving tolbutamide, the patient should be observed closely for hypoglycemia. When such drugs are withdrawn from a patient receiving tolbutamide, the patient should be observed closely for loss of control. Certain drugs tend to produce hyperglycemia and may lead to loss of control. These drugs include the thiazides and other diuretics, corticosteroids, phenothiazines, thyroid products, estrogens, oral contraceptives, phenytoin, nicotinic acid, sympathomimetics, calcium channel blocking drugs, and isoniazid. When such drugs are administered to a patient receiving tolbutamide, the patient should be closely observed for loss of control. When such drugs are withdrawn from a patient receiving tolbutamide, the patient should be observed closely for hypoglycemia. A potential interaction between oral miconazole and oral hypoglycemic agents leading to severe hypoglycemia has been reported. Whether this interaction also occurs with the intravenous, topical or vaginal preparations of miconazole is not known. Bioassay for carcinogenicity was performed in both sexes of rats and mice following ingestion of tolbutamide for 78 weeks. No evidence of carcinogenicity was found. Tolbutamide has also been demonstrated to be nonmutagenic in the Ames salmonella/mammalian microsome mutagenicity test. Tolbutamide has been shown to be teratogenic in rats when given in doses 25 to 100 times the human dose. In some studies, pregnant rats given high doses of tolbutamide have shown ocular and bony abnormalities and increased mortality in offspring. Repeat studies in other species (rabbits) have not demonstrated a teratogenic effect. There are no adequate and well controlled studies in pregnant women. Tolbutamide is not recommended for the treatment of pregnant diabetic patients. Serious consideration should also be given to the possible hazards of the use of tolbutamide in women of childbearing age and in those who might become pregnant while using the drug. Because recent information suggests that abnormal blood glucose levels during pregnancy are associated with a higher incidence of congenital abnormalities, many experts recommend that insulin be used during pregnancy to maintain blood glucose levels as close to normal as possible. Prolonged severe hypoglycemia (4 to 10 days) has been reported in neonates born to mothers who were receiving a sulfonylurea drug at the time of delivery. This has been reported more frequently with the use of agents with prolonged half-lives. If tolbutamide is used during pregnancy, it should be discontinued at least 2 weeks before the expected delivery date. Although it is not known whether tolbutamide is excreted in human milk, some sulfonylurea drugs are known to be excreted in human milk. Because the potential for hypoglycemia in nursing infants may exist, a decision should be made whether to discontinue nursing or to discontinue the drug, taking into account the importance of the drug to the mother. If the drug is discontinued and if diet alone is inadequate for controlling blood glucose, insulin therapy should be considered. Safety and effectiveness in children have not been established.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS SECTION" id="34071-1">
The administration of oral hypoglycemic drugs has been reported to be associated with increased cardiovascular mortality as compared to treatment with diet alone or diet plus insulin. This warning is based on the study conducted by the University Group Diabetes Program (UGDP), a long-term prospective clinical trial designed to evaluate the effectiveness of glucose-lowering drugs in preventing or delaying vascular complications in patients with non-insulin-dependent diabetes. The study involved 823 patients who were randomly assigned to one of four treatment groups (Diabetes, 19 (supp.2):747-830, 1970). UGDP reported that patients treated for 5 to 8 years with diet plus a fixed dose of tolbutamide (1.5 grams per day) had a rate of cardiovascular mortality approximately 2½ times that of patients treated with diet alone. A significant increase in total mortality was not observed, but the use of tolbutamide was discontinued based on the increase in cardiovascular mortality, thus limiting the opportunity for the study to show an increase in overall mortality. Despite controversy regarding the interpretation of these results, the findings of the UGDP study provide an adequate basis for this warning. The patient should be informed of the potential risks and advantages of tolbutamide and of alternative modes of therapy. Although only one drug in the sulfonylurea class (tolbutamide) was included in this study, it is prudent from a safety standpoint to consider that this warning may also apply to other oral hypoglycemic drugs in this class, in view of their close similarities in mode of action and chemical structure.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Tolbutamide appears to lower the blood glucose acutely by stimulating the release of insulin from the pancreas, an effect dependent upon functioning beta cells in the pancreatic islets. The mechanism by which tolbutamide lowers blood glucose during long-term administration has not been clearly established. With chronic administration in Type II diabetic patients, the blood-glucose-lowering effect persists despite a gradual decline in the insulin secretory response to the drug. Extrapancreatic effects may be involved in the mechanism of action of oral sulfonylurea hypoglycemic drugs. Some patients who are initially responsive to oral hypoglycemic drugs, including tolbutamide, may become unresponsive or poorly responsive over time. Alternatively, tolbutamide may be effective in some patients who have become unresponsive to one or more of the other sulfonylurea drugs. When administered orally, tolbutamide is readily absorbed from the gastrointestinal tract. Absorption is not impaired and glucose lowering and insulin releasing effects are not altered if the drug is taken with food. Detectable levels are present in the plasma within 20 minutes after oral ingestion of a 500 mg tolbutamide tablet, with peak levels occurring at 3 to 4 hours and only small amounts detectable at 24 hours. The half-life of tolbutamide is 4.5 to 6.5 hours. As tolbutamide has no p-amino group, it cannot be acetylated, which is one of the common modes of metabolic degradation for the antibacterial sulfonamides. However, the presence of the p-methyl group renders tolbutamide susceptible to oxidation, and this appears to be the principal manner of its metabolic degradation in man. The p-methyl group is oxidized to form a carboxyl group, converting tolbutamide into the totally inactive metabolite 1-butyl-3-p-carboxy-phenylsulfonylurea, which can be recovered in the urine within 24 hours in amounts accounting for up to 75% of the administered dose. The major tolbutamide metabolite has been found to have no hypoglycemic or other action when administered orally and IV to both normal and diabetic subjects. This tolbutamide metabolite is highly soluble over the critical acid range of urinary pH values, and its solubility increases with increase in pH. Because of the marked solubility of the tolbutamide metabolite, crystalluria does not occur. A second metabolite, 1-butyl-3-(p-hydroxymethyl) phenyl sulfonylurea also occurs to a limited extent. It is an inactive metabolite. The administration of 3 grams of tolbutamide to either nondiabetic or tolbutamide-responsive diabetic subjects will, in both instances, occasion a gradual lowering of blood glucose. Increasing the dose to 6 grams does not usually cause a response which is significantly different from that produced by the 3 gram dose. Following the administration of a 3 gram dose of tolbutamide solution, non-diabetic fasting adults exhibit a 30% or greater reduction in blood glucose within one hour, following which the blood glucose gradually returns to the fasting level over 6 to 12 hours. Following the administration of a 3 gram dose of tolbutamide solution, tolbutamide responsive diabetic patients show a gradually progressive blood glucose lowering effect, the maximal response being reached between 5 to 8 hours after ingestion of a single 3 gram dose. The blood glucose then rises gradually and by the 24 th hour has usually returned to pretest levels. The magnitude of the reduction, when expressed in terms of percent of the pretest blood glucose, tends to be similar to the response seen in the nondiabetic subject.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="2635" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Tolbutamide tablets are contraindicated in patients with: Known hypersensitivity or allergy to the drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2636" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Diabetic ketoacidosis, with or without coma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2637" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>This condition should be treated with insulin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2638" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>There is no fixed dosage regimen for the management of diabetes mellitus with tolbutamide tablets or any other hypoglycemic agent.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2639" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In addition to the usual monitoring of urinary glucose, the patient's blood glucose must also be monitored periodically to determine the minimum effective dose for the patient; to detect primary failure, i.e., inadequate lowering of blood glucose at the maximum recommended dose of medication; and to detect secondary failure, i.e., loss of an adequate blood glucose lowering response after an initial period of effectiveness.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2640" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Glycosylated hemoglobin levels may also be of value in monitoring the patient's response to therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2641" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Short-term administration of tolbutamide tablets may be sufficient during periods of transient loss of control in patients usually controlled well on diet.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2642" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The usual starting dose is 1 to 2 grams daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2643" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>This may be increased or decreased, depending on individual patient response.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2644" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Failure to follow an appropriate dosage regimen may precipitate hypoglycemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2645" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Patients who do not adhere to their prescribed dietary regimens are more prone to exhibit unsatisfactory response to drug therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2646" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Transfer of patients from other oral antidiabetes regimens to tolbutamide tablets should be done conservatively.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M1" type="Trigger" span="0 8;82 29" str="Transfer | should be done conservatively"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="32 26" str="oral antidiabetes regimens" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M1" precipitant="M2"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2647" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>When transferring patients from oral hypoglycemic agents other than chlorpropamide to tolbutamide, no transition period and no initial or priming doses are necessary.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2648" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>When transferring patients from chlorpropamide, however, particular care should be exercised during the first 2 weeks because of the prolonged retention of chlorpropamide, in the body and the possibility that subsequent overlapping drug effects might provoke hypoglycemia.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M3" type="Trigger" span="220 24" str="overlapping drug effects "/>
<Mention id="M4" type="Trigger" span="251 7" str=" provoke"/>
<Mention id="M5" type="Precipitant" span="32 14" str="chlorpropamide" code="WTM2C3IL2X"/>
<Mention id="M6" type="SpecificInteraction" span="259 12" str="hypoglycemia" code="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M3;M4" precipitant="M5" effect="M6" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2649" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Patients requiring 20 units or less of insulin daily may be placed directly on tolbutamide tablets and insulin abruptly discontinued.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2650" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Patients whose insulin requirement is between 20 and 40 units daily may be started on therapy with tolbutamide tablets with a concurrent 30% to 50% reduction in insulin dose, with further daily reduction of the insulin when response to tolbutamide tablets is observed.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M7" type="Trigger" span="148 9;169 4" str="reduction | dose "/>
<Mention id="M8" type="Trigger" span="169 4;148 9" str=" dose | reduction"/>
<Mention id="M9" type="Precipitant" span="15 7" str="insulin" code="N0000004931 | N0000175944"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M7;M8" precipitant="M9"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2651" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In patients requiring more than 40 units of insulin daily, therapy with tolbutamide tablets may be initiated in conjunction with a 20% reduction in insulin dose the first day, with further careful reduction of insulin as response is observed.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M10" type="Trigger" span="135 9;156 4" str="reduction | dose "/>
<Mention id="M11" type="Trigger" span="156 4;135 9" str=" dose | reduction"/>
<Mention id="M12" type="Precipitant" span="44 7" str="insulin" code="N0000004931 | N0000175944"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M10;M11" precipitant="M12"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2652" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Occasionally, conversion to tolbutamide tablets in the hospital may be advisable in candidates who require more than 40 units of insulin daily.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M13" type="Trigger" span="14 10;71 9" str="conversion | advisable"/>
<Mention id="M14" type="Precipitant" span="129 7" str="insulin" code="N0000004931 | N0000175944"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M13" precipitant="M14"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2653" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>During this conversion period when both insulin and tolbutamide tablets are being used hypoglycemia may rarely occur.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M15" type="Trigger" span="111 5" str="occur"/>
<Mention id="M16" type="Precipitant" span="40 7" str="insulin" code="N0000004931 | N0000175944"/>
<Mention id="M17" type="SpecificInteraction" span="87 12" str="hypoglycemia" code="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M15" precipitant="M16" effect="M17" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2654" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>During insulin withdrawal, patients should test their urine for glucose and acetone at least 3 times daily and report results to their physician.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M21" type="Trigger" span="15 10;36 11" str="withdrawal | should test"/>
<Mention id="M22" type="Precipitant" span="7 7" str="insulin" code="N0000004931 | N0000175944"/>
<Mention id="M20" type="SpecificInteraction" span="54 5;76 7" str="urine | acetone" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M23" type="SpecificInteraction" span="54 5;64 7" str="urine | glucose" code="45154002: Glycosuria (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M21" precipitant="M22" effect="M20" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M21" precipitant="M22" effect="M23" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2655" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The appearance of persistent acetonuria with glycosuria indicates that the patient is type I diabetic who requires insulin therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2656" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Daily doses of greater than 3 grams are not recommended.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2657" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The maintenance dose is in the range of 0.25 to 3 grams daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2658" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Maintenance doses above 2 grams are seldom required.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2659" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The total daily dose may be taken either in the morning or in divided doses through the day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2660" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>While either schedule is usually effective, the divided dose system is preferred by some clinicians from the standpoint of digestive tolerance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2661" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In elderly patients, debilitated or malnourished patients, and patients with impaired renal or hepatic function, the initial and maintenance dosing should be conservative to avoid hypoglycemic reactions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2662" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The hypoglycemia action of sulfonylurea may be potentiated by certain drugs including non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agents and other drugs that are highly protein bound, salicylates, sulfonamides, chloramphenicol, probenecid, coumarins, monoamine oxidase inhibitors, and beta-adrenergic blocking agents.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M48" type="Trigger" span="47 11" str="potentiated"/>
<Mention id="M25" type="Precipitant" span="273 31" str="beta-adrenergic blocking agents" code="N0000000161 | N0000175556"/>
<Mention id="M50" type="SpecificInteraction" span="4 12" str="hypoglycemia" code="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M28" type="Precipitant" span="199 15" str="chloramphenicol" code="66974FR9Q1"/>
<Mention id="M31" type="Precipitant" span="228 9" str="coumarins" code="A4VZ22K1WT"/>
<Mention id="M34" type="Precipitant" span="135 35" str="drugs that are highly protein bound" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M37" type="Precipitant" span="239 28" str="monoamine oxidase inhibitors" code="N0000000184 | N0000175744"/>
<Mention id="M40" type="Precipitant" span="86 38" str="non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agents" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M43" type="Precipitant" span="216 10" str="probenecid" code="PO572Z7917"/>
<Mention id="M46" type="Precipitant" span="172 11" str="salicylates" code="N0000006035 | O414PZ4LPZ"/>
<Mention id="M49" type="Precipitant" span="185 12" str="sulfonamides" code="N0000175880"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M48" precipitant="M25" effect="M50" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M48" precipitant="M28" effect="M50" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M48" precipitant="M31" effect="M50" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M48" precipitant="M34" effect="M50" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M48" precipitant="M37" effect="M50" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M48" precipitant="M40" effect="M50" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M48" precipitant="M43" effect="M50" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M48" precipitant="M46" effect="M50" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M48" precipitant="M49" effect="M50" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2663" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>When such drugs are administered to a patient receiving tolbutamide, the patient should be observed closely for hypoglycemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2664" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>When such drugs are withdrawn from a patient receiving tolbutamide, the patient should be observed closely for loss of control.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2665" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Certain drugs tend to produce hyperglycemia and may lead to loss of control.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2666" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>These drugs include the thiazides and other diuretics, corticosteroids, phenothiazines, thyroid products, estrogens, oral contraceptives, phenytoin, nicotinic acid, sympathomimetics, calcium channel blocking drugs, and isoniazid.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2667" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>When such drugs are administered to a patient receiving tolbutamide, the patient should be closely observed for loss of control.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2668" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>When such drugs are withdrawn from a patient receiving tolbutamide, the patient should be observed closely for hypoglycemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2669" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>A potential interaction between oral miconazole and oral hypoglycemic agents leading to severe hypoglycemia has been reported.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M51" type="Trigger" span="12 11" str="interaction "/>
<Mention id="M52" type="Trigger" span="77 10" str=" leading to"/>
<Mention id="M53" type="Precipitant" span="32 15" str="oral miconazole" code="7NNO0D7S5M"/>
<Mention id="M54" type="SpecificInteraction" span="88 19" str="severe hypoglycemia" code="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M51;M52" precipitant="M53" effect="M54" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2670" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Whether this interaction also occurs with the intravenous, topical or vaginal preparations of miconazole is not known.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M55" type="Trigger" span="13 11" str="interaction"/>
<Mention id="M56" type="Precipitant" span="94 10" str="miconazole" code="7NNO0D7S5M"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M55" precipitant="M56"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2671" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>All sulfonylurea drugs are capable of producing severe hypoglycemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2672" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Proper patient selection, dosage, and instructions are important to avoid hypoglycemic episodes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2673" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Renal or hepatic insufficiency may cause elevated blood levels of tolbutamide and the latter may also diminish gluconeogenic capacity, both of which increase the risk of serious hypoglycemic reactions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2674" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Elderly, debilitated or malnourished patients, and those with adrenal or pituitary insufficiency are particularly susceptible to the hypoglycemic action of glucose-lowering drugs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2675" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Hypoglycemia may be difficult to recognize in the elderly, and in people who are taking beta-adrenergic blocking drugs.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M57" type="Trigger" span="0 12" str="Hypoglycemia"/>
<Mention id="M58" type="Precipitant" span="88 30" str="beta-adrenergic blocking drugs" code="N0000000161"/>
<Mention id="M59" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 12" str="hypoglycemia" code="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M57" precipitant="M58" effect="M59" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2676" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Hypoglycemia is more likely to occur when caloric intake is deficient, after severe or prolonged exercise, when alcohol is ingested, or when more than one glucose-lowering drug is used.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M63" type="Trigger" span="31 5" str="occur"/>
<Mention id="M61" type="Precipitant" span="112 7" str="alcohol" code="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M"/>
<Mention id="M65" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 12" str="hypoglycemia" code="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M64" type="Precipitant" span="155 21" str="glucose-lowering drug" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M63" precipitant="M61" effect="M65" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M63" precipitant="M64" effect="M65" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2677" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>When a patient stabilized on any diabetic regimen is exposed to stress such as fever, trauma, infection, or surgery, a loss of control may occur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2678" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>At such times, it may be necessary to discontinue tolbutamide and administer insulin.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M66" type="Trigger" span="38 11;66 10" str="discontinue | administer"/>
<Mention id="M67" type="Precipitant" span="77 7" str="insulin" code="N0000004931 | N0000175944"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M66" precipitant="M67"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2679" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The effectiveness of any oral hypoglycemic drug, including tolbutamide, in lowering blood glucose to a desired level decreases in many patients over a period of time, which may be due to progression of the severity of the diabetes or to diminished responsiveness to the drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2680" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>This phenomenon is known as a secondary failure, to distinguish it from primary failure in which the drug is ineffective in an individual patient when first given.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2681" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Adequate adjustment of dose and adherence to diet should be assessed before classifying a patient as a secondary failure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2682" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Treatment of patients with glucose 6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PD) deficiency with sulfonylurea agents can lead to hemolytic anemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2683" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because tolbutamide belongs to the class of sulfonylurea agents, caution should be used in patients with G6PD deficiency and a non-sulfonylurea alternative should be considered.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2684" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In post-marketing reports, hemolytic anemia has also been reported in patients who did not have known G6PD deficiency.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2685" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Patients should be informed of the potential risks and advantages of tolbutamide and of alternative modes of therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2686" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>They should also be informed about the importance of adherence to dietary instructions, of a regular exercise program, and of regular testing of urine and/or blood glucose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2687" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The risks of hypoglycemia, its symptoms and treatment, and conditions that predispose to its development should be explained to patients and responsible family members.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2688" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Primary and secondary failure should also be explained.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2689" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Blood and urine glucose should be monitored periodically.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2690" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Measurement of glycosylated hemoglobin may be useful.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2691" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>A metabolite of tolbutamide in urine may give a false positive reaction for albumin if measured by the acidification-after-boiling test, which causes the metabolite to precipitate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2692" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>There is no interference with the sulfosalicylic acid test.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2693" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Bioassay for carcinogenicity was performed in both sexes of rats and mice following ingestion of tolbutamide for 78 weeks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2694" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>No evidence of carcinogenicity was found.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2695" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Tolbutamide has also been demonstrated to be nonmutagenic in the Ames salmonella/mammalian microsome mutagenicity test.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2696" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Tolbutamide has been shown to be teratogenic in rats when given in doses 25 to 100 times the human dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2697" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In some studies, pregnant rats given high doses of tolbutamide have shown ocular and bony abnormalities and increased mortality in offspring.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2698" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Repeat studies in other species (rabbits) have not demonstrated a teratogenic effect.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2699" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>There are no adequate and well controlled studies in pregnant women.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2700" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Tolbutamide is not recommended for the treatment of pregnant diabetic patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2701" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Serious consideration should also be given to the possible hazards of the use of tolbutamide in women of childbearing age and in those who might become pregnant while using the drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2702" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because recent information suggests that abnormal blood glucose levels during pregnancy are associated with a higher incidence of congenital abnormalities, many experts recommend that insulin be used during pregnancy to maintain blood glucose levels as close to normal as possible.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2703" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Prolonged severe hypoglycemia (4 to 10 days) has been reported in neonates born to mothers who were receiving a sulfonylurea drug at the time of delivery.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2704" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>This has been reported more frequently with the use of agents with prolonged half-lives.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2705" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>If tolbutamide is used during pregnancy, it should be discontinued at least 2 weeks before the expected delivery date.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2706" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Although it is not known whether tolbutamide is excreted in human milk, some sulfonylurea drugs are known to be excreted in human milk.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2707" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because the potential for hypoglycemia in nursing infants may exist, a decision should be made whether to discontinue nursing or to discontinue the drug, taking into account the importance of the drug to the mother.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2708" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>If the drug is discontinued and if diet alone is inadequate for controlling blood glucose, insulin therapy should be considered.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2709" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Safety and effectiveness in children have not been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2710" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The administration of oral hypoglycemic drugs has been reported to be associated with increased cardiovascular mortality as compared to treatment with diet alone or diet plus insulin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2711" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>This warning is based on the study conducted by the University Group Diabetes Program (UGDP), a long-term prospective clinical trial designed to evaluate the effectiveness of glucose-lowering drugs in preventing or delaying vascular complications in patients with non-insulin-dependent diabetes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2712" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The study involved 823 patients who were randomly assigned to one of four treatment groups (Diabetes, 19 (supp.2):747-830, 1970).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2713" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>UGDP reported that patients treated for 5 to 8 years with diet plus a fixed dose of tolbutamide (1.5 grams per day) had a rate of cardiovascular mortality approximately 2½ times that of patients treated with diet alone.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2714" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>A significant increase in total mortality was not observed, but the use of tolbutamide was discontinued based on the increase in cardiovascular mortality, thus limiting the opportunity for the study to show an increase in overall mortality.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2715" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Despite controversy regarding the interpretation of these results, the findings of the UGDP study provide an adequate basis for this warning.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2716" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The patient should be informed of the potential risks and advantages of tolbutamide and of alternative modes of therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2717" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Although only one drug in the sulfonylurea class (tolbutamide) was included in this study, it is prudent from a safety standpoint to consider that this warning may also apply to other oral hypoglycemic drugs in this class, in view of their close similarities in mode of action and chemical structure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2718" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Tolbutamide appears to lower the blood glucose acutely by stimulating the release of insulin from the pancreas, an effect dependent upon functioning beta cells in the pancreatic islets.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2719" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mechanism by which tolbutamide lowers blood glucose during long-term administration has not been clearly established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2720" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>With chronic administration in Type II diabetic patients, the blood-glucose-lowering effect persists despite a gradual decline in the insulin secretory response to the drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2721" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Extrapancreatic effects may be involved in the mechanism of action of oral sulfonylurea hypoglycemic drugs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2722" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Some patients who are initially responsive to oral hypoglycemic drugs, including tolbutamide, may become unresponsive or poorly responsive over time.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2723" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Alternatively, tolbutamide may be effective in some patients who have become unresponsive to one or more of the other sulfonylurea drugs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2724" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>When administered orally, tolbutamide is readily absorbed from the gastrointestinal tract.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2725" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Absorption is not impaired and glucose lowering and insulin releasing effects are not altered if the drug is taken with food.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2726" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Detectable levels are present in the plasma within 20 minutes after oral ingestion of a 500 mg tolbutamide tablet, with peak levels occurring at 3 to 4 hours and only small amounts detectable at 24 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2727" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The half-life of tolbutamide is 4.5 to 6.5 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2728" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>As tolbutamide has no p-amino group, it cannot be acetylated, which is one of the common modes of metabolic degradation for the antibacterial sulfonamides.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2729" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>However, the presence of the p-methyl group renders tolbutamide susceptible to oxidation, and this appears to be the principal manner of its metabolic degradation in man.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2730" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The p-methyl group is oxidized to form a carboxyl group, converting tolbutamide into the totally inactive metabolite 1-butyl-3-p-carboxy-phenylsulfonylurea, which can be recovered in the urine within 24 hours in amounts accounting for up to 75% of the administered dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2731" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The major tolbutamide metabolite has been found to have no hypoglycemic or other action when administered orally and IV to both normal and diabetic subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2732" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This tolbutamide metabolite is highly soluble over the critical acid range of urinary pH values, and its solubility increases with increase in pH.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2733" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Because of the marked solubility of the tolbutamide metabolite, crystalluria does not occur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2734" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A second metabolite, 1-butyl-3-(p-hydroxymethyl) phenyl sulfonylurea also occurs to a limited extent.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2735" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The administration of 3 grams of tolbutamide to either nondiabetic or tolbutamide-responsive diabetic subjects will, in both instances, occasion a gradual lowering of blood glucose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2736" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Increasing the dose to 6 grams does not usually cause a response which is significantly different from that produced by the 3 gram dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2737" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following the administration of a 3 gram dose of tolbutamide solution, non-diabetic fasting adults exhibit a 30% or greater reduction in blood glucose within one hour, following which the blood glucose gradually returns to the fasting level over 6 to 12 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2738" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following the administration of a 3 gram dose of tolbutamide solution, tolbutamide responsive diabetic patients show a gradually progressive blood glucose lowering effect, the maximal response being reached between 5 to 8 hours after ingestion of a single 3 gram dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2739" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The blood glucose then rises gradually and by the 24th hour has usually returned to pretest levels.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2740" LabelDrug="Tolbutamide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The magnitude of the reduction, when expressed in terms of percent of the pretest blood glucose, tends to be similar to the response seen in the nondiabetic subject.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="oral antidiabetes regimens" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="chlorpropamide" precipitantCode="WTM2C3IL2X" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="insulin" precipitantCode="N0000004931 | N0000175944" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="insulin" precipitantCode="N0000004931 | N0000175944" effect="45154002: Glycosuria (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="insulin" precipitantCode="N0000004931 | N0000175944" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="insulin" precipitantCode="N0000004931 | N0000175944"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="beta-adrenergic blocking agents" precipitantCode="N0000000161 | N0000175556" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="chloramphenicol" precipitantCode="66974FR9Q1" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="coumarins" precipitantCode="A4VZ22K1WT" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="drugs that are highly protein bound" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="monoamine oxidase inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000000184 | N0000175744" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agents" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="probenecid" precipitantCode="PO572Z7917" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="salicylates" precipitantCode="N0000006035 | O414PZ4LPZ" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sulfonamides" precipitantCode="N0000175880" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="oral miconazole" precipitantCode="7NNO0D7S5M" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="miconazole" precipitantCode="7NNO0D7S5M"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="beta-adrenergic blocking drugs" precipitantCode="N0000000161" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="alcohol" precipitantCode="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="glucose-lowering drug" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>