<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Sensipar" setid="45028573-13c4-4c8b-ae62-6c75bba97c81">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
Sensipar treatment initiation is contraindicated if serum calcium is less than the lower limit of the normal range [see Warnings and Precautions ( 5.1 )]. Sensipar treatment initiation is contraindicated if serum calcium is less than the lower limit of the normal range. ( 4 , 5.1 )</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
Sensipar tablets should be taken with food or shortly after a meal ( 2.1 ).   Tablets should always be taken whole and not divided ( 2.1 ) Secondary HPT in patients with CKD on dialysis ( 2.2 ): ○ Starting dose is 30 mg once daily. ○ Titrate dose no more frequently than every 2 to 4 weeks through sequential doses of 30, 60, 90, 120, and 180 mg once daily as necessary to achieve targeted intact parathyroid hormone (iPTH) levels. ○ iPTH levels should be measured no earlier than 12 hours after most recent dose. Hypercalcemia in patients with PC or hypercalcemia in patients with primary HPT ( 2.3 ): ○ Starting dose is 30 mg twice daily. ○ Titrate dose every 2 to 4 weeks through sequential doses of 30 mg twice daily, 60 mg twice daily, 90 mg twice daily, and 90 mg three or four times daily as necessary to normalize serum calcium levels. Once the maintenance dose has been established, monitor serum calcium approximately monthly for patients with secondary HPT and every 2 months for patients with PC or primary HPT ( 2.4 ) Sensipar should be taken with food or shortly after a meal. Sensipar tablets are administered orally and should always be taken whole and not chewed, crushed, or divided.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
Co-administration with a strong CYP3A4 inhibitor may increase serum levels of cinacalcet. Dose adjustment and monitoring of iPTH serum phosphorus and serum calcium may be required. ( 7.1 ) Cinacalcet is a strong inhibitor of CYP2D6. Dose adjustments may be required for concomitant medications that are predominantly metabolized by CYP2D6. ( 7.2 ) Cinacalcet is partially metabolized by CYP3A4. Dose adjustment of Sensipar may be required if a patient initiates or discontinues therapy with a strong CYP3A4 inhibitor (e.g., ketoconazole, itraconazole). The iPTH and serum calcium concentrations should be closely monitored in these patients  [see Clinical Pharmacology ( 12.3 )] . Cinacalcet is a strong inhibitor of CYP2D6. Dose adjustments may be required for concomitant medications that are predominantly metabolized by CYP2D6 (e.g., desipramine, metoprolol, and carvedilol) and particularly those with a narrow therapeutic index (e.g., flecainide and most tricyclic antidepressants) [see Clinical Pharmacology ( 12.3 )] .</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
Hypocalcemia : Life threatening events and fatal outcomes were reported. Hypocalcemia can prolong QT interval, lower the threshold for seizures, and cause hypotension, worsening heart failure, and/or arrhythmia.  Monitor serum calcium carefully for the occurrence of hypocalcemia during treatment ( 2.4 , 5.1 ) Upper Gastrointestinal (GI) Bleeding: Patients with risk factors for upper GI bleeding may be at increased risk. Monitor patients and promptly evaluate and treat any suspected GI bleeding. ( 5.2 ) Hypotension, Worsening Heart Failure and/or Arrhythmias : In postmarketing safety surveillance, isolated, idiosyncratic cases of hypotension, worsening heart failure, and/or arrhythmia have been reported in patients with impaired cardiac function. ( 5.3 ) Adynamic B one D isease : May develop if iPTH levels are suppressed below 100 pg/mL. ( 5.4 ) Sensipar lowers serum calcium and can lead to hypocalcemia [see Adverse Reactions ( 6.1 )]. Significant lowering of serum calcium can cause paresthesias, myalgias, muscle spasms, tetany, seizures, QT interval prolongation and ventricular arrhythmia. Life threatening events and fatal outcomes associated with hypocalcemia have been reported in patients treated with Sensipar, including in pediatric patients. The safety and effectiveness of Sensipar have not been established in pediatric patients  [see Pediatric Use ( 8.4 )]. Sensipar is not indicated for patients with CKD not on dialysis  [see I ndications and Usage ( 1 )] .  In patients with secondary HPT and CKD not on dialysis, the long term safety and efficacy of Sensipar have not been established.  Clinical studies indicate that Sensipar-treated patients with CKD not on dialysis have an increased risk for hypocalcemia compared with Sensipar-treated patients with CKD on dialysis, which may be due to lower baseline calcium levels.  In a phase 3 study of 32 weeks duration and including 404 patients with CKD not on dialysis (302 cinacalcet, 102 placebo), in which the median dose for cinacalcet was 60 mg per day at the completion of the study, 80% of Sensipar-treated patients experienced at least one serum calcium value &amp;lt; 8.4 mg/dL compared with 5% of patients receiving placebo. QT Interval Prolongation and V entricular A rr h ythmia Decreases in serum calcium can also prolong the QT interval, potentially resulting in ventricular arrhythmia. Cases of QT prolongation and ventricular arrhythmia have been reported in patients treated with Sensipar. Patients with congenital long QT syndrome, history of QT interval prolongation, family history of long QT syndrome or sudden cardiac death, and other conditions that predispose to QT interval prolongation and ventricular arrhythmia may be at increased risk for QT interval prolongation and ventricular arrhythmias if they develop hypocalcemia due to Sensipar. Closely monitor corrected serum calcium and QT interval in patients at risk receiving Sensipar. Seizures In clinical studies, seizures (primarily generalized or tonic-clonic) were observed in 1.4% (43/3049) of Sensipar-treated patients and 0.7% (5/687) of placebo-treated patients. While the basis for the reported difference in seizure rate is not clear, the threshold for seizures is lowered by significant reductions in serum calcium levels. Monitor serum calcium levels in patients with seizure disorders receiving Sensipar . Concurrent administration of Sensipar with calcium-lowering drugs including other calcium-sensing receptor agonists could result in severe hypocalcemia. Closely monitor serum calcium in patients receiving Sensipar and concomitant therapies known to lower serum calcium levels. Educate patients on the symptoms of hypocalcemia and advise them to contact a healthcare provider if they occur. If corrected serum calcium falls below the lower limit of normal or symptoms of hypocalcemia develop, start or increase calcium supplementation (including calcium, calcium-containing phosphate binders, and/or vitamin D sterols or increases in dialysate calcium concentration). Sensipar dose reduction or discontinuation of Sensipar may be necessary [see Dosage and Administration ( 2.2 )]. Cases of gastrointestinal bleeding, mostly upper gastrointestinal bleeding, have occurred in patients using calcimimetics, including Sensipar, from postmarketing and clinical trial sources. The exact cause of GI bleeding in these patients is unknown. Patients with risk factors for upper GI bleeding (such as known gastritis, esophagitis, ulcers or severe vomiting) may be at increased risk for GI bleeding when receiving Sensipar treatment. Monitor patients for worsening of common GI adverse reactions of nausea and vomiting associated with Sensipar [see Adverse Reactions ( 6.1 )] and for signs and symptoms of GI bleeding and ulcerations during Sensipar therapy. Promptly evaluate and treat any suspected GI bleeding. In postmarketing safety surveillance, isolated, idiosyncratic cases of hypotension, worsening heart failure, and/or arrhythmia have been reported in patients with impaired cardiac function, in which a causal relationship to Sensipar could not be completely excluded and which may be mediated by reductions in serum calcium levels [see Adverse Reactions ( 6.2 )]. Adynamic bone disease may develop if iPTH levels are suppressed below 100 pg/mL. One clinical study evaluated bone histomorphometry in patients treated with Sensipar for 1 year. Three patients with mild hyperparathyroid bone disease at the beginning of the study developed adynamic bone disease during treatment with Sensipar. Two of these patients had iPTH levels below 100 pg/mL at multiple time points during the study. In three 6-month, phase 3 studies conducted in patients with CKD on dialysis, 11% of patients treated with Sensipar had mean iPTH values below 100 pg/mL during the efficacy-assessment phase. If iPTH levels decrease below 150 pg/mL in patients treated with Sensipar, the dose of Sensipar and/or vitamin D sterols should be reduced or therapy discontinued.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
The calcium-sensing receptor on the surface of the chief cell of the parathyroid gland is the principal regulator of PTH synthesis and secretion. Cinacalcet, the active ingredient in Sensipar, directly lowers PTH levels by increasing the sensitivity of the calcium-sensing receptor to extracellular calcium. The reduction in PTH is associated with a concomitant decrease in serum calcium levels. Reduction in iPTH levels correlated with the plasma cinacalcet concentrations in patients with CKD. The nadir in iPTH level occurs approximately 2 to 6 hours post dose, corresponding with the maximum plasma concentration (C max ) of cinacalcet. After steady-state cinacalcet concentrations are reached (which occurs within 7 days of dose change), serum calcium concentrations remain constant over the dosing interval in patients with CKD. Reductions in PTH are associated with a decrease in bone turnover and bone fibrosis in patients with CKD on dialysis and uncontrolled secondary HPT. Absorption and Distribution After oral administration of cinacalcet, C max is achieved in approximately 2 to 6 hours. Cinacalcet C max and AUC (0-inf inite ) were increased by 82% and 68%, respectively, following administration with a high-fat meal compared with fasting in healthy volunteers. The C max and AUC (0-inf inite ) of cinacalcet were increased by 65% and 50%, respectively, when cinacalcet was administered with a low-fat meal compared with fasting. After absorption, cinacalcet concentrations decline in a biphasic fashion with an initial half-life of approximately 6 hours and terminal half-life of 30 to 40 hours. Steady-state drug levels are achieved within 7 days, and the mean accumulation ratio is approximately 2 with once daily oral administration. The median accumulation ratio is approximately 2 to 5 with twice daily oral administration. The AUC and C max of cinacalcet increase proportionally over the dose range of 30 to 180 mg once daily. The pharmacokinetic profile of cinacalcet does not change over time with once daily dosing of 30 to 180 mg. The volume of distribution is approximately 1000 L, indicating extensive distribution. Cinacalcet is approximately 93% to 97% bound to plasma protein(s). The ratio of blood cinacalcet concentration to plasma cinacalcet concentration is 0.80 at a blood cinacalcet concentration of 10 ng/mL.   Metabolism and Excretion Cinacalcet is metabolized by multiple enzymes, primarily CYP3A4, CYP2D6, and CYP1A2. After administration of a 75 mg radiolabeled dose to healthy volunteers, cinacalcet was metabolized via: 1) oxidative N-dealkylation to hydrocinnamic acid and hydroxy-hydrocinnamic acid, which are further metabolized via β-oxidation and glycine conjugation; the oxidative N-dealkylation process also generates metabolites that contain the naphthalene ring; and 2) oxidation of the naphthalene ring on the parent drug forming dihydrodiols, which are further conjugated with glucuronic acid. The plasma concentrations of the major circulating metabolites, including the cinnamic acid derivatives and glucuronidated dihydrodiols, markedly exceed the parent drug concentrations. The hydrocinnamic acid metabolite and glucuronide conjugates have minimal or no calcimimetic activity. Renal excretion of metabolites was the primary route of elimination of radioactivity. Approximately 80% of the dose was recovered in the urine and 15% in the feces. Specific Populations Age: Geriatric P opulation The pharmacokinetic profile of cinacalcet in geriatric patients (age ≥ 65 years, n = 12) is similar to that for patients who are &amp;lt; 65 years of age (n = 268) [see Use in Specific Populations ( 8.5 )] . Hepatic Impairment The disposition of a 50 mg Sensipar single dose was compared between patients with hepatic impairment and patients with normal hepatic function. Cinacalcet exposure (AUC (0-inf inite ) ) was comparable between healthy volunteers and patients with mild hepatic impairment. However, in patients with moderate and severe hepatic impairment (as indicated by the Child-Pugh method), cinacalcet exposures (AUC (0-inf inite ) ) were 2.4 and 4.2 fold higher, respectively, than that in healthy volunteers. The mean half-life of cinacalcet increased from 49 hours in healthy volunteers to 65 hours and 84 hours in patients with moderate and severe hepatic impairment, respectively. Protein binding of cinacalcet is not affected by impaired hepatic function [see Use in Specific Populations ( 8.7 )]. Renal Impairment The pharmacokinetic profile of a 75 mg Sensipar single dose in patients with mild, moderate, and severe renal impairment, and those on hemodialysis or peritoneal dialysis is comparable with that in healthy volunteers [see Use in Specific Populations ( 8.6 )] . Drug Interactions In vitro studies indicate that cinacalcet is a strong inhibitor of CYP2D6, but not an inhibitor of CYP1A2, CYP2C9, CYP2C19, and CYP3A4. In vitro induction studies indicate that cinacalcet is not an inducer of CYP450 enzymes. Tables 5 and 6 list the findings from in vivo drug-drug interaction studies. Table 5. Effect of co-administered drugs on cinacalcet Co - administered drug and dosing regimen Cinacalcet Dose * Mean change in AUC (0-inf) Mean change in C max 200 mg ketoconazole twice daily for 7 days 90 mg on day 5 ↑127% ↑116% 1500 mg calcium carbonate, single dose 100 mg ↓6% ↓5% 80 mg pantoprazole daily for 3 days 90 mg on day 3 ↑1% ↓3% 2400 mg sevelamer HCl three times a  day for 2 days 90 mg on day 1 with first dose of sevelamer ↓4% ↓7% *Single dose. Table 6. Effect of cinacalcet co-administration on other drugs Cinacalcet dosing regimen Co - administered drug Name and Dose Mean change in AUC (0-inf) Mean change in C max 30 mg twice daily for 8 days 25 mg warfarin * tablet † ↑1% for R-warfarin ↓1% for S-warfarin ↓10% for R-warfarin ↓12% for S-warfarin 90 mg daily for 7 days to CYP2D6 extensive metabolizers 50 mg desipramine † ↑264% ↑75% 90 mg daily for 5 days 2 mg midazolam † ↑5% ↓5% 25 or 100 mg single dose to CYP2D6 extensive metabolizers 50 mg amitriptyline single dose ↑21-22% for amitriptyline ↑17-23% for nortriptyline ‡ ↑13-21% for amitriptyline ↑11-15% for nortriptyline ‡ *No significant change in prothrombin time. † Single dose on day 5. ‡ Nortriptyline is an active metabolite of amitriptyline.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="9442" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Sensipar treatment initiation is contraindicated if serum calcium is less than the lower limit of the normal range.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9443" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Sensipar tablets should be taken with food or shortly after a meal (2.1).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9444" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Tablets should always be taken whole and not divided (2.1) Secondary HPT in patients with CKD on dialysis (2.2):○ Starting dose is 30 mg once daily.○ Titrate dose no more frequently than every 2 to 4 weeks through sequential doses of 30, 60, 90, 120, and 180 mg once daily as necessary to achieve targeted intact parathyroid hormone (iPTH) levels.○ iPTH levels should be measured no earlier than 12 hours after most recent dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9445" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Hypercalcemia in patients with PC or hypercalcemia in patients with primary HPT (2.3):○ Starting dose is 30 mg twice daily.○ Titrate dose every 2 to 4 weeks through sequential doses of 30 mg twice daily, 60 mg twice daily, 90 mg twice daily, and 90 mg three or four times daily as necessary to normalize serum calcium levels.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9446" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Once the maintenance dose has been established, monitor serum calcium approximately monthly for patients with secondary HPT and every 2 months for patients with PC or primary HPT (2.4) Sensipar should be taken with food or shortly after a meal.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9447" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Sensipar tablets are administered orally and should always be taken whole and not chewed, crushed, or divided.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9448" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Co-administration with a strong CYP3A4 inhibitor may increase serum levels of cinacalcet.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M1" type="Trigger" span="53 21" str="increase serum levels"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="25 23" str="strong CYP3A4 inhibitor" code="N0000182141"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M1" precipitant="M2" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9449" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Dose adjustment and monitoring of iPTH serum phosphorus and serum calcium may be required.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9450" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Cinacalcet is a strong inhibitor of CYP2D6.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9451" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Dose adjustments may be required for concomitant medications that are predominantly metabolized by CYP2D6.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M3" type="Trigger" span="0 16" str="Dose adjustments"/>
<Mention id="M4" type="Precipitant" span="49 56" str="medications that are predominantly metabolized by CYP2D6" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M3" precipitant="M4"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9452" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Cinacalcet is partially metabolized by CYP3A4.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9453" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Dose adjustment of Sensipar may be required if a patient initiates or discontinues therapy with a strong CYP3A4 inhibitor (e.g., ketoconazole, itraconazole).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M9" type="Trigger" span="0 15" str="Dose adjustment"/>
<Mention id="M6" type="Precipitant" span="143 12" str="itraconazole" code="304NUG5GF4 | N0000006753"/>
<Mention id="M8" type="Precipitant" span="129 12" str="ketoconazole" code="N0000007319 | R9400W927I"/>
<Mention id="M10" type="Precipitant" span="98 23" str="strong CYP3A4 inhibitor" code="N0000182141"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M9" precipitant="M6"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M9" precipitant="M8"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M9" precipitant="M10"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9454" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The iPTH and serum calcium concentrations should be closely monitored in these patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9455" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Dose adjustments may be required for concomitant medications that are predominantly metabolized by CYP2D6 (e.g., desipramine, metoprolol, and carvedilol) and particularly those with a narrow therapeutic index (e.g., flecainide and most tricyclic antidepressants).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M21" type="Trigger" span="0 16" str="Dose adjustments"/>
<Mention id="M12" type="Precipitant" span="142 10" str="carvedilol" code="0K47UL67F2"/>
<Mention id="M14" type="Precipitant" span="113 11" str="desipramine" code="TG537D343B"/>
<Mention id="M16" type="Precipitant" span="216 10" str="flecainide" code="N0000006966 | K94FTS1806"/>
<Mention id="M18" type="Precipitant" span="49 56" str="medications that are predominantly metabolized by CYP2D6" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M20" type="Precipitant" span="126 10" str="metoprolol" code="GEB06NHM23"/>
<Mention id="M22" type="Precipitant" span="236 25" str="tricyclic antidepressants" code="N0000029148 | N0000175752"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M21" precipitant="M12"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M21" precipitant="M14"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M21" precipitant="M16"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M21" precipitant="M18"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M21" precipitant="M20"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M21" precipitant="M22"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9456" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hypocalcemia : Life threatening events and fatal outcomes were reported.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9457" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hypocalcemia can prolong QT interval, lower the threshold for seizures, and cause hypotension, worsening heart failure, and/or arrhythmia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9458" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor serum calcium carefully for the occurrence of hypocalcemia during treatment (2.4, 5.1) Upper Gastrointestinal (GI) Bleeding: Patients with risk factors for upper GI bleeding may be at increased risk.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9459" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor patients and promptly evaluate and treat any suspected GI bleeding.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9460" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hypotension, Worsening Heart Failure and/or Arrhythmias: In postmarketing safety surveillance, isolated, idiosyncratic cases of hypotension, worsening heart failure, and/or arrhythmia have been reported in patients with impaired cardiac function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9461" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Adynamic B one D isease: May develop if iPTH levels are suppressed below 100 pg/mL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9462" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Sensipar lowers serum calcium and can lead to hypocalcemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9463" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Significant lowering of serum calcium can cause paresthesias, myalgias, muscle spasms, tetany, seizures, QT interval prolongation and ventricular arrhythmia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9464" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Life threatening events and fatal outcomes associated with hypocalcemia have been reported in patients treated with Sensipar, including in pediatric patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9465" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The safety and effectiveness of Sensipar have not been established in pediatric patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9466" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Sensipar is not indicated for patients with CKD not on dialysis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9467" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In patients with secondary HPT and CKD not on dialysis, the long term safety and efficacy of Sensipar have not been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9468" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Clinical studies indicate that Sensipar-treated patients with CKD not on dialysis have an increased risk for hypocalcemia compared with Sensipar-treated patients with CKD on dialysis, which may be due to lower baseline calcium levels.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9469" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In a phase 3 study of 32 weeks duration and including 404 patients with CKD not on dialysis (302 cinacalcet, 102 placebo), in which the median dose for cinacalcet was 60 mg per day at the completion of the study, 80% of Sensipar-treated patients experienced at least one serum calcium value &lt; 8.4 mg/dL compared with 5% of patients receiving placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9470" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>QT Interval Prolongation and V entricular A rr h ythmia Decreases in serum calcium can also prolong the QT interval, potentially resulting in ventricular arrhythmia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9471" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Cases of QT prolongation and ventricular arrhythmia have been reported in patients treated with Sensipar.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9472" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients with congenital long QT syndrome, history of QT interval prolongation, family history of long QT syndrome or sudden cardiac death, and other conditions that predispose to QT interval prolongation and ventricular arrhythmia may be at increased risk for QT interval prolongation and ventricular arrhythmias if they develop hypocalcemia due to Sensipar.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9473" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Closely monitor corrected serum calcium and QT interval in patients at risk receiving Sensipar.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9474" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Seizures In clinical studies, seizures (primarily generalized or tonic-clonic) were observed in 1.4% (43/3049) of Sensipar-treated patients and 0.7% (5/687) of placebo-treated patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9475" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>While the basis for the reported difference in seizure rate is not clear, the threshold for seizures is lowered by significant reductions in serum calcium levels.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9476" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor serum calcium levels in patients with seizure disorders receiving Sensipar.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9477" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Concurrent administration of Sensipar with calcium-lowering drugs including other calcium-sensing receptor agonists could result in severe hypocalcemia.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M26" type="Trigger" span="122 9" str="result in"/>
<Mention id="M24" type="Precipitant" span="43 22" str="calcium-lowering drugs" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M28" type="SpecificInteraction" span="132 19" str="severe hypocalcemia" code="5291005: Hypocalcemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M27" type="Precipitant" span="82 33" str="calcium-sensing receptor agonists" code="N0000175902"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M26" precipitant="M24" effect="M28" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M26" precipitant="M27" effect="M28" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9478" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Closely monitor serum calcium in patients receiving Sensipar and concomitant therapies known to lower serum calcium levels.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M29" type="Trigger" span="8 7" str="monitor "/>
<Mention id="M30" type="Trigger" span="96 5" str=" lower"/>
<Mention id="M31" type="Precipitant" span="77 45" str="therapies known to lower serum calcium levels" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M32" type="SpecificInteraction" span="96 26" str="lower serum calcium levels" code="5291005: Hypocalcemia (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M29;M30" precipitant="M31" effect="M32" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9479" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Educate patients on the symptoms of hypocalcemia and advise them to contact a healthcare provider if they occur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9480" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If corrected serum calcium falls below the lower limit of normal or symptoms of hypocalcemia develop, start or increase calcium supplementation (including calcium, calcium-containing phosphate binders, and/or vitamin D sterols or increases in dialysate calcium concentration).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9481" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Sensipar dose reduction or discontinuation of Sensipar may be necessary.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9482" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Cases of gastrointestinal bleeding, mostly upper gastrointestinal bleeding, have occurred in patients using calcimimetics, including Sensipar, from postmarketing and clinical trial sources.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9483" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The exact cause of GI bleeding in these patients is unknown.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9484" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients with risk factors for upper GI bleeding (such as known gastritis, esophagitis, ulcers or severe vomiting) may be at increased risk for GI bleeding when receiving Sensipar treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9485" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor patients for worsening of common GI adverse reactions of nausea and vomiting associated with Sensipar and for signs and symptoms of GI bleeding and ulcerations during Sensipar therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9486" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Promptly evaluate and treat any suspected GI bleeding.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9487" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In postmarketing safety surveillance, isolated, idiosyncratic cases of hypotension, worsening heart failure, and/or arrhythmia have been reported in patients with impaired cardiac function, in which a causal relationship to Sensipar could not be completely excluded and which may be mediated by reductions in serum calcium levels.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9488" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Adynamic bone disease may develop if iPTH levels are suppressed below 100 pg/mL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9489" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>One clinical study evaluated bone histomorphometry in patients treated with Sensipar for 1 year.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9490" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Three patients with mild hyperparathyroid bone disease at the beginning of the study developed adynamic bone disease during treatment with Sensipar.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9491" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Two of these patients had iPTH levels below 100 pg/mL at multiple time points during the study.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9492" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In three 6-month, phase 3 studies conducted in patients with CKD on dialysis, 11% of patients treated with Sensipar had mean iPTH values below 100 pg/mL during the efficacy-assessment phase.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9493" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If iPTH levels decrease below 150 pg/mL in patients treated with Sensipar, the dose of Sensipar and/or vitamin D sterols should be reduced or therapy discontinued.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M33" type="Trigger" span="0 2;15 8" str="If | decrease "/>
<Mention id="M34" type="Trigger" span="79 4;131 7" str=" dose | reduced "/>
<Mention id="M35" type="Trigger" span="150 12" str=" discontinued"/>
<Mention id="M36" type="Precipitant" span="103 17" str="vitamin D sterols" code="N0000175952"/>
<Mention id="M37" type="SpecificInteraction" span="3 36" str="iPTH levels decrease below 150 pg/mL" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M33;M34;M35" precipitant="M36" effect="M37" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9494" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The calcium-sensing receptor on the surface of the chief cell of the parathyroid gland is the principal regulator of PTH synthesis and secretion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9495" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Cinacalcet, the active ingredient in Sensipar, directly lowers PTH levels by increasing the sensitivity of the calcium-sensing receptor to extracellular calcium.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9496" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The reduction in PTH is associated with a concomitant decrease in serum calcium levels.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9497" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Reduction in iPTH levels correlated with the plasma cinacalcet concentrations in patients with CKD.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9498" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The nadir in iPTH level occurs approximately 2 to 6 hours post dose, corresponding with the maximum plasma concentration (Cmax) of cinacalcet.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9499" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>After steady-state cinacalcet concentrations are reached (which occurs within 7 days of dose change), serum calcium concentrations remain constant over the dosing interval in patients with CKD.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9500" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Reductions in PTH are associated with a decrease in bone turnover and bone fibrosis in patients with CKD on dialysis and uncontrolled secondary HPT.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9501" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Absorption and Distribution After oral administration of cinacalcet, Cmax is achieved in approximately 2 to 6 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9502" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Cinacalcet Cmax and AUC(0-inf inite ) were increased by 82% and 68%, respectively, following administration with a high-fat meal compared with fasting in healthy volunteers.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M38" type="Trigger" span="20 3;43 9" str="AUC | increased"/>
<Mention id="M41" type="Precipitant" span="115 13" str="high-fat meal" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M40" type="Trigger" span="11 4;43 9" str="Cmax | increased"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M38" precipitant="M41" effect="C54605"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M40" precipitant="M41" effect="C54602"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9503" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The Cmax and AUC(0-inf inite ) of cinacalcet were increased by 65% and 50%, respectively, when cinacalcet was administered with a low-fat meal compared with fasting.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M42" type="Trigger" span="13 3;50 9" str="AUC | increased"/>
<Mention id="M45" type="Precipitant" span="130 12" str="low-fat meal" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M44" type="Trigger" span="4 4;50 9" str="Cmax | increased"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M42" precipitant="M45" effect="C54605"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M44" precipitant="M45" effect="C54602"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9504" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>After absorption, cinacalcet concentrations decline in a biphasic fashion with an initial half-life of approximately 6 hours and terminal half-life of 30 to 40 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9505" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Steady-state drug levels are achieved within 7 days, and the mean accumulation ratio is approximately 2 with once daily oral administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9506" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The median accumulation ratio is approximately 2 to 5 with twice daily oral administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9507" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The AUC and Cmax of cinacalcet increase proportionally over the dose range of 30 to 180 mg once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9508" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacokinetic profile of cinacalcet does not change over time with once daily dosing of 30 to 180 mg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9509" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The volume of distribution is approximately 1000 L, indicating extensive distribution.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9510" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Cinacalcet is approximately 93% to 97% bound to plasma protein(s).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9511" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The ratio of blood cinacalcet concentration to plasma cinacalcet concentration is 0.80 at a blood cinacalcet concentration of 10 ng/mL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9512" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Metabolism and Excretion Cinacalcet is metabolized by multiple enzymes, primarily CYP3A4, CYP2D6, and CYP1A2.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9513" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>After administration of a 75 mg radiolabeled dose to healthy volunteers, cinacalcet was metabolized via: 1) oxidative N-dealkylation to hydrocinnamic acid and hydroxy-hydrocinnamic acid, which are further metabolized via β-oxidation and glycine conjugation; the oxidative N-dealkylation process also generates metabolites that contain the naphthalene ring; and 2) oxidation of the naphthalene ring on the parent drug forming dihydrodiols, which are further conjugated with glucuronic acid.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9514" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The plasma concentrations of the major circulating metabolites, including the cinnamic acid derivatives and glucuronidated dihydrodiols, markedly exceed the parent drug concentrations.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9515" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The hydrocinnamic acid metabolite and glucuronide conjugates have minimal or no calcimimetic activity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9516" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Renal excretion of metabolites was the primary route of elimination of radioactivity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9517" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Approximately 80% of the dose was recovered in the urine and 15% in the feces.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9518" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Specific Populations Age: Geriatric P opulation The pharmacokinetic profile of cinacalcet in geriatric patients (age ≥ 65 years, n = 12) is similar to that for patients who are &lt; 65 years of age (n = 268).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9519" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Hepatic Impairment The disposition of a 50 mg Sensipar single dose was compared between patients with hepatic impairment and patients with normal hepatic function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9520" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Cinacalcet exposure (AUC(0-inf inite )) was comparable between healthy volunteers and patients with mild hepatic impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9521" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>However, in patients with moderate and severe hepatic impairment (as indicated by the Child-Pugh method), cinacalcet exposures (AUC(0-inf inite )) were 2.4 and 4.2 fold higher, respectively, than that in healthy volunteers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9522" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mean half-life of cinacalcet increased from 49 hours in healthy volunteers to 65 hours and 84 hours in patients with moderate and severe hepatic impairment, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9523" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Protein binding of cinacalcet is not affected by impaired hepatic function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9524" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Renal Impairment The pharmacokinetic profile of a 75 mg Sensipar single dose in patients with mild, moderate, and severe renal impairment, and those on hemodialysis or peritoneal dialysis is comparable with that in healthy volunteers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9525" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Drug Interactions In vitro studies indicate that cinacalcet is a strong inhibitor of CYP2D6, but not an inhibitor of CYP1A2, CYP2C9, CYP2C19, and CYP3A4.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9526" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In vitro induction studies indicate that cinacalcet is not an inducer of CYP450 enzymes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9527" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Tables 5 and 6 list the findings from in vivo drug-drug interaction studies.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9528" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Effect of co-administered drugs on cinacalcet Co-administered drug and dosing regimen Cinacalcet Dose * Mean change in AUC (0-inf) Mean change in C max 200 mg ketoconazole twice daily for 7 days 90 mg on day 5 ↑127% ↑116% 1500 mg calcium carbonate, single dose 100 mg ↓6% ↓5% 80 mg pantoprazole daily for 3 days 90 mg on day 3 ↑1% ↓3% 2400 mg sevelamer HCl three times a day for 2 days 90 mg on day 1 with firstdose of sevelamer ↓4% ↓7% *Single dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9529" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Effect of cinacalcet co-administration on other drugs Cinacalcet dosing regimen Co-administered drug Name and Dose Mean change in AUC (0-inf) Mean change in C max 30 mg twice daily for 8 days 25 mg warfarin* tablet† ↑1% for R-warfarin↓1% for S-warfarin ↓10% for R-warfarin ↓12% for S-warfarin 90 mg daily for 7 days to CYP2D6 extensive metabolizers 50 mg desipramine† ↑264% ↑75% 90 mg daily for 5 days 2 mg midazolam† ↑5% ↓5% 25 or 100 mg single dose to CYP2D6 extensive metabolizers 50 mg amitriptylinesingle dose ↑21-22% for amitriptyline↑17-23% for nortriptyline‡ ↑13-21% for amitriptyline↑11-15% for nortriptyline‡ *No significant change in prothrombin time.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9530" LabelDrug="Sensipar" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>‡Nortriptyline is an active metabolite of amitriptyline.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="strong cyp3a4 inhibitor" precipitantCode="N0000182141" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="strong cyp3a4 inhibitor" precipitantCode="N0000182141"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="medications that are predominantly metabolized by cyp2d6" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="itraconazole" precipitantCode="304NUG5GF4 | N0000006753"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="ketoconazole" precipitantCode="N0000007319 | R9400W927I"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="carvedilol" precipitantCode="0K47UL67F2"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="desipramine" precipitantCode="TG537D343B"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="flecainide" precipitantCode="N0000006966 | K94FTS1806"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="metoprolol" precipitantCode="GEB06NHM23"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="tricyclic antidepressants" precipitantCode="N0000029148 | N0000175752"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="calcium-lowering drugs" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="5291005: Hypocalcemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="calcium-sensing receptor agonists" precipitantCode="N0000175902" effect="5291005: Hypocalcemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="therapies known to lower serum calcium levels" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="5291005: Hypocalcemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="vitamin d sterols" precipitantCode="N0000175952" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="high-fat meal" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54602"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="high-fat meal" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54605"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="low-fat meal" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54602"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="low-fat meal" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54605"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>