<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="QUDEXY" setid="46f54677-3a22-4c38-9b92-923020164e15">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
QUDEXY XR is contraindicated in patients with metabolic acidosis who are taking concomitant metformin [see Warnings and Precautions (5.4) , Drug Interactions (7.5) , and Clinical Pharmacology (12.3) ] . In patients with metabolic acidosis taking concomitant metformin ( 4 ) ( 5.4 )</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
Initial Dose Titration Recommended Dose Monotherapy: Partial Onset or Primary Generalized Tonic-Clonic Seizures Adults and pediatric patients 10 years and older ( 2.1 ) 50 mg once daily Increase dose weekly by increments of 50 mg for the first 4 weeks then 100 mg for weeks 5 to 6 400 mg once daily Pediatric patients 2 to less than 10 years ( 2.1 ) 25 mg once daily at nighttime for the first week Titrate the dosage over 5 to 7 weeks Once daily doses based on weight (Table 2) Adjunctive Therapy Adults with partial onset seizures or LGS ( 2.1 ) 25 mg to 50 mg once daily Increase dose weekly by increments of 25 mg to 50 mg to achieve an effective dose 200 mg to 400 mg once daily Adults with primary generalized tonic-clonic seizures ( 2.1 ) 25 mg to 50 mg once daily Increase dose weekly to an effective dose by increments of 25 mg to 50 mg 400 mg once daily Pediatric patients 2 years and older with partial onset seizures, primary generalized tonic-clonic seizures or LGS ( 2.1 ) 25 mg once daily at nighttime for the first week Increase dosage at 1 or 2 week intervals by increments of 1 mg/kg to 3 mg/kg; dose titration should be guided by clinical outcome 5 mg/kg to 9 mg/kg once daily Migraine ( 2.2 ) 25 mg once daily at nighttime for the first week Increase dose weekly by increments of 25 mg. Dosage and titration should be guided by clinical outcome. 100 mg once daily Capsules may be swallowed whole or opened and sprinkled on a spoonful of soft food ( 2.8 ) Monotherapy Use Adults and Pediatric Patients 10 Years and Older with Partial Onset or Primary Generalized Tonic-Clonic Seizures The recommended dose for QUDEXY XR monotherapy in adults and pediatric patients 10 years of age and older is 400 mg orally once daily. Titrate QUDEXY XR according to the following schedule [Table 1]: Table 1: Monotherapy Titration Schedule for Adults and Pediatric Patients 10 years and older QUDEXY XR Once Daily Dose Week 1 50 mg Week 2 100 mg Week 3 150 mg Week 4 200 mg Week 5 300 mg Week 6 400 mg Pediatric Patients 2 to less than 10 Years with Partial Onset or Primary Generalized Tonic-Clonic Seizures Dosing in patients 2 to less than 10 years is based on weight. During the titration period, the initial dose of QUDEXY XR should be 25 mg once daily given at nighttime for the first week. Based upon tolerability, the dosage can be increased to 50 mg once daily in the second week. Dosage can be increased by 25 mg to 50 mg once daily each subsequent week, as tolerated. Titration to the minimum maintenance dose should be attempted over 5 to 7 weeks. Based upon tolerability and clinical response, additional titration to a higher dose (up to the maximum maintenance dose) can be attempted in weekly increments by 25 mg to 50 mg once daily, up to the maximum recommended maintenance dose for each range of body weight [see Table 2 ] . Table 2: Monotherapy Target Once Daily Maintenance Dosing for Patients 2 to Less Than 10 Years Weight (kg) Once Daily Dose (mg per day) Minimum Maintenance Dose Once Daily Dose (mg per day) Maximum Maintenance Dose Up to 11 150 250 12 to 22 200 300 23 to 31 200 350 32 to 38 250 350 Greater than 38 250 400 Adjunctive Therapy Use Adults (17 Years of Age and Older) - Partial Onset Seizures, Primary Generalized Tonic-Clonic Seizures, or Lennox-Gastaut Syndrome The recommended total daily dose of QUDEXY XR as adjunctive therapy in adults with partial onset seizures or Lennox-Gastaut Syndrome is 200 mg to 400 mg orally once daily. The recommended total dose for adults with primary generalized tonic-clonic seizures is 400 mg orally once daily. Initiate therapy at 25 mg to 50 mg once daily followed by titration to an effective dose in increments of 25 mg to 50 mg every week. Daily topiramate doses above 1,600 mg have not been studied. In the study of primary generalized tonic-clonic seizures using topiramate, the assigned dose was reached at the end of 8 weeks [see Clinical Studies (14.4) ] . Pediatric Patients (Ages 2 Years to 16 Years) - Partial Onset Seizures, Primary Generalized Tonic-Clonic Seizures, or Lennox-Gastaut Syndrome The recommended total daily dose of QUDEXY XR as adjunctive therapy for pediatric patients with partial onset seizures, primary generalized tonic-clonic seizures, or seizures associated with Lennox-Gastaut syndrome is approximately 5 mg/kg to 9 mg/kg orally once daily. Begin titration at 25 mg once daily (based on a range of 1 mg/kg/day to 3 mg/kg/day) given nightly for the first week. Subsequently, increase the dosage at 1 or 2 week intervals by increments of 1 mg/kg to 3 mg/kg to achieve optimal clinical response. Dose titration should be guided by clinical outcome. If required, longer intervals between dose adjustments can be used. In the study of primary generalized tonic-clonic seizures, the assigned dose of 6 mg/kg once daily was reached at the end of 8 weeks [see Clinical Studies (14.3 , 14.4 , and 14.5) ] . The recommended total daily dose of QUDEXY XR as treatment for prophylaxis of migraine headache in adults and adolescents 12 years of age and older is 100 mg once daily. The recommended titration rate for QUDEXY XR for migraine prophylaxis to 100 mg/day is: Table 3: Migraine Prophylaxis Titration Schedule for Adults and Adolescents 12 years of Age and Older QUDEXY XR Once Daily Dose Week 1 25 mg Week 2 50 mg Week 3 75 mg Week 4 100 mg Dose and titration rate should be guided by clinical outcome. If required, longer intervals between dose adjustments can be used. In patients with renal impairment (creatinine clearance less than 70 mL/min/1.73 m 2 ), one-half of the usual adult dose is recommended. Such patients will require a longer time to reach steady-state at each dose [see Use in Specific Populations (8.7) and Clinical Pharmacology (12.3) ]. Prior to dosing, obtain an estimated creatinine clearance (CrCl) in patients at high risk for renal insufficiency (e.g., older patients, or those with diabetes mellitus, hypertension, or autoimmune disease). CrCl can be estimated using the following equation (multiply by 0.85 for women): CrCl = (140 – age ) × weight ( kg ) SerumCr ( mg / dl ) × 72 Topiramate is cleared by hemodialysis at a rate that is 4 to 6 times greater than in patients with normal renal function. Accordingly, a prolonged period of dialysis may cause topiramate concentration to fall below that required to maintain an anti-seizure effect. To avoid rapid drops in topiramate plasma concentration during hemodialysis, a supplemental dose of topiramate may be required. The actual adjustment should take into account the: duration of dialysis period clearance rate of the dialysis system being used effective renal clearance of topiramate in the patient being dialyzed [see Use in Specific Populations (8.8) and Clinical Pharmacology (12.3) ] . Measurement of baseline and periodic serum bicarbonate during QUDEXY XR treatment is recommended [see Warnings and Precautions (5.4) ] . The co-administration of QUDEXY XR with phenytoin may require an adjustment of the dose of phenytoin to achieve optimal clinical outcome. Addition or withdrawal of phenytoin and/or carbamazepine during adjunctive therapy with QUDEXY XR may require adjustment of the dose of QUDEXY XR [see Drug Interactions (7.2) and Clinical Pharmacology (12.3) ] . It is not necessary to monitor topiramate plasma concentrations to optimize QUDEXY XR therapy. QUDEXY XR capsules may be swallowed whole or may be administered by carefully opening the capsule and sprinkling the entire contents on a small amount (teaspoon) of soft food. This drug/food mixture should be swallowed immediately and not chewed or crushed. Do not store drug/food mixture for further use. QUDEXY XR can be taken without regard to meals [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3) ] .</Section>
<Section name="DRUG &amp;amp; OR LABORATORY TEST INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34074-5">
Drug/Laboratory Tests Interactions There are no known interactions of QUDEXY XR with commonly used laboratory tests.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
Oral contraceptives: Decreased contraceptive efficacy and increased breakthrough bleeding, especially at doses greater than 200 mg per day ( 7.1 ) Phenytoin or carbamazepine: Concomitant administration with topiramate decreased plasma concentrations of topiramate ( 7.2 ) Lithium: Monitor lithium levels when co-administered with high-dose topiramate ( 7.6 ) The possibility of decreased contraceptive efficacy and increased breakthrough bleeding should be considered in patients taking combination oral contraceptive products with QUDEXY XR. Patients taking estrogen-containing contraceptives should be asked to report any change in their bleeding patterns. Contraceptive efficacy can be decreased even in the absence of breakthrough bleeding [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3) ] . Concomitant administration of phenytoin or carbamazepine with topiramate decreased plasma concentrations of topiramate [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3) ] . Concomitant administration of valproic acid and topiramate has been associated with hyperammonemia with and without encephalopathy. Concomitant administration of topiramate with valproic acid has also been associated with hypothermia (with and without hyperammonemia) in patients who have tolerated either drug alone. It may be prudent to examine blood ammonia levels in patients in whom the onset of hypothermia has been reported [see Warnings and Precautions (5.9) and Clinical Pharmacology (12.3) ] . Numerous AEDs are substrates of the CYP enzyme system. In vitro studies indicate that topiramate does not inhibit enzyme activity for CYP1A2, CYP2A6, CYP2B6, CYP2C9, CYP2D6, CYP2E1, and CYP3A4/5 isozymes. In vitro studies indicate that immediate-release topiramate is a mild inhibitor of CYP2C19 and a mild inducer of CYP3A4. The same drug interactions can be expected with the use of QUDEXY XR. Topiramate is a CNS depressant. Concomitant administration of topiramate with other CNS depressant drugs or alcohol can result in significant CNS depression. Concomitant use of alcohol should be avoided [see Warnings and Precautions (5.13) and Clinical Pharmacology (12.3) ] . Concomitant use of topiramate, a carbonic anhydrase inhibitor, with any other carbonic anhydrase inhibitor (e.g., zonisamide, acetazolamide or dichlorphenamide), may increase the severity of metabolic acidosis and may also increase the risk of kidney stone formation. Patients should be monitored for the appearance or worsening of metabolic acidosis when QUDEXY XR is given concomitantly with another carbonic anhydrase inhibitor [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3) ] . Topiramate treatment can frequently cause metabolic acidosis, a condition for which the use of metformin is contraindicated. The concomitant use of QUDEXY XR and metformin is contraindicated in patients with metabolic acidosis [see Contraindications (4) , Warnings and Precautions (5.4) and Clinical Pharmacology (12.3) ] . In patients, there was an observed increase in systemic exposure of lithium following topiramate doses of up to 600 mg per day. Lithium levels should be monitored when co-administered with high-dose QUDEXY XR [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3) ] .</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
Acute myopia and secondary angle closure glaucoma: Untreated elevated intraocular pressure can lead to permanent visual loss. Discontinue QUDEXY XR if it occurs ( 5.1 ) Visual field defects: These have been reported independent of elevated intraocular pressure. Consider discontinuation of QUDEXY XR ( 5.2 ) Oligohydrosis and hyperthermia: Monitor decreased sweating and increased body temperature, especially in pediatric patients ( 5.3 ) Metabolic acidosis: Measure baseline and periodic measurement of serum bicarbonate. Consider dose reduction or discontinuation of QUDEXY XR if clinically appropriate ( 5.4 ) Suicidal behavior and ideation: Antiepileptic drugs increase the risk of suicidal behavior or ideation ( 5.5 ) Cognitive/neuropsychiatric: QUDEXY XR may cause cognitive dysfunction. Use caution when operating machinery including automobiles. Depression and mood problems may occur ( 5.6 ) Fetal toxicity: Topiramate use during pregnancy can cause cleft lip and/or palate and increases the risk of being small for gestational age ( 5.7 ) Withdrawal of AEDs: Withdrawal of QUDEXY XR should be done gradually ( 5.8 ) Hyperammonemia and encephalopathy: Patients with inborn errors of metabolism or reduced mitochondrial activity may have an increased risk of hyperammonemia. Measure ammonia if encephalopathic symptoms occur ( 5.9 ) Kidney stones: Avoid use with other carbonic anhydrase inhibitors, other drugs causing metabolic acidosis, or in patients on a ketogenic diet ( 5.10 ) Hypothermia: Reported with concomitant valproic acid use ( 5.11 ) A syndrome consisting of acute myopia associated with secondary angle closure glaucoma has been reported in patients receiving topiramate. Symptoms include acute onset of decreased visual acuity and/or ocular pain. Ophthalmologic findings can include myopia, anterior chamber shallowing, ocular hyperemia (redness) and increased intraocular pressure. Mydriasis may or may not be present. This syndrome may be associated with supraciliary effusion resulting in anterior displacement of the lens and iris, with secondary angle closure glaucoma. Symptoms typically occur within 1 month of initiating topiramate therapy. In contrast to primary narrow angle glaucoma, which is rare under 40 years of age, secondary angle closure glaucoma associated with topiramate has been reported in pediatric patients as well as adults. The primary treatment to reverse symptoms is discontinuation of QUDEXY XR as rapidly as possible, according to the judgment of the treating physician. Other measures, in conjunction with discontinuation of QUDEXY XR, may be helpful. Elevated intraocular pressure of any etiology, if left untreated, can lead to serious sequelae including permanent vision loss. Visual field defects have been reported in patients receiving topiramate independent of elevated intraocular pressure. In clinical trials, most of these events were reversible after topiramate discontinuation. If visual problems occur at any time during treatment with QUDEXY XR, consideration should be given to discontinuing the drug. Oligohydrosis (decreased sweating), resulting in hospitalization in some cases, has been reported in association with topiramate use. Decreased sweating and an elevation in body temperature above normal characterized these cases. Some of the cases were reported after exposure to elevated environmental temperatures. The majority of the reports have been in pediatric patients. Patients, especially pediatric patients, treated with QUDEXY XR should be monitored closely for evidence of decreased sweating and increased body temperature, especially in hot weather. Caution should be used when QUDEXY XR is prescribed with other drugs that predispose patients to heat-related disorders; these drugs include, but are not limited to, other carbonic anhydrase inhibitors and drugs with anticholinergic activity [see Drug Interactions (7.4) ] . Hyperchloremic, non-anion gap, metabolic acidosis (i.e., decreased serum bicarbonate below the normal reference range in the absence of chronic respiratory alkalosis) is associated with topiramate treatment. This metabolic acidosis is caused by renal bicarbonate loss due to the inhibitory effect of topiramate on carbonic anhydrase. Such electrolyte imbalance has been observed with the use of topiramate in placebo-controlled clinical trials and in the post-marketing period. Generally, topiramate-induced metabolic acidosis occurs early in treatment although cases can occur at any time during treatment. Bicarbonate decrements are usually mild-moderate (average decrease of 4 mEq/L at daily doses of 400 mg in adults and at approximately 6 mg/kg/day in pediatric patients); rarely, patients can experience severe decrements to values below 10 mEq/L. Conditions or therapies that predispose patients to acidosis (such as renal disease, severe respiratory disorders, status epilepticus, diarrhea, ketogenic diet or specific drugs) may be additive to the bicarbonate lowering effects of topiramate. Manifestations of Metabolic Acidosis Some manifestations of acute or chronic metabolic acidosis may include hyperventilation, nonspecific symptoms such as fatigue and anorexia, or more severe sequelae including cardiac arrhythmias or stupor. Chronic, untreated metabolic acidosis may increase the risk for nephrolithiasis or nephrocalcinosis, and may also result in osteomalacia (referred to as rickets in pediatric patients) and/or osteoporosis with an increased risk for fractures. Chronic metabolic acidosis in pediatric patients may also reduce growth rates. A reduction in growth rate may eventually decrease the maximal height achieved. The effect of topiramate on growth and bone-related sequelae has not been systematically investigated in long-term, placebo-controlled trials. Long-term, open-label treatment of infants/toddlers, with intractable partial epilepsy, for up to 1 year, showed reductions from baseline in Z SCORES for length, weight, and head circumference compared to age and sex-matched normative data, although these patients are likely to have different growth rates than normal infants. Reductions in Z SCORES for length and weight were correlated to the degree of acidosis [see Use in Specific Populations (8.4) ] . Topiramate treatment that causes metabolic acidosis during pregnancy can possibly produce adverse effects on the fetus and might also cause metabolic acidosis in the neonate from possible transfer of topiramate to the fetus [see Warnings and Precautions (5.7) and Use in Specific Populations (8.1) ] . Epilepsy Adult Patients In adults, the incidence of persistent decreases in serum bicarbonate (levels of less than 20 mEq/L at two consecutive visits or at the final visit) in controlled clinical trials for adjunctive treatment of epilepsy was 32% for 400 mg per day, and 1% for placebo. Metabolic acidosis has been observed at doses as low as 50 mg per day. The incidence of a markedly abnormally low serum bicarbonate (i.e., absolute value less than 17 mEq/L and greater than 5 mEq/L decrease from pretreatment) in the adjunctive therapy trials was 3% for 400 mg per day and 0% for placebo. The incidence of persistent decreases in serum bicarbonate in adult patients (≥16 years of age) in the epilepsy controlled clinical trial for monotherapy was 14% for 50 mg per day and 25% for 400 mg per day. The incidence of a markedly abnormally low serum bicarbonate (i.e., absolute value less than 17 mEq/L and greater than 5 mEq/L decrease from pretreatment) in this trial for adults was 1% for 50 mg per day and 6% for 400 mg per day. Serum bicarbonate levels have not been systematically evaluated at daily doses greater than 400 mg per day. Pediatric Patients (2 years to 16 years of age) The incidence of persistent decreases in serum bicarbonate in placebo-controlled trials for adjunctive treatment of Lennox-Gastaut syndrome or refractory partial onset seizures in patients age 2 years to 16 years was 67% for topiramate (at approximately 6 mg/kg/day), and 10% for placebo. The incidence of a markedly abnormally low serum bicarbonate (i.e., absolute value less than 17 mEq/L and greater than 5 mEq/L decrease from pretreatment) in these trials was 11% for topiramate and 0% for placebo. Cases of moderately severe metabolic acidosis have been reported in patients as young as 5 months old, especially at daily doses above 5 mg/kg/day. In pediatric patients (6 years to 15 years of age), the incidence of persistent decreases in serum bicarbonate in the epilepsy controlled clinical trial for monotherapy performed with topiramate was 9% for 50 mg per day and 25% for 400 mg per day. The incidence of a markedly abnormally low serum bicarbonate (i.e., absolute value less than 17 mEq/L and greater than 5 mEq/L decrease from pretreatment) in this trial was 1% for 50 mg per day and 6% for 400 mg per day. Pediatric Patients (under 2 years of age) Although QUDEXY XR is not approved for use in patients less than 2 years of age, a study of topiramate as adjunctive use in patients under 2 years of age with partial onset seizures revealed that topiramate produced a metabolic acidosis that is notably greater in magnitude than that observed in controlled trials in older children and adults. The mean treatment difference (25 mg/kg/day topiramate-placebo) was -5.9 mEq/L for bicarbonate. The incidence of metabolic acidosis (defined by a serum bicarbonate less than 20 mEq/L) was 0% for placebo, 30% for 5 mg/kg/day, 50% for 15 mg/kg/day, and 45% for 25 mg/kg/day. The incidence of markedly abnormal changes (i.e., less than 17 mEq/L and greater than 5 mEq/L decrease from baseline of greater than or equal to 20 mEq/L) was 0% for placebo, 4% for 5 mg/kg/day, 5% for 15 mg/kg/day and 5% for 25 mg/kg/day [see Use in Specific Populations (8.4) ] . Migraine Adult Patients The incidence of persistent decreases in serum bicarbonate in placebo-controlled trials in adults for the prophylaxis of migraine was 44% for 200 mg/day, 39% for 100 mg/day, 23% for 50 mg/day, and 7% for placebo. The incidence of markedly abnormally low serum bicarbonate (i.e., absolute value less than 17 mEq/L and greater than 5 mEq/L decrease from pretreatment) in these trials was 11% for 200 mg/day, 9% for 100 mg/day, 2% for 50 mg/day, and &amp;lt;1% for placebo. Adolescent Patients In pooled, double-blind migraine prophylaxis studies in adolescent patients (12 to 17 years of age), the incidence of persistent decreases in serum bicarbonate was 77% for 200 mg/day, 27% for 100 mg/day, 30% for 50 mg/day, and 9% for placebo. The incidence of markedly low serum bicarbonate (i.e., absolute value &amp;lt;17 mEq/L and &amp;gt;5 mEq/L decrease from pretreatment) was 6% for 100 mg/day, 2% for 50 mg/day, and 2% for placebo. This bicarbonate criterion was not met by any patients in the 200 mg/day group, which had a low number of subjects (n=13). Measurement of Serum Bicarbonate in Epilepsy and Migraine Patients Measurement of baseline and periodic serum bicarbonate during topiramate treatment is recommended. If metabolic acidosis develops and persists, consideration should be given to reducing the dose or discontinuing topiramate (using dose tapering). If the decision is made to continue patients on topiramate in the face of persistent acidosis, alkali treatment should be considered. Antiepileptic drugs (AEDs) increase the risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior in patients taking these drugs for any indication. Patients treated with any AED, including QUDEXY XR, for any indication should be monitored for the emergence or worsening of depression, suicidal thoughts or behavior, and/or any unusual changes in mood or behavior. Pooled analyses of 199 placebo-controlled clinical trials (mono- and adjunctive therapy) of 11 different AEDs showed that patients randomized to one of the AEDs had approximately twice the risk (adjusted Relative Risk 1.8, 95% CI:1.2, 2.7) of suicidal thinking or behavior compared to patients randomized to placebo. In these trials, which had a median treatment duration of 12 weeks, the estimated incidence rate of suicidal behavior or ideation among 27,863 AED-treated patients was 0.43%, compared to 0.24% among 16,029 placebo-treated patients, representing an increase of approximately one case of suicidal thinking or behavior for every 530 patients treated. There were four suicides in drug-treated patients in the trials and none in placebo-treated patients, but the number is too small to allow any conclusion about drug effect on suicide. The increased risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior with AEDs was observed as early as one week after starting drug treatment with AEDs and persisted for the duration of treatment assessed. Because most trials included in the analysis did not extend beyond 24 weeks, the risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior beyond 24 weeks could not be assessed. The risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior was generally consistent among drugs in the data analyzed. The finding of increased risk with AEDs of varying mechanisms of action and across a range of indications suggests that the risk applies to all AEDs used for any indication. The risk did not vary substantially by age (5 to 100 years) in the clinical trials analyzed. Table 4 shows absolute and relative risk by indication for all evaluated AEDs. Table 4: Risk by Indication for Antiepileptic Drugs in the Pooled Analysis Indication Placebo Patients with Events per 1,000 Patients Drug Patients with Events per 1,000 Patients Relative Risk: Incidence of Events in Drug Patients/ Incidence in Placebo Patients Risk Difference: Additional Drug Patients with Events per 1,000 Patients Epilepsy 1.0 3.4 3.5 2.4 Psychiatric 5.7 8.5 1.5 2.9 Other 1.0 1.8 1.9 0.9 Total 2.4 4.3 1.8 1.9 The relative risk for suicidal thoughts or behavior was higher in clinical trials for epilepsy than in clinical trials for psychiatric or other conditions, but the absolute risk differences were similar for the epilepsy and psychiatric indications. Anyone considering prescribing QUDEXY XR or any other AED must balance the risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior with the risk of untreated illness. Epilepsy and many other illnesses for which AEDs are prescribed are themselves associated with morbidity and mortality and an increased risk of suicidal thoughts and behavior. Should suicidal thoughts and behavior emerge during treatment, the prescriber needs to consider whether the emergence of these symptoms in any given patient may be related to the illness being treated. Patients, their caregivers, and families should be informed that AEDs increase the risk of suicidal thoughts and behavior and should be advised of the need to be alert for the emergence or worsening of the signs and symptoms of depression, any unusual changes in mood or behavior or the emergence of suicidal thoughts, behavior or thoughts about self-harm. Behaviors of concern should be reported immediately to healthcare providers. Adverse reactions most often associated with the use of topiramate, and therefore expected to be associated with the use of QUDEXY XR, were related to the central nervous system and were observed in both the epilepsy and migraine populations. In adults, the most frequent of these can be classified into three general categories: 1) Cognitive-related dysfunction (e.g. confusion, psychomotor slowing, difficulty with concentration/attention, difficulty with memory, speech or language problems, particularly word-finding difficulties), 2) Psychiatric/behavioral disturbances (e.g. depression or mood problems), and 3) Somnolence or fatigue. Adult Patients Cognitive Related Dysfunction The majority of cognitive-related adverse reactions were mild to moderate in severity, and they frequently occurred in isolation. Rapid titration rate and higher initial dose were associated with higher incidences of these reactions. Many of these reactions contributed to withdrawal from treatment [see Adverse Reactions (6.1) ] . In the adjunctive epilepsy controlled trials conducted with topiramate (using rapid titration such as 100 mg per day to 200 mg per day weekly increments), the proportion of patients who experienced one or more cognitive-related adverse reactions was 42% for 200 mg per day, 41% for 400 mg per day, 52% for 600 mg per day, 56% for 800 and 1,000 mg per day, and 14% for placebo. These dose-related adverse reactions began with a similar frequency in the titration or in the maintenance phase, although in some patients the events began during titration and persisted into the maintenance phase. Some patients who experienced one or more cognitive-related adverse reactions in the titration phase had a dose-related recurrence of these reactions in the maintenance phase. In the monotherapy epilepsy controlled trial conducted with topiramate, the proportion of patients who experienced one or more cognitive-related adverse reactions was 19% for topiramate 50 mg per day and 26% for 400 mg per day. In the 6-month migraine prophylaxis controlled trials using a slower titration regimen (25 mg/day weekly increments), the proportion of patients who experienced one or more cognitive-related adverse reactions was 19% for topiramate 50 mg/day, 22% for 100 mg/day (the recommended dose), 28% for 200 mg/day, and 10% for placebo. These dose-related adverse reactions typically began in the titration phase and often persisted into the maintenance phase, but infrequently began in the maintenance phase. Some patients experienced a recurrence of one or more of these cognitive adverse reactions and this recurrence was typically in the titration phase. A relatively small proportion of topiramate-treated patients experienced more than one concurrent cognitive adverse reaction. The most common cognitive adverse reactions occurring together included difficulty with memory along with difficulty with concentration/attention, difficulty with memory along with language problems, and difficulty with concentration/attention along with language problems. Rarely, topiramate-treated patients experienced three concurrent cognitive reactions. Psychiatric/Behavioral Disturbances Psychiatric/behavioral disturbances (depression or mood) were dose-related for both the epilepsy and migraine populations treated with topiramate [see Warnings and Precautions (5.5) and Adverse Reactions (6.1) ] . Somnolence/Fatigue Somnolence and fatigue were the adverse reactions most frequently reported during clinical trials of topiramate for adjunctive epilepsy. For the adjunctive epilepsy population, the incidence of somnolence did not differ substantially between 200 mg per day and 1,000 mg per day, but the incidence of fatigue was dose-related and increased at dosages above 400 mg per day. For the monotherapy epilepsy population in the 50 mg per day and 400 mg per day groups, the incidence of somnolence was dose-related (9% for the 50 mg per day group and 15% for the 400 mg per day group) and the incidence of fatigue was comparable in both treatment groups (14% each). For the migraine population, somnolence and fatigue were dose-related and more common in the titration phase. Additional nonspecific CNS events commonly observed with topiramate in the adjunctive epilepsy population include dizziness or ataxia. Pediatric Patients Epilepsy In double-blind adjunctive therapy and monotherapy epilepsy clinical studies conducted with topiramate, the incidences of cognitive/neuropsychiatric adverse reactions in pediatric patients were generally lower than observed in adults. These reactions included psychomotor slowing, difficulty with concentration/attention, speech disorders/related speech problems and language problems. The most frequently reported neuropsychiatric reactions in pediatric patients during adjunctive therapy double-blind studies were somnolence and fatigue. The most frequently reported neuropsychiatric reactions in pediatric patients in the 50 mg per day and 400 mg per day groups during the monotherapy double-blind study were headache, dizziness, anorexia, and somnolence. No patients discontinued treatment due to any adverse reactions in the adjunctive epilepsy double-blind trials. In the monotherapy epilepsy double-blind trial conducted with immediate-release topiramate product, 1 pediatric patient (2%) in the 50 mg per day group and 7 pediatric patients (12%) in the 400 mg per day group discontinued treatment due to any adverse reactions. The most common adverse reaction associated with discontinuation of therapy was difficulty with concentration/attention; all occurred in the 400 mg per day group. Migraine The incidence of cognitive adverse reactions was increased in topiramate-treated patients (7%) versus placebo (4%) in pooled, double-blind placebo-controlled studies in which adolescent patients (12 to 17 years) were randomized to placebo or one of several fixed daily doses of topiramate (50 mg, 100 mg, 200 mg). The incidence of cognitive adverse reactions was also increased in a placebo-controlled study of pediatric patients (6 to 16 years) treated with 2 to 3 mg/kg/day of topiramate (10%) versus placebo treatment (2%). QUDEXY XR is not approved for prophylaxis of migraine in pediatric patients under 12 years of age. The risk for cognitive adverse reactions was dose-dependent, and was particularly evident at the 200 mg dose. This risk for cognitive adverse reactions was also greater in younger patients (6 to 11 years) than in older patients (12 to 17 years). The most common cognitive adverse reaction in these trials was difficulty with concentration/attention. Cognitive adverse reactions most commonly developed in the titration period and sometimes persisted into the maintenance period. These adverse reactions typically occurred in isolation as single type of cognitive adverse reaction. Cognitive adverse reactions that led to study discontinuation occurred in one patient (difficulty with concentration/attention and language problems). The Cambridge Neuropsychological Test Automated Battery (CANTAB) was administered to adolescents (12 to 17 years) to assess the effects of topiramate on cognitive function at baseline and at the end of the Study 3 [see Clinical Studies (14.7) ] . Mean change from baseline in certain CANTAB tests suggests that topiramate treatment may result in psychomotor slowing and decreased verbal fluency. Topiramate can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. Data from pregnancy registries indicate that infants exposed to topiramate in utero have an increased risk for cleft lip and/or cleft palate (oral clefts) and for being small for gestational age. In multiple species, oral administration of topiramate to pregnant animals at clinically relevant doses resulted in structural malformations, including craniofacial defects, and reduced body weights in offspring [see Use in Specific Populations (8.1) ] . Consider the benefits and risks of QUDEXY XR when administering the drug in women of childbearing potential, particularly when QUDEXY XR is considered for a condition not usually associated with permanent injury or death [see Use in Specific Populations (8.1) ] . QUDEXY XR should be used during pregnancy only if the potential benefit outweighs the potential risk. If this drug is used during pregnancy, or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking this drug, the patient should be informed of the potential hazard to a fetus [see Use in Specific Populations (8.1) ] . In patients with or without a history of seizures or epilepsy, antiepileptic drugs including QUDEXY XR, should be gradually withdrawn to minimize the potential for seizures or increased seizure frequency [see Clinical Studies (14) ] . In situations where rapid withdrawal of QUDEXY XR is medically required, appropriate monitoring is recommended. Hyperammonemia/Encephalopathy Without Concomitant Valproic Acid (VPA) Topiramate treatment has produced hyperammonemia (in some instances dose-related) in a clinical investigational program in adolescent patients (12 to 17 years) who were treated with topiramate for migraine prophylaxis. The incidence of hyperammonemia (above the upper limit of normal reference) at any time in the trial was 9% for placebo, 14% for 50 mg, and 26% for 100 mg topiramate daily. In some patients, hyperammonemia was observed at the end of the trial at the final visit. The incidence of markedly increased hyperammonemia (at least 50% or higher above upper limit of normal) at any time in the trial in adolescent patients was also increased at 100 mg/day (9%) compared to 50 mg topiramate (0%) or placebo (3%). During this trial, markedly increased ammonia levels returned to normal in all but one patient (in whom the ammonia level fell to high instead of markedly abnormal). Topiramate treatment has produced hyperammonemia in a clinical investigational program in very young pediatric patients (1 month to 24 months) who were treated with adjunctive topiramate for partial onset epilepsy (8% for placebo, 10% for 5 mg/kg/day, 0% for 15 mg/kg/day, 9% for 25 mg/kg/day). QUDEXY XR is not approved as adjunctive treatment of partial onset seizures in pediatric patients less than 2 years old. In some patients, ammonia was markedly increased (greater than 50% above upper limit of normal). The hyperammonemia associated with topiramate treatment occurred with and without encephalopathy in placebo-controlled trials, and in an open-label, extension trial of infants with refractory epilepsy. Dose-related hyperammonemia was also observed in the extension trial in pediatric patients up to 2 years old. Clinical symptoms of hyperammonemic encephalopathy often include acute alterations in level of consciousness and/or cognitive function with lethargy or vomiting. Hyperammonemia with and without encephalopathy has also been observed in post-marketing reports in patients who were taking topiramate without concomitant valproic acid (VPA). Hyperammonemia/Encephalopathy With Concomitant Valproic Acid (VPA) Concomitant administration of topiramate and valproic acid (VPA) has been associated with hyperammonemia with or without encephalopathy in patients who have tolerated either drug alone based upon post-marketing reports. Although hyperammonemia may be asymptomatic, clinical symptoms of hyperammonemic encephalopathy often include acute alterations in level of consciousness and/or cognitive function with lethargy or vomiting. In most cases, symptoms and signs abated with discontinuation of either drug. This adverse reaction is not due to a pharmacokinetic interaction. Although QUDEXY XR is not indicated for use in infants/toddlers (1 month to 24 months), topiramate with concomitant VPA clearly produced a dose-related increase in the incidence of hyperammonemia (above the upper limit of normal, 0% for placebo, 12% for 5 mg/kg/day, 7% for 15 mg/kg/day, 17% for 25 mg/kg/day) in an investigational program using topiramate. Markedly increased, dose-related hyperammonemia (0% for placebo and 5 mg/kg/day, 7% for 15 mg/kg/day, and 8% for 25 mg/kg/day) also occurred in these infants/toddlers. Dose-related hyperammonemia was similarly observed in a long-term, extension trial utilizing topiramate in these very young, pediatric patients [see Use in Specific Populations (8.4) ] . Hyperammonemia with and without encephalopathy has also been observed in post-marketing reports in patients taking topiramate with valproic acid (VPA). The hyperammonemia associated with topiramate treatment appears to be more common when used concomitantly with VPA. Monitoring for Hyperammonemia Patients with inborn errors of metabolism or reduced hepatic mitochondrial activity may be at an increased risk for hyperammonemia with or without encephalopathy. Although not studied, topiramate or QUDEXY XR treatment or an interaction of concomitant topiramate-based product and valproic acid treatment may exacerbate existing defects or unmask deficiencies in susceptible persons. In patients who develop unexplained lethargy, vomiting, or changes in mental status associated with any topiramate treatment, hyperammonemic encephalopathy should be considered and an ammonia level should be measured. A total of 32/2086 (1.5%) of adults exposed to topiramate during its adjunctive epilepsy therapy development reported the occurrence of kidney stones, an incidence about 2 to 4 times greater than expected in a similar, untreated population. In the double-blind monotherapy epilepsy study, a total of 4/319 (1.3%) of adults exposed to topiramate reported the occurrence of kidney stones. As in the general population, the incidence of stone formation among topiramate-treated patients was higher in men. Kidney stones have also been reported in pediatric patients taking topiramate for epilepsy or migraine. During long-term (up to 1 year) topiramate treatment in an open-label extension study of 284 pediatric patients 1 month to 24 months old with epilepsy, 7% developed kidney or bladder stones that were diagnosed clinically or by sonogram. QUDEXY XR is not approved for pediatric patients less than 2 years old [see Use in Specific Populations (8.4) ] . Kidney stones have also been reported in pediatric patients taking topiramate for migraine prophylaxis. For the double-blind migraine prophylaxis studies, one adverse event (renal calculus) occurred in a topiramate-treated subject in the age 12 to 17 years group. The overall experience with open-label, long-term, topiramate treatment for migraine prophylaxis is limited in pediatric patients. QUDEXY XR would be expected to have the same effect as topiramate on the formation of kidney stones. An explanation for the association of topiramate and kidney stones may lay in the fact that topiramate is a carbonic anhydrase inhibitor. Carbonic anhydrase inhibitors (e.g., zonisamide, acetazolamide or dichlorphenamide) can promote stone formation by reducing urinary citrate excretion and by increasing urinary pH [see Warnings and Precautions (5.4) , Drug Interactions (7.4) and Clinical Pharmacology (12.3) ] . The concomitant use of QUDEXY XR with any other drug producing metabolic acidosis, or potentially in patients on a ketogenic diet, may create a physiological environment that increases the risk of kidney stone formation, and should therefore be avoided. Increased fluid intake increases the urinary output, lowering the concentration of substances involved in stone formation. Hydration is recommended to reduce new stone formation. Hypothermia, defined as an unintentional drop in body core temperature to less than 35ºC (95ºF) has been reported in association with topiramate use with concomitant valproic acid (VPA) both in the presence and in the absence of hyperammonemia. This adverse reaction in patients using concomitant topiramate and valproate can occur after starting topiramate treatment or after increasing the daily dose of topiramate [see Drug Interactions (7.2) and Clinical Pharmacology (12.3) ] . Consideration should be given to stopping topiramate or valproate in patients who develop hypothermia, which may be manifested by a variety of clinical abnormalities including lethargy, confusion, coma, and significant alterations in other major organ systems such as the cardiovascular and respiratory systems. Clinical management and assessment should include examination of blood ammonia levels. Paresthesia (usually tingling of the extremities), an effect associated with the use of other carbonic anhydrase inhibitors, appears to be a common effect of topiramate in adult and pediatric patients. Paresthesia was more frequently reported in the monotherapy epilepsy trials and migraine prophylaxis trials conducted with immediate-release topiramate than in the adjunctive therapy epilepsy trials conducted with the same product. In the majority of instances, paresthesia did not lead to treatment discontinuation [see Adverse Reactions (6.1) ] . Topiramate is a CNS depressant. Concomitant administration of topiramate with other CNS depressant drugs or alcohol can result in significant CNS depression. Patients should be watched carefully when QUDEXY XR is co-administered with other CNS depressant drugs [see Drug Interactions (7.3) and Clinical Pharmacology (12.3) ] .</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
The precise mechanisms by which topiramate exerts its anticonvulsant and migraine prophylaxis effects are unknown; however, preclinical studies have revealed four properties that may contribute to topiramate's efficacy for epilepsy and migraine prophylaxis. Electrophysiological and biochemical evidence suggests that topiramate, at pharmacologically relevant concentrations, blocks voltage-dependent sodium channels, augments the activity of the neurotransmitter gamma-aminobutyrate at some subtypes of the GABA-A receptor, antagonizes the AMPA/kainate subtype of the glutamate receptor, and inhibits the carbonic anhydrase enzyme, particularly isozymes II and IV. Topiramate has anticonvulsant activity in rat and mouse maximal electroshock seizure (MES) tests. Topiramate is only weakly effective in blocking clonic seizures induced by the GABA-A receptor antagonist, pentylenetetrazole. Topiramate is also effective in rodent models of epilepsy, which include tonic and absence-like seizures in the spontaneous epileptic rat (SER) and tonic and clonic seizures induced in rats by kindling of the amygdala or by global ischemia. Changes (increases and decreases) from baseline in vital signs (systolic blood pressure-SBP, diastolic blood pressure-DBP, pulse) occurred more frequently in pediatric patients (6 to 17 years) treated with various daily doses of topiramate (50 mg, 100 mg, 200 mg, 2 to 3 mg/kg) than in patients treated with placebo in controlled trials for migraine prophylaxis. The most notable changes were SBP &amp;lt; 90 mm Hg, DBP &amp;lt; 50 mm Hg, SBP or DBP increases or decreases ≥ 20 mm Hg, and pulse increases or decreases ≥ 30 beats per minute. These changes were often dose-related, and were most frequently associated with the greatest treatment difference at the 200 mg dose level. When a position was specified for measurement of vital signs in a trial, measurements were made in a sitting position. Systematic collection of orthostatic vital signs has not been conducted. The clinical significance of these various changes in vital signs has not been clearly established. Absorption and Distribution The pharmacokinetics of QUDEXY XR are linear with dose proportional increases in plasma concentration when administered as a single oral dose over the range of 50 mg to 1,400 mg. At 25 mg, the pharmacokinetics of QUDEXY XR are nonlinear, possibly due to the binding of topiramate to carbonic anhydrase in red blood cells. QUDEXY XR sprinkled on a spoonful of soft food is bioequivalent to the intact capsule formulation. Following a single 200 mg oral dose of QUDEXY XR, peak plasma concentrations (T max ) occurred approximately 20 hours after dosing. Steady-state was reached in about 5 days following daily dosing of QUDEXY XR in subjects with normal renal function, with a T max of approximately 6 hours. At steady-state, the plasma exposure (AUC 0-24hr , C max , and C min ) of topiramate from QUDEXY XR administered once daily and the immediate-release topiramate tablets administered twice-daily were shown to be bioequivalent. Fluctuation of topiramate plasma concentrations at steady-state for QUDEXY XR administered once daily was approximately 40% in healthy subjects, compared to approximately 53% for immediate-release topiramate [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.6) ] . Compared to the fasted state, high-fat meal had no effect on bioavailability (AUC and C max ) but delayed the T max by approximately 4 hours following a single dose of QUDEXY XR. QUDEXY XR can be taken without regard to meals. Topiramate is 15% to 41% bound to human plasma proteins over the blood concentration range of 0.5 mcg/mL to 250 mcg/mL. The fraction bound decreased as blood concentration increased. Carbamazepine and phenytoin do not alter the binding of immediate-release topiramate. Sodium valproate, at 500 mcg/mL (a concentration 5 to 10 times higher than considered therapeutic for valproate) decreased the protein binding of immediate-release topiramate from 23% to 13%. Immediate-release topiramate does not influence the binding of sodium valproate. Metabolism and Excretion Topiramate is not extensively metabolized and is primarily eliminated unchanged in the urine (approximately 70% of an administered dose). Six metabolites have been identified in humans, none of which constitutes more than 5% of an administered dose. The metabolites are formed via hydroxylation, hydrolysis, and glucuronidation. There is evidence of renal tubular reabsorption of topiramate. In rats, given probenecid to inhibit tubular reabsorption, along with topiramate, a significant increase in renal clearance of topiramate was observed. This interaction has not been evaluated in humans. Overall, oral plasma clearance (CL/F) is approximately 20 mL/min to 30 mL/min in adults following oral administration. The mean effective half-life of QUDEXY XR is approximately 56 hours. Steady-state is reached in about 5 days after QUDEXY XR dosing in subjects with normal renal function. Specific Populations Renal Impairment The clearance of topiramate was reduced by 42% in subjects with moderate renal impairment (creatinine clearance 30 to 69 mL/min/1.73 m 2 ) and by 54% in subjects with severe renal impairment (creatinine clearance less than 30 mL/min/1.73 m 2 ) compared to subjects with normal renal function (creatinine clearance greater than70 mL/min/1.73 m 2 ). Since topiramate is presumed to undergo significant tubular reabsorption, it is uncertain whether this experience can be generalized to all situations of renal impairment. It is conceivable that some forms of renal disease could differentially affect glomerular filtration rate and tubular reabsorption resulting in a clearance of topiramate not predicted by creatinine clearance. In general, however, use of one-half the usual starting and maintenance dose is recommended in patients with creatinine clearance less than 70 mL/min/1.73 m 2 [see Dosage and Administration (2.3) and Use in Specific Populations (8.7) ] . Hemodialysis Topiramate is cleared by hemodialysis. Using a high-efficiency, counterflow, single pass-dialysate hemodialysis procedure, topiramate dialysis clearance was 120 mL/min with blood flow through the dialyzer at 400 mL/min. This high clearance (compared to 20 mL/min to 30 mL/min total oral clearance in healthy adults) will remove a clinically significant amount of topiramate from the patient over the hemodialysis treatment period. Therefore, a supplemental dose may be required [see Dosage and Administration (2.4) and Use in Specific Populations (8.8) ] . Hepatic Impairment In subjects with hepatic impairment, the clearance of topiramate may be decreased; the mechanism underlying the decrease is not well understood. Age, Gender and Race The pharmacokinetics of topiramate in elderly subjects (65 to 85 years of age, N=16) were evaluated in a controlled clinical study. The elderly subject population had reduced renal function (creatinine clearance [-20%]) compared to young adults. Following a single oral 100 mg dose, maximum plasma concentration for elderly and young adults was achieved at approximately 1 to 2 hours. Reflecting the primary renal elimination of topiramate, topiramate plasma and renal clearance were reduced 21% and 19%, respectively, in elderly subjects, compared to young adults. Similarly, topiramate half-life was longer (13%) in the elderly. Reduced topiramate clearance resulted in slightly higher maximum plasma concentration (23%) and AUC (25%) in elderly subjects than observed in young adults. Topiramate clearance is decreased in the elderly only to the extent that renal function is reduced. Because of this, dosage adjustment may be necessary [see Dosage and Administration (2.3) , Use in Specific Populations (8.5 and 8.7) and Clinical Pharmacology (12.3) ] . Clearance of topiramate in adults was not affected by gender or race. Pediatric Pharmacokinetics Pharmacokinetics of immediate-release topiramate were evaluated in patients ages 2 years to less than 16 years. Patients received either no or a combination of other antiepileptic drugs. A population pharmacokinetic model was developed on the basis of pharmacokinetic data from relevant topiramate clinical studies. This dataset contained data from 1217 subjects including 258 pediatric patients aged 2 years to less than 16 years (95 pediatric patients less than 10 years of age). Pediatric patients on adjunctive treatment exhibited a higher oral clearance (L/h) of topiramate compared to patients on monotherapy, presumably because of increased clearance from concomitant enzyme-inducing antiepileptic drugs. In comparison, topiramate clearance per kg is greater in pediatric patients than in adults and in young pediatric patients (down to 2 years) than in older pediatric patients. Consequently, the plasma drug concentration for the same mg/kg/day dose would be lower in pediatric patients compared to adults and also in younger pediatric patients compared to older pediatric patients. Clearance was independent of dose. As in adults, hepatic enzyme-inducing antiepileptic drugs decrease the steady state plasma concentrations of topiramate. Drug-Drug Interaction Studies Antiepileptic Drugs Potential interactions between immediate-release topiramate and standard AEDs were assessed in controlled clinical pharmacokinetic studies in patients with epilepsy. The effects of these interactions on mean plasma AUCs are summarized in Table 14. Interaction of QUDEXY XR and standard AEDs is not expected to differ from the experience with immediate-release topiramate products. In Table 14, the second column (AED concentration) describes what happened to the concentration of the AED listed in the first column when topiramate was added. The third column (topiramate concentration) describes how the co-administration of a drug listed in the first column modified the concentration of topiramate in experimental settings when topiramate was given alone. Table 14: Summary of AED Interactions with topiramate AED Co-administered AED Concentration Topiramate Concentration NC=Less than 10% change in plasma concentration AED=Antiepileptic drug NE=Not evaluated TPM=topiramate Phenytoin NC or 25% increase Plasma concentration increased 25% in some patients, generally those on a twice a day dosing regimen of phenytoin 48% decrease Carbamazepine (CBZ) NC 40% decrease CBZ epoxide Is not administered, but is an active metabolite of carbamazepine NC NE Valproic acid 11% decrease 14% decrease Phenobarbital NC NE Primidone NC NE Lamotrigine NC at TPM doses up to 400 mg per day 13% decrease In addition to the pharmacokinetic interaction described in the above table, concomitant administration of valproic acid and topiramate has been associated with hyperammonemia with and without encephalopathy and hypothermia [see Warnings and Precautions (5.9 and 5.11) and Drug Interactions (7.2) ] . CNS Depressants or Alcohol Concomitant administration of topiramate and alcohol or other CNS depressant drugs has not been evaluated in clinical studies [see Warnings and Precautions (5.13) and Drug Interactions (7.3) ] . Oral Contraceptives In a pharmacokinetic interaction study in healthy volunteers with a concomitantly administered combination oral contraceptive product containing 1 mg norethindrone (NET) plus 35 mcg ethinyl estradiol (EE), topiramate, given in the absence of other medications at doses of 50 to 200 mg per day, was not associated with statistically significant changes in mean exposure (AUC) to either component of the oral contraceptive. In another study, exposure to EE was statistically significantly decreased at doses of 200, 400, and 800 mg per day (18%, 21%, and 30%, respectively) when given as adjunctive therapy in patients taking valproic acid. In both studies, topiramate (50 mg per day to 800 mg per day) did not significantly affect exposure to NET. Although there was a dose-dependent decrease in EE exposure for doses between 200 to 800 mg per day, there was no significant dose-dependent change in EE exposure for doses of 50 to 200 mg per day. The clinical significance of the changes observed is not known. The possibility of decreased contraceptive efficacy and increased breakthrough bleeding should be considered in patients taking combination oral contraceptive products with QUDEXY XR. Patients taking estrogen-containing contraceptives should be asked to report any change in their bleeding patterns. Contraceptive efficacy can be decreased even in the absence of breakthrough bleeding [see Drug Interactions (7.1) ] . Digoxin In a single-dose study, serum digoxin AUC was decreased by 12% with concomitant topiramate administration. The clinical relevance of this observation has not been established. Hydrochlorothiazide A drug-drug interaction study conducted in healthy volunteers evaluated the steady-state pharmacokinetics of hydrochlorothiazide (HCTZ) (25 mg every 24 hours) and topiramate (96 mg every 12 hours) when administered alone and concomitantly. The results of this study indicate that topiramate C max increased by 27% and AUC increased by 29% when HCTZ was added to topiramate. The clinical significance of this change is unknown. The addition of HCTZ to QUDEXY XR therapy may require an adjustment of the QUDEXY XR dose. The steady-state pharmacokinetics of HCTZ were not significantly influenced by the concomitant administration of topiramate. Clinical laboratory results indicated decreases in serum potassium after topiramate or HCTZ administration, which were greater when HCTZ and topiramate were administered in combination. Metformin Topiramate treatment can frequently cause metabolic acidosis, a condition for which the use of metformin is contraindicated. QUDEXY XR is expected to exhibit the same degree of metabolic acidosis as topiramate. A drug-drug interaction study conducted in healthy volunteers evaluated the steady-state pharmacokinetics of metformin (500 mg every 12 hr) and topiramate in plasma when metformin was given alone and when metformin and topiramate (100 mg every 12 hr) were given simultaneously. The results of this study indicated that the mean metformin C max and AUC 0-12h increased by 18% and 25%, respectively, when topiramate was added. Topiramate did not affect metformin T max . The clinical significance of the effect of topiramate on metformin pharmacokinetics is not known. Oral plasma clearance of topiramate appears to be reduced when administered with metformin. The clinical significance of the effect of metformin on topiramate QUDEXY XR pharmacokinetics is unclear [see Contraindications (4) , Warnings and Precautions (5.4) and Drug Interactions (7.5) ] . Pioglitazone A drug-drug interaction study conducted in healthy volunteers evaluated the steady-state pharmacokinetics of topiramate and pioglitazone when administered alone and concomitantly. A 15% decrease in the AUC τ,ss of pioglitazone with no alteration in C max,ss was observed. This finding was not statistically significant. In addition, a 13% and 16% decrease in C max,ss and AUC τ,ss respectively, of the active hydroxy-metabolite was noted as well as a 60% decrease in C max,ss and AUC τ,ss of the active keto-metabolite. The clinical significance of these findings is not known. When QUDEXY XR is added to pioglitazone therapy or pioglitazone is added to QUDEXY XR therapy, careful attention should be given to the routine monitoring of patients for adequate control of their diabetic disease state. Glyburide A drug-drug interaction study conducted in patients with type 2 diabetes evaluated the steady-state pharmacokinetics of glyburide (5 mg per day) alone and concomitantly with topiramate (150 mg per day). There was a 22% decrease in C max and 25% reduction in AUC 24 for glyburide during topiramate administration. Systemic exposure (AUC) of the active metabolites, 4- trans -hydroxy glyburide (M1) and 3- cis -hydroxyglyburide (M2), was also reduced by 13% and 15%, reduced C max by 18% and 25%, respectively. The steady-state pharmacokinetics of topiramate were unaffected by concomitant administration of glyburide. Lithium In patients, the pharmacokinetics of lithium were unaffected during treatment with topiramate at doses of 200 mg per day; however, there was an observed increase in systemic exposure of lithium (27% for C max and 26% for AUC) following topiramate doses up to 600 mg per day. Lithium levels should be monitored when co-administered with high-dose QUDEXY XR [see Drug Interactions (7.6) ] . Haloperidol The pharmacokinetics of a single dose of haloperidol (5 mg) were not affected following multiple dosing of topiramate (100 mg every 12 hr) in 13 healthy adults (6 males, 7 females). Amitriptyline There was a 12% increase in AUC and C max for amitriptyline (25 mg per day) in 18 normal subjects (9 males, 9 females) receiving 200 mg per day of topiramate. Some subjects may experience a large increase in amitriptyline concentration in the presence of QUDEXY XR and any adjustments in amitriptyline dose should be made according to the patient's clinical response and not on the basis of plasma levels. Sumatriptan Multiple dosing of topiramate (100 mg every 12 hrs) in 24 healthy volunteers (14 males, 10 females) did not affect the pharmacokinetics of single-dose sumatriptan either orally (100 mg) or subcutaneously (6 mg). Risperidone When administered concomitantly with topiramate at escalating doses of 100, 250, and 400 mg per day, there was a reduction in risperidone systemic exposure (16% and 33% for steady-state AUC at the 250 and 400 mg per day doses of topiramate). No alterations of 9-hydroxyrisperidone levels were observed. Coadministration of topiramate 400 mg per day with risperidone resulted in a 14% increase in C max and a 12% increase in AUC 12 of topiramate. There were no clinically significant changes in the systemic exposure of risperidone plus 9- hydroxyrisperidone or of topiramate; therefore, this interaction is not likely to be of clinical significance. Propranolol Multiple dosing of topiramate (200 mg per day) in 34 healthy volunteers (17 males, 17 females) did not affect the pharmacokinetics of propranolol following daily 160 mg doses. Propranolol doses of 160 mg per day in 39 volunteers (27 males, 12 females) had no effect on the exposure to topiramate at a dose of 200 mg per day of topiramate. Dihydroergotamine Multiple dosing of topiramate (200 mg per day) in 24 healthy volunteers (12 males, 12 females) did not affect the pharmacokinetics of a 1 mg subcutaneous dose of dihydroergotamine. Similarly, a 1 mg subcutaneous dose of dihydroergotamine did not affect the pharmacokinetics of a 200 mg per day dose of topiramate in the same study. Diltiazem Co-administration of diltiazem (240 mg) with topiramate (150 mg per day) resulted in a 10% decrease in C max and 25% decrease in diltiazem AUC, 27% decrease in C max and 18% decrease in des-acetyl diltiazem AUC, and no effect on N-desmethyl diltiazem. Co-administration of topiramate with diltiazem resulted in a 16% increase in C max and a 19% increase in AUC 12 of topiramate. Venlafaxine Multiple dosing of topiramate (150 mg per day) in healthy volunteers did not affect the pharmacokinetics of venlafaxine or O-desmethyl venlafaxine. Multiple dosing of venlafaxine (150 mg) did not affect the pharmacokinetics of topiramate. Other Carbonic Anhydrase Inhibitors Concomitant use of QUDEXY XR, a carbonic anhydrase inhibitor, with any other carbonic anhydrase inhibitor (e.g., zonisamide, acetazolamide, or dichlorphenamide), may increase the severity of metabolic acidosis and may also increase the risk of kidney stone formation. Therefore, if QUDEXY XR is given concomitantly with another carbonic anhydrase inhibitor, the patient should be monitored for the appearance or worsening of metabolic acidosis [see Drug Interactions (7.4) ] . Drug/Laboratory Tests Interactions There are no known interactions of QUDEXY XR with commonly used laboratory tests. QUDEXY XR, taken once daily, provides similar steady-state topiramate concentrations to immediate-release topiramate taken every 12 hours, when administered at the same total daily dose. In a healthy volunteer, multiple-dose crossover study, the 90% CI for the ratios of AUC 0-24 , C max and C min , as well as partial AUC (the area under the concentration-time curve from time 0 to time p (post dose)) for multiple time points were within the 80 to 125% bioequivalence limits, indicating no clinically significant difference between the two formulations. In addition, the 90% CI for the ratios of topiramate plasma concentration at each of multiple time points over 24 hours for the two formulations were within the 80 to 125% bioequivalence limits, except for the initial time points before 3 hours and at 8 hours post-dose, which is not expected to have a significant clinical impact. The effects of switching between QUDEXY XR and immediate-release topiramate were also evaluated in the same multiple-dose, crossover, comparative bioavailability study. In healthy subjects switched from immediate-release topiramate given every 12 hours to QUDEXY XR given once daily, similar concentrations were maintained immediately after the formulation switch. On the first day following the switch, there were no significant differences in AUC 0-24 , C max , and C min , as the 90% CI for the ratios were contained within the 80% to 125% equivalence limits.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="3653" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>QUDEXY XR is contraindicated in patients with metabolic acidosis who are taking concomitant metformin.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M1" type="Trigger" span="13 15" str="contraindicated"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="92 9" str="metformin" code="9100L32L2N"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M1" precipitant="M2"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3654" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>In patients with metabolic acidosis taking concomitant metformin (4) (5.4)</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3655" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Initial Dose Titration Recommended Dose Monotherapy: Partial Onset or Primary Generalized Tonic-Clonic Seizures Adults and pediatric patients 10 years and older (2.1) 50 mg once daily Increase dose weekly by increments of 50 mg for the first 4 weeks then 100 mg for weeks 5 to 6 400 mg once daily Pediatric patients 2 to less than 10 years (2.1) 25 mg once daily at nighttime for the first week Titrate the dosage over 5 to 7 weeks Once daily doses based on weight (Table 2) Adjunctive Therapy Adults with partial onset seizures or LGS (2.1) 25 mg to 50 mg once daily Increase dose weekly by increments of 25 mg to 50 mg to achieve an effective dose 200 mg to 400 mg once daily Adults with primary generalized tonic-clonic seizures (2.1) 25 mg to 50 mg once daily Increase dose weekly to an effective dose by increments of 25 mg to 50 mg 400 mg once daily Pediatric patients 2 years and older with partial onset seizures, primary generalized tonic-clonic seizures or LGS (2.1) 25 mg once daily at nighttime for the first week Increase dosage at 1 or 2 week intervals by increments of 1 mg/kg to 3 mg/kg; dose titration should be guided by clinical outcome 5 mg/kg to 9 mg/kg once daily Migraine (2.2) 25 mg once daily at nighttime for the first week Increase dose weekly by increments of 25 mg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3656" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dosage and titration should be guided by clinical outcome.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3657" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>100 mg once daily Capsules may be swallowed whole or opened and sprinkled on a spoonful of soft food (2.8) Monotherapy Use Adults and Pediatric Patients 10 Years and Older with Partial Onset or Primary Generalized Tonic-Clonic Seizures The recommended dose for QUDEXY XR monotherapy in adults and pediatric patients 10 years of age and older is 400 mg orally once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3658" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Titrate QUDEXY XR according to the following schedule [Table 1]: Table 1: Monotherapy Titration Schedule for Adults and Pediatric Patients 10 years and older QUDEXY XR Once Daily Dose Week 1 50 mg Week 2 100 mg Week 3 150 mg Week 4 200 mg Week 5 300 mg Week 6 400 mg Pediatric Patients 2 to less than 10 Years with Partial Onset or Primary Generalized Tonic-Clonic Seizures Dosing in patients 2 to less than 10 years is based on weight.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3659" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>During the titration period, the initial dose of QUDEXY XR should be 25 mg once daily given at nighttime for the first week.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3660" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Based upon tolerability, the dosage can be increased to 50 mg once daily in the second week.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3661" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dosage can be increased by 25 mg to 50 mg once daily each subsequent week, as tolerated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3662" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Titration to the minimum maintenance dose should be attempted over 5 to 7 weeks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3663" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Based upon tolerability and clinical response, additional titration to a higher dose (up to the maximum maintenance dose) can be attempted in weekly increments by 25 mg to 50 mg once daily, up to the maximum recommended maintenance dose for each range of body weight.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3664" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Table 2: Monotherapy Target Once Daily Maintenance Dosing for Patients 2 to Less Than 10 Years Weight (kg) Once Daily Dose(mg per day) Minimum Maintenance Dose Once Daily Dose(mg per day) Maximum Maintenance Dose Up to 11 150 250 12 to 22 200 300 23 to 31 200 350 32 to 38 250 350 Greater than 38 250 400 Adjunctive Therapy Use Adults (17 Years of Age and Older) - Partial Onset Seizures, Primary Generalized Tonic-Clonic Seizures, or Lennox-Gastaut Syndrome The recommended total daily dose of QUDEXY XR as adjunctive therapy in adults with partial onset seizures or Lennox-Gastaut Syndrome is 200 mg to 400 mg orally once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3665" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommended total dose for adults with primary generalized tonic-clonic seizures is 400 mg orally once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3666" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Initiate therapy at 25 mg to 50 mg once daily followed by titration to an effective dose in increments of 25 mg to 50 mg every week.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3667" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Daily topiramate doses above 1,600 mg have not been studied.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3668" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In the study of primary generalized tonic-clonic seizures using topiramate, the assigned dose was reached at the end of 8 weeks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3669" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Pediatric Patients (Ages 2 Years to 16 Years) - Partial Onset Seizures, Primary Generalized Tonic-Clonic Seizures, or Lennox-Gastaut Syndrome The recommended total daily dose of QUDEXY XR as adjunctive therapy for pediatric patients with partial onset seizures, primary generalized tonic-clonic seizures, or seizures associated with Lennox-Gastaut syndrome is approximately 5 mg/kg to 9 mg/kg orally once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3670" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Begin titration at 25 mg once daily (based on a range of 1 mg/kg/day to 3 mg/kg/day) given nightly for the first week.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3671" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Subsequently, increase the dosage at 1 or 2 week intervals by increments of 1 mg/kg to 3 mg/kg to achieve optimal clinical response.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3672" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dose titration should be guided by clinical outcome.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3673" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If required, longer intervals between dose adjustments can be used.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3674" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In the study of primary generalized tonic-clonic seizures, the assigned dose of 6 mg/kg once daily was reached at the end of 8 weeks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3675" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommended total daily dose of QUDEXY XR as treatment for prophylaxis of migraine headache in adults and adolescents 12 years of age and older is 100 mg once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3676" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommended titration rate for QUDEXY XR for migraine prophylaxis to 100 mg/day is: Table 3: Migraine Prophylaxis Titration Schedule for Adults and Adolescents 12 years of Age and Older QUDEXY XR Once Daily Dose Week 1 25 mg Week 2 50 mg Week 3 75 mg Week 4 100 mg Dose and titration rate should be guided by clinical outcome.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3677" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In patients with renal impairment (creatinine clearance less than 70 mL/min/1.73 m2), one-half of the usual adult dose is recommended.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3678" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Such patients will require a longer time to reach steady-state at each dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3679" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Prior to dosing, obtain an estimated creatinine clearance (CrCl) in patients at high risk for renal insufficiency (e.g., older patients, or those with diabetes mellitus, hypertension, or autoimmune disease).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3680" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>CrCl can be estimated using the following equation (multiply by 0.85 for women): CrCl = (140 – age) × weight(kg) SerumCr(mg / dl) × 72 Topiramate is cleared by hemodialysis at a rate that is 4 to 6 times greater than in patients with normal renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3681" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Accordingly, a prolonged period of dialysis may cause topiramate concentration to fall below that required to maintain an anti-seizure effect.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3682" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>To avoid rapid drops in topiramate plasma concentration during hemodialysis, a supplemental dose of topiramate may be required.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3683" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The actual adjustment should take into account the: duration of dialysis period clearance rate of the dialysis system being used effective renal clearance of topiramate in the patient being dialyzed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3684" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Measurement of baseline and periodic serum bicarbonate during QUDEXY XR treatment is recommended.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3685" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The co-administration of QUDEXY XR with phenytoin may require an adjustment of the dose of phenytoin to achieve optimal clinical outcome.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3686" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Addition or withdrawal of phenytoin and/or carbamazepine during adjunctive therapy with QUDEXY XR may require adjustment of the dose of QUDEXY XR.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3687" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>It is not necessary to monitor topiramate plasma concentrations to optimize QUDEXY XR therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3688" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>QUDEXY XR capsules may be swallowed whole or may be administered by carefully opening the capsule and sprinkling the entire contents on a small amount (teaspoon) of soft food.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3689" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>This drug/food mixture should be swallowed immediately and not chewed or crushed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3690" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not store drug/food mixture for further use.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3691" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>QUDEXY XR can be taken without regard to meals.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3692" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34074-5">
<SentenceText>Drug/Laboratory Tests Interactions There are no known interactions of QUDEXY XR with commonly used laboratory tests.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3693" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Oral contraceptives: Decreased contraceptive efficacy and increased breakthrough bleeding, especially at doses greater than 200 mg per day (7.1) Phenytoin or carbamazepine: Concomitant administration with topiramate decreased plasma concentrations of topiramate (7.2) Lithium: Monitor lithium levels when co-administered with high-dose topiramate (7.6) The possibility of decreased contraceptive efficacy and increased breakthrough bleeding should be considered in patients taking combination oral contraceptive products with QUDEXY XR.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M12" type="Trigger" span="58 9" str="increased"/>
<Mention id="M7" type="Precipitant" span="481 39" str="combination oral contraceptive products" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M14" type="SpecificInteraction" span="68 21" str="breakthrough bleeding" code="56169002: Break-through bleeding (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M6" type="Trigger" span="21 9;45 8" str="decreased | efficacy"/>
<Mention id="M17" type="SpecificInteraction" span="21 32" str="Decreased contraceptive efficacy" code="102955006: Contraception failure (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M9" type="Trigger" span="277 7" str="Monitor"/>
<Mention id="M10" type="Precipitant" span="268 7" str="lithium" code="9FN79X2M3F | N0000147892"/>
<Mention id="M11" type="SpecificInteraction" span="285 14" str="lithium levels" code="442174001: Lithium in blood specimen outside therapeutic range (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M16" type="Precipitant" span="0 19" str="Oral contraceptives" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M15" type="Trigger" span="21 9;45 8" str="Decreased | efficacy"/>
<Mention id="M20" type="Trigger" span="216 31" str="decreased plasma concentrations"/>
<Mention id="M19" type="Precipitant" span="158 13" str="carbamazepine" code="33CM23913M | N0000007470"/>
<Mention id="M21" type="Precipitant" span="145 9" str="Phenytoin" code="6158TKW0C5 | N0000006023"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M12" precipitant="M7" effect="M14" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M6" precipitant="M7" effect="M17" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M9" precipitant="M10" effect="M11" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M12" precipitant="M16" effect="M14" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M15" precipitant="M16" effect="M17" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M20" precipitant="M19" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M20" precipitant="M21" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3694" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Patients taking estrogen-containing contraceptives should be asked to report any change in their bleeding patterns.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M22" type="Trigger" span="81 6;106 8" str="change | patterns"/>
<Mention id="M23" type="Precipitant" span="16 34" str="estrogen-containing contraceptives" code="N0000175825"/>
<Mention id="M24" type="SpecificInteraction" span="81 33" str="change in their bleeding patterns" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M22" precipitant="M23" effect="M24" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3695" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Contraceptive efficacy can be decreased even in the absence of breakthrough bleeding.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M25" type="Trigger" span="14 8;30 9" str="efficacy | decreased"/>
<Mention id="M26" type="Precipitant" span="0 13" str="Contraceptive" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M27" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 22;30 9" str="Contraceptive efficacy | decreased" code="102955006: Contraception failure (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M25" precipitant="M26" effect="M27" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3696" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant administration of phenytoin or carbamazepine with topiramate decreased plasma concentrations of topiramate.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M30" type="Trigger" span="73 31" str="decreased plasma concentrations"/>
<Mention id="M29" type="Precipitant" span="43 13" str="carbamazepine" code="33CM23913M | N0000007470"/>
<Mention id="M31" type="Precipitant" span="30 9" str="phenytoin" code="6158TKW0C5 | N0000006023"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M30" precipitant="M29" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M30" precipitant="M31" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3697" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant administration of valproic acid and topiramate has been associated with hyperammonemia with and without encephalopathy.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M32" type="Trigger" span="68 15" str="associated with"/>
<Mention id="M33" type="Precipitant" span="30 13" str="valproic acid" code="614OI1Z5WI"/>
<Mention id="M34" type="SpecificInteraction" span="84 14" str="Hyperammonemia" code="9360008: Hyperammonemia (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M32" precipitant="M33" effect="M34" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3698" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant administration of topiramate with valproic acid has also been associated with hypothermia (with and without hyperammonemia) in patients who have tolerated either drug alone.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M35" type="Trigger" span="74 15" str="associated with"/>
<Mention id="M36" type="Precipitant" span="46 13" str="valproic acid" code="614OI1Z5WI"/>
<Mention id="M37" type="SpecificInteraction" span="90 11" str="hypothermia" code="386689009: Hypothermia (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M36" effect="M37" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3699" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>It may be prudent to examine blood ammonia levels in patients in whom the onset of hypothermia has been reported.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3700" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Numerous AEDs are substrates of the CYP enzyme system.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3701" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>In vitro studies indicate that topiramate does not inhibit enzyme activity for CYP1A2, CYP2A6, CYP2B6, CYP2C9, CYP2D6, CYP2E1, and CYP3A4/5 isozymes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3702" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>In vitro studies indicate that immediate-release topiramate is a mild inhibitor of CYP2C19 and a mild inducer of CYP3A4.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3703" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The same drug interactions can be expected with the use of QUDEXY XR.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3704" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant administration of topiramate with other CNS depressant drugs or alcohol can result in significant CNS depression.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M41" type="Trigger" span="88 9" str="result in"/>
<Mention id="M39" type="Precipitant" span="76 7" str="alcohol" code="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M"/>
<Mention id="M43" type="SpecificInteraction" span="110 14" str="CNS depression" code="418072004: Central nervous system depression (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M42" type="Precipitant" span="52 20" str="CNS depressant drugs" code="N0000175758"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M41" precipitant="M39" effect="M43" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M41" precipitant="M42" effect="M43" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3705" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant use of alcohol should be avoided.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M44" type="Trigger" span="27 17" str="should be avoided"/>
<Mention id="M45" type="Precipitant" span="19 7" str="alcohol" code="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M44" precipitant="M45"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3706" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant use of topiramate, a carbonic anhydrase inhibitor, with any other carbonic anhydrase inhibitor (e.g., zonisamide, acetazolamide or dichlorphenamide), may increase the severity of metabolic acidosis and may also increase the risk of kidney stone formation.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M64" type="Trigger" span="223 17" str="increase the risk"/>
<Mention id="M50" type="Precipitant" span="126 13" str="acetazolamide" code="O3FX965V0I"/>
<Mention id="M66" type="SpecificInteraction" span="244 22" str="kidney stone formation" code="95570007: Kidney stone (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M67" type="Trigger" span="166 21" str="increase the severity"/>
<Mention id="M69" type="SpecificInteraction" span="191 18" str="metabolic acidosis" code="59455009: Metabolic acidosis (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M56" type="Precipitant" span="33 28" str="carbonic anhydrase inhibitor" code="N0000000235"/>
<Mention id="M62" type="Precipitant" span="143 16" str="dichlorphenamide" code="VVJ6673MHY"/>
<Mention id="M68" type="Precipitant" span="114 10" str="zonisamide" code="459384H98V"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M64" precipitant="M50" effect="M66" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M67" precipitant="M50" effect="M69" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M64" precipitant="M56" effect="M66" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M67" precipitant="M56" effect="M69" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M64" precipitant="M62" effect="M66" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M67" precipitant="M62" effect="M69" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M64" precipitant="M68" effect="M66" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M67" precipitant="M68" effect="M69" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3707" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Patients should be monitored for the appearance or worsening of metabolic acidosis when QUDEXY XR is given concomitantly with another carbonic anhydrase inhibitor.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M70" type="Trigger" span="9 19" str="should be monitored"/>
<Mention id="M71" type="Precipitant" span="134 28" str="carbonic anhydrase inhibitor" code="N0000000235"/>
<Mention id="M72" type="SpecificInteraction" span="64 18" str="metabolic acidosis" code="59455009: Metabolic acidosis (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M70" precipitant="M71" effect="M72" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3708" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Topiramate treatment can frequently cause metabolic acidosis, a condition for which the use of metformin is contraindicated.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M73" type="Trigger" span="108 15" str="contraindicated"/>
<Mention id="M74" type="Precipitant" span="95 9" str="metformin" code="9100L32L2N"/>
<Mention id="M75" type="SpecificInteraction" span="42 18" str="metabolic acidosis" code="59455009: Metabolic acidosis (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M73" precipitant="M74" effect="M75" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3709" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The concomitant use of QUDEXY XR and metformin is contraindicated in patients with metabolic acidosis.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M76" type="Trigger" span="50 15" str="contraindicated"/>
<Mention id="M77" type="Precipitant" span="37 9" str="metformin" code="9100L32L2N"/>
<Mention id="M78" type="SpecificInteraction" span="83 18" str="metabolic acidosis" code="59455009: Metabolic acidosis (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M76" precipitant="M77" effect="M78" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3710" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>In patients, there was an observed increase in systemic exposure of lithium following topiramate doses of up to 600 mg per day.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M79" type="Trigger" span="35 29" str="increase in systemic exposure"/>
<Mention id="M80" type="Precipitant" span="68 7" str="lithium" code="9FN79X2M3F | N0000147892"/>
<Interaction id="I29" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M79" precipitant="M80" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3711" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Lithium levels should be monitored when co-administered with high-dose QUDEXY XR.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M81" type="Trigger" span="15 19" str="should be monitored"/>
<Mention id="M82" type="Precipitant" span="0 7" str="Lithium" code="9FN79X2M3F | N0000147892"/>
<Mention id="M83" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 14" str="lithium levels" code="442174001: Lithium in blood specimen outside therapeutic range (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I30" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M81" precipitant="M82" effect="M83" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3712" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Acute myopia and secondary angle closure glaucoma: Untreated elevated intraocular pressure can lead to permanent visual loss.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3713" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Discontinue QUDEXY XR if it occurs (5.1) Visual field defects: These have been reported independent of elevated intraocular pressure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3714" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Consider discontinuation of QUDEXY XR (5.2) Oligohydrosis and hyperthermia: Monitor decreased sweating and increased body temperature, especially in pediatric patients (5.3) Metabolic acidosis: Measure baseline and periodic measurement of serum bicarbonate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3715" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Consider dose reduction or discontinuation of QUDEXY XR if clinically appropriate (5.4) Suicidal behavior and ideation: Antiepileptic drugs increase the risk of suicidal behavior or ideation (5.5) Cognitive/neuropsychiatric: QUDEXY XR may cause cognitive dysfunction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3716" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Use caution when operating machinery including automobiles.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3717" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Depression and mood problems may occur (5.6) Fetal toxicity: Topiramate use during pregnancy can cause cleft lip and/or palate and increases the risk of being small for gestational age (5.7) Withdrawal of AEDs: Withdrawal of QUDEXY XR should be done gradually (5.8) Hyperammonemia and encephalopathy: Patients with inborn errors of metabolism or reduced mitochondrial activity may have an increased risk of hyperammonemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3718" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Measure ammonia if encephalopathic symptoms occur (5.9) Kidney stones: Avoid use with other carbonic anhydrase inhibitors, other drugs causing metabolic acidosis, or in patients on a ketogenic diet (5.10) Hypothermia: Reported with concomitant valproic acid use (5.11) A syndrome consisting of acute myopia associated with secondary angle closure glaucoma has been reported in patients receiving topiramate.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M92" type="SpecificInteraction" span="56 13" str="Kidney stones" code="95570007: Kidney stone (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M85" type="Precipitant" span="92 29" str="carbonic anhydrase inhibitors" code="N0000000235"/>
<Mention id="M88" type="Precipitant" span="129 32" str="drugs causing metabolic acidosis" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M91" type="Precipitant" span="183 14" str="ketogenic diet" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M93" type="Trigger" span="205 11" str="Hypothermia"/>
<Mention id="M94" type="Precipitant" span="244 13" str="valproic acid" code="614OI1Z5WI"/>
<Mention id="M95" type="SpecificInteraction" span="205 11" str="hypothermia" code="386689009: Hypothermia (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I31" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M92" precipitant="M85" effect="M92" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I32" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M92" precipitant="M88" effect="M92" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I33" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M92" precipitant="M91" effect="M92" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I34" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M93" precipitant="M94" effect="M95" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3719" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Symptoms include acute onset of decreased visual acuity and/or ocular pain.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3720" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Ophthalmologic findings can include myopia, anterior chamber shallowing, ocular hyperemia (redness) and increased intraocular pressure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3721" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>This syndrome may be associated with supraciliary effusion resulting in anterior displacement of the lens and iris, with secondary angle closure glaucoma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3722" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Symptoms typically occur within 1 month of initiating topiramate therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3723" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In contrast to primary narrow angle glaucoma, which is rare under 40 years of age, secondary angle closure glaucoma associated with topiramate has been reported in pediatric patients as well as adults.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3724" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The primary treatment to reverse symptoms is discontinuation of QUDEXY XR as rapidly as possible, according to the judgment of the treating physician.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3725" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Other measures, in conjunction with discontinuation of QUDEXY XR, may be helpful.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3726" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Elevated intraocular pressure of any etiology, if left untreated, can lead to serious sequelae including permanent vision loss.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3727" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Visual field defects have been reported in patients receiving topiramate independent of elevated intraocular pressure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3728" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In clinical trials, most of these events were reversible after topiramate discontinuation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3729" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If visual problems occur at any time during treatment with QUDEXY XR, consideration should be given to discontinuing the drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3730" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Oligohydrosis (decreased sweating), resulting in hospitalization in some cases, has been reported in association with topiramate use.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3731" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Decreased sweating and an elevation in body temperature above normal characterized these cases.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3732" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Some of the cases were reported after exposure to elevated environmental temperatures.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3733" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The majority of the reports have been in pediatric patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3734" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients, especially pediatric patients, treated with QUDEXY XR should be monitored closely for evidence of decreased sweating and increased body temperature, especially in hot weather.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3735" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Caution should be used when QUDEXY XR is prescribed with other drugs that predispose patients to heat-related disorders; these drugs include, but are not limited to, other carbonic anhydrase inhibitors and drugs with anticholinergic activity.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M102" type="Trigger" span="74 10" str="predispose"/>
<Mention id="M97" type="Precipitant" span="172 29" str="carbonic anhydrase inhibitors" code="N0000000235"/>
<Mention id="M104" type="SpecificInteraction" span="97 22" str="heat-related disorders" code="111735006: Effects of heat (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M100" type="Precipitant" span="63 56" str="drugs that predispose patients to heat-related disorders" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M103" type="Precipitant" span="206 35" str="drugs with anticholinergic activity" code="N0000175574"/>
<Interaction id="I35" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M102" precipitant="M97" effect="M104" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I36" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M102" precipitant="M100" effect="M104" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I37" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M102" precipitant="M103" effect="M104" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3736" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hyperchloremic, non-anion gap, metabolic acidosis (i.e., decreased serum bicarbonate below the normal reference range in the absence of chronic respiratory alkalosis) is associated with topiramate treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3737" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>This metabolic acidosis is caused by renal bicarbonate loss due to the inhibitory effect of topiramate on carbonic anhydrase.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3738" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Such electrolyte imbalance has been observed with the use of topiramate in placebo-controlled clinical trials and in the post-marketing period.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3739" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Generally, topiramate-induced metabolic acidosis occurs early in treatment although cases can occur at any time during treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3740" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Bicarbonate decrements are usually mild-moderate (average decrease of 4 mEq/L at daily doses of 400 mg in adults and at approximately 6 mg/kg/day in pediatric patients); rarely, patients can experience severe decrements to values below 10 mEq/L.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3741" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Conditions or therapies that predispose patients to acidosis (such as renal disease, severe respiratory disorders, status epilepticus, diarrhea, ketogenic diet or specific drugs) may be additive to the bicarbonate lowering effects of topiramate.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M108" type="Trigger" span="186 8;223 7" str="additive | effects"/>
<Mention id="M106" type="Precipitant" span="145 14" str="ketogenic diet" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M110" type="SpecificInteraction" span="202 20" str="bicarbonate lowering" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M109" type="Precipitant" span="14 46" str="therapies that predispose patients to acidosis" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I38" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M108" precipitant="M106" effect="M110" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I39" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M108" precipitant="M109" effect="M110" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3742" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Manifestations of Metabolic Acidosis Some manifestations of acute or chronic metabolic acidosis may include hyperventilation, nonspecific symptoms such as fatigue and anorexia, or more severe sequelae including cardiac arrhythmias or stupor.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3743" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Chronic, untreated metabolic acidosis may increase the risk for nephrolithiasis or nephrocalcinosis, and may also result in osteomalacia (referred to as rickets in pediatric patients) and/or osteoporosis with an increased risk for fractures.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3744" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Chronic metabolic acidosis in pediatric patients may also reduce growth rates.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3745" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>A reduction in growth rate may eventually decrease the maximal height achieved.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3746" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The effect of topiramate on growth and bone-related sequelae has not been systematically investigated in long-term, placebo-controlled trials.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3747" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Long-term, open-label treatment of infants/toddlers, with intractable partial epilepsy, for up to 1 year, showed reductions from baseline in Z SCORES for length, weight, and head circumference compared to age and sex-matched normative data, although these patients are likely to have different growth rates than normal infants.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3748" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Reductions in Z SCORES for length and weight were correlated to the degree of acidosis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3749" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Topiramate treatment that causes metabolic acidosis during pregnancy can possibly produce adverse effects on the fetus and might also cause metabolic acidosis in the neonate from possible transfer of topiramate to the fetus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3750" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Epilepsy Adult Patients In adults, the incidence of persistent decreases in serum bicarbonate (levels of less than 20 mEq/L at two consecutive visits or at the final visit) in controlled clinical trials for adjunctive treatment of epilepsy was 32% for 400 mg per day, and 1% for placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3751" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Metabolic acidosis has been observed at doses as low as 50 mg per day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3752" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The incidence of a markedly abnormally low serum bicarbonate (i.e., absolute value less than 17 mEq/L and greater than 5 mEq/L decrease from pretreatment) in the adjunctive therapy trials was 3% for 400 mg per day and 0% for placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3753" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The incidence of persistent decreases in serum bicarbonate in adult patients (≥16 years of age) in the epilepsy controlled clinical trial for monotherapy was 14% for 50 mg per day and 25% for 400 mg per day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3754" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The incidence of a markedly abnormally low serum bicarbonate (i.e., absolute value less than 17 mEq/L and greater than 5 mEq/L decrease from pretreatment) in this trial for adults was 1% for 50 mg per day and 6% for 400 mg per day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3755" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Serum bicarbonate levels have not been systematically evaluated at daily doses greater than 400 mg per day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3756" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Pediatric Patients (2 years to 16 years of age) The incidence of persistent decreases in serum bicarbonate in placebo-controlled trials for adjunctive treatment of Lennox-Gastaut syndrome or refractory partial onset seizures in patients age 2 years to 16 years was 67% for topiramate (at approximately 6 mg/kg/day), and 10% for placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3757" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The incidence of a markedly abnormally low serum bicarbonate (i.e., absolute value less than 17 mEq/L and greater than 5 mEq/L decrease from pretreatment) in these trials was 11% for topiramate and 0% for placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3758" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Cases of moderately severe metabolic acidosis have been reported in patients as young as 5 months old, especially at daily doses above 5 mg/kg/day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3759" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In pediatric patients (6 years to 15 years of age), the incidence of persistent decreases in serum bicarbonate in the epilepsy controlled clinical trial for monotherapy performed with topiramate was 9% for 50 mg per day and 25% for 400 mg per day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3760" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The incidence of a markedly abnormally low serum bicarbonate (i.e., absolute value less than 17 mEq/L and greater than 5 mEq/L decrease from pretreatment) in this trial was 1% for 50 mg per day and 6% for 400 mg per day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3761" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Pediatric Patients (under 2 years of age) Although QUDEXY XR is not approved for use in patients less than 2 years of age, a study of topiramate as adjunctive use in patients under 2 years of age with partial onset seizures revealed that topiramate produced a metabolic acidosis that is notably greater in magnitude than that observed in controlled trials in older children and adults.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3762" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The mean treatment difference (25 mg/kg/day topiramate-placebo) was -5.9 mEq/L for bicarbonate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3763" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The incidence of metabolic acidosis (defined by a serum bicarbonate less than 20 mEq/L) was 0% for placebo, 30% for 5 mg/kg/day, 50% for 15 mg/kg/day, and 45% for 25 mg/kg/day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3764" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The incidence of markedly abnormal changes (i.e., less than 17 mEq/L and greater than 5 mEq/L decrease from baseline of greater than or equal to 20 mEq/L) was 0% for placebo, 4% for 5 mg/kg/day, 5% for 15 mg/kg/day and 5% for 25 mg/kg/day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3765" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Migraine Adult Patients The incidence of persistent decreases in serum bicarbonate in placebo-controlled trials in adults for the prophylaxis of migraine was 44% for 200 mg/day, 39% for 100 mg/day, 23% for 50 mg/day, and 7% for placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3766" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The incidence of markedly abnormally low serum bicarbonate (i.e., absolute value less than 17 mEq/L and greater than 5 mEq/L decrease from pretreatment) in these trials was 11% for 200 mg/day, 9% for 100 mg/day, 2% for 50 mg/day, and &lt;1% for placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3767" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Adolescent Patients In pooled, double-blind migraine prophylaxis studies in adolescent patients (12 to 17 years of age), the incidence of persistent decreases in serum bicarbonate was 77% for 200 mg/day, 27% for 100 mg/day, 30% for 50 mg/day, and 9% for placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3768" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The incidence of markedly low serum bicarbonate (i.e., absolute value &lt;17 mEq/L and &gt;5 mEq/L decrease from pretreatment) was 6% for 100 mg/day, 2% for 50 mg/day, and 2% for placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3769" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>This bicarbonate criterion was not met by any patients in the 200 mg/day group, which had a low number of subjects (n=13).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3770" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Measurement of Serum Bicarbonate in Epilepsy and Migraine Patients Measurement of baseline and periodic serum bicarbonate during topiramate treatment is recommended.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3771" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If metabolic acidosis develops and persists, consideration should be given to reducing the dose or discontinuing topiramate (using dose tapering).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3772" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If the decision is made to continue patients on topiramate in the face of persistent acidosis, alkali treatment should be considered.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3773" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Antiepileptic drugs (AEDs) increase the risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior in patients taking these drugs for any indication.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3774" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients treated with any AED, including QUDEXY XR, for any indication should be monitored for the emergence or worsening of depression, suicidal thoughts or behavior, and/or any unusual changes in mood or behavior.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3775" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Pooled analyses of 199 placebo-controlled clinical trials (mono- and adjunctive therapy) of 11 different AEDs showed that patients randomized to one of the AEDs had approximately twice the risk (adjusted Relative Risk 1.8, 95% CI:1.2, 2.7) of suicidal thinking or behavior compared to patients randomized to placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3776" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In these trials, which had a median treatment duration of 12 weeks, the estimated incidence rate of suicidal behavior or ideation among 27,863 AED-treated patients was 0.43%, compared to 0.24% among 16,029 placebo-treated patients, representing an increase of approximately one case of suicidal thinking or behavior for every 530 patients treated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3777" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There were four suicides in drug-treated patients in the trials and none in placebo-treated patients, but the number is too small to allow any conclusion about drug effect on suicide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3778" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The increased risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior with AEDs was observed as early as one week after starting drug treatment with AEDs and persisted for the duration of treatment assessed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3779" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Because most trials included in the analysis did not extend beyond 24 weeks, the risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior beyond 24 weeks could not be assessed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3780" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior was generally consistent among drugs in the data analyzed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3781" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The finding of increased risk with AEDs of varying mechanisms of action and across a range of indications suggests that the risk applies to all AEDs used for any indication.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3782" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The risk did not vary substantially by age (5 to 100 years) in the clinical trials analyzed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3783" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Table 4 shows absolute and relative risk by indication for all evaluated AEDs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3784" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Table 4: Risk by Indication for Antiepileptic Drugs in the Pooled Analysis Indication Placebo Patients with Events per 1,000 Patients Drug Patients with Events per 1,000 Patients Relative Risk: Incidence of Events in Drug Patients/ Incidence in Placebo Patients Risk Difference: Additional Drug Patients with Events per 1,000 Patients Epilepsy 1.0 3.4 3.5 2.4 Psychiatric 5.7 8.5 1.5 2.9 Other 1.0 1.8 1.9 0.9 Total 2.4 4.3 1.8 1.9 The relative risk for suicidal thoughts or behavior was higher in clinical trials for epilepsy than in clinical trials for psychiatric or other conditions, but the absolute risk differences were similar for the epilepsy and psychiatric indications.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3785" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Anyone considering prescribing QUDEXY XR or any other AED must balance the risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior with the risk of untreated illness.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3786" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Epilepsy and many other illnesses for which AEDs are prescribed are themselves associated with morbidity and mortality and an increased risk of suicidal thoughts and behavior.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3787" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Should suicidal thoughts and behavior emerge during treatment, the prescriber needs to consider whether the emergence of these symptoms in any given patient may be related to the illness being treated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3788" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients, their caregivers, and families should be informed that AEDs increase the risk of suicidal thoughts and behavior and should be advised of the need to be alert for the emergence or worsening of the signs and symptoms of depression, any unusual changes in mood or behavior or the emergence of suicidal thoughts, behavior or thoughts about self-harm.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3789" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Behaviors of concern should be reported immediately to healthcare providers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3790" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Adverse reactions most often associated with the use of topiramate, and therefore expected to be associated with the use of QUDEXY XR, were related to the central nervous system and were observed in both the epilepsy and migraine populations.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3791" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In adults, the most frequent of these can be classified into three general categories: 1) Cognitive-related dysfunction (e.g. confusion, psychomotor slowing, difficulty with concentration/attention, difficulty with memory, speech or language problems, particularly word-finding difficulties), 2) Psychiatric/behavioral disturbances (e.g. depression or mood problems), and 3) Somnolence or fatigue.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3792" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Adult Patients Cognitive Related Dysfunction The majority of cognitive-related adverse reactions were mild to moderate in severity, and they frequently occurred in isolation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3793" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Rapid titration rate and higher initial dose were associated with higher incidences of these reactions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3794" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Many of these reactions contributed to withdrawal from treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3795" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In the adjunctive epilepsy controlled trials conducted with topiramate (using rapid titration such as 100 mg per day to 200 mg per day weekly increments), the proportion of patients who experienced one or more cognitive-related adverse reactions was 42% for 200 mg per day, 41% for 400 mg per day, 52% for 600 mg per day, 56% for 800 and 1,000 mg per day, and 14% for placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3796" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>These dose-related adverse reactions began with a similar frequency in the titration or in the maintenance phase, although in some patients the events began during titration and persisted into the maintenance phase.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3797" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Some patients who experienced one or more cognitive-related adverse reactions in the titration phase had a dose-related recurrence of these reactions in the maintenance phase.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3798" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In the monotherapy epilepsy controlled trial conducted with topiramate, the proportion of patients who experienced one or more cognitive-related adverse reactions was 19% for topiramate 50 mg per day and 26% for 400 mg per day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3799" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In the 6-month migraine prophylaxis controlled trials using a slower titration regimen (25 mg/day weekly increments), the proportion of patients who experienced one or more cognitive-related adverse reactions was 19% for topiramate 50 mg/day, 22% for 100 mg/day (the recommended dose), 28% for 200 mg/day, and 10% for placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3800" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>These dose-related adverse reactions typically began in the titration phase and often persisted into the maintenance phase, but infrequently began in the maintenance phase.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3801" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Some patients experienced a recurrence of one or more of these cognitive adverse reactions and this recurrence was typically in the titration phase.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3802" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>A relatively small proportion of topiramate-treated patients experienced more than one concurrent cognitive adverse reaction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3803" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The most common cognitive adverse reactions occurring together included difficulty with memory along with difficulty with concentration/attention, difficulty with memory along with language problems, and difficulty with concentration/attention along with language problems.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3804" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Rarely, topiramate-treated patients experienced three concurrent cognitive reactions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3805" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Psychiatric/Behavioral Disturbances Psychiatric/behavioral disturbances (depression or mood) were dose-related for both the epilepsy and migraine populations treated with topiramate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3806" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Somnolence/Fatigue Somnolence and fatigue were the adverse reactions most frequently reported during clinical trials of topiramate for adjunctive epilepsy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3807" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>For the adjunctive epilepsy population, the incidence of somnolence did not differ substantially between 200 mg per day and 1,000 mg per day, but the incidence of fatigue was dose-related and increased at dosages above 400 mg per day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3808" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>For the monotherapy epilepsy population in the 50 mg per day and 400 mg per day groups, the incidence of somnolence was dose-related (9% for the 50 mg per day group and 15% for the 400 mg per day group) and the incidence of fatigue was comparable in both treatment groups (14% each).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3809" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>For the migraine population, somnolence and fatigue were dose-related and more common in the titration phase.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3810" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Additional nonspecific CNS events commonly observed with topiramate in the adjunctive epilepsy population include dizziness or ataxia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3811" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Pediatric Patients Epilepsy In double-blind adjunctive therapy and monotherapy epilepsy clinical studies conducted with topiramate, the incidences of cognitive/neuropsychiatric adverse reactions in pediatric patients were generally lower than observed in adults.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3812" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>These reactions included psychomotor slowing, difficulty with concentration/attention, speech disorders/related speech problems and language problems.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3813" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The most frequently reported neuropsychiatric reactions in pediatric patients during adjunctive therapy double-blind studies were somnolence and fatigue.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3814" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The most frequently reported neuropsychiatric reactions in pediatric patients in the 50 mg per day and 400 mg per day groups during the monotherapy double-blind study were headache, dizziness, anorexia, and somnolence.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3815" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>No patients discontinued treatment due to any adverse reactions in the adjunctive epilepsy double-blind trials.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3816" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In the monotherapy epilepsy double-blind trial conducted with immediate-release topiramate product, 1 pediatric patient (2%) in the 50 mg per day group and 7 pediatric patients (12%) in the 400 mg per day group discontinued treatment due to any adverse reactions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3817" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The most common adverse reaction associated with discontinuation of therapy was difficulty with concentration/attention; all occurred in the 400 mg per day group.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3818" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Migraine The incidence of cognitive adverse reactions was increased in topiramate-treated patients (7%) versus placebo (4%) in pooled, double-blind placebo-controlled studies in which adolescent patients (12 to 17 years) were randomized to placebo or one of several fixed daily doses of topiramate (50 mg, 100 mg, 200 mg).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3819" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The incidence of cognitive adverse reactions was also increased in a placebo-controlled study of pediatric patients (6 to 16 years) treated with 2 to 3 mg/kg/day of topiramate (10%) versus placebo treatment (2%).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3820" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>QUDEXY XR is not approved for prophylaxis of migraine in pediatric patients under 12 years of age.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3821" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The risk for cognitive adverse reactions was dose-dependent, and was particularly evident at the 200 mg dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3822" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>This risk for cognitive adverse reactions was also greater in younger patients (6 to 11 years) than in older patients (12 to 17 years).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3823" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The most common cognitive adverse reaction in these trials was difficulty with concentration/attention.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3824" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Cognitive adverse reactions most commonly developed in the titration period and sometimes persisted into the maintenance period.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3825" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>These adverse reactions typically occurred in isolation as single type of cognitive adverse reaction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3826" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Cognitive adverse reactions that led to study discontinuation occurred in one patient (difficulty with concentration/attention and language problems).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3827" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The Cambridge Neuropsychological Test Automated Battery (CANTAB) was administered to adolescents (12 to 17 years) to assess the effects of topiramate on cognitive function at baseline and at the end of the Study 3.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3828" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Mean change from baseline in certain CANTAB tests suggests that topiramate treatment may result in psychomotor slowing and decreased verbal fluency.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3829" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Topiramate can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3830" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Data from pregnancy registries indicate that infants exposed to topiramate in utero have an increased risk for cleft lip and/or cleft palate (oral clefts) and for being small for gestational age.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3831" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In multiple species, oral administration of topiramate to pregnant animals at clinically relevant doses resulted in structural malformations, including craniofacial defects, and reduced body weights in offspring.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3832" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Consider the benefits and risks of QUDEXY XR when administering the drug in women of childbearing potential, particularly when QUDEXY XR is considered for a condition not usually associated with permanent injury or death.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3833" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>QUDEXY XR should be used during pregnancy only if the potential benefit outweighs the potential risk.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3834" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If this drug is used during pregnancy, or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking this drug, the patient should be informed of the potential hazard to a fetus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3835" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In patients with or without a history of seizures or epilepsy, antiepileptic drugs including QUDEXY XR, should be gradually withdrawn to minimize the potential for seizures or increased seizure frequency.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3836" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In situations where rapid withdrawal of QUDEXY XR is medically required, appropriate monitoring is recommended.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3837" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hyperammonemia/Encephalopathy Without Concomitant Valproic Acid (VPA) Topiramate treatment has produced hyperammonemia (in some instances dose-related) in a clinical investigational program in adolescent patients (12 to 17 years) who were treated with topiramate for migraine prophylaxis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3838" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The incidence of hyperammonemia (above the upper limit of normal reference) at any time in the trial was 9% for placebo, 14% for 50 mg, and 26% for 100 mg topiramate daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3839" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In some patients, hyperammonemia was observed at the end of the trial at the final visit.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3840" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The incidence of markedly increased hyperammonemia (at least 50% or higher above upper limit of normal) at any time in the trial in adolescent patients was also increased at 100 mg/day (9%) compared to 50 mg topiramate (0%) or placebo (3%).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3841" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>During this trial, markedly increased ammonia levels returned to normal in all but one patient (in whom the ammonia level fell to high instead of markedly abnormal).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3842" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Topiramate treatment has produced hyperammonemia in a clinical investigational program in very young pediatric patients (1 month to 24 months) who were treated with adjunctive topiramate for partial onset epilepsy (8% for placebo, 10% for 5 mg/kg/day, 0% for 15 mg/kg/day, 9% for 25 mg/kg/day).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3843" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>QUDEXY XR is not approved as adjunctive treatment of partial onset seizures in pediatric patients less than 2 years old.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3844" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In some patients, ammonia was markedly increased (greater than 50% above upper limit of normal).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3845" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The hyperammonemia associated with topiramate treatment occurred with and without encephalopathy in placebo-controlled trials, and in an open-label, extension trial of infants with refractory epilepsy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3846" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Dose-related hyperammonemia was also observed in the extension trial in pediatric patients up to 2 years old.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3847" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Clinical symptoms of hyperammonemic encephalopathy often include acute alterations in level of consciousness and/or cognitive function with lethargy or vomiting.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3848" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hyperammonemia with and without encephalopathy has also been observed in post-marketing reports in patients who were taking topiramate without concomitant valproic acid (VPA).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3849" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hyperammonemia/Encephalopathy With Concomitant Valproic Acid (VPA) Concomitant administration of topiramate and valproic acid (VPA) has been associated with hyperammonemia with or without encephalopathy in patients who have tolerated either drug alone based upon post-marketing reports.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M114" type="Trigger" span="141 15" str="associated with"/>
<Mention id="M112" type="Precipitant" span="47 13" str="valproic acid" code="614OI1Z5WI"/>
<Mention id="M116" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 14" str="Hyperammonemia" code="9360008: Hyperammonemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M115" type="Precipitant" span="62 3" str="VPA" code="614OI1Z5WI"/>
<Interaction id="I40" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M114" precipitant="M112" effect="M116" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I41" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M114" precipitant="M115" effect="M116" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3850" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Although hyperammonemia may be asymptomatic, clinical symptoms of hyperammonemic encephalopathy often include acute alterations in level of consciousness and/or cognitive function with lethargy or vomiting.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3851" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In most cases, symptoms and signs abated with discontinuation of either drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3852" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>This adverse reaction is not due to a pharmacokinetic interaction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3853" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Although QUDEXY XR is not indicated for use in infants/toddlers (1 month to 24 months), topiramate with concomitant VPA clearly produced a dose-related increase in the incidence of hyperammonemia (above the upper limit of normal, 0% for placebo, 12% for 5 mg/kg/day, 7% for 15 mg/kg/day, 17% for 25 mg/kg/day) in an investigational program using topiramate.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M117" type="Trigger" span="152 25" str="increase in the incidence"/>
<Mention id="M118" type="Precipitant" span="116 3" str="VPA" code="614OI1Z5WI"/>
<Mention id="M119" type="SpecificInteraction" span="181 14" str="Hyperammonemia" code="9360008: Hyperammonemia (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I42" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M117" precipitant="M118" effect="M119" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3854" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Markedly increased, dose-related hyperammonemia (0% for placebo and 5 mg/kg/day, 7% for 15 mg/kg/day, and 8% for 25 mg/kg/day) also occurred in these infants/toddlers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3855" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Dose-related hyperammonemia was similarly observed in a long-term, extension trial utilizing topiramate in these very young, pediatric patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3856" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hyperammonemia with and without encephalopathy has also been observed in post-marketing reports in patients taking topiramate with valproic acid (VPA).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M125" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 14" str="Hyperammonemia" code="9360008: Hyperammonemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M121" type="Precipitant" span="131 13" str="valproic acid" code="614OI1Z5WI"/>
<Mention id="M124" type="Precipitant" span="146 3" str="VPA" code="614OI1Z5WI"/>
<Interaction id="I43" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M125" precipitant="M121" effect="M125" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I44" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M125" precipitant="M124" effect="M125" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3857" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The hyperammonemia associated with topiramate treatment appears to be more common when used concomitantly with VPA.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M126" type="Trigger" span="19 15" str="associated with "/>
<Mention id="M127" type="Trigger" span="70 11" str=" more common"/>
<Mention id="M128" type="Precipitant" span="111 3" str="VPA" code="614OI1Z5WI"/>
<Mention id="M129" type="SpecificInteraction" span="4 14" str="Hyperammonemia" code="9360008: Hyperammonemia (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I45" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M126;M127" precipitant="M128" effect="M129" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3858" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Monitoring for Hyperammonemia Patients with inborn errors of metabolism or reduced hepatic mitochondrial activity may be at an increased risk for hyperammonemia with or without encephalopathy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3859" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Although not studied, topiramate or QUDEXY XR treatment or an interaction of concomitant topiramate-based product and valproic acid treatment may exacerbate existing defects or unmask deficiencies in susceptible persons.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M130" type="Trigger" span="146 10" str="exacerbate"/>
<Mention id="M134" type="Precipitant" span="118 13" str="valproic acid" code="614OI1Z5WI"/>
<Mention id="M132" type="SpecificInteraction" span="146 27" str="exacerbate existing defects" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M133" type="Trigger" span="177 6" str="unmask"/>
<Mention id="M135" type="SpecificInteraction" span="177 19" str="unmask deficiencies" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I46" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M130" precipitant="M134" effect="M132" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I47" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M133" precipitant="M134" effect="M135" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3860" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In patients who develop unexplained lethargy, vomiting, or changes in mental status associated with any topiramate treatment, hyperammonemic encephalopathy should be considered and an ammonia level should be measured.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3861" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>A total of 32/2086 (1.5%) of adults exposed to topiramate during its adjunctive epilepsy therapy development reported the occurrence of kidney stones, an incidence about 2 to 4 times greater than expected in a similar, untreated population.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3862" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In the double-blind monotherapy epilepsy study, a total of 4/319 (1.3%) of adults exposed to topiramate reported the occurrence of kidney stones.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3863" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>As in the general population, the incidence of stone formation among topiramate-treated patients was higher in men.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3864" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Kidney stones have also been reported in pediatric patients taking topiramate for epilepsy or migraine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3865" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>During long-term (up to 1 year) topiramate treatment in an open-label extension study of 284 pediatric patients 1 month to 24 months old with epilepsy, 7% developed kidney or bladder stones that were diagnosed clinically or by sonogram.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3866" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>QUDEXY XR is not approved for pediatric patients less than 2 years old.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3867" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Kidney stones have also been reported in pediatric patients taking topiramate for migraine prophylaxis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3868" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>For the double-blind migraine prophylaxis studies, one adverse event (renal calculus) occurred in a topiramate-treated subject in the age 12 to 17 years group.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3869" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The overall experience with open-label, long-term, topiramate treatment for migraine prophylaxis is limited in pediatric patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3870" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>QUDEXY XR would be expected to have the same effect as topiramate on the formation of kidney stones.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3871" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>An explanation for the association of topiramate and kidney stones may lay in the fact that topiramate is a carbonic anhydrase inhibitor.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3872" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Carbonic anhydrase inhibitors (e.g., zonisamide, acetazolamide or dichlorphenamide) can promote stone formation by reducing urinary citrate excretion and by increasing urinary pH.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3873" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The concomitant use of QUDEXY XR with any other drug producing metabolic acidosis, or potentially in patients on a ketogenic diet, may create a physiological environment that increases the risk of kidney stone formation, and should therefore be avoided.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M139" type="Trigger" span="175 18" str="increases the risk"/>
<Mention id="M137" type="Precipitant" span="48 33" str="drug producing metabolic acidosis" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M141" type="SpecificInteraction" span="197 22" str="kidney stone formation" code="95570007: Kidney stone (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M140" type="Precipitant" span="115 14" str="ketogenic diet" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I48" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M139" precipitant="M137" effect="M141" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I49" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M139" precipitant="M140" effect="M141" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3874" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Increased fluid intake increases the urinary output, lowering the concentration of substances involved in stone formation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3875" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hydration is recommended to reduce new stone formation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3876" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hypothermia, defined as an unintentional drop in body core temperature to less than 35ºC (95ºF) has been reported in association with topiramate use with concomitant valproic acid (VPA) both in the presence and in the absence of hyperammonemia.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M151" type="Trigger" span="117 16" str="association with"/>
<Mention id="M146" type="Precipitant" span="166 13" str="valproic acid" code="614OI1Z5WI"/>
<Mention id="M150" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 11" str="Hypothermia" code="386689009: Hypothermia (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M153" type="SpecificInteraction" span="27 68" str="unintentional drop in body core temperature to less than 35ºC (95ºF)" code="386689009: Hypothermia (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M152" type="Precipitant" span="181 3" str="VPA" code="614OI1Z5WI"/>
<Interaction id="I50" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M151" precipitant="M146" effect="M150" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I51" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M151" precipitant="M146" effect="M153" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I52" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M151" precipitant="M152" effect="M150" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I53" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M151" precipitant="M152" effect="M153" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3877" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>This adverse reaction in patients using concomitant topiramate and valproate can occur after starting topiramate treatment or after increasing the daily dose of topiramate.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M154" type="Trigger" span="5 16" str="adverse reaction"/>
<Mention id="M155" type="Precipitant" span="67 9" str="valproate" code="614OI1Z5WI"/>
<Interaction id="I54" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M154" precipitant="M155"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3878" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Consideration should be given to stopping topiramate or valproate in patients who develop hypothermia, which may be manifested by a variety of clinical abnormalities including lethargy, confusion, coma, and significant alterations in other major organ systems such as the cardiovascular and respiratory systems.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M176" type="Trigger" span="82 7" str="develop "/>
<Mention id="M177" type="Trigger" span="152 13" str=" abnormalities"/>
<Mention id="M178" type="Precipitant" span="56 9" str="valproate" code="614OI1Z5WI"/>
<Mention id="M159" type="SpecificInteraction" span="197 4" str="coma" code="371632003: Coma (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M163" type="SpecificInteraction" span="186 9" str="confusion" code="40917007: Clouded consciousness (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M167" type="SpecificInteraction" span="90 11" str="hypothermia" code="386689009: Hypothermia (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M171" type="SpecificInteraction" span="176 8" str="lethargy" code="214264003: Lethargy (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M175" type="SpecificInteraction" span="207 23;272 14" str="significant alterations | cardiovascular" code="267037003: Cardiovascular symptoms (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M179" type="SpecificInteraction" span="207 23;291 11" str="significant alterations | respiratory" code="161920001: Respiratory symptom (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I55" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M176;M177" precipitant="M178" effect="M159" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I56" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M176;M177" precipitant="M178" effect="M163" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I57" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M176;M177" precipitant="M178" effect="M167" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I58" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M176;M177" precipitant="M178" effect="M171" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I59" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M176;M177" precipitant="M178" effect="M175" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I60" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M176;M177" precipitant="M178" effect="M179" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3879" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Clinical management and assessment should include examination of blood ammonia levels.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3880" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Paresthesia (usually tingling of the extremities), an effect associated with the use of other carbonic anhydrase inhibitors, appears to be a common effect of topiramate in adult and pediatric patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3881" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Paresthesia was more frequently reported in the monotherapy epilepsy trials and migraine prophylaxis trials conducted with immediate-release topiramate than in the adjunctive therapy epilepsy trials conducted with the same product.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3882" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In the majority of instances, paresthesia did not lead to treatment discontinuation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3883" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients should be watched carefully when QUDEXY XR is co-administered with other CNS depressant drugs.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M180" type="Trigger" span="9 27" str="should be watched carefully"/>
<Mention id="M181" type="Precipitant" span="82 14" str="CNS depressant" code="N0000175758"/>
<Interaction id="I61" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M180" precipitant="M181"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3884" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The precise mechanisms by which topiramate exerts its anticonvulsant and migraine prophylaxis effects are unknown; however, preclinical studies have revealed four properties that may contribute to topiramate's efficacy for epilepsy and migraine prophylaxis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3885" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Electrophysiological and biochemical evidence suggests that topiramate, at pharmacologically relevant concentrations, blocks voltage-dependent sodium channels, augments the activity of the neurotransmitter gamma-aminobutyrate at some subtypes of the GABA-A receptor, antagonizes the AMPA/kainate subtype of the glutamate receptor, and inhibits the carbonic anhydrase enzyme, particularly isozymes II and IV.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3886" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Topiramate has anticonvulsant activity in rat and mouse maximal electroshock seizure (MES) tests.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3887" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Topiramate is only weakly effective in blocking clonic seizures induced by the GABA-A receptor antagonist, pentylenetetrazole.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3888" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Topiramate is also effective in rodent models of epilepsy, which include tonic and absence-like seizures in the spontaneous epileptic rat (SER) and tonic and clonic seizures induced in rats by kindling of the amygdala or by global ischemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3889" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Changes (increases and decreases) from baseline in vital signs (systolic blood pressure-SBP, diastolic blood pressure-DBP, pulse) occurred more frequently in pediatric patients (6 to 17 years) treated with various daily doses of topiramate (50 mg, 100 mg, 200 mg, 2 to 3 mg/kg) than in patients treated with placebo in controlled trials for migraine prophylaxis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3890" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The most notable changes were SBP &lt; 90 mm Hg, DBP &lt; 50 mm Hg, SBP or DBP increases or decreases ≥ 20 mm Hg, and pulse increases or decreases ≥ 30 beats per minute.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3891" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>These changes were often dose-related, and were most frequently associated with the greatest treatment difference at the 200 mg dose level.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3892" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>When a position was specified for measurement of vital signs in a trial, measurements were made in a sitting position.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3893" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Systematic collection of orthostatic vital signs has not been conducted.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3894" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The clinical significance of these various changes in vital signs has not been clearly established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3895" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Absorption and Distribution The pharmacokinetics of QUDEXY XR are linear with dose proportional increases in plasma concentration when administered as a single oral dose over the range of 50 mg to 1,400 mg. At 25 mg, the pharmacokinetics of QUDEXY XR are nonlinear, possibly due to the binding of topiramate to carbonic anhydrase in red blood cells.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3896" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>QUDEXY XR sprinkled on a spoonful of soft food is bioequivalent to the intact capsule formulation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3897" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following a single 200 mg oral dose of QUDEXY XR, peak plasma concentrations (Tmax) occurred approximately 20 hours after dosing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3898" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Steady-state was reached in about 5 days following daily dosing of QUDEXY XR in subjects with normal renal function, with a Tmax of approximately 6 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3899" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>At steady-state, the plasma exposure (AUC0-24hr, Cmax, and Cmin) of topiramate from QUDEXY XR administered once daily and the immediate-release topiramate tablets administered twice-daily were shown to be bioequivalent.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3900" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Fluctuation of topiramate plasma concentrations at steady-state for QUDEXY XR administered once daily was approximately 40% in healthy subjects, compared to approximately 53% for immediate-release topiramate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3901" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Compared to the fasted state, high-fat meal had no effect on bioavailability (AUC and Cmax) but delayed the Tmax by approximately 4 hours following a single dose of QUDEXY XR.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M182" type="Trigger" span="96 16" str="delayed the Tmax"/>
<Mention id="M183" type="Precipitant" span="30 13" str="high-fat meal" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I62" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M182" precipitant="M183" effect="C54604"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3902" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Topiramate is 15% to 41% bound to human plasma proteins over the blood concentration range of 0.5 mcg/mL to 250 mcg/mL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3903" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The fraction bound decreased as blood concentration increased.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3904" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Carbamazepine and phenytoin do not alter the binding of immediate-release topiramate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3905" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Sodium valproate, at 500 mcg/mL (a concentration 5 to 10 times higher than considered therapeutic for valproate) decreased the protein binding of immediate-release topiramate from 23% to 13%.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M184" type="Trigger" span="113 29" str="decreased the protein binding"/>
<Mention id="M185" type="Precipitant" span="0 16" str="Sodium valproate" code="5VOM6GYJ0D"/>
<Mention id="M186" type="SpecificInteraction" span="113 61" str="decreased the protein binding of immediate-release topiramate" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I63" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M184" precipitant="M185" effect="M186" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3906" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Immediate-release topiramate does not influence the binding of sodium valproate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3907" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Metabolism and Excretion Topiramate is not extensively metabolized and is primarily eliminated unchanged in the urine (approximately 70% of an administered dose).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3908" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Six metabolites have been identified in humans, none of which constitutes more than 5% of an administered dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3909" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The metabolites are formed via hydroxylation, hydrolysis, and glucuronidation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3910" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There is evidence of renal tubular reabsorption of topiramate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3911" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In rats, given probenecid to inhibit tubular reabsorption, along with topiramate, a significant increase in renal clearance of topiramate was observed.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M187" type="Trigger" span="29 7" str="inhibit"/>
<Mention id="M191" type="Precipitant" span="15 10" str="probenecid" code="PO572Z7917"/>
<Mention id="M189" type="SpecificInteraction" span="29 28" str="inhibit tubular reabsorption" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M190" type="Trigger" span="96 27" str="increase in renal clearance"/>
<Interaction id="I64" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M187" precipitant="M191" effect="M189" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I65" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M190" precipitant="M191" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3912" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This interaction has not been evaluated in humans.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3913" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Overall, oral plasma clearance (CL/F) is approximately 20 mL/min to 30 mL/min in adults following oral administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3914" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mean effective half-life of QUDEXY XR is approximately 56 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3915" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Steady-state is reached in about 5 days after QUDEXY XR dosing in subjects with normal renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3916" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Specific Populations Renal Impairment The clearance of topiramate was reduced by 42% in subjects with moderate renal impairment (creatinine clearance 30 to 69 mL/min/1.73 m2) and by 54% in subjects with severe renal impairment (creatinine clearance less than 30 mL/min/1.73 m2) compared to subjects with normal renal function (creatinine clearance greater than70 mL/min/1.73 m2).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3917" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Since topiramate is presumed to undergo significant tubular reabsorption, it is uncertain whether this experience can be generalized to all situations of renal impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3918" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>It is conceivable that some forms of renal disease could differentially affect glomerular filtration rate and tubular reabsorption resulting in a clearance of topiramate not predicted by creatinine clearance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3919" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In general, however, use of one-half the usual starting and maintenance dose is recommended in patients with creatinine clearance less than 70 mL/min/1.73 m2.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3920" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Hemodialysis Topiramate is cleared by hemodialysis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3921" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Using a high-efficiency, counterflow, single pass-dialysate hemodialysis procedure, topiramate dialysis clearance was 120 mL/min with blood flow through the dialyzer at 400 mL/min.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3922" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This high clearance (compared to 20 mL/min to 30 mL/min total oral clearance in healthy adults) will remove a clinically significant amount of topiramate from the patient over the hemodialysis treatment period.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3923" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Therefore, a supplemental dose may be required.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3924" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Hepatic Impairment In subjects with hepatic impairment, the clearance of topiramate may be decreased; the mechanism underlying the decrease is not well understood.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3925" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Age, Gender and Race The pharmacokinetics of topiramate in elderly subjects (65 to 85 years of age, N=16) were evaluated in a controlled clinical study.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3926" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The elderly subject population had reduced renal function (creatinine clearance [-20%]) compared to young adults.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3927" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following a single oral 100 mg dose, maximum plasma concentration for elderly and young adults was achieved at approximately 1 to 2 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3928" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Reflecting the primary renal elimination of topiramate, topiramate plasma and renal clearance were reduced 21% and 19%, respectively, in elderly subjects, compared to young adults.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3929" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Similarly, topiramate half-life was longer (13%) in the elderly.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3930" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Reduced topiramate clearance resulted in slightly higher maximum plasma concentration (23%) and AUC (25%) in elderly subjects than observed in young adults.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3931" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Topiramate clearance is decreased in the elderly only to the extent that renal function is reduced.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3932" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Because of this, dosage adjustment may be necessary.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3933" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Clearance of topiramate in adults was not affected by gender or race.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3934" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Pediatric Pharmacokinetics Pharmacokinetics of immediate-release topiramate were evaluated in patients ages 2 years to less than 16 years.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3935" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Patients received either no or a combination of other antiepileptic drugs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3936" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A population pharmacokinetic model was developed on the basis of pharmacokinetic data from relevant topiramate clinical studies.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3937" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This dataset contained data from 1217 subjects including 258 pediatric patients aged 2 years to less than 16 years (95 pediatric patients less than 10 years of age).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3938" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Pediatric patients on adjunctive treatment exhibited a higher oral clearance (L/h) of topiramate compared to patients on monotherapy, presumably because of increased clearance from concomitant enzyme-inducing antiepileptic drugs.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M192" type="Trigger" span="156 19" str="increased clearance"/>
<Mention id="M193" type="Precipitant" span="193 35" str="enzyme-inducing antiepileptic drugs" code="N0000175753"/>
<Interaction id="I66" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M192" precipitant="M193" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3939" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In comparison, topiramate clearance per kg is greater in pediatric patients than in adults and in young pediatric patients (down to 2 years) than in older pediatric patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3940" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Consequently, the plasma drug concentration for the same mg/kg/day dose would be lower in pediatric patients compared to adults and also in younger pediatric patients compared to older pediatric patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3941" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>As in adults, hepatic enzyme-inducing antiepileptic drugs decrease the steady state plasma concentrations of topiramate.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M194" type="Trigger" span="58 8;84 21" str="decrease | plasma concentrations"/>
<Mention id="M195" type="Precipitant" span="14 43" str="hepatic enzyme-inducing antiepileptic drugs" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I67" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M194" precipitant="M195" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3942" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Drug-Drug Interaction Studies Antiepileptic Drugs Potential interactions between immediate-release topiramate and standard AEDs were assessed in controlled clinical pharmacokinetic studies in patients with epilepsy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3943" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The effects of these interactions on mean plasma AUCs are summarized in Table 14.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3944" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Interaction of QUDEXY XR and standard AEDs is not expected to differ from the experience with immediate-release topiramate products.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3945" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In Table 14, the second column (AED concentration) describes what happened to the concentration of the AED listed in the first column when topiramate was added.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3946" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The third column (topiramate concentration) describes how the co-administration of a drug listed in the first column modified the concentration of topiramate in experimental settings when topiramate was given alone.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3947" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Table 14: Summary of AED Interactions with topiramate AED Co-administered AED Concentration Topiramate Concentration NC=Less than 10% change in plasma concentrationAED=Antiepileptic drugNE=Not evaluatedTPM=topiramate Phenytoin NC or 25% increasePlasma concentration increased 25% in some patients, generally those on a twice a day dosing regimen of phenytoin 48% decrease Carbamazepine (CBZ) NC 40% decrease CBZ epoxideIs not administered, but is an active metabolite of carbamazepine NC NE Valproic acid 11% decrease 14% decrease Phenobarbital NC NE Primidone NC NE Lamotrigine NC at TPM doses up to 400 mg per day 13% decrease In addition to the pharmacokinetic interaction described in the above table, concomitant administration of valproic acid and topiramate has been associated with hyperammonemia with and without encephalopathy and hypothermia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3948" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>CNS Depressants or Alcohol Concomitant administration of topiramate and alcohol or other CNS depressant drugs has not been evaluated in clinical studies.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3949" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Oral Contraceptives In a pharmacokinetic interaction study in healthy volunteers with a concomitantly administered combination oral contraceptive product containing 1 mg norethindrone (NET) plus 35 mcg ethinyl estradiol (EE), topiramate, given in the absence of other medications at doses of 50 to 200 mg per day, was not associated with statistically significant changes in mean exposure (AUC) to either component of the oral contraceptive.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3950" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In another study, exposure to EE was statistically significantly decreased at doses of 200, 400, and 800 mg per day (18%, 21%, and 30%, respectively) when given as adjunctive therapy in patients taking valproic acid.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3951" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In both studies, topiramate (50 mg per day to 800 mg per day) did not significantly affect exposure to NET.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3952" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Although there was a dose-dependent decrease in EE exposure for doses between 200 to 800 mg per day, there was no significant dose-dependent change in EE exposure for doses of 50 to 200 mg per day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3953" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The clinical significance of the changes observed is not known.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3954" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The possibility of decreased contraceptive efficacy and increased breakthrough bleeding should be considered in patients taking combination oral contraceptive products with QUDEXY XR.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M196" type="Trigger" span="56 9" str="increased"/>
<Mention id="M200" type="Precipitant" span="128 30" str="combination oral contraceptive" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M198" type="SpecificInteraction" span="66 21" str="breakthrough bleeding" code="56169002: Break-through bleeding (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M199" type="Trigger" span="19 9;43 8" str="decreased | efficacy"/>
<Mention id="M201" type="SpecificInteraction" span="19 32" str="Decreased contraceptive efficacy" code="102955006: Contraception failure (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I68" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M196" precipitant="M200" effect="M198" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I69" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M199" precipitant="M200" effect="M201" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3955" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Digoxin In a single-dose study, serum digoxin AUC was decreased by 12% with concomitant topiramate administration.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M202" type="Trigger" span="46 17" str="AUC was decreased"/>
<Mention id="M203" type="Precipitant" span="0 7" str="digoxin" code="73K4184T59 | N0000005903"/>
<Interaction id="I70" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M202" precipitant="M203" effect="C54614"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3956" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The clinical relevance of this observation has not been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3957" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Hydrochlorothiazide A drug-drug interaction study conducted in healthy volunteers evaluated the steady-state pharmacokinetics of hydrochlorothiazide (HCTZ) (25 mg every 24 hours) and topiramate (96 mg every 12 hours) when administered alone and concomitantly.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3958" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The results of this study indicate that topiramate Cmax increased by 27% and AUC increased by 29% when HCTZ was added to topiramate.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M204" type="Trigger" span="77 13" str="AUC increased"/>
<Mention id="M207" type="Precipitant" span="103 4" str="HCTZ" code="0J48LPH2TH"/>
<Mention id="M206" type="Trigger" span="51 14" str="Cmax increased"/>
<Interaction id="I71" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M204" precipitant="M207" effect="C54605"/>
<Interaction id="I72" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M206" precipitant="M207" effect="C54602"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3959" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The clinical significance of this change is unknown.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3960" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The addition of HCTZ to QUDEXY XR therapy may require an adjustment of the QUDEXY XR dose.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M208" type="Trigger" span="57 10;85 4" str="adjustment | dose"/>
<Mention id="M209" type="Precipitant" span="16 4" str="HCTZ" code="0J48LPH2TH"/>
<Interaction id="I73" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M208" precipitant="M209"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3961" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The steady-state pharmacokinetics of HCTZ were not significantly influenced by the concomitant administration of topiramate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3962" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Clinical laboratory results indicated decreases in serum potassium after topiramate or HCTZ administration, which were greater when HCTZ and topiramate were administered in combination.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M210" type="Trigger" span="38 9;119 7" str="decreases | greater"/>
<Mention id="M211" type="Precipitant" span="87 4" str="HCTZ" code="0J48LPH2TH"/>
<Mention id="M212" type="SpecificInteraction" span="38 28;119 7" str="decreases in serum potassium | greater" code="166690008: Low serum potassium level (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I74" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M210" precipitant="M211" effect="M212" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3963" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Metformin Topiramate treatment can frequently cause metabolic acidosis, a condition for which the use of metformin is contraindicated.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M213" type="Trigger" span="118 15" str="contraindicated"/>
<Mention id="M214" type="Precipitant" span="0 9" str="metformin" code="9100L32L2N"/>
<Mention id="M215" type="SpecificInteraction" span="52 18" str="metabolic acidosis" code="59455009: Metabolic acidosis (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I75" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M213" precipitant="M214" effect="M215" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3964" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>QUDEXY XR is expected to exhibit the same degree of metabolic acidosis as topiramate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3965" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A drug-drug interaction study conducted in healthy volunteers evaluated the steady-state pharmacokinetics of metformin (500 mg every 12 hr) and topiramate in plasma when metformin was given alone and when metformin and topiramate (100 mg every 12 hr) were given simultaneously.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3966" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The results of this study indicated that the mean metformin Cmax and AUC0-12h increased by 18% and 25%, respectively, when topiramate was added.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M216" type="Trigger" span="69 3;78 9" str="AUC | increased"/>
<Mention id="M219" type="Precipitant" span="50 9" str="metformin" code="9100L32L2N"/>
<Mention id="M218" type="Trigger" span="60 4;78 9" str="Cmax | increased"/>
<Interaction id="I76" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M216" precipitant="M219" effect="C54613"/>
<Interaction id="I77" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M218" precipitant="M219" effect="C54610"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3967" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Topiramate did not affect metformin Tmax.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3968" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The clinical significance of the effect of topiramate on metformin pharmacokinetics is not known.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3969" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Oral plasma clearance of topiramate appears to be reduced when administered with metformin.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M220" type="Trigger" span="0 21;50 7" str="Oral plasma clearance | reduced"/>
<Mention id="M221" type="Precipitant" span="81 9" str="metformin" code="9100L32L2N"/>
<Mention id="M222" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 35;50 7" str="Oral plasma clearance of topiramate | reduced" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I78" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M220" precipitant="M221" effect="M222" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3970" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The clinical significance of the effect of metformin on topiramate QUDEXY XR pharmacokinetics is unclear.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3971" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Pioglitazone A drug-drug interaction study conducted in healthy volunteers evaluated the steady-state pharmacokinetics of topiramate and pioglitazone when administered alone and concomitantly.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3972" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A 15% decrease in the AUCτ,ss of pioglitazone with no alteration in Cmax,ss was observed.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M223" type="Trigger" span="6 19" str="decrease in the AUC"/>
<Mention id="M224" type="Precipitant" span="33 12" str="pioglitazone" code="X4OV71U42S"/>
<Interaction id="I79" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M223" precipitant="M224" effect="C54614"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3973" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This finding was not statistically significant.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3974" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In addition, a 13% and 16% decrease in Cmax,ss and AUCτ,ss respectively, of the active hydroxy-metabolite was noted as well as a 60% decrease in Cmax,ss and AUCτ,ss of the active keto-metabolite.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M231" type="Trigger" span="27 8;51 3" str="decrease | AUC"/>
<Mention id="M228" type="Precipitant" span="80 25" str="active hydroxy-metabolite" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M229" type="Trigger" span="27 16" str="decrease in Cmax"/>
<Mention id="M232" type="Precipitant" span="172 22" str="active keto-metabolite" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I80" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M231" precipitant="M228" effect="C54614"/>
<Interaction id="I81" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M229" precipitant="M228" effect="C54615"/>
<Interaction id="I82" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M229" precipitant="M232" effect="C54615"/>
<Interaction id="I83" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M231" precipitant="M232" effect="C54614"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3975" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The clinical significance of these findings is not known.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3976" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>When QUDEXY XR is added to pioglitazone therapy or pioglitazone is added to QUDEXY XR therapy, careful attention should be given to the routine monitoring of patients for adequate control of their diabetic disease state.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M233" type="Trigger" span="103 9" str="attention "/>
<Mention id="M234" type="Trigger" span="144 10" str=" monitoring"/>
<Mention id="M235" type="Precipitant" span="27 12" str="pioglitazone" code="X4OV71U42S"/>
<Mention id="M236" type="SpecificInteraction" span="197 22" str="diabetic disease state" code="73211009: Diabetes mellitus (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I84" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M233;M234" precipitant="M235" effect="M236" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3977" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Glyburide A drug-drug interaction study conducted in patients with type 2 diabetes evaluated the steady-state pharmacokinetics of glyburide (5 mg per day) alone and concomitantly with topiramate (150 mg per day).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3978" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There was a 22% decrease in Cmax and 25% reduction in AUC24 for glyburide during topiramate administration.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M237" type="Trigger" span="16 16" str="decrease in Cmax"/>
<Mention id="M240" type="Precipitant" span="64 9" str="glyburide" code="N0000006295 | SX6K58TVWC"/>
<Mention id="M239" type="Trigger" span="41 16" str="reduction in AUC"/>
<Interaction id="I85" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M237" precipitant="M240" effect="C54615"/>
<Interaction id="I86" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M239" precipitant="M240" effect="C54614"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3979" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Systemic exposure (AUC) of the active metabolites, 4-trans-hydroxy glyburide (M1) and 3-cis-hydroxyglyburide (M2), was also reduced by 13% and 15%, reduced Cmax by 18% and 25%, respectively.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M241" type="Trigger" span="19 3;124 7" str="AUC | reduced"/>
<Mention id="M246" type="Precipitant" span="67 9" str="glyburide" code="N0000006295 | SX6K58TVWC"/>
<Mention id="M243" type="Trigger" span="148 12" str="reduced Cmax"/>
<Mention id="M245" type="Trigger" span="0 17;124 7" str="Systemic exposure | reduced"/>
<Interaction id="I87" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M241" precipitant="M246" effect="C54614"/>
<Interaction id="I88" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M243" precipitant="M246" effect="C54615"/>
<Interaction id="I89" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M245" precipitant="M246" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3980" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The steady-state pharmacokinetics of topiramate were unaffected by concomitant administration of glyburide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3981" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Lithium In patients, the pharmacokinetics of lithium were unaffected during treatment with topiramate at doses of 200 mg per day; however, there was an observed increase in systemic exposure of lithium (27% for Cmax and 26% for AUC) following topiramate doses up to 600 mg per day.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M247" type="Trigger" span="161 8;228 3" str="increase | AUC"/>
<Mention id="M252" type="Precipitant" span="0 7" str="lithium" code="9FN79X2M3F | N0000147892"/>
<Mention id="M249" type="Trigger" span="161 8;211 4" str="increase | Cmax"/>
<Mention id="M251" type="Trigger" span="161 29" str="increase in systemic exposure"/>
<Interaction id="I90" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M247" precipitant="M252" effect="C54613"/>
<Interaction id="I91" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M249" precipitant="M252" effect="C54610"/>
<Interaction id="I92" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M251" precipitant="M252" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3982" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Haloperidol The pharmacokinetics of a single dose of haloperidol (5 mg) were not affected following multiple dosing of topiramate (100 mg every 12 hr) in 13 healthy adults (6 males, 7 females).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3983" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Amitriptyline There was a 12% increase in AUC and Cmax for amitriptyline (25 mg per day) in 18 normal subjects (9 males, 9 females) receiving 200 mg per day of topiramate.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M253" type="Trigger" span="30 8;50 4" str="increase | Cmax"/>
<Mention id="M256" type="Precipitant" span="0 13" str="amitriptyline" code="1806D8D52K"/>
<Mention id="M255" type="Trigger" span="30 15" str="increase in AUC"/>
<Interaction id="I93" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M253" precipitant="M256" effect="C54610"/>
<Interaction id="I94" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M255" precipitant="M256" effect="C54613"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3984" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Some subjects may experience a large increase in amitriptyline concentration in the presence of QUDEXY XR and any adjustments in amitriptyline dose should be made according to the patient's clinical response and not on the basis of plasma levels.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M257" type="Trigger" span="37 8;63 13" str="increase | concentration"/>
<Mention id="M258" type="Precipitant" span="49 13" str="amitriptyline" code="1806D8D52K"/>
<Interaction id="I95" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M257" precipitant="M258" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3985" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Sumatriptan Multiple dosing of topiramate (100 mg every 12 hrs) in 24 healthy volunteers (14 males, 10 females) did not affect the pharmacokinetics of single-dose sumatriptan either orally (100 mg) or subcutaneously (6 mg).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3986" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Risperidone When administered concomitantly with topiramate at escalating doses of 100, 250, and 400 mg per day, there was a reduction in risperidone systemic exposure (16% and 33% for steady-state AUC at the 250 and 400 mg per day doses of topiramate).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M259" type="Trigger" span="125 9;198 3" str="reduction | AUC"/>
<Mention id="M262" type="Precipitant" span="0 11" str="risperidone" code="L6UH7ZF8HC"/>
<Mention id="M261" type="Trigger" span="125 9;150 17" str="reduction | systemic exposure"/>
<Interaction id="I96" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M259" precipitant="M262" effect="C54614"/>
<Interaction id="I97" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M261" precipitant="M262" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3987" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No alterations of 9-hydroxyrisperidone levels were observed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3988" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Coadministration of topiramate 400 mg per day with risperidone resulted in a 14% increase in Cmax and a 12% increase in AUC12 of topiramate.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M263" type="Trigger" span="108 15" str="increase in AUC"/>
<Mention id="M266" type="Precipitant" span="51 11" str="risperidone" code="L6UH7ZF8HC"/>
<Mention id="M265" type="Trigger" span="81 16" str="increase in Cmax"/>
<Interaction id="I98" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M266" effect="C54605"/>
<Interaction id="I99" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M265" precipitant="M266" effect="C54602"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3989" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There were no clinically significant changes in the systemic exposure of risperidone plus 9- hydroxyrisperidone or of topiramate; therefore, this interaction is not likely to be of clinical significance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3990" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Propranolol Multiple dosing of topiramate (200 mg per day) in 34 healthy volunteers (17 males, 17 females) did not affect the pharmacokinetics of propranolol following daily 160 mg doses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3991" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Propranolol doses of 160 mg per day in 39 volunteers (27 males, 12 females) had no effect on the exposure to topiramate at a dose of 200 mg per day of topiramate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3992" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Dihydroergotamine Multiple dosing of topiramate (200 mg per day) in 24 healthy volunteers (12 males, 12 females) did not affect the pharmacokinetics of a 1 mg subcutaneous dose of dihydroergotamine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3993" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Similarly, a 1 mg subcutaneous dose of dihydroergotamine did not affect the pharmacokinetics of a 200 mg per day dose of topiramate in the same study.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3994" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Diltiazem Co-administration of diltiazem (240 mg) with topiramate (150 mg per day) resulted in a 10% decrease in Cmax and 25% decrease in diltiazem AUC, 27% decrease in Cmax and 18% decrease in des-acetyl diltiazem AUC, and no effect on N-desmethyl diltiazem.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M267" type="Trigger" span="101 8;148 3" str="decrease | AUC"/>
<Mention id="M270" type="Precipitant" span="0 9" str="diltiazem" code="EE92BBP03H | N0000006682"/>
<Mention id="M269" type="Trigger" span="101 16" str="decrease in Cmax"/>
<Interaction id="I100" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M267" precipitant="M270" effect="C54614"/>
<Interaction id="I101" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M269" precipitant="M270" effect="C54615"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3995" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Co-administration of topiramate with diltiazem resulted in a 16% increase in Cmax and a 19% increase in AUC12 of topiramate.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M271" type="Trigger" span="92 15" str="increase in AUC"/>
<Mention id="M274" type="Precipitant" span="37 9" str="diltiazem" code="EE92BBP03H | N0000006682"/>
<Mention id="M273" type="Trigger" span="65 16" str="increase in Cmax"/>
<Interaction id="I102" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M271" precipitant="M274" effect="C54605"/>
<Interaction id="I103" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M273" precipitant="M274" effect="C54602"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3996" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Venlafaxine Multiple dosing of topiramate (150 mg per day) in healthy volunteers did not affect the pharmacokinetics of venlafaxine or O-desmethyl venlafaxine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3997" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Multiple dosing of venlafaxine (150 mg) did not affect the pharmacokinetics of topiramate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3998" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Other Carbonic Anhydrase Inhibitors Concomitant use of QUDEXY XR, a carbonic anhydrase inhibitor, with any other carbonic anhydrase inhibitor (e.g., zonisamide, acetazolamide, or dichlorphenamide), may increase the severity of metabolic acidosis and may also increase the risk of kidney stone formation.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M293" type="Trigger" span="259 17" str="increase the risk"/>
<Mention id="M279" type="Precipitant" span="161 13" str="acetazolamide" code="O3FX965V0I"/>
<Mention id="M295" type="SpecificInteraction" span="280 22" str="kidney stone formation" code="95570007: Kidney stone (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M296" type="Trigger" span="202 21" str="increase the severity"/>
<Mention id="M298" type="SpecificInteraction" span="227 18" str="metabolic acidosis" code="59455009: Metabolic acidosis (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M285" type="Precipitant" span="6 28" str="carbonic anhydrase inhibitor" code="N0000000235"/>
<Mention id="M291" type="Precipitant" span="179 16" str="dichlorphenamide" code="VVJ6673MHY"/>
<Mention id="M297" type="Precipitant" span="149 10" str="zonisamide" code="459384H98V"/>
<Interaction id="I104" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M293" precipitant="M279" effect="M295" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I105" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M296" precipitant="M279" effect="M298" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I106" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M293" precipitant="M285" effect="M295" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I107" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M296" precipitant="M285" effect="M298" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I108" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M293" precipitant="M291" effect="M295" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I109" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M296" precipitant="M291" effect="M298" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I110" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M293" precipitant="M297" effect="M295" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I111" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M296" precipitant="M297" effect="M298" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3999" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Therefore, if QUDEXY XR is given concomitantly with another carbonic anhydrase inhibitor, the patient should be monitored for the appearance or worsening of metabolic acidosis.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M299" type="Trigger" span="112 9" str="monitored"/>
<Mention id="M300" type="Precipitant" span="60 28" str="carbonic anhydrase inhibitor" code="N0000000235"/>
<Mention id="M301" type="SpecificInteraction" span="157 18" str="metabolic acidosis" code="59455009: Metabolic acidosis (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I112" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M299" precipitant="M300" effect="M301" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4000" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>QUDEXY XR, taken once daily, provides similar steady-state topiramate concentrations to immediate-release topiramate taken every 12 hours, when administered at the same total daily dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4001" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In a healthy volunteer, multiple-dose crossover study, the 90% CI for the ratios of AUC0-24, Cmax and Cmin, as well as partial AUC (the area under the concentration-time curve from time 0 to time p (post dose)) for multiple time points were within the 80 to 125% bioequivalence limits, indicating no clinically significant difference between the two formulations.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4002" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In addition, the 90% CI for the ratios of topiramate plasma concentration at each of multiple time points over 24 hours for the two formulations were within the 80 to 125% bioequivalence limits, except for the initial time points before 3 hours and at 8 hours post-dose, which is not expected to have a significant clinical impact.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4003" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The effects of switching between QUDEXY XR and immediate-release topiramate were also evaluated in the same multiple-dose, crossover, comparative bioavailability study.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4004" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In healthy subjects switched from immediate-release topiramate given every 12 hours to QUDEXY XR given once daily, similar concentrations were maintained immediately after the formulation switch.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4005" LabelDrug="QUDEXY" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>On the first day following the switch, there were no significant differences in AUC0-24, Cmax, and Cmin, as the 90% CI for the ratios were contained within the 80% to 125% equivalence limits.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="metformin" precipitantCode="9100L32L2N" effect="59455009: Metabolic acidosis (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="metformin" precipitantCode="9100L32L2N" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="metformin" precipitantCode="9100L32L2N" effect="C54610"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="metformin" precipitantCode="9100L32L2N" effect="C54613"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="metformin" precipitantCode="9100L32L2N"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="combination oral contraceptive products" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="102955006: Contraception failure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="combination oral contraceptive products" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="56169002: Break-through bleeding (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="lithium" precipitantCode="9FN79X2M3F | N0000147892" effect="442174001: Lithium in blood specimen outside therapeutic range (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="lithium" precipitantCode="9FN79X2M3F | N0000147892" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="lithium" precipitantCode="9FN79X2M3F | N0000147892" effect="C54610"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="lithium" precipitantCode="9FN79X2M3F | N0000147892" effect="C54613"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="oral contraceptives" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="102955006: Contraception failure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="oral contraceptives" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="56169002: Break-through bleeding (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="carbamazepine" precipitantCode="33CM23913M | N0000007470" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="phenytoin" precipitantCode="6158TKW0C5 | N0000006023" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="estrogen-containing contraceptives" precipitantCode="N0000175825" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="contraceptive" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="102955006: Contraception failure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="valproic acid" precipitantCode="614OI1Z5WI" effect="386689009: Hypothermia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="valproic acid" precipitantCode="614OI1Z5WI" effect="9360008: Hyperammonemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="valproic acid" precipitantCode="614OI1Z5WI" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="alcohol" precipitantCode="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M" effect="418072004: Central nervous system depression (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="alcohol" precipitantCode="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cns depressant drugs" precipitantCode="N0000175758" effect="418072004: Central nervous system depression (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="acetazolamide" precipitantCode="O3FX965V0I" effect="59455009: Metabolic acidosis (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="acetazolamide" precipitantCode="O3FX965V0I" effect="95570007: Kidney stone (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="carbonic anhydrase inhibitor" precipitantCode="N0000000235" effect="59455009: Metabolic acidosis (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="carbonic anhydrase inhibitor" precipitantCode="N0000000235" effect="95570007: Kidney stone (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="dichlorphenamide" precipitantCode="VVJ6673MHY" effect="59455009: Metabolic acidosis (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="dichlorphenamide" precipitantCode="VVJ6673MHY" effect="95570007: Kidney stone (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="zonisamide" precipitantCode="459384H98V" effect="59455009: Metabolic acidosis (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="zonisamide" precipitantCode="459384H98V" effect="95570007: Kidney stone (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="carbonic anhydrase inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000000235" effect="111735006: Effects of heat (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="carbonic anhydrase inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000000235" effect="95570007: Kidney stone (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="drugs causing metabolic acidosis" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="95570007: Kidney stone (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ketogenic diet" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="95570007: Kidney stone (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ketogenic diet" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="drugs that predispose patients to heat-related disorders" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="111735006: Effects of heat (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="drugs with anticholinergic activity" precipitantCode="N0000175574" effect="111735006: Effects of heat (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="therapies that predispose patients to acidosis" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="vpa" precipitantCode="614OI1Z5WI" effect="386689009: Hypothermia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="vpa" precipitantCode="614OI1Z5WI" effect="9360008: Hyperammonemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="drug producing metabolic acidosis" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="95570007: Kidney stone (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="valproate" precipitantCode="614OI1Z5WI" effect="161920001: Respiratory symptom (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="valproate" precipitantCode="614OI1Z5WI" effect="214264003: Lethargy (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="valproate" precipitantCode="614OI1Z5WI" effect="267037003: Cardiovascular symptoms (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="valproate" precipitantCode="614OI1Z5WI" effect="371632003: Coma (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="valproate" precipitantCode="614OI1Z5WI" effect="386689009: Hypothermia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="valproate" precipitantCode="614OI1Z5WI" effect="40917007: Clouded consciousness (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="valproate" precipitantCode="614OI1Z5WI"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="cns depressant" precipitantCode="N0000175758"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="high-fat meal" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54604"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sodium valproate" precipitantCode="5VOM6GYJ0D" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="probenecid" precipitantCode="PO572Z7917" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="probenecid" precipitantCode="PO572Z7917" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="enzyme-inducing antiepileptic drugs" precipitantCode="N0000175753" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="hepatic enzyme-inducing antiepileptic drugs" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="combination oral contraceptive" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="102955006: Contraception failure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="combination oral contraceptive" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="56169002: Break-through bleeding (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="digoxin" precipitantCode="73K4184T59 | N0000005903" effect="C54614"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="hctz" precipitantCode="0J48LPH2TH" effect="166690008: Low serum potassium level (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="hctz" precipitantCode="0J48LPH2TH" effect="C54602"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="hctz" precipitantCode="0J48LPH2TH" effect="C54605"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="hctz" precipitantCode="0J48LPH2TH"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="pioglitazone" precipitantCode="X4OV71U42S" effect="73211009: Diabetes mellitus (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="pioglitazone" precipitantCode="X4OV71U42S" effect="C54614"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="active hydroxy-metabolite" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54614"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="active hydroxy-metabolite" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54615"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="active keto-metabolite" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54614"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="active keto-metabolite" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54615"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="glyburide" precipitantCode="N0000006295 | SX6K58TVWC" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="glyburide" precipitantCode="N0000006295 | SX6K58TVWC" effect="C54614"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="glyburide" precipitantCode="N0000006295 | SX6K58TVWC" effect="C54615"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="amitriptyline" precipitantCode="1806D8D52K" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="amitriptyline" precipitantCode="1806D8D52K" effect="C54610"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="amitriptyline" precipitantCode="1806D8D52K" effect="C54613"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="risperidone" precipitantCode="L6UH7ZF8HC" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="risperidone" precipitantCode="L6UH7ZF8HC" effect="C54602"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="risperidone" precipitantCode="L6UH7ZF8HC" effect="C54605"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="risperidone" precipitantCode="L6UH7ZF8HC" effect="C54614"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="diltiazem" precipitantCode="EE92BBP03H | N0000006682" effect="C54602"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="diltiazem" precipitantCode="EE92BBP03H | N0000006682" effect="C54605"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="diltiazem" precipitantCode="EE92BBP03H | N0000006682" effect="C54614"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="diltiazem" precipitantCode="EE92BBP03H | N0000006682" effect="C54615"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>