<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Herceptin" setid="492dbdb2-077e-4064-bff3-372d6af0a7a2">
<Text><Section name="Boxed Warning section" id="34066-1">
Cardiomyopathy Herceptin administration can result in sub-clinical and clinical cardiac failure. The incidence and severity was highest in patients receiving Herceptin with anthracycline-containing chemotherapy regimens. Evaluate left ventricular function in all patients prior to and during treatment with Herceptin. Discontinue Herceptin treatment in patients receiving adjuvant therapy and withhold Herceptin in patients with metastatic disease for clinically significant decrease in left ventricular function [see Dosage and Administration (2.3) and Warnings and Precautions (5.1) ]. Infusion Reactions; Pulmonary Toxicity Herceptin administration can result in serious and fatal infusion reactions and pulmonary toxicity. Symptoms usually occur during or within 24 hours of Herceptin administration. Interrupt Herceptin infusion for dyspnea or clinically significant hypotension. Monitor patients until symptoms completely resolve. Discontinue Herceptin for anaphylaxis, angioedema, interstitial pneumonitis, or acute respiratory distress syndrome [see Warnings and Precautions ( 5.2 , 5.4 )]. Embryo Fetal Toxicity Exposure to Herceptin during pregnancy can result in oligohydramnios and oligohydramnios sequence manifesting as pulmonary hypoplasia, skeletal abnormalities, and neonatal death. Advise patients of these risks and the need for effective contraception [see Warnings and Precautions ( 5.3 ) and Use in Specific Populations ( 8.1 , 8.3 )]. WARNING: CARDIOMYOPATHY, INFUSION REACTIONS, EMBRYO-FETAL TOXICITY, and PULMONARY TOXICITY See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning Cardiomyopathy: Herceptin can result in subclinical and clinical cardiac failure manifesting as CHF, and decreased LVEF, with greatest risk when administered concurrently with anthracyclines. Evaluate cardiac function prior to and during treatment. Discontinue Herceptin for cardiomyopathy. ( 2.3 , 5.1 ) Infusion Reactions, Pulmonary Toxicity: Discontinue Herceptin for anaphylaxis, angioedema, interstitial pneumonitis, or acute respiratory distress syndrome. ( 5.2 , 5.4 ) Embryo-Fetal Toxicity: Exposure to Herceptin during pregnancy can result in oligohydramnios, in some cases complicated by pulmonary hypoplasia and neonatal death. Advise patients of these risks and the need for effective contraception. ( 5.3 , 8.1 , 8.3 )</Section>
<Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
None. None. ( 4 )</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
For intravenous (IV) infusion only. Do not administer as an IV push or bolus. ( 2.2 ) Do not substitute Herceptin (trastuzumab) for or with ado-trastuzumab emtansine. ( 2.2 ) Perform HER2 testing using FDA-approved tests by laboratories with demonstrated proficiency. ( 1 , 2.1 ) Adjuvant Treatment of HER2-Overexpressing Breast Cancer ( 2.2 ) Administer at either: Initial dose of 4 mg/kg over 90 minute IV infusion, then 2 mg/kg over 30 minute IV infusion weekly for 12 weeks (with paclitaxel or docetaxel) or 18 weeks (with docetaxel/carboplatin). One week after the last weekly dose of Herceptin, administer 6 mg/kg as an IV infusion over 30–90 minutes every three weeks to complete a total of 52 weeks of therapy, or Initial dose of 8 mg/kg over 90 minutes IV infusion, then 6 mg/kg over 30–90 minutes IV infusion every three weeks for 52 weeks. Metastatic HER2-Overexpressing Breast Cancer ( 2.2 ) Initial dose of 4 mg/kg as a 90 minute IV infusion followed by subsequent weekly doses of 2 mg/kg as 30 minute IV infusions. Metastatic HER2-Overexpressing Gastric Cancer ( 2.2 ) Initial dose of 8 mg/kg over 90 minutes IV infusion, followed by 6 mg/kg over 30 to 90 minutes IV infusion every 3 weeks. Select patients based on HER2 protein overexpression or HER2 gene amplification in tumor specimens [see Indications and Usage (1) and Clinical Studies (14) ] . Assessment of HER2 protein overexpression and HER2 gene amplification should be performed using FDA-approved tests specific for breast or gastric cancers by laboratories with demonstrated proficiency. Information on the FDA-approved tests for the detection of HER2 protein overexpression and HER2 gene amplification is available at: http://www.fda.gov/CompanionDiagnostics. Assessment of HER2 protein overexpression and HER2 gene amplification in metastatic gastric cancer should be performed using FDA-approved tests specifically for gastric cancers due to differences in gastric vs. breast histopathology, including incomplete membrane staining and more frequent heterogeneous expression of HER2 seen in gastric cancers. Improper assay performance, including use of suboptimally fixed tissue, failure to utilize specified reagents, deviation from specific assay instructions, and failure to include appropriate controls for assay validation, can lead to unreliable results. Do not administer as an intravenous push or bolus. Do not mix Herceptin with other drugs. Do not substitute Herceptin (trastuzumab) for or with ado-trastuzumab emtansine. Adjuvant Treatment, Breast Cancer Administer according to one of the following doses and schedules for a total of 52 weeks of Herceptin therapy: During and following paclitaxel, docetaxel, or docetaxel/carboplatin: Initial dose of 4 mg/kg as an intravenous infusion over 90 minutes then at 2 mg/kg as an intravenous infusion over 30 minutes weekly during chemotherapy for the first 12 weeks (paclitaxel or docetaxel) or 18 weeks (docetaxel/carboplatin). One week following the last weekly dose of Herceptin, administer Herceptin at 6 mg/kg as an intravenous infusion over 30–90 minutes every three weeks. As a single agent within three weeks following completion of multi-modality, anthracycline-based chemotherapy regimens: Initial dose at 8 mg/kg as an intravenous infusion over 90 minutes Subsequent doses at 6 mg/kg as an intravenous infusion over 30–90 minutes every three weeks [see Dosage and Administration (2.3) ]. Extending adjuvant treatment beyond one year is not recommended [see Adverse Reactions ( 6.1 )] . Metastatic Treatment, Breast Cancer Administer Herceptin, alone or in combination with paclitaxel, at an initial dose of 4 mg/kg as a 90-minute intravenous infusion followed by subsequent once weekly doses of 2 mg/kg as 30-minute intravenous infusions until disease progression. Metastatic Gastric Cancer Administer Herceptin at an initial dose of 8 mg/kg as a 90-minute intravenous infusion followed by subsequent doses of 6 mg/kg as an intravenous infusion over 30–90 minutes every three weeks until disease progression [see Dosage and Administration ( 2.3 )]. If the patient has missed a dose of Herceptin by one week or less, then the usual maintenance dose (weekly schedule: 2 mg/kg; three-weekly schedule: 6 mg/kg) should be administered as soon as possible. Do not wait until the next planned cycle. Subsequent Herceptin maintenance doses should be administered 7 days or 21 days later according to the weekly or three-weekly schedules, respectively. If the patient has missed a dose of Herceptin by more than one week, a re-loading dose of Herceptin should be administered over approximately 90 minutes (weekly schedule: 4 mg/kg; three-weekly schedule: 8 mg/kg) as soon as possible. Subsequent Herceptin maintenance doses (weekly schedule: 2 mg/kg; three-weekly schedule 6 mg/kg) should be administered 7 days or 21 days later according to the weekly or three-weekly schedules, respectively. Infusion Reactions [See Boxed Warning , Warnings and Precautions ( 5.2 )] Decrease the rate of infusion for mild or moderate infusion reactions Interrupt the infusion in patients with dyspnea or clinically significant hypotension Discontinue Herceptin for severe or life-threatening infusion reactions. Cardiomyopathy [See Boxed Warning , Warnings and Precautions ( 5.1 )] Assess left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) prior to initiation of Herceptin and at regular intervals during treatment. Withhold Herceptin dosing for at least 4 weeks for either of the following: ≥ 16% absolute decrease in LVEF from pre-treatment values LVEF below institutional limits of normal and ≥ 10% absolute decrease in LVEF from pretreatment values. Herceptin may be resumed if, within 4–8 weeks, the LVEF returns to normal limits and the absolute decrease from baseline is ≤ 15%. Permanently discontinue Herceptin for a persistent (&amp;gt; 8 weeks) LVEF decline or for suspension of Herceptin dosing on more than 3 occasions for cardiomyopathy. To prevent medication errors, it is important to check the vial labels to ensure that the drug being prepared and administered is Herceptin (trastuzumab) and not ado-trastuzumab emtansine. 420 mg Multiple-dose vial Reconstitution Reconstitute each 420 mg vial of Herceptin with 20 mL of Bacteriostatic Water for Injection (BWFI), USP, containing 1.1% benzyl alcohol as a preservative to yield a multiple-dose solution containing 21 mg/mL trastuzumab that delivers 20 mL (420 mg trastuzumab). In patients with known hypersensitivity to benzyl alcohol, reconstitute with 20 mL of Sterile Water for Injection (SWFI) without preservative to yield a single use solution. Use appropriate aseptic technique when performing the following reconstitution steps: Using a sterile syringe, slowly inject the 20 mL of diluent into the vial containing the lyophilized powder of Herceptin, which has a cake-like appearance. The stream of diluent should be directed into the cake. The reconstituted vial yields a solution for multiple-dose use, containing 21 mg/mL trastuzumab. Swirl the vial gently to aid reconstitution. DO NOT SHAKE. Slight foaming of the product may be present upon reconstitution. Allow the vial to stand undisturbed for approximately 5 minutes. Parenteral drug products should be inspected visually for particulate matter and discoloration prior to administration, whenever solution and container permit. Inspect visually for particulates and discoloration. The solution should be free of visible particulates, clear to slightly opalescent and colorless to pale yellow. Store reconstituted Herceptin in the refrigerator at 2°C to 8° C (36°F to 46°F) ; discard unused Herceptin after 28 days. If Herceptin is reconstituted with SWFI without preservative, use immediately and discard any unused portion. Do not freeze. Dilution Determine the dose (mg) of Herceptin [see Dosage and Administration ( 2.2 )] . Calculate the volume of the 21 mg/mL reconstituted Herceptin solution needed, withdraw this amount from the vial and add it to an infusion bag containing 250 mL of 0.9% Sodium Chloride Injection, USP. DO NOT USE DEXTROSE (5%) SOLUTION. Gently invert the bag to mix the solution. The solution of Herceptin for infusion diluted in polyvinylchloride or polyethylene bags containing 0.9% Sodium Chloride Injection, USP, should be stored at 2°C to 8°C (36°F to 46°F) for no more than 24 hours prior to use. Do not freeze. 150 mg Single-dose vial Reconstitution Reconstitute each 150 mg vial of Herceptin with 7.4 mL of Sterile Water for Injection (SWFI) (not supplied) to yield a single-dose solution containing 21 mg/mL trastuzumab that delivers 7.15 mL (150 mg trastuzumab). Use appropriate aseptic technique when performing the following reconstitution steps: Using a sterile syringe, slowly inject 7.4 mL of SWFI (not supplied) into the vial containing the lyophilized powder of Herceptin, which has a cake-like appearance. The stream of diluent should be directed into the cake. The reconstituted vial yields a solution for single-dose use, containing 21 mg/mL trastuzumab. Swirl the vial gently to aid reconstitution. DO NOT SHAKE. Slight foaming of the product may be present upon reconstitution. Allow the vial to stand undisturbed for approximately 5 minutes. Parenteral drug products should be inspected visually for particulate matter and discoloration prior to administration, whenever solution and container permit. Inspect visually for particulates and discoloration. The solution should be free of visible particulates, clear to slightly opalescent and colorless to pale yellow. Use the Herceptin solution immediately following reconstitution with SWFI, as it contains no preservative and is intended for single-dose only. If not used immediately, store the reconstituted Herceptin solution for up to 24 hours at 2°C to 8°C (36°F to 46°F) ; discard any unused Herceptin after 24 hours. Do not freeze . Dilution Determine the dose (mg) of Herceptin [see Dosage and Administration (2.1) ] . Calculate the volume of the 21 mg/mL reconstituted Herceptin solution needed. Withdraw this amount from the vial and add it to an infusion bag containing 250 mL of 0.9% Sodium Chloride Injection, USP. DO NOT USE DEXTROSE (5%) SOLUTION. Gently invert the bag to mix the solution. The solution of Herceptin for infusion diluted in polyvinylchloride or polyethylene bags containing 0.9% Sodium Chloride Injection, USP, should be stored at 2°C to 8°C (36°F to 46°F) for no more than 24 hours prior to use. Discard after 24 hours. This storage time is additional to the time allowed for the reconstituted vials. Do not freeze .</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
Patients who receive anthracycline after stopping Herceptin may be at increased risk of cardiac dysfunction because of trastuzumab's long washout period based on population PK analysis [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3) ] . If possible, physicians should avoid anthracycline-based therapy for up to 7 months after stopping Herceptin. If anthracyclines are used, the patient's cardiac function should be monitored carefully.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
Exacerbation of Chemotherapy-Induced Neutropenia. ( 5.5 , 6.1 ) Herceptin can cause left ventricular cardiac dysfunction, arrhythmias, hypertension, disabling cardiac failure, cardiomyopathy, and cardiac death [see Boxed Warning: Cardiomyopathy ] . Herceptin can also cause asymptomatic decline in left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF). There is a 4–6 fold increase in the incidence of symptomatic myocardial dysfunction among patients receiving Herceptin as a single agent or in combination therapy compared with those not receiving Herceptin. The highest absolute incidence occurs when Herceptin is administered with an anthracycline. Withhold Herceptin for ≥ 16% absolute decrease in LVEF from pre-treatment values or an LVEF value below institutional limits of normal and ≥ 10% absolute decrease in LVEF from pretreatment values [see Dosage and Administration ( 2.3 )] . The safety of continuation or resumption of Herceptin in patients with Herceptin-induced left ventricular cardiac dysfunction has not been studied. Patients who receive anthracycline after stopping Herceptin may also be at increased risk of cardiac dysfunction [see Drug Interactions (7) and Clinical Pharmacology (12.3) ] . Cardiac Monitoring Conduct thorough cardiac assessment, including history, physical examination, and determination of LVEF by echocardiogram or MUGA scan. The following schedule is recommended: Baseline LVEF measurement immediately prior to initiation of Herceptin LVEF measurements every 3 months during and upon completion of Herceptin Repeat LVEF measurement at 4 week intervals if Herceptin is withheld for significant left ventricular cardiac dysfunction [see Dosage and Administration ( 2.3 )] LVEF measurements every 6 months for at least 2 years following completion of Herceptin as a component of adjuvant therapy. In Study 1, 15% (158/1031) of patients discontinued Herceptin due to clinical evidence of myocardial dysfunction or significant decline in LVEF after a median follow-up duration of 8.7 years in the AC-TH arm. In Study 3 (one-year Herceptin treatment), the number of patients who discontinued Herceptin due to cardiac toxicity at 12.6 months median duration of follow-up was 2.6% (44/1678). In Study 4, a total of 2.9% (31/1056) of patients in the TCH arm (1.5% during the chemotherapy phase and 1.4% during the monotherapy phase) and 5.7% (61/1068) of patients in the AC-TH arm (1.5% during the chemotherapy phase and 4.2% during the monotherapy phase) discontinued Herceptin due to cardiac toxicity. Among 64 patients receiving adjuvant chemotherapy (Studies 1 and 2) who developed congestive heart failure, one patient died of cardiomyopathy, one patient died suddenly without documented etiology, and 33 patients were receiving cardiac medication at last follow-up. Approximately 24% of the surviving patients had recovery to a normal LVEF (defined as ≥50%) and no symptoms on continuing medical management at the time of last follow-up. Incidence of congestive heart failure (CHF) is presented in Table 1 . The safety of continuation or resumption of Herceptin in patients with Herceptin-induced left ventricular cardiac dysfunction has not been studied. Table 1: Incidence of Congestive Heart Failure in Adjuvant Breast Cancer Studies Incidence of CHF Study Regimen Herceptin Control 1 &amp;amp; 2 Median follow-up duration for studies 1 and 2 combined was 8.3 years in the AC→TH arm. AC Anthracycline (doxorubicin) and cyclophosphamide. → Paclitaxel+Herceptin 3.2% (64/2000) Includes 1 patient with fatal cardiomyopathy and 1 patient with sudden death without documented etiology. 1.3% (21/1655) 3 Includes NYHA II-IV and cardiac death at 12.6 months median duration of follow-up in the one-year Herceptin arm. Chemo → Herceptin 2% (30/1678) 0.3% (5/1708) 4 AC → Docetaxel+Herceptin 2% (20/1068) 0.3% (3/1050) 4 Docetaxel+Carbo+Herceptin 0.4% (4/1056) 0.3% (3/1050) In Study 3 (one-year Herceptin treatment), at a median follow-up duration of 8 years, the incidence of severe CHF (NYHA III &amp;amp; IV) was 0.8%, and the rate of mild symptomatic and asymptomatic left ventricular dysfunction was 4.6%. Table 2: Incidence of Cardiac Dysfunction Congestive heart failure or significant asymptomatic decrease in LVEF. in Metastatic Breast Cancer Studies Incidence NYHA I-IV NYHA III-IV Study Event Herceptin Control Herceptin Control 5 (AC) Anthracycline (doxorubicin or epirubicin) and cyclophosphamide. Cardiac Dysfunction 28% 7% 19% 3% 5 (paclitaxel) Cardiac Dysfunction 11% 1% 4% 1% 6 Cardiac Dysfunction Includes 1 patient with fatal cardiomyopathy. 7% N/A 5% N/A In Study 4, the incidence of NCI-CTC Grade 3/4 cardiac ischemia/infarction was higher in the Herceptin containing regimens (AC-TH: 0.3% (3/1068) and TCH: 0.2% (2/1056)) as compared to none in AC-T. Infusion reactions consist of a symptom complex characterized by fever and chills, and on occasion included nausea, vomiting, pain (in some cases at tumor sites), headache, dizziness, dyspnea, hypotension, rash, and asthenia [see Adverse Reactions ( 6.1 )]. In post-marketing reports, serious and fatal infusion reactions have been reported. Severe reactions, which include bronchospasm, anaphylaxis, angioedema, hypoxia, and severe hypotension, were usually reported during or immediately following the initial infusion. However, the onset and clinical course were variable, including progressive worsening, initial improvement followed by clinical deterioration, or delayed post-infusion events with rapid clinical deterioration. For fatal events, death occurred within hours to days following a serious infusion reaction. Interrupt Herceptin infusion in all patients experiencing dyspnea, clinically significant hypotension, and intervention of medical therapy administered (which may include epinephrine, corticosteroids, diphenhydramine, bronchodilators, and oxygen). Patients should be evaluated and carefully monitored until complete resolution of signs and symptoms. Permanent discontinuation should be strongly considered in all patients with severe infusion reactions. There are no data regarding the most appropriate method of identification of patients who may safely be retreated with Herceptin after experiencing a severe infusion reaction. Prior to resumption of Herceptin infusion, the majority of patients who experienced a severe infusion reaction were pre-medicated with antihistamines and/or corticosteroids. While some patients tolerated Herceptin infusions, others had recurrent severe infusion reactions despite pre-medications. Herceptin can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. In post marketing reports, use of Herceptin during pregnancy resulted in cases of oligohydramnios and oligohydramnios sequence manifesting as pulmonary hypoplasia, skeletal abnormalities, and neonatal death. Verify the pregnancy status of females of reproductive potential prior to the initiation of Herceptin. Advise pregnant women and females of reproductive potential that exposure to Herceptin during pregnancy or within 7 months prior to conception can result in fetal harm. Advise females of reproductive potential to use effective contraception during treatment and for 7 months following the last dose of Herceptin [see Use in Specific Populations (8.1 , 8.3) and Clinical Pharmacology (12.3) ]. Herceptin use can result in serious and fatal pulmonary toxicity. Pulmonary toxicity includes dyspnea, interstitial pneumonitis, pulmonary infiltrates, pleural effusions, non-cardiogenic pulmonary edema, pulmonary insufficiency and hypoxia, acute respiratory distress syndrome, and pulmonary fibrosis. Such events can occur as sequelae of infusion reactions [see Warnings and Precautions ( 5.2 )] . Patients with symptomatic intrinsic lung disease or with extensive tumor involvement of the lungs, resulting in dyspnea at rest, appear to have more severe toxicity. In randomized, controlled clinical trials, the per-patient incidences of NCI-CTC Grade 3–4 neutropenia and of febrile neutropenia were higher in patients receiving Herceptin in combination with myelosuppressive chemotherapy as compared to those who received chemotherapy alone. The incidence of septic death was similar among patients who received Herceptin and those who did not [see Adverse Reactions ( 6.1 )].</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
The HER2 (or c-erbB2) proto-oncogene encodes a transmembrane receptor protein of 185 kDa, which is structurally related to the epidermal growth factor receptor. Herceptin has been shown, in both in vitro assays and in animals, to inhibit the proliferation of human tumor cells that overexpress HER2. Herceptin is a mediator of antibody-dependent cellular cytotoxicity (ADCC). In vitro , Herceptin-mediated ADCC has been shown to be preferentially exerted on HER2 overexpressing cancer cells compared with cancer cells that do not overexpress HER2. Cardiac Electrophysiology The effects of trastuzumab on electrocardiographic (ECG) endpoints, including QTc interval duration, were evaluated in patients with HER2 positive solid tumors. Trastuzumab had no clinically relevant effect on the QTc interval duration and there was no apparent relationship between serum trastuzumab concentrations and change in QTcF interval duration in patients with HER2 positive solid tumors. The pharmacokinetics of trastuzumab was evaluated in a pooled population pharmacokinetic (PK) model analysis of 1,582 subjects with primarily breast cancer and metastatic gastric cancer (MGC) receiving intravenous Herceptin. Total trastuzumab clearance increases with decreasing concentrations due to parallel linear and non-linear elimination pathways. Although the average trastuzumab exposure was higher following the first cycle in breast cancer patients receiving the three-weekly schedule compared to the weekly schedule of Herceptin, the average steady-state exposure was essentially the same at both dosages. The average trastuzumab exposure following the first cycle and at steady state as well as the time to steady state was higher in breast cancer patients compared to MGC patients at the same dosage; however, the reason for this exposure difference is unknown. Additional predicted trastuzumab exposure and PK parameters following the first Herceptin cycle and at steady state exposure are described in Tables 7 and 8 , respectively. Population PK based simulations indicate that following discontinuation of Herceptin, concentrations in at least 95% of breast cancer and MGC patients will decrease to approximately 3% of the population predicted steady-state trough serum concentration (approximately 97% washout) by 7 months [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1) and Use in Specific Populations (8.1 , 8.3) ] . Table 7: Population Predicted Cycle 1 PK Exposures (Median with 5 th – 95 th Percentiles) in Breast Cancer and MGC Patients Schedule Primary tumor type N C min (µg/mL) C max (µg/mL) AUC 0-21days (µg.day/mL) 8 mg/kg + 6 mg/kg q3w Breast cancer 1195 29.4 (5.8 - 59.5) 178 (117 - 291) 1373 (736 - 2245) MGC 274 23.1 (6.1 - 50.3) 132 (84.2 - 225) 1109 (588 - 1938) 4 mg/kg + 2 mg/kg qw Breast cancer 1195 37.7 (12.3 - 70.9) 88.3 (58 - 144) 1066 (586 - 1754) Table 8: Population Predicted Steady State PK Exposures (Median with 5 th - 95 th Percentiles) in Breast Cancer and MGC Patients Schedule Primary tumor type N C min,ss Steady-state trough serum concentration of trastuzumab (µg/mL) C max,ss Maximum steady-state serum concentration of trastuzumab (µg/mL) AUC ss, 0-21 days (µg.day/mL) Time to steady-state (week) Total CL range at steady-state (L/day) 8 mg/kg + 6 mg/kg q3w Breast cancer 1195 47.4 (5 - 115) 179 (107 - 309) 1794 (673 - 3618) 12 0.173 - 0.283 MGC 274 32.9 (6.1 - 88.9) 131 (72.5 - 251) 1338 (557 - 2875) 9 0.189 - 0.337 4 mg/kg + 2 mg/kg qw Breast cancer 1195 66.1 (14.9 - 142) 109 (51.0 - 209) 1765 (647 - 3578) 12 0.201 - 0.244 Specific Populations Based on a population pharmacokinetic analysis, no clinically significant differences were observed in the pharmacokinetics of trastuzumab based on age (&amp;lt; 65 (n = 1294); ≥ 65 (n = 288)), race (Asian (n = 264); non-Asian (n = 1324)) and renal impairment (mild (creatinine clearance [CLcr] 60 to 90 mL/min) (n = 636) or moderate (CLcr 30 to 60 mL/min) (n = 133)). The pharmacokinetics of trastuzumab in patients with severe renal impairment, end-stage renal disease with or without hemodialysis, or hepatic impairment is unknown. Drug Interaction Studies There have been no formal drug interaction studies performed with Herceptin in humans. Clinically significant interactions between Herceptin and concomitant medications used in clinical trials have not been observed. Paclitaxel and doxorubicin : Concentrations of paclitaxel and doxorubicin and their major metabolites (i.e., 6-α hydroxyl-paclitaxel [POH], and doxorubicinol [DOL], respectively) were not altered in the presence of trastuzumab when used as combination therapy in clinical trials. Trastuzumab concentrations were not altered as part of this combination therapy. Docetaxel and carboplatin: When Herceptin was administered in combination with docetaxel or carboplatin, neither the plasma concentrations of docetaxel or carboplatin nor the plasma concentrations of trastuzumab were altered. Cisplatin and capecitabine : In a drug interaction substudy conducted in patients in Study 7, the pharmacokinetics of cisplatin, capecitabine and their metabolites were not altered when administered in combination with Herceptin.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="7563" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Cardiomyopathy Herceptin administration can result in sub-clinical and clinical cardiac failure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7564" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>The incidence and severity was highest in patients receiving Herceptin with anthracycline-containing chemotherapy regimens.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M4" type="Trigger" span="4 9;31 7" str="incidence | highest "/>
<Mention id="M5" type="Trigger" span="18 20" str=" severity was highest"/>
<Mention id="M3" type="Precipitant" span="76 13" str="anthracycline" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M6" type="Precipitant" span="76 46" str="anthracycline-containing chemotherapy regimens" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M4;M5" precipitant="M3"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M4;M5" precipitant="M6"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7565" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Evaluate left ventricular function in all patients prior to and during treatment with Herceptin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7566" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Discontinue Herceptin treatment in patients receiving adjuvant therapy and withhold Herceptin in patients with metastatic disease for clinically significant decrease in left ventricular function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7567" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Infusion Reactions; Pulmonary Toxicity Herceptin administration can result in serious and fatal infusion reactions and pulmonary toxicity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7568" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Symptoms usually occur during or within 24 hours of Herceptin administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7569" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Interrupt Herceptin infusion for dyspnea or clinically significant hypotension.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7570" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Monitor patients until symptoms completely resolve.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7571" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Discontinue Herceptin for anaphylaxis, angioedema, interstitial pneumonitis, or acute respiratory distress syndrome.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7572" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Embryo Fetal Toxicity Exposure to Herceptin during pregnancy can result in oligohydramnios and oligohydramnios sequence manifesting as pulmonary hypoplasia, skeletal abnormalities, and neonatal death.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7573" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Advise patients of these risks and the need for effective contraception.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7574" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>WARNING: CARDIOMYOPATHY, INFUSION REACTIONS, EMBRYO-FETAL TOXICITY, and PULMONARY TOXICITY See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning Cardiomyopathy: Herceptin can result in subclinical and clinical cardiac failure manifesting as CHF, and decreased LVEF, with greatest risk when administered concurrently with anthracyclines.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M25" type="Trigger" span="277 13" str="greatest risk"/>
<Mention id="M26" type="Precipitant" span="327 14" str="anthracyclines" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M9" type="SpecificInteraction" span="216 15" str="cardiac failure" code="84114007: Heart failure (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M12" type="SpecificInteraction" span="9 14" str="CARDIOMYOPATHY" code="85898001: Cardiomyopathy (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M15" type="SpecificInteraction" span="247 3" str="CHF" code="42343007: Congestive heart failure (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M18" type="SpecificInteraction" span="256 14" str="decreased LVEF" code="275514001: Impaired left ventricular function (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M21" type="SpecificInteraction" span="45 21" str="EMBRYO-FETAL TOXICITY" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M24" type="SpecificInteraction" span="25 18" str="INFUSION REACTIONS" code="441940003: Adverse reaction caused by drug or medicament administered by infusion (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M27" type="SpecificInteraction" span="72 18" str="PULMONARY TOXICITY" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M25" precipitant="M26" effect="M9" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M25" precipitant="M26" effect="M12" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M25" precipitant="M26" effect="M15" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M25" precipitant="M26" effect="M18" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M25" precipitant="M26" effect="M21" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M25" precipitant="M26" effect="M24" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M25" precipitant="M26" effect="M27" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7575" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Evaluate cardiac function prior to and during treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7576" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Discontinue Herceptin for cardiomyopathy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7577" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Infusion Reactions, Pulmonary Toxicity: Discontinue Herceptin for anaphylaxis, angioedema, interstitial pneumonitis, or acute respiratory distress syndrome.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7578" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Embryo-Fetal Toxicity: Exposure to Herceptin during pregnancy can result in oligohydramnios, in some cases complicated by pulmonary hypoplasia and neonatal death.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7579" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not administer as an IV push or bolus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7580" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not substitute Herceptin (trastuzumab) for or with ado-trastuzumab emtansine.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M28" type="Trigger" span="0 17" str="Do not substitute"/>
<Mention id="M29" type="Precipitant" span="54 25" str="ado-trastuzumab emtansine" code="SE2KH7T06F"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M28" precipitant="M29"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7581" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Perform HER2 testing using FDA-approved tests by laboratories with demonstrated proficiency.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7582" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Adjuvant Treatment of HER2-Overexpressing Breast Cancer (2.2) Administer at either: Initial dose of 4 mg/kg over 90 minute IV infusion, then 2 mg/kg over 30 minute IV infusion weekly for 12 weeks (with paclitaxel or docetaxel) or 18 weeks (with docetaxel/carboplatin).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7583" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>One week after the last weekly dose of Herceptin, administer 6 mg/kg as an IV infusion over 30–90 minutes every three weeks to complete a total of 52 weeks of therapy, or Initial dose of 8 mg/kg over 90 minutes IV infusion, then 6 mg/kg over 30–90 minutes IV infusion every three weeks for 52 weeks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7584" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Metastatic HER2-Overexpressing Breast Cancer (2.2) Initial dose of 4 mg/kg as a 90 minute IV infusion followed by subsequent weekly doses of 2 mg/kg as 30 minute IV infusions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7585" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Metastatic HER2-Overexpressing Gastric Cancer ( 2.2 ) Initial dose of 8 mg/kg over 90 minutes IV infusion, followed by 6 mg/kg over 30 to 90 minutes IV infusion every 3 weeks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7586" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Select patients based on HER2 protein overexpression or HER2 gene amplification in tumor specimens.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7587" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Assessment of HER2 protein overexpression and HER2 gene amplification should be performed using FDA-approved tests specific for breast or gastric cancers by laboratories with demonstrated proficiency.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7588" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Information on the FDA-approved tests for the detection of HER2 protein overexpression and HER2 gene amplification is available at: http://www.fda.gov/CompanionDiagnostics.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7589" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Assessment of HER2 protein overexpression and HER2 gene amplification in metastatic gastric cancer should be performed using FDA-approved tests specifically for gastric cancers due to differences in gastric vs. breast histopathology, including incomplete membrane staining and more frequent heterogeneous expression of HER2 seen in gastric cancers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7590" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Improper assay performance, including use of suboptimally fixed tissue, failure to utilize specified reagents, deviation from specific assay instructions, and failure to include appropriate controls for assay validation, can lead to unreliable results.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7591" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not administer as an intravenous push or bolus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7592" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Adjuvant Treatment, Breast Cancer Administer according to one of the following doses and schedules for a total of 52 weeks of Herceptin therapy: During and following paclitaxel, docetaxel, or docetaxel/carboplatin: Initial dose of 4 mg/kg as an intravenous infusion over 90 minutes then at 2 mg/kg as an intravenous infusion over 30 minutes weekly during chemotherapy for the first 12 weeks (paclitaxel or docetaxel) or 18 weeks (docetaxel/carboplatin).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7593" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>One week following the last weekly dose of Herceptin, administer Herceptin at 6 mg/kg as an intravenous infusion over 30–90 minutes every three weeks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7594" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>As a single agent within three weeks following completion of multi-modality, anthracycline-based chemotherapy regimens: Initial dose at 8 mg/kg as an intravenous infusion over 90 minutes Subsequent doses at 6 mg/kg as an intravenous infusion over 30–90 minutes every three weeks.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M32" type="Trigger" span="37 23" str="following completion of"/>
<Mention id="M31" type="Precipitant" span="77 13" str="anthracycline" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M33" type="Precipitant" span="77 41" str="anthracycline-based chemotherapy regimens" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M32" precipitant="M31"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M32" precipitant="M33"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7595" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Extending adjuvant treatment beyond one year is not recommended.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7596" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Metastatic Treatment, Breast Cancer Administer Herceptin, alone or in combination with paclitaxel, at an initial dose of 4 mg/kg as a 90-minute intravenous infusion followed by subsequent once weekly doses of 2 mg/kg as 30-minute intravenous infusions until disease progression.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7597" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Metastatic Gastric Cancer Administer Herceptin at an initial dose of 8 mg/kg as a 90-minute intravenous infusion followed by subsequent doses of 6 mg/kg as an intravenous infusion over 30–90 minutes every three weeks until disease progression.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7598" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If the patient has missed a dose of Herceptin by one week or less, then the usual maintenance dose (weekly schedule: 2 mg/kg; three-weekly schedule: 6 mg/kg) should be administered as soon as possible.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7599" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not wait until the next planned cycle.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7600" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Subsequent Herceptin maintenance doses should be administered 7 days or 21 days later according to the weekly or three-weekly schedules, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7601" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If the patient has missed a dose of Herceptin by more than one week, a re-loading dose of Herceptin should be administered over approximately 90 minutes (weekly schedule: 4 mg/kg; three-weekly schedule: 8 mg/kg) as soon as possible.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7602" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Subsequent Herceptin maintenance doses (weekly schedule: 2 mg/kg; three-weekly schedule 6 mg/kg) should be administered 7 days or 21 days later according to the weekly or three-weekly schedules, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7603" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Infusion Reactions Decrease the rate of infusion for mild or moderate infusion reactions Interrupt the infusion in patients with dyspnea or clinically significant hypotension Discontinue Herceptin for severe or life-threatening infusion reactions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7604" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Cardiomyopathy Assess left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) prior to initiation of Herceptin and at regular intervals during treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7605" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Withhold Herceptin dosing for at least 4 weeks for either of the following: ≥ 16% absolute decrease in LVEF from pre-treatment values LVEF below institutional limits of normal and ≥ 10% absolute decrease in LVEF from pretreatment values.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7606" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Herceptin may be resumed if, within 4–8 weeks, the LVEF returns to normal limits and the absolute decrease from baseline is ≤ 15%.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7607" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Permanently discontinue Herceptin for a persistent (&gt; 8 weeks) LVEF decline or for suspension of Herceptin dosing on more than 3 occasions for cardiomyopathy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7608" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>To prevent medication errors, it is important to check the vial labels to ensure that the drug being prepared and administered is Herceptin (trastuzumab) and not ado-trastuzumab emtansine.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M34" type="Trigger" span="11 17" str="medication errors"/>
<Mention id="M35" type="Precipitant" span="162 25" str="ado-trastuzumab emtansine" code="SE2KH7T06F"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M34" precipitant="M35"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7609" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>420 mg Multiple-dose vial Reconstitution Reconstitute each 420 mg vial of Herceptin with 20 mL of Bacteriostatic Water for Injection (BWFI), USP, containing 1.1% benzyl alcohol as a preservative to yield a multiple-dose solution containing 21 mg/mL trastuzumab that delivers 20 mL (420 mg trastuzumab).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7610" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In patients with known hypersensitivity to benzyl alcohol, reconstitute with 20 mL of Sterile Water for Injection (SWFI) without preservative to yield a single use solution.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7611" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Use appropriate aseptic technique when performing the following reconstitution steps: Using a sterile syringe, slowly inject the 20 mL of diluent into the vial containing the lyophilized powder of Herceptin, which has a cake-like appearance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7612" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The stream of diluent should be directed into the cake.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7613" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The reconstituted vial yields a solution for multiple-dose use, containing 21 mg/mL trastuzumab.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7614" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Swirl the vial gently to aid reconstitution.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7615" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Slight foaming of the product may be present upon reconstitution.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7616" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Allow the vial to stand undisturbed for approximately 5 minutes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7617" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Parenteral drug products should be inspected visually for particulate matter and discoloration prior to administration, whenever solution and container permit.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7618" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Inspect visually for particulates and discoloration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7619" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The solution should be free of visible particulates, clear to slightly opalescent and colorless to pale yellow.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7620" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Store reconstituted Herceptin in the refrigerator at 2°C to 8° C (36°F to 46°F); discard unused Herceptin after 28 days.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7621" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If Herceptin is reconstituted with SWFI without preservative, use immediately and discard any unused portion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7622" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dilution Determine the dose (mg) of Herceptin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7623" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Calculate the volume of the 21 mg/mL reconstituted Herceptin solution needed, withdraw this amount from the vial and add it to an infusion bag containing 250 mL of 0.9% Sodium Chloride Injection, USP.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7624" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Gently invert the bag to mix the solution.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7625" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The solution of Herceptin for infusion diluted in polyvinylchloride or polyethylene bags containing 0.9% Sodium Chloride Injection, USP, should be stored at 2°C to 8°C (36°F to 46°F) for no more than 24 hours prior to use.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7626" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>150 mg Single-dose vial Reconstitution Reconstitute each 150 mg vial of Herceptin with 7.4 mL of Sterile Water for Injection (SWFI) (not supplied) to yield a single-dose solution containing 21 mg/mL trastuzumab that delivers 7.15 mL (150 mg trastuzumab).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7627" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Use appropriate aseptic technique when performing the following reconstitution steps: Using a sterile syringe, slowly inject 7.4 mL of SWFI (not supplied) into the vial containing the lyophilized powder of Herceptin, which has a cake-like appearance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7628" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The reconstituted vial yields a solution for single-dose use, containing 21 mg/mL trastuzumab.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7629" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Use the Herceptin solution immediately following reconstitution with SWFI, as it contains no preservative and is intended for single-dose only.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7630" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If not used immediately, store the reconstituted Herceptin solution for up to 24 hours at 2°C to 8°C (36°F to 46°F); discard any unused Herceptin after 24 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7631" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Calculate the volume of the 21 mg/mL reconstituted Herceptin solution needed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7632" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Withdraw this amount from the vial and add it to an infusion bag containing 250 mL of 0.9% Sodium Chloride Injection, USP.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7633" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>This storage time is additional to the time allowed for the reconstituted vials.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7634" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Patients who receive anthracycline after stopping Herceptin may be at increased risk of cardiac dysfunction because of trastuzumab's long washout period based on population PK analysis.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M36" type="Trigger" span="70 14" str="increased risk"/>
<Mention id="M37" type="Precipitant" span="21 13" str="anthracycline" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M38" type="SpecificInteraction" span="88 19" str="cardiac dysfunction" code="105981003: Disorder of cardiac function (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M36" precipitant="M37" effect="M38" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7635" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>If possible, physicians should avoid anthracycline-based therapy for up to 7 months after stopping Herceptin.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M39" type="Trigger" span="31 5" str="avoid"/>
<Mention id="M40" type="Precipitant" span="37 13" str="anthracycline" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M39" precipitant="M40"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7636" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>If anthracyclines are used, the patient's cardiac function should be monitored carefully.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M41" type="Trigger" span="59 19" str="should be monitored"/>
<Mention id="M42" type="Precipitant" span="3 14" str="anthracyclines" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M43" type="SpecificInteraction" span="42 16" str="cardiac function" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M41" precipitant="M42" effect="M43" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7637" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Exacerbation of Chemotherapy-Induced Neutropenia.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M44" type="Trigger" span="0 12" str="Exacerbation"/>
<Mention id="M45" type="Precipitant" span="16 12" str="Chemotherapy" code="N0000178307"/>
<Mention id="M46" type="SpecificInteraction" span="16 32" str="Chemotherapy-Induced Neutropenia" code="767658000: Neutropenia due to and following chemotherapy (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M44" precipitant="M45" effect="M46" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7638" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Herceptin can cause left ventricular cardiac dysfunction, arrhythmias, hypertension, disabling cardiac failure, cardiomyopathy, and cardiac death.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7639" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Herceptin can also cause asymptomatic decline in left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7640" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There is a 4–6 fold increase in the incidence of symptomatic myocardial dysfunction among patients receiving Herceptin as a single agent or in combination therapy compared with those not receiving Herceptin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7641" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The highest absolute incidence occurs when Herceptin is administered with an anthracycline.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M47" type="Trigger" span="4 7;21 9" str="highest | incidence"/>
<Mention id="M48" type="Precipitant" span="77 13" str="anthracycline" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M47" precipitant="M48"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7642" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Withhold Herceptin for ≥ 16% absolute decrease in LVEF from pre-treatment values or an LVEF value below institutional limits of normal and ≥ 10% absolute decrease in LVEF from pretreatment values.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7643" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The safety of continuation or resumption of Herceptin in patients with Herceptin-induced left ventricular cardiac dysfunction has not been studied.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7644" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients who receive anthracycline after stopping Herceptin may also be at increased risk of cardiac dysfunction.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M49" type="Trigger" span="75 14" str="increased risk"/>
<Mention id="M50" type="Precipitant" span="21 13" str="anthracycline" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M51" type="SpecificInteraction" span="93 19" str="cardiac dysfunction" code="105981003: Disorder of cardiac function (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M49" precipitant="M50" effect="M51" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7645" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Cardiac Monitoring Conduct thorough cardiac assessment, including history, physical examination, and determination of LVEF by echocardiogram or MUGA scan.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7646" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The following schedule is recommended: Baseline LVEF measurement immediately prior to initiation of Herceptin LVEF measurements every 3 months during and upon completion of Herceptin Repeat LVEF measurement at 4 week intervals if Herceptin is withheld for significant left ventricular cardiac dysfunction LVEF measurements every 6 months for at least 2 years following completion of Herceptin as a component of adjuvant therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7647" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In Study 1, 15% (158/1031) of patients discontinued Herceptin due to clinical evidence of myocardial dysfunction or significant decline in LVEF after a median follow-up duration of 8.7 years in the AC-TH arm.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7648" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In Study 3 (one-year Herceptin treatment), the number of patients who discontinued Herceptin due to cardiac toxicity at 12.6 months median duration of follow-up was 2.6% (44/1678).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7649" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In Study 4, a total of 2.9% (31/1056) of patients in the TCH arm (1.5% during the chemotherapy phase and 1.4% during the monotherapy phase) and 5.7% (61/1068) of patients in the AC-TH arm (1.5% during the chemotherapy phase and 4.2% during the monotherapy phase) discontinued Herceptin due to cardiac toxicity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7650" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Among 64 patients receiving adjuvant chemotherapy (Studies 1 and 2) who developed congestive heart failure, one patient died of cardiomyopathy, one patient died suddenly without documented etiology, and 33 patients were receiving cardiac medication at last follow-up.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7651" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Approximately 24% of the surviving patients had recovery to a normal LVEF (defined as ≥50%) and no symptoms on continuing medical management at the time of last follow-up.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7652" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Incidence of congestive heart failure (CHF) is presented in Table 1.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7653" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Table 1: Incidence of Congestive Heart Failure in Adjuvant Breast Cancer Studies Incidence of CHF Study Regimen Herceptin Control 1 &amp; 2Median follow-up duration for studies 1 and 2 combined was 8.3 years in the AC→TH arm.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7654" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>ACAnthracycline (doxorubicin) and cyclophosphamide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7655" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>→ Paclitaxel+Herceptin 3.2% (64/2000)Includes 1 patient with fatal cardiomyopathy and 1 patient with sudden death without documented etiology.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7656" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>1.3% (21/1655) 3Includes NYHA II-IV and cardiac death at 12.6 months median duration of follow-up in the one-year Herceptin arm.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7657" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Chemo → Herceptin 2% (30/1678) 0.3% (5/1708) 4 AC → Docetaxel+Herceptin 2% (20/1068) 0.3% (3/1050) 4 Docetaxel+Carbo+Herceptin 0.4% (4/1056) 0.3% (3/1050) In Study 3 (one-year Herceptin treatment), at a median follow-up duration of 8 years, the incidence of severe CHF (NYHA III &amp; IV) was 0.8%, and the rate of mild symptomatic and asymptomatic left ventricular dysfunction was 4.6%.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7658" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Table 2: Incidence of Cardiac DysfunctionCongestive heart failure or significant asymptomatic decrease in LVEF. in Metastatic Breast Cancer Studies Incidence NYHA I-IV NYHA III-IV Study Event Herceptin Control Herceptin Control 5 (AC)Anthracycline (doxorubicin or epirubicin) and cyclophosphamide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7659" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Cardiac Dysfunction 28% 7% 19% 3% 5 (paclitaxel) Cardiac Dysfunction 11% 1% 4% 1% 6 Cardiac DysfunctionIncludes 1 patient with fatal cardiomyopathy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7660" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>7% N/A 5% N/A In Study 4, the incidence of NCI-CTC Grade 3/4 cardiac ischemia/infarction was higher in the Herceptin containing regimens (AC-TH: 0.3% (3/1068) and TCH: 0.2% (2/1056)) as compared to none in AC-T. Infusion reactions consist of a symptom complex characterized by fever and chills, and on occasion included nausea, vomiting, pain (in some cases at tumor sites), headache, dizziness, dyspnea, hypotension, rash, and asthenia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7661" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In post-marketing reports, serious and fatal infusion reactions have been reported.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7662" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Severe reactions, which include bronchospasm, anaphylaxis, angioedema, hypoxia, and severe hypotension, were usually reported during or immediately following the initial infusion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7663" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>However, the onset and clinical course were variable, including progressive worsening, initial improvement followed by clinical deterioration, or delayed post-infusion events with rapid clinical deterioration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7664" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>For fatal events, death occurred within hours to days following a serious infusion reaction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7665" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Interrupt Herceptin infusion in all patients experiencing dyspnea, clinically significant hypotension, and intervention of medical therapy administered (which may include epinephrine, corticosteroids, diphenhydramine, bronchodilators, and oxygen).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M79" type="Trigger" span="0 9;20 8" str="Interrupt | infusion"/>
<Mention id="M56" type="Precipitant" span="218 15" str="bronchodilators" code="N0000008322"/>
<Mention id="M78" type="SpecificInteraction" span="67 34" str="clinically significant hypotension" code="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M81" type="SpecificInteraction" span="58 7" str="dyspnea" code="267036007: Dyspnea (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M62" type="Precipitant" span="184 15" str="corticosteroids" code="N0000011309 | N0000175576"/>
<Mention id="M68" type="Precipitant" span="201 15" str="diphenhydramine" code="8GTS82S83M"/>
<Mention id="M74" type="Precipitant" span="171 11" str="epinephrine" code="YKH834O4BH | N0000006261"/>
<Mention id="M80" type="Precipitant" span="239 6" str="oxygen" code="S88TT14065"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M79" precipitant="M56" effect="M78" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M79" precipitant="M56" effect="M81" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M79" precipitant="M62" effect="M78" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M79" precipitant="M62" effect="M81" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M79" precipitant="M68" effect="M78" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M79" precipitant="M68" effect="M81" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M79" precipitant="M74" effect="M78" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M79" precipitant="M74" effect="M81" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M79" precipitant="M80" effect="M78" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I29" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M79" precipitant="M80" effect="M81" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7666" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients should be evaluated and carefully monitored until complete resolution of signs and symptoms.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7667" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Permanent discontinuation should be strongly considered in all patients with severe infusion reactions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7668" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There are no data regarding the most appropriate method of identification of patients who may safely be retreated with Herceptin after experiencing a severe infusion reaction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7669" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Prior to resumption of Herceptin infusion, the majority of patients who experienced a severe infusion reaction were pre-medicated with antihistamines and/or corticosteroids.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M85" type="Trigger" span="59 24;111 23" str="patients who experienced | were pre-medicated with"/>
<Mention id="M83" type="Precipitant" span="135 14" str="antihistamines" code="N0000175750 | N0000029071"/>
<Mention id="M87" type="SpecificInteraction" span="86 24" str="severe infusion reaction" code="441940003: Adverse reaction caused by drug or medicament administered by infusion (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M86" type="Precipitant" span="157 15" str="corticosteroids" code="N0000011309 | N0000175576"/>
<Interaction id="I30" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M85" precipitant="M83" effect="M87" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I31" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M85" precipitant="M86" effect="M87" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7670" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>While some patients tolerated Herceptin infusions, others had recurrent severe infusion reactions despite pre-medications.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7671" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Herceptin can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7672" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In post marketing reports, use of Herceptin during pregnancy resulted in cases of oligohydramnios and oligohydramnios sequence manifesting as pulmonary hypoplasia, skeletal abnormalities, and neonatal death.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7673" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Verify the pregnancy status of females of reproductive potential prior to the initiation of Herceptin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7674" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Advise pregnant women and females of reproductive potential that exposure to Herceptin during pregnancy or within 7 months prior to conception can result in fetal harm.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7675" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Advise females of reproductive potential to use effective contraception during treatment and for 7 months following the last dose of Herceptin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7676" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Herceptin use can result in serious and fatal pulmonary toxicity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7677" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Pulmonary toxicity includes dyspnea, interstitial pneumonitis, pulmonary infiltrates, pleural effusions, non-cardiogenic pulmonary edema, pulmonary insufficiency and hypoxia, acute respiratory distress syndrome, and pulmonary fibrosis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7678" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Such events can occur as sequelae of infusion reactions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7679" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients with symptomatic intrinsic lung disease or with extensive tumor involvement of the lungs, resulting in dyspnea at rest, appear to have more severe toxicity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7680" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In randomized, controlled clinical trials, the per-patient incidences of NCI-CTC Grade 3–4 neutropenia and of febrile neutropenia were higher in patients receiving Herceptin in combination with myelosuppressive chemotherapy as compared to those who received chemotherapy alone.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M91" type="Trigger" span="59 10;135 6" str="incidences | higher"/>
<Mention id="M92" type="Precipitant" span="194 29" str="myelosuppressive chemotherapy" code="N0000008759"/>
<Mention id="M90" type="SpecificInteraction" span="110 19" str="febrile neutropenia" code="409089005: Febrile neutropenia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M93" type="SpecificInteraction" span="73 29" str="NCI-CTC Grade 3–4 neutropenia" code="165517008: Neutropenia (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I32" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M91" precipitant="M92" effect="M90" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I33" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M91" precipitant="M92" effect="M93" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7681" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The incidence of septic death was similar among patients who received Herceptin and those who did not.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7682" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The HER2 (or c-erbB2) proto-oncogene encodes a transmembrane receptor protein of 185 kDa, which is structurally related to the epidermal growth factor receptor.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7683" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Herceptin has been shown, in both in vitro assays and in animals, to inhibit the proliferation of human tumor cells that overexpress HER2.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7684" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Herceptin is a mediator of antibody-dependent cellular cytotoxicity (ADCC).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7685" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In vitro, Herceptin-mediated ADCC has been shown to be preferentially exerted on HER2 overexpressing cancer cells compared with cancer cells that do not overexpress HER2.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7686" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Cardiac Electrophysiology The effects of trastuzumab on electrocardiographic (ECG) endpoints, including QTc interval duration, were evaluated in patients with HER2 positive solid tumors.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7687" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Trastuzumab had no clinically relevant effect on the QTc interval duration and there was no apparent relationship between serum trastuzumab concentrations and change in QTcF interval duration in patients with HER2 positive solid tumors.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7688" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacokinetics of trastuzumab was evaluated in a pooled population pharmacokinetic (PK) model analysis of 1,582 subjects with primarily breast cancer and metastatic gastric cancer (MGC) receiving intravenous Herceptin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7689" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Total trastuzumab clearance increases with decreasing concentrations due to parallel linear and non-linear elimination pathways.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7690" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Although the average trastuzumab exposure was higher following the first cycle in breast cancer patients receiving the three-weekly schedule compared to the weekly schedule of Herceptin, the average steady-state exposure was essentially the same at both dosages.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7691" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The average trastuzumab exposure following the first cycle and at steady state as well as the time to steady state was higher in breast cancer patients compared to MGC patients at the same dosage; however, the reason for this exposure difference is unknown.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7692" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Additional predicted trastuzumab exposure and PK parameters following the first Herceptin cycle and at steady state exposure are described in Tables 7 and 8, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7693" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Population PK based simulations indicate that following discontinuation of Herceptin, concentrations in at least 95% of breast cancer and MGC patients will decrease to approximately 3% of the population predicted steady-state trough serum concentration (approximately 97% washout) by 7 months.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7694" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Table 7: Population Predicted Cycle 1 PK Exposures (Median with 5th – 95th Percentiles) in Breast Cancer and MGC Patients Schedule Primary tumor type N Cmin (µg/mL) Cmax (µg/mL) AUC0-21days (µg.day/mL) 8 mg/kg + 6 mg/kg q3w Breast cancer 1195 29.4(5.8 - 59.5) 178(117 - 291) 1373(736 - 2245) MGC 274 23.1(6.1 - 50.3) 132(84.2 - 225) 1109(588 - 1938) 4 mg/kg + 2 mg/kg qw Breast cancer 1195 37.7(12.3 - 70.9) 88.3(58 - 144) 1066(586 - 1754) Table 8: Population Predicted Steady State PK Exposures (Median with 5th - 95th Percentiles) in Breast Cancer and MGC Patients Schedule Primary tumor type N Cmin,ss Steady-state trough serum concentration of trastuzumab (µg/mL) Cmax,ss Maximum steady-state serum concentration of trastuzumab (µg/mL) AUCss, 0-21 days (µg.day/mL) Time to steady-state (week) Total CL range at steady-state (L/day) 8 mg/kg + 6 mg/kg q3w Breast cancer 1195 47.4(5 - 115) 179(107 - 309) 1794(673 - 3618) 12 0.173 - 0.283 MGC 274 32.9(6.1 - 88.9) 131(72.5 - 251) 1338(557 - 2875) 9 0.189 - 0.337 4 mg/kg + 2 mg/kg qw Breast cancer 1195 66.1(14.9 - 142) 109(51.0 - 209) 1765(647 - 3578) 12 0.201 - 0.244 Specific Populations Based on a population pharmacokinetic analysis, no clinically significant differences were observed in the pharmacokinetics of trastuzumab based on age (&lt; 65 (n = 1294); ≥ 65 (n = 288)), race (Asian (n = 264); non-Asian (n = 1324)) and renal impairment (mild (creatinine clearance [CLcr] 60 to 90 mL/min) (n = 636) or moderate (CLcr 30 to 60 mL/min) (n = 133)).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7695" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacokinetics of trastuzumab in patients with severe renal impairment, end-stage renal disease with or without hemodialysis, or hepatic impairment is unknown.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7696" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Drug Interaction Studies There have been no formal drug interaction studies performed with Herceptin in humans.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7697" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Clinically significant interactions between Herceptin and concomitant medications used in clinical trials have not been observed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7698" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Paclitaxel and doxorubicin: Concentrations of paclitaxel and doxorubicin and their major metabolites (i.e., 6-α hydroxyl-paclitaxel [POH], and doxorubicinol [DOL], respectively) were not altered in the presence of trastuzumab when used as combination therapy in clinical trials.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7699" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Trastuzumab concentrations were not altered as part of this combination therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7700" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Docetaxel and carboplatin: When Herceptin was administered in combination with docetaxel or carboplatin, neither the plasma concentrations of docetaxel or carboplatin nor the plasma concentrations of trastuzumab were altered.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7701" LabelDrug="Herceptin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Cisplatin and capecitabine: In a drug interaction substudy conducted in patients in Study 7, the pharmacokinetics of cisplatin, capecitabine and their metabolites were not altered when administered in combination with Herceptin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="anthracycline" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="105981003: Disorder of cardiac function (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="anthracycline" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="anthracycline-containing chemotherapy regimens" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="anthracyclines" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="275514001: Impaired left ventricular function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="anthracyclines" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="42343007: Congestive heart failure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="anthracyclines" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="441940003: Adverse reaction caused by drug or medicament administered by infusion (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="anthracyclines" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="84114007: Heart failure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="anthracyclines" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="85898001: Cardiomyopathy (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="anthracyclines" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="ado-trastuzumab emtansine" precipitantCode="SE2KH7T06F"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="anthracycline-based chemotherapy regimens" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="chemotherapy" precipitantCode="N0000178307" effect="767658000: Neutropenia due to and following chemotherapy (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="bronchodilators" precipitantCode="N0000008322" effect="267036007: Dyspnea (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="bronchodilators" precipitantCode="N0000008322" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="corticosteroids" precipitantCode="N0000011309 | N0000175576" effect="267036007: Dyspnea (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="corticosteroids" precipitantCode="N0000011309 | N0000175576" effect="441940003: Adverse reaction caused by drug or medicament administered by infusion (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="corticosteroids" precipitantCode="N0000011309 | N0000175576" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="diphenhydramine" precipitantCode="8GTS82S83M" effect="267036007: Dyspnea (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="diphenhydramine" precipitantCode="8GTS82S83M" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="epinephrine" precipitantCode="YKH834O4BH | N0000006261" effect="267036007: Dyspnea (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="epinephrine" precipitantCode="YKH834O4BH | N0000006261" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="oxygen" precipitantCode="S88TT14065" effect="267036007: Dyspnea (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="oxygen" precipitantCode="S88TT14065" effect="45007003: Low blood pressure (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="antihistamines" precipitantCode="N0000175750 | N0000029071" effect="441940003: Adverse reaction caused by drug or medicament administered by infusion (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="myelosuppressive chemotherapy" precipitantCode="N0000008759" effect="165517008: Neutropenia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="myelosuppressive chemotherapy" precipitantCode="N0000008759" effect="409089005: Febrile neutropenia (disorder)"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>