<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Cytotec" setid="4ab12da7-5731-4e06-bf1c-bc3f2e711f12">
<Text><Section name="BOXED WARNING SECTION" id="34066-1">
CYTOTEC (MISOPROSTOL) ADMINISTRATION TO WOMEN WHO ARE PREGNANT CAN CAUSE BIRTH DEFECTS, ABORTION, PREMATURE BIRTH OR UTERINE RUPTURE. UTERINE RUPTURE HAS BEEN REPORTED WHEN CYTOTEC WAS ADMINISTERED IN PREGNANT WOMEN TO INDUCE LABOR OR TO INDUCE ABORTION. THE RISK OF UTERINE RUPTURE INCREASES WITH ADVANCING GESTATIONAL AGES AND WITH PRIOR UTERINE SURGERY, INCLUDING CESAREAN DELIVERY (see also PRECAUTIONS and LABOR AND DELIVERY ). CYTOTEC SHOULD NOT BE TAKEN BY PREGNANT WOMEN TO REDUCE THE RISK OF ULCERS INDUCED BY NONSTEROIDAL ANTI-INFLAMMATORY DRUGS (NSAIDs) (see CONTRAINDICATIONS , WARNINGS , and PRECAUTIONS ). PATIENTS MUST BE ADVISED OF THE ABORTIFACIENT PROPERTY AND WARNED NOT TO GIVE THE DRUG TO OTHERS. Cytotec should not be used for reducing the risk of NSAID-induced ulcers in women of childbearing potential unless the patient is at high risk of complications from gastric ulcers associated with use of the NSAID, or is at high risk of developing gastric ulceration. In such patients, Cytotec may be prescribed if the patient has had a negative serum pregnancy test within 2 weeks prior to beginning therapy. is capable of complying with effective contraceptive measures. has received both oral and written warnings of the hazards of misoprostol, the risk of possible contraception failure, and the danger to other women of childbearing potential should the drug be taken by mistake. will begin Cytotec only on the second or third day of the next normal menstrual period.</Section>
<Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
See boxed WARNINGS . Cytotec should not be taken by pregnant women to reduce the risk of ulcers induced by nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs). Cytotec should not be taken by anyone with a history of allergy to prostaglandins.</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
The recommended adult oral dose of Cytotec for reducing the risk of NSAID-induced gastric ulcers is 200 mcg four times daily with food. If this dose cannot be tolerated, a dose of 100 mcg can be used. (See Clinical Pharmacology: Clinical studies . ) Cytotec should be taken for the duration of NSAID therapy as prescribed by the physician. Cytotec should be taken with a meal, and the last dose of the day should be at bedtime. Adjustment of the dosing schedule in renally impaired patients is not routinely needed, but dosage can be reduced if the 200-mcg dose is not tolerated. (See Clinical Pharmacology . )</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
See Clinical Pharmacology . Cytotec has not been shown to interfere with the beneficial effects of aspirin on signs and symptoms of rheumatoid arthritis. Cytotec does not exert clinically significant effects on the absorption, blood levels, and antiplatelet effects of therapeutic doses of aspirin. Cytotec has no clinically significant effect on the kinetics of diclofenac or ibuprofen. Prostaglandins such as Cytotec may augment the activity of oxytocic agents, especially when given less than 4 hours prior to initiating oxytocin treatment. Concomitant use is not recommended .</Section>
<Section name="PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="42232-9">
Caution should be employed when administering Cytotec (misoprostol) to patients with pre-existing cardiovascular disease. Women of childbearing potential using Cytotec to decrease the risk of NSAID-induced ulcers should be told that they must not be pregnant when Cytotec therapy is initiated, and that they must use an effective contraception method while taking Cytotec. See boxed WARNINGS . Cytotec is intended for administration along with nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), including aspirin, to decrease the chance of developing an NSAID-induced gastric ulcer. Cytotec should be taken only according to the directions given by a physician. If the patient has questions about or problems with Cytotec, the physician should be contacted promptly. THE PATIENT SHOULD NOT GIVE CYTOTEC TO ANYONE ELSE. Cytotec has been prescribed for the patient's specific condition, may not be the correct treatment for another person, and may be dangerous to the other person if she were to become pregnant. The Cytotec package the patient receives from the pharmacist will include a leaflet containing patient information. The patient should read the leaflet before taking Cytotec and each time the prescription is renewed because the leaflet may have been revised. Keep Cytotec out of the reach of children. SPECIAL NOTE FOR WOMEN: Cytotec may cause birth defects, abortion (sometimes incomplete), premature labor or rupture of the uterus if given to pregnant women. Cytotec is available only as a unit-of-use package that includes a leaflet containing patient information. See Patient Information at the end of this labeling. See Clinical Pharmacology . Cytotec has not been shown to interfere with the beneficial effects of aspirin on signs and symptoms of rheumatoid arthritis. Cytotec does not exert clinically significant effects on the absorption, blood levels, and antiplatelet effects of therapeutic doses of aspirin. Cytotec has no clinically significant effect on the kinetics of diclofenac or ibuprofen. Prostaglandins such as Cytotec may augment the activity of oxytocic agents, especially when given less than 4 hours prior to initiating oxytocin treatment. Concomitant use is not recommended . A reversible increase in the number of normal surface gastric epithelial cells occurred in the dog, rat, and mouse. No such increase has been observed in humans administered Cytotec for up to 1 year. An apparent response of the female mouse to Cytotec in long-term studies at 100 to 1000 times the human dose was hyperostosis, mainly of the medulla of sternebrae. Hyperostosis did not occur in long-term studies in the dog and rat and has not been seen in humans treated with Cytotec. There was no evidence of an effect of Cytotec on tumor occurrence or incidence in rats receiving daily doses up to 150 times the human dose for 24 months. Similarly, there was no effect of Cytotec on tumor occurrence or incidence in mice receiving daily doses up to 1000 times the human dose for 21 months. The mutagenic potential of Cytotec was tested in several in vitro assays, all of which were negative. Misoprostol, when administered to breeding male and female rats at doses 6.25 times to 625 times the maximum recommended human therapeutic dose, produced dose-related pre- and post-implantation losses and a significant decrease in the number of live pups born at the highest dose. These findings suggest the possibility of a general adverse effect on fertility in males and females. See boxed WARNINGS . Congenital anomalies sometimes associated with fetal death have been reported subsequent to the unsuccessful use of misoprostol as an abortifacient, but the drug's teratogenic mechanism has not been demonstrated. Several reports in the literature associate the use of misoprostol during the first trimester of pregnancy with skull defects, cranial nerve palsies, facial malformations, and limb defects. Cytotec is not fetotoxic or teratogenic in rats and rabbits at doses 625 and 63 times the human dose, respectively. See boxed WARNINGS . Cytotec may endanger pregnancy (may cause abortion) and thereby cause harm to the fetus when administered to a pregnant woman. Cytotec may produce uterine contractions, uterine bleeding, and expulsion of the products of conception. Abortions caused by Cytotec may be incomplete. If a woman is or becomes pregnant while taking this drug to reduce the risk of NSAID-induced ulcers, the drug should be discontinued and the patient apprised of the potential hazard to the fetus. Cytotec can induce or augment uterine contractions. Vaginal administration of Cytotec, outside of its approved indication, has been used as a cervical ripening agent, for the induction of labor and for treatment of serious postpartum hemorrhage in the presence of uterine atony. A major adverse effect of the obstetrical use of Cytotec is uterine tachysystole which may progress to uterine tetany with marked impairment of uteroplacental blood flow, uterine rupture (requiring surgical repair, hysterectomy, and/or salpingo-oophorectomy), or amniotic fluid embolism and lead to adverse fetal heart changes. Uterine activity and fetal status should be monitored by trained obstetrical personnel in a hospital setting. The risk of uterine rupture associated with misoprostol use in pregnancy increases with advancing gestational ages and prior uterine surgery, including Cesarean delivery. Grand multiparity also appears to be a risk factor for uterine rupture. The use of Cytotec outside of its approved indication may also be associated with meconium passage, meconium staining of amniotic fluid, and Cesarean delivery. Maternal shock, maternal death, fetal bradycardia, and fetal death have also been reported with the use of misoprostol. Cytotec should not be used in the third trimester in women with a history of Cesarean section or major uterine surgery because of an increased risk of uterine rupture. Cytotec should not be used in cases where uterotonic drugs are generally contraindicated or where hyperstimulation of the uterus is considered inappropriate, such as cephalopelvic disproportion, grand multiparity, hypertonic or hyperactive uterine patterns, or fetal distress where delivery is not imminent, or when surgical intervention is more appropriate. The effect of Cytotec on later growth, development, and functional maturation of the child when Cytotec is used for cervical ripening or induction of labor has not been established. Information on Cytotec's effect on the need for forceps delivery or other intervention is unknown. The use of Cytotec (misoprostol) for the management of postpartum hemorrhage has been associated with reports of high fevers (greater than 40 degrees Celsius or 104 degrees Fahrenheit), accompanied by autonomic and central nervous system effects, such as tachycardia, disorientation, agitation, and convulsions. These fevers were transient in nature. Supportive therapy should be dictated by the patient's clinical presentation. Misoprostol is rapidly metabolized in the mother to misoprostol acid, which is biologically active and is excreted in breast milk. There are no published reports of adverse effects of misoprostol in breast-feeding infants of mothers taking misoprostol. Caution should be exercised when misoprostol is administered to a nursing woman. Safety and effectiveness of Cytotec in pediatric patients have not been established.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS SECTION" id="34071-1">
See boxed WARNINGS . For hospital use only if misoprostol were to be used for cervical ripening, induction of labor, or for the treatment of serious post-partum hemorrhage, which are outside of the approved indication.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Misoprostol is extensively absorbed, and undergoes rapid de-esterification to its free acid, which is responsible for its clinical activity and, unlike the parent compound, is detectable in plasma. The alpha side chain undergoes beta oxidation and the beta side chain undergoes omega oxidation followed by reduction of the ketone to give prostaglandin F analogs. In normal volunteers, Cytotec (misoprostol) is rapidly absorbed after oral administration with a T max of misoprostol acid of 12 ± 3 minutes and a terminal half-life of 20–40 minutes. There is high variability of plasma levels of misoprostol acid between and within studies but mean values after single doses show a linear relationship with dose over the range of 200–400 mcg. No accumulation of misoprostol acid was noted in multiple dose studies; plasma steady state was achieved within two days. Maximum plasma concentrations of misoprostol acid are diminished when the dose is taken with food and total availability of misoprostol acid is reduced by use of concomitant antacid. Clinical trials were conducted with concomitant antacid, however, so this effect does not appear to be clinically important. Mean ± SD C max (pg/ml) AUC(0–4) (pg∙hr/ml) T max (min) Fasting 811 ± 317 417 ± 135 14 ± 8 With Antacid 689 ± 315 349 ± 108 Comparisons with fasting results statistically significant, p&amp;lt;0.05. 20 ± 14 With High Fat Breakfast 303 ± 176 373 ± 111 64 ± 79 After oral administration of radiolabeled misoprostol, about 80% of detected radioactivity appears in urine. Pharmacokinetic studies in patients with varying degrees of renal impairment showed an approximate doubling of T 1/2 , C max , and AUC compared to normals, but no clear correlation between the degree of impairment and AUC. In subjects over 64 years of age, the AUC for misoprostol acid is increased. No routine dosage adjustment is recommended in older patients or patients with renal impairment, but dosage may need to be reduced if the usual dose is not tolerated. Drug interaction studies between misoprostol and several nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs showed no effect on the kinetics of ibuprofen or diclofenac, and a 20% decrease in aspirin AUC, not thought to be clinically significant. Pharmacokinetic studies also showed a lack of drug interaction with antipyrine and propranolol when these drugs were given with misoprostol. Misoprostol given for 1 week had no effect on the steady state pharmacokinetics of diazepam when the two drugs were administered 2 hours apart. The serum protein binding of misoprostol acid is less than 90% and is concentration-independent in the therapeutic range. After a single oral dose of misoprostol to nursing mothers, misoprostol acid was excreted in breast milk. The maximum concentration of misoprostol acid in expressed breast milk was achieved within 1 hour after dosing and was 7.6 pg/ml (CV 37%) and 20.9 pg/ml (CV 62%) after single 200 µg and 600 µg misoprostol administration, respectively. The misoprostol acid concentrations in breast milk declined to &amp;lt; 1 pg/ml at 5 hours post-dose. Misoprostol has both antisecretory (inhibiting gastric acid secretion) and (in animals) mucosal protective properties. NSAIDs inhibit prostaglandin synthesis, and a deficiency of prostaglandins within the gastric mucosa may lead to diminishing bicarbonate and mucus secretion and may contribute to the mucosal damage caused by these agents. Misoprostol can increase bicarbonate and mucus production, but in man this has been shown at doses 200 mcg and above that are also antisecretory. It is therefore not possible to tell whether the ability of misoprostol to reduce the risk of gastric ulcer is the result of its antisecretory effect, its mucosal protective effect, or both. In vitro studies on canine parietal cells using tritiated misoprostol acid as the ligand have led to the identification and characterization of specific prostaglandin receptors. Receptor binding is saturable, reversible, and stereospecific. The sites have a high affinity for misoprostol, for its acid metabolite, and for other E type prostaglandins, but not for F or I prostaglandins and other unrelated compounds, such as histamine or cimetidine. Receptor-site affinity for misoprostol correlates well with an indirect index of antisecretory activity. It is likely that these specific receptors allow misoprostol taken with food to be effective topically, despite the lower serum concentrations attained. Misoprostol produces a moderate decrease in pepsin concentration during basal conditions, but not during histamine stimulation. It has no significant effect on fasting or postprandial gastrin nor on intrinsic factor output. Misoprostol, over the range of 50–200 mcg, inhibits basal and nocturnal gastric acid secretion, and acid secretion in response to a variety of stimuli, including meals, histamine, pentagastrin, and coffee. Activity is apparent 30 minutes after oral administration and persists for at least 3 hours. In general, the effects of 50 mcg were modest and shorter lived, and only the 200-mcg dose had substantial effects on nocturnal secretion or on histamine and meal-stimulated secretion. Cytotec has been shown to produce uterine contractions that may endanger pregnancy. (See boxed WARNINGS . ) Cytotec does not produce clinically significant effects on serum levels of prolactin, gonadotropins, thyroid-stimulating hormone, growth hormone, thyroxine, cortisol, gastrointestinal hormones (somatostatin, gastrin, vasoactive intestinal polypeptide, and motilin), creatinine, or uric acid. Gastric emptying, immunologic competence, platelet aggregation, pulmonary function, or the cardiovascular system are not modified by recommended doses of Cytotec. In a series of small short-term (about 1 week) placebo-controlled studies in healthy human volunteers, doses of misoprostol were evaluated for their ability to reduce the risk of NSAID-induced mucosal injury. Studies of 200 mcg q.i.d. of misoprostol with tolmetin and naproxen, and of 100 and 200 mcg q.i.d. with ibuprofen, all showed reduction of the rate of significant endoscopic injury from about 70–75% on placebo to 10–30% on misoprostol. Doses of 25–200 mcg q.i.d. reduced aspirin-induced mucosal injury and bleeding. Two 12-week, randomized, double-blind trials in osteoarthritic patients who had gastrointestinal symptoms but no ulcer on endoscopy while taking an NSAID compared the ability of 200 mcg of Cytotec, 100 mcg of Cytotec, and placebo to reduce the risk of gastric ulcer (GU) formation. Patients were approximately equally divided between ibuprofen, piroxicam, and naproxen, and continued this treatment throughout the 12 weeks. The 200-mcg dose caused a marked, statistically significant reduction in gastric ulcers in both studies. The lower dose was somewhat less effective, with a significant result in only one of the studies. Reduction of Risk of Gastric Ulcers Induced by Ibuprofen, Piroxicam, or Naproxen [No. of patients with ulcer(s) (%)] Therapy Duration Therapy 4 weeks 8 weeks 12 weeks Study No. 1 Cytotec 200 mcg q.i.d. (n=74) 1 (1.4) 0 0 1 (1.4) Statistically significantly different from placebo at the 5% level. Cytotec 100 mcg q.i.d. (n=77) 3 (3.9) 1 (1.3) 1 (1.3) 5 (6.5) Placebo (n=76) 11 (14.5) 4 (5.3) 4 (5.3) 19 (25.0) Study No. 2 Cytotec 200 mcg q.i.d. (n=65) 1 (1.5) 1 (1.5) 0 2 (3.1) Cytotec 100 mcg q.i.d. (n=66) 2 (3.0) 2 (3.0) 1 (1.5) 5 (7.6) Placebo (n=62) 6 (9.7) 2 (3.2) 3 (4.8) 11 (17.7) Studies No. 1 &amp;amp; No. 2 Combined data from Study No. 1 and Study No. 2. Cytotec 200 mcg q.i.d. (n=139) 2 (1.4) 1 (0.7) 0 3 (2.2) Cytotec 100 mcg q.i.d. (n=143) 5 (3.5) 3 (2.1) 2 (1.4) 10 (7.0) Placebo (n=138) 17 (12.3) 6 (4.3) 7 (5.1) 30 (21.7) In these trials there were no significant differences between Cytotec and placebo in relief of day or night abdominal pain. No effect of Cytotec in reducing the risk of duodenal ulcers was demonstrated, but relatively few duodenal lesions were seen. In another clinical trial, 239 patients receiving aspirin 650–1300 mg q.i.d. for rheumatoid arthritis who had endoscopic evidence of duodenal and/or gastric inflammation were randomized to misoprostol 200 mcg q.i.d. or placebo for 8 weeks while continuing to receive aspirin. The study evaluated the possible interference of Cytotec on the efficacy of aspirin in these patients with rheumatoid arthritis by analyzing joint tenderness, joint swelling, physician's clinical assessment, patient's assessment, change in ARA classification, change in handgrip strength, change in duration of morning stiffness, patient's assessment of pain at rest, movement, interference with daily activity, and ESR. Cytotec did not interfere with the efficacy of aspirin in these patients with rheumatoid arthritis.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="3134" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>CYTOTEC (MISOPROSTOL) ADMINISTRATION TO WOMEN WHO ARE PREGNANT CAN CAUSE BIRTH DEFECTS, ABORTION, PREMATURE BIRTH OR UTERINE RUPTURE.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3135" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>UTERINE RUPTURE HAS BEEN REPORTED WHEN CYTOTEC WAS ADMINISTERED IN PREGNANT WOMEN TO INDUCE LABOR OR TO INDUCE ABORTION.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3136" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>THE RISK OF UTERINE RUPTURE INCREASES WITH ADVANCING GESTATIONAL AGES AND WITH PRIOR UTERINE SURGERY, INCLUDING CESAREAN DELIVERY.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3138" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>PATIENTS MUST BE ADVISED OF THE ABORTIFACIENT PROPERTY AND WARNED NOT TO GIVE THE DRUG TO OTHERS.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3139" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Cytotec should not be used for reducing the risk of NSAID-induced ulcers in women of childbearing potential unless the patient is at high risk of complications from gastric ulcers associated with use of the NSAID, or is at high risk of developing gastric ulceration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3140" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>In such patients, Cytotec may be prescribed if the patient has had a negative serum pregnancy test within 2 weeks prior to beginning therapy. is capable of complying with effective contraceptive measures. has received both oral and written warnings of the hazards of misoprostol, the risk of possible contraception failure, and the danger to other women of childbearing potential should the drug be taken by mistake. will begin Cytotec only on the second or third day of the next normal menstrual period.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3142" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Cytotec should not be taken by anyone with a history of allergy to prostaglandins.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3143" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommended adult oral dose of Cytotec for reducing the risk of NSAID-induced gastric ulcers is 200 mcg four times daily with food.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3144" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If this dose cannot be tolerated, a dose of 100 mcg can be used.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3145" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Cytotec should be taken for the duration of NSAID therapy as prescribed by the physician.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3146" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Cytotec should be taken with a meal, and the last dose of the day should be at bedtime.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3147" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Adjustment of the dosing schedule in renally impaired patients is not routinely needed, but dosage can be reduced if the 200-mcg dose is not tolerated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3148" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Cytotec has not been shown to interfere with the beneficial effects of aspirin on signs and symptoms of rheumatoid arthritis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3149" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Cytotec does not exert clinically significant effects on the absorption, blood levels, and antiplatelet effects of therapeutic doses of aspirin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3150" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Cytotec has no clinically significant effect on the kinetics of diclofenac or ibuprofen.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3151" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Prostaglandins such as Cytotec may augment the activity of oxytocic agents, especially when given less than 4 hours prior to initiating oxytocin treatment.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M4" type="Trigger" span="35 7" str="augment"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="59 15" str="oxytocic agents" code="N0000175828"/>
<Mention id="M3" type="SpecificInteraction" span="35 7;59 15" str="augment | oxytocic agents" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M5" type="Precipitant" span="136 8" str="oxytocin" code="1JQS135EYN"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M4" precipitant="M2" effect="M3" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M4" precipitant="M5"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3152" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Caution should be employed when administering Cytotec (misoprostol) to patients with pre-existing cardiovascular disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3153" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Women of childbearing potential using Cytotec to decrease the risk of NSAID-induced ulcers should be told that they must not be pregnant when Cytotec therapy is initiated, and that they must use an effective contraception method while taking Cytotec.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3154" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Cytotec is intended for administration along with nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), including aspirin, to decrease the chance of developing an NSAID-induced gastric ulcer.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3155" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Cytotec should be taken only according to the directions given by a physician.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3156" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>If the patient has questions about or problems with Cytotec, the physician should be contacted promptly.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3157" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>THE PATIENT SHOULD NOT GIVE CYTOTEC TO ANYONE ELSE.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3158" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Cytotec has been prescribed for the patient's specific condition, may not be the correct treatment for another person, and may be dangerous to the other person if she were to become pregnant.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3159" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The Cytotec package the patient receives from the pharmacist will include a leaflet containing patient information.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3160" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The patient should read the leaflet before taking Cytotec and each time the prescription is renewed because the leaflet may have been revised.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3161" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Keep Cytotec out of the reach of children.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3162" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>SPECIAL NOTE FOR WOMEN: Cytotec may cause birth defects, abortion (sometimes incomplete), premature labor or rupture of the uterus if given to pregnant women.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3163" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Cytotec is available only as a unit-of-use package that includes a leaflet containing patient information.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3164" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>See Patient Information at the end of this labeling.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3165" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>A reversible increase in the number of normal surface gastric epithelial cells occurred in the dog, rat, and mouse.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3166" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>No such increase has been observed in humans administered Cytotec for up to 1 year.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3167" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>An apparent response of the female mouse to Cytotec in long-term studies at 100 to 1000 times the human dose was hyperostosis, mainly of the medulla of sternebrae.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3168" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Hyperostosis did not occur in long-term studies in the dog and rat and has not been seen in humans treated with Cytotec.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3169" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>There was no evidence of an effect of Cytotec on tumor occurrence or incidence in rats receiving daily doses up to 150 times the human dose for 24 months.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3170" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Similarly, there was no effect of Cytotec on tumor occurrence or incidence in mice receiving daily doses up to 1000 times the human dose for 21 months.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3171" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The mutagenic potential of Cytotec was tested in several in vitro assays, all of which were negative.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3172" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Misoprostol, when administered to breeding male and female rats at doses 6.25 times to 625 times the maximum recommended human therapeutic dose, produced dose-related pre- and post-implantation losses and a significant decrease in the number of live pups born at the highest dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3173" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>These findings suggest the possibility of a general adverse effect on fertility in males and females.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3174" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Congenital anomalies sometimes associated with fetal death have been reported subsequent to the unsuccessful use of misoprostol as an abortifacient, but the drug's teratogenic mechanism has not been demonstrated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3175" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Several reports in the literature associate the use of misoprostol during the first trimester of pregnancy with skull defects, cranial nerve palsies, facial malformations, and limb defects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3176" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Cytotec is not fetotoxic or teratogenic in rats and rabbits at doses 625 and 63 times the human dose, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3177" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Cytotec may endanger pregnancy (may cause abortion) and thereby cause harm to the fetus when administered to a pregnant woman.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3178" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Cytotec may produce uterine contractions, uterine bleeding, and expulsion of the products of conception.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3179" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Abortions caused by Cytotec may be incomplete.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3180" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>If a woman is or becomes pregnant while taking this drug to reduce the risk of NSAID-induced ulcers, the drug should be discontinued and the patient apprised of the potential hazard to the fetus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3181" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Cytotec can induce or augment uterine contractions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3182" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Vaginal administration of Cytotec, outside of its approved indication, has been used as a cervical ripening agent, for the induction of labor and for treatment of serious postpartum hemorrhage in the presence of uterine atony.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3183" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>A major adverse effect of the obstetrical use of Cytotec is uterine tachysystole which may progress to uterine tetany with marked impairment of uteroplacental blood flow, uterine rupture (requiring surgical repair, hysterectomy, and/or salpingo-oophorectomy), or amniotic fluid embolism and lead to adverse fetal heart changes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3184" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Uterine activity and fetal status should be monitored by trained obstetrical personnel in a hospital setting.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3185" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The risk of uterine rupture associated with misoprostol use in pregnancy increases with advancing gestational ages and prior uterine surgery, including Cesarean delivery.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3186" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Grand multiparity also appears to be a risk factor for uterine rupture.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3187" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The use of Cytotec outside of its approved indication may also be associated with meconium passage, meconium staining of amniotic fluid, and Cesarean delivery.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3188" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Maternal shock, maternal death, fetal bradycardia, and fetal death have also been reported with the use of misoprostol.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3189" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Cytotec should not be used in the third trimester in women with a history of Cesarean section or major uterine surgery because of an increased risk of uterine rupture.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3190" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Cytotec should not be used in cases where uterotonic drugs are generally contraindicated or where hyperstimulation of the uterus is considered inappropriate, such as cephalopelvic disproportion, grand multiparity, hypertonic or hyperactive uterine patterns, or fetal distress where delivery is not imminent, or when surgical intervention is more appropriate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3191" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The effect of Cytotec on later growth, development, and functional maturation of the child when Cytotec is used for cervical ripening or induction of labor has not been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3192" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Information on Cytotec's effect on the need for forceps delivery or other intervention is unknown.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3193" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The use of Cytotec (misoprostol) for the management of postpartum hemorrhage has been associated with reports of high fevers (greater than 40 degrees Celsius or 104 degrees Fahrenheit), accompanied by autonomic and central nervous system effects, such as tachycardia, disorientation, agitation, and convulsions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3194" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Supportive therapy should be dictated by the patient's clinical presentation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3195" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Misoprostol is rapidly metabolized in the mother to misoprostol acid, which is biologically active and is excreted in breast milk.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3196" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>There are no published reports of adverse effects of misoprostol in breast-feeding infants of mothers taking misoprostol.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3197" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Caution should be exercised when misoprostol is administered to a nursing woman.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3198" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Safety and effectiveness of Cytotec in pediatric patients have not been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3199" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>For hospital use only if misoprostol were to be used for cervical ripening, induction of labor, or for the treatment of serious post-partum hemorrhage, which are outside of the approved indication.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3200" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Misoprostol is extensively absorbed, and undergoes rapid de-esterification to its free acid, which is responsible for its clinical activity and, unlike the parent compound, is detectable in plasma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3201" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The alpha side chain undergoes beta oxidation and the beta side chain undergoes omega oxidation followed by reduction of the ketone to give prostaglandin F analogs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3202" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In normal volunteers, Cytotec (misoprostol) is rapidly absorbed after oral administration with a Tmax of misoprostol acid of 12 ± 3 minutes and a terminal half-life of 20–40 minutes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3203" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There is high variability of plasma levels of misoprostol acid between and within studies but mean values after single doses show a linear relationship with dose over the range of 200–400 mcg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3204" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No accumulation of misoprostol acid was noted in multiple dose studies; plasma steady state was achieved within two days.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3205" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Maximum plasma concentrations of misoprostol acid are diminished when the dose is taken with food and total availability of misoprostol acid is reduced by use of concomitant antacid.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M6" type="Trigger" span="102 18;144 7" str="total availability | reduced"/>
<Mention id="M7" type="Precipitant" span="174 7" str="antacid" code="N0000029169 | N0000008295"/>
<Mention id="M8" type="Trigger" span="0 29;54 10" str="Maximum plasma concentrations | diminished"/>
<Mention id="M9" type="Precipitant" span="93 4" str="food" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M6" precipitant="M7" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M8" precipitant="M9" effect="C54606"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3206" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Clinical trials were conducted with concomitant antacid, however, so this effect does not appear to be clinically important.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3207" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Mean ± SD Cmax(pg/ml) AUC(0–4)(pg∙hr/ml) Tmax(min) Fasting 811 ± 317 417 ± 135 14 ± 8 With Antacid 689 ± 315 349 ± 108Comparisons with fasting results statistically significant, p&lt;0.05.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3208" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>20 ± 14 With High Fat Breakfast 303 ± 176 373 ± 111 64 ± 79 After oral administration of radiolabeled misoprostol, about 80% of detected radioactivity appears in urine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3209" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Pharmacokinetic studies in patients with varying degrees of renal impairment showed an approximate doubling of T1/2, Cmax, and AUC compared to normals, but no clear correlation between the degree of impairment and AUC.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3210" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In subjects over 64 years of age, the AUC for misoprostol acid is increased.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3211" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No routine dosage adjustment is recommended in older patients or patients with renal impairment, but dosage may need to be reduced if the usual dose is not tolerated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3212" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Drug interaction studies between misoprostol and several nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs showed no effect on the kinetics of ibuprofen or diclofenac, and a 20% decrease in aspirin AUC, not thought to be clinically significant.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M10" type="Trigger" span="165 8;185 3" str="decrease | AUC"/>
<Mention id="M11" type="Precipitant" span="177 7" str="aspirin" code="N0000006582 | R16CO5Y76E"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M10" precipitant="M11" effect="C54614"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3213" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Pharmacokinetic studies also showed a lack of drug interaction with antipyrine and propranolol when these drugs were given with misoprostol.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3214" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Misoprostol given for 1 week had no effect on the steady state pharmacokinetics of diazepam when the two drugs were administered 2 hours apart.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3215" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The serum protein binding of misoprostol acid is less than 90% and is concentration-independent in the therapeutic range.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3216" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>After a single oral dose of misoprostol to nursing mothers, misoprostol acid was excreted in breast milk.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3217" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The maximum concentration of misoprostol acid in expressed breast milk was achieved within 1 hour after dosing and was 7.6 pg/ml (CV 37%) and 20.9 pg/ml (CV 62%) after single 200 µg and 600 µg misoprostol administration, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3218" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The misoprostol acid concentrations in breast milk declined to &lt; 1 pg/ml at 5 hours post-dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3219" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Misoprostol has both antisecretory (inhibiting gastric acid secretion) and (in animals) mucosal protective properties.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3220" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>NSAIDs inhibit prostaglandin synthesis, and a deficiency of prostaglandins within the gastric mucosa may lead to diminishing bicarbonate and mucus secretion and may contribute to the mucosal damage caused by these agents.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3221" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Misoprostol can increase bicarbonate and mucus production, but in man this has been shown at doses 200 mcg and above that are also antisecretory.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3222" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>It is therefore not possible to tell whether the ability of misoprostol to reduce the risk of gastric ulcer is the result of its antisecretory effect, its mucosal protective effect, or both.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3223" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In vitro studies on canine parietal cells using tritiated misoprostol acid as the ligand have led to the identification and characterization of specific prostaglandin receptors.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3224" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Receptor binding is saturable, reversible, and stereospecific.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3225" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The sites have a high affinity for misoprostol, for its acid metabolite, and for other E type prostaglandins, but not for F or I prostaglandins and other unrelated compounds, such as histamine or cimetidine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3226" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Receptor-site affinity for misoprostol correlates well with an indirect index of antisecretory activity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3227" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>It is likely that these specific receptors allow misoprostol taken with food to be effective topically, despite the lower serum concentrations attained.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3228" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Misoprostol produces a moderate decrease in pepsin concentration during basal conditions, but not during histamine stimulation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3229" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>It has no significant effect on fasting or postprandial gastrin nor on intrinsic factor output.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3230" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Misoprostol, over the range of 50–200 mcg, inhibits basal and nocturnal gastric acid secretion, and acid secretion in response to a variety of stimuli, including meals, histamine, pentagastrin, and coffee.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3231" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Activity is apparent 30 minutes after oral administration and persists for at least 3 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3232" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In general, the effects of 50 mcg were modest and shorter lived, and only the 200-mcg dose had substantial effects on nocturnal secretion or on histamine and meal-stimulated secretion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3233" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Cytotec has been shown to produce uterine contractions that may endanger pregnancy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3234" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Cytotec does not produce clinically significant effects on serum levels of prolactin, gonadotropins, thyroid-stimulating hormone, growth hormone, thyroxine, cortisol, gastrointestinal hormones (somatostatin, gastrin, vasoactive intestinal polypeptide, and motilin), creatinine, or uric acid.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3235" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Gastric emptying, immunologic competence, platelet aggregation, pulmonary function, or the cardiovascular system are not modified by recommended doses of Cytotec.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3236" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In a series of small short-term (about 1 week) placebo-controlled studies in healthy human volunteers, doses of misoprostol were evaluated for their ability to reduce the risk of NSAID-induced mucosal injury.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3237" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Studies of 200 mcg q.i.d. of misoprostol with tolmetin and naproxen, and of 100 and 200 mcg q.i.d. with ibuprofen, all showed reduction of the rate of significant endoscopic injury from about 70–75% on placebo to 10–30% on misoprostol.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3238" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Doses of 25–200 mcg q.i.d. reduced aspirin-induced mucosal injury and bleeding.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3239" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Two 12-week, randomized, double-blind trials in osteoarthritic patients who had gastrointestinal symptoms but no ulcer on endoscopy while taking an NSAID compared the ability of 200 mcg of Cytotec, 100 mcg of Cytotec, and placebo to reduce the risk of gastric ulcer (GU) formation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3240" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Patients were approximately equally divided between ibuprofen, piroxicam, and naproxen, and continued this treatment throughout the 12 weeks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3241" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The 200-mcg dose caused a marked, statistically significant reduction in gastric ulcers in both studies.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3242" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The lower dose was somewhat less effective, with a significant result in only one of the studies.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3243" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Reduction of Risk of Gastric Ulcers Induced by Ibuprofen, Piroxicam, or Naproxen [No. of patients with ulcer(s) (%)] Therapy Duration Therapy 4 weeks 8 weeks 12 weeks Study No.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3244" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>(n=74) 1 (1.4) 0 0 1 (1.4)Statistically significantly different from placebo at the 5% level.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3245" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>(n=77) 3 (3.9) 1 (1.3) 1 (1.3) 5 (6.5) Placebo (n=76) 11 (14.5) 4 (5.3) 4 (5.3) 19 (25.0) Study No.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3246" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>(n=65) 1 (1.5) 1 (1.5) 0 2 (3.1) Cytotec 100 mcg q.i.d.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3247" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>(n=66) 2 (3.0) 2 (3.0) 1 (1.5) 5 (7.6) Placebo (n=62) 6 (9.7) 2 (3.2) 3 (4.8) 11 (17.7) Studies No.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3248" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>(n=139) 2 (1.4) 1 (0.7) 0 3 (2.2) Cytotec 100 mcg q.i.d.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3249" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>(n=143) 5 (3.5) 3 (2.1) 2 (1.4) 10 (7.0) Placebo (n=138) 17 (12.3) 6 (4.3) 7 (5.1) 30 (21.7) In these trials there were no significant differences between Cytotec and placebo in relief of day or night abdominal pain.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3250" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No effect of Cytotec in reducing the risk of duodenal ulcers was demonstrated, but relatively few duodenal lesions were seen.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3251" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In another clinical trial, 239 patients receiving aspirin 650–1300 mg q.i.d. for rheumatoid arthritis who had endoscopic evidence of duodenal and/or gastric inflammation were randomized to misoprostol 200 mcg q.i.d. or placebo for 8 weeks while continuing to receive aspirin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3252" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The study evaluated the possible interference of Cytotec on the efficacy of aspirin in these patients with rheumatoid arthritis by analyzing joint tenderness, joint swelling, physician's clinical assessment, patient's assessment, change in ARA classification, change in handgrip strength, change in duration of morning stiffness, patient's assessment of pain at rest, movement, interference with daily activity, and ESR.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3253" LabelDrug="Cytotec" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Cytotec did not interfere with the efficacy of aspirin in these patients with rheumatoid arthritis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="oxytocic agents" precipitantCode="N0000175828" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="oxytocin" precipitantCode="1JQS135EYN"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="antacid" precipitantCode="N0000029169 | N0000008295" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="food" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54606"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="aspirin" precipitantCode="N0000006582 | R16CO5Y76E" effect="C54614"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>