<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="ACCOLATE" setid="4bf90772-58d5-456d-ad1c-fc448cc5a231">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
ACCOLATE is contraindicated in patients who are hypersensitive to zafirlukast or any of its inactive ingredients.</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
Because food can reduce the bioavailability of zafirlukast, ACCOLATE should be taken at least 1 hour before or 2 hours after meals. The recommended dose of ACCOLATE in adults and children 12 years and older is 20 mg twice daily. The recommended dose of ACCOLATE in children 5 through 11 years of age is 10 mg twice daily. Elderly Patients: Based on cross-study comparisons, the clearance of zafirlukast is reduced in elderly patients (65 years of age and older), such that C max and AUC are approximately twice those of younger adults. In clinical trials, a dose of 20 mg twice daily was not associated with an increase in the overall incidence of adverse events or withdrawals because of adverse events in elderly patients. Patients with Hepatic Impairment: The clearance of zafirlukast is reduced in patients with stable alcoholic cirrhosis such that the C max and AUC are approximately 50 - 60% greater than those of normal adults. ACCOLATE has not been evaluated in patients with hepatitis or in long-term studies of patients with cirrhosis. Patients with Renal Impairment: Dosage adjustment is not required for patients with renal impairment.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
In a drug interaction study in 16 healthy male volunteers, coadministration of multiple doses of zafirlukast (160 mg/day) to steady-state with a single 25 mg dose of warfarin resulted in a significant increase in the mean AUC (+ 63%) and half-life (+36%) of S-warfarin. The mean prothrombin time (PT) increased by approximately 35%. This interaction is probably due to an inhibition by zafirlukast of the cytochrome P450 2C9 isoenzyme system. Patients on oral warfarin anticoagulant therapy and ACCOLATE should have their prothrombin times monitored closely and anticoagulant dose adjusted accordingly (see WARNINGS, Concomitant Warfarin Administration ). No formal drug-drug interaction studies with ACCOLATE and other drugs known to be metabolized by the cytochrome P450 2C9 isoenzyme (eg, tolbutamide, phenytoin, carbamazepine) have been conducted; however, care should be exercised when ACCOLATE is coadministered with these drugs. In a drug interaction study in 11 asthmatic patients, coadministration of a single dose of zafirlukast (40 mg) with erythromycin (500 mg three times daily for 5 days) to steady-state resulted in decreased mean plasma levels of zafirlukast by approximately 40% due to a decrease in zafirlukast bioavailability. Coadministration of zafirlukast (20 mg/day) or placebo at steady-state with a single dose of sustained release theophylline preparation (16 mg/kg) in 16 healthy boys and girls (6 through 11 years of age) resulted in no significant differences in the pharmacokinetic parameters of theophylline. Coadministration of zafirlukast (80 mg/day) at steady-state with a single dose of a liquid theophylline preparation (6 mg/kg) in 13 asthmatic patients, 18 to 44 years of age, resulted in decreased mean plasma levels of zafirlukast by approximately 30%, but no effect on plasma theophylline levels was observed. Rare cases of patients experiencing increased theophylline levels with or without clinical signs or symptoms of theophylline toxicity after the addition of ACCOLATE to an existing theophylline regimen have been reported. The mechanism of the interaction between ACCOLATE and theophylline in these patients is unknown (see ADVERSE REACTIONS ). Coadministration of zafirlukast (40 mg/day) with aspirin (650 mg four times daily) resulted in mean increased plasma levels of zafirlukast by approximately 45%. In a single-blind, parallel-group, 3-week study in 39 healthy female subjects taking oral contraceptives, 40 mg twice daily of zafirlukast had no significant effect on ethinyl estradiol plasma concentrations or contraceptive efficacy. No formal drug-drug interaction studies between ACCOLATE and marketed drugs known to be metabolized by the P450 3A4 (CYP3A4) isoenzyme (eg, dihydropyridine calcium-channel blockers, cyclosporin, cisapride) have been conducted. As ACCOLATE is known to be an inhibitor of CYP3A4 in vitro , it is reasonable to employ appropriate clinical monitoring when these drugs are coadministered with ACCOLATE.</Section>
<Section name="PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="42232-9">
Patients should be told that a rare side effect of ACCOLATE is hepatic dysfunction, and to contact their physician immediately if they experience symptoms of hepatic dysfunction (eg. right upper quadrant abdominal pain, nausea, fatigue, lethargy, pruritus, jaundice, flu-like symptoms, and anorexia). Liver failure resulting in liver transplantation and death has occurred in patients taking zafirlukast (see WARNINGS, Hepatotoxicity and ADVERSE REACTIONS ). ACCOLATE is indicated for the chronic treatment of asthma and should be taken regularly as prescribed, even during symptom-free periods. ACCOLATE is not a bronchodilator and should not be used to treat acute episodes of asthma. Patients receiving ACCOLATE should be instructed not to decrease the dose or stop taking any other antiasthma medications unless instructed by a physician. Patients should be instructed to notify their physician if neuropsychiatric events occur while using ACCOLATE (see PRECAUTIONS, Neuropsychiatric Events ). Women who are breast-feeding should be instructed not to take ACCOLATE (see PRECAUTIONS, Nursing Mothers ). Alternative antiasthma medication should be considered in such patients. The bioavailability of ACCOLATE may be decreased when taken with food. Patients should be instructed to take ACCOLATE at least 1 hour before or 2 hours after meals. In rare cases, patients on ACCOLATE therapy may present with systemic eosinophilia, eosinophilic pneumonia, or clinical features of vasculitis consistent with Churg-Strauss syndrome, a condition which is often treated with systemic steroid therapy. These events usually, but not always, have been associated with the reduction of oral steroid therapy. Physicians should be alert to eosinophilia, vasculitic rash, worsening pulmonary symptoms, cardiac complications, and/or neuropathy presenting in their patients. A causal association between ACCOLATE and these underlying conditions has not been established (see ADVERSE REACTIONS ). Neuropsychiatric events have been reported in adult, adolescent and pediatric patients taking ACCOLATE. Post-marketing reports with ACCOLATE include insomnia and depression. The clinical details of some post-marketing reports involving ACCOLATE appear consistent with a drug-induced effect. Patients and prescribers should be alert for neuropsychiatric events. Patients should be instructed to notify their prescriber if these changes occur. Prescribers should carefully evaluate the risks and benefits of continuing treatment with ACCOLATE if such events occur (see Adverse Reactions). In a drug interaction study in 16 healthy male volunteers, coadministration of multiple doses of zafirlukast (160 mg/day) to steady-state with a single 25 mg dose of warfarin resulted in a significant increase in the mean AUC (+ 63%) and half-life (+36%) of S-warfarin. The mean prothrombin time (PT) increased by approximately 35%. This interaction is probably due to an inhibition by zafirlukast of the cytochrome P450 2C9 isoenzyme system. Patients on oral warfarin anticoagulant therapy and ACCOLATE should have their prothrombin times monitored closely and anticoagulant dose adjusted accordingly (see WARNINGS, Concomitant Warfarin Administration ). No formal drug-drug interaction studies with ACCOLATE and other drugs known to be metabolized by the cytochrome P450 2C9 isoenzyme (eg, tolbutamide, phenytoin, carbamazepine) have been conducted; however, care should be exercised when ACCOLATE is coadministered with these drugs. In a drug interaction study in 11 asthmatic patients, coadministration of a single dose of zafirlukast (40 mg) with erythromycin (500 mg three times daily for 5 days) to steady-state resulted in decreased mean plasma levels of zafirlukast by approximately 40% due to a decrease in zafirlukast bioavailability. Coadministration of zafirlukast (20 mg/day) or placebo at steady-state with a single dose of sustained release theophylline preparation (16 mg/kg) in 16 healthy boys and girls (6 through 11 years of age) resulted in no significant differences in the pharmacokinetic parameters of theophylline. Coadministration of zafirlukast (80 mg/day) at steady-state with a single dose of a liquid theophylline preparation (6 mg/kg) in 13 asthmatic patients, 18 to 44 years of age, resulted in decreased mean plasma levels of zafirlukast by approximately 30%, but no effect on plasma theophylline levels was observed. Rare cases of patients experiencing increased theophylline levels with or without clinical signs or symptoms of theophylline toxicity after the addition of ACCOLATE to an existing theophylline regimen have been reported. The mechanism of the interaction between ACCOLATE and theophylline in these patients is unknown (see ADVERSE REACTIONS ). Coadministration of zafirlukast (40 mg/day) with aspirin (650 mg four times daily) resulted in mean increased plasma levels of zafirlukast by approximately 45%. In a single-blind, parallel-group, 3-week study in 39 healthy female subjects taking oral contraceptives, 40 mg twice daily of zafirlukast had no significant effect on ethinyl estradiol plasma concentrations or contraceptive efficacy. No formal drug-drug interaction studies between ACCOLATE and marketed drugs known to be metabolized by the P450 3A4 (CYP3A4) isoenzyme (eg, dihydropyridine calcium-channel blockers, cyclosporin, cisapride) have been conducted. As ACCOLATE is known to be an inhibitor of CYP3A4 in vitro , it is reasonable to employ appropriate clinical monitoring when these drugs are coadministered with ACCOLATE. In two-year carcinogenicity studies, zafirlukast was administered at dietary doses of 10, 100, and 300 mg/kg to mice and 40, 400, and 2000 mg/kg to rats. Male mice at an oral dose of 300 mg/kg/day (approximately 30 times the maximum recommended daily oral dose in adults and in children on a mg/m 2 basis) showed an increased incidence of hepatocellular adenomas; female mice at this dose showed a greater incidence of whole body histocytic sarcomas. Male and female rats at an oral dose of 2000 mg/kg/day (resulting in approximately 160 times the exposure to drug plus metabolites from the maximum recommended daily oral dose in adults and in children based on a comparison of the plasma area-under the curve [AUC] values) of zafirlukast showed an increased incidence of urinary bladder transitional cell papillomas. Zafirlukast was not tumorigenic at oral doses up to 100 mg/kg (approximately 10 times the maximum recommended daily oral dose in adults and in children on a mg/m 2 basis) in mice and at oral doses up to 400 mg/kg (resulting in approximately 140 times the exposure to drug plus metabolites from the maximum recommended daily oral dose in adults and in children based on a comparison of the plasma AUC values) in rats. The clinical significance of these findings for the long-term use of ACCOLATE is unknown. Zafirlukast showed no evidence of mutagenic potential in the reverse microbial assay, in 2 forward point mutation (CHO-HGPRT and mouse lymphoma) assays or in two assays for chromosomal aberrations (the in vitro human peripheral blood lymphocyte clastogenic assay and the in vivo rat bone marrow micronucleus assay). No evidence of impairment of fertility and reproduction was seen in male and female rats treated with zafirlukast at oral doses up to 2000 mg/kg (approximately 410 times the maximum recommended daily oral dose in adults on a mg/m 2 basis). No teratogenicity was observed at oral doses up to 1600 mg/kg/day in mice (approximately 160 times the maximum recommended daily oral dose in adults on a mg/m 2 basis), up to 2000 mg/kg/day in rats (approximately 410 times the maximum recommended daily oral dose in adults on a mg/m 2 basis) and up to 2000 mg/kg/day in cynomolgus monkeys (which resulted in approximately 20 times the exposure to drug plus metabolites compared to that from the maximum recommended daily oral dose in adults based on comparison of the AUC values). At an oral dose of 2000 mg/kg/day in rats, maternal toxicity and deaths were seen with increased incidence of early fetal resorption. Spontaneous abortions occurred in cynomolgus monkeys at the maternally toxic oral dose of 2000 mg/kg/day. There are no adequate and well-controlled trials in pregnant women. Because animal reproductive studies are not always predictive of human response, ACCOLATE should be used during pregnancy only if clearly needed. Zafirlukast is excreted in breast milk. Following repeated 40 mg twice-a-day dosing in healthy women, average steady-state concentrations of zafirlukast in breast milk were 50 ng/mL compared to 255 ng/mL in plasma. Because of the potential for tumorigenicity shown for zafirlukast in mouse and rat studies and the enhanced sensitivity of neonatal rats and dogs to the adverse effects of zafirlukast, ACCOLATE should not be administered to mothers who are breast-feeding. The safety of ACCOLATE at doses of 10 mg twice daily has been demonstrated in 205 pediatric patients 5 through 11 years of age in placebo-controlled trials lasting up to six weeks and with 179 patients in this age range participating in 52 weeks of treatment in an open label extension. The effectiveness of ACCOLATE for the prophylaxis and chronic treatment of asthma in pediatric patients 5 through 11 years of age is based on an extrapolation of the demonstrated efficacy of ACCOLATE in adults with asthma and the likelihood that the disease course, and pathophysiology and the drug’s effect are substantially similar between the two populations. The recommended dose for the patients 5 through 11 years of age is based upon a cross-study comparison of the pharmacokinetics of zafirlukast in adults and pediatric subjects, and on the safety profile of zafirlukast in both adult and pediatric patients at doses equal to or higher than the recommended dose. The safety and effectiveness of zafirlukast for pediatric patients less than 5 years of age has not been established. The effect of ACCOLATE on growth in children has not been determined. Based on cross-study comparison, the clearance of zafirlukast is reduced in patients 65 years of age and older such that C max and AUC are approximately 2- to 3-fold greater than those of younger patients (see DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION and CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY ). A total of 8094 patients were exposed to zafirlukast in North American and European short-term placebo-controlled clinical trials. Of these, 243 patients were elderly (age 65 years and older). No overall difference in adverse events was seen in the elderly patients, except for an increase in the frequency of infections among zafirlukast-treated elderly patients compared to placebo-treated elderly patients (7.0% vs. 2.9%). The infections were not severe, occurred mostly in the lower respiratory tract, and did not necessitate withdrawal of therapy. An open-label, uncontrolled, 4-week trial of 3759 asthma patients compared the safety and efficacy of ACCOLATE 20 mg given twice daily in three patient age groups, adolescents (12-17 years), adults (18-65 years), and elderly (greater than 65 years). A higher percentage of elderly patients (n=384) reported adverse events when compared to adults and adolescents. These elderly patients showed less improvement in efficacy measures. In the elderly patients, adverse events occurring in greater than 1% of the population included headache (4.7%), diarrhea and nausea (1.8%), and pharyngitis (1.3%). The elderly reported the lowest percentage of infections of all three age groups in this study.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS SECTION" id="34071-1">
Cases of life-threatening hepatic failure have been reported in patients treated with ACCOLATE. Cases of liver injury without other attributable cause have been reported from post-marketing adverse event surveillance of patients who have received the recommended dose of ACCOLATE (40 mg/day). In most, but not all post-marketing reports, the patient’s symptoms abated and the liver enzymes returned to normal or near normal after stopping ACCOLATE. In rare cases, patients have either presented with fulminant hepatitis or progressed to hepatic failure, liver transplantation and death. In extremely rare post-marketing cases, no clinical symptoms or signs suggestive of liver dysfunction were reported to precede the latter observations. Physicians may consider the value of liver function testing. Periodic serum transaminase testing has not proven to prevent serious injury but it is generally believed that early detection of drug-induced hepatic injury along with immediate withdrawal of the suspect drug enhances the likelihood for recovery. Patients should be advised to be alert for signs and symptoms of liver dysfunction (eg, right upper quadrant abdominal pain, nausea, fatigue, lethargy, pruritus, jaundice, flu-like symptoms, and anorexia) and to contact their physician immediately if they occur. Ongoing clinical assessment of patients should govern physician interventions, including diagnostic evaluations and treatment. If liver dysfunction is suspected based upon clinical signs or symptoms (eg, right upper quadrant abdominal pain, nausea, fatigue, lethargy, pruritus, jaundice, flu-like symptoms, anorexia, and enlarged liver), ACCOLATE should be discontinued. Liver function tests, in particular serum ALT, should be measured immediately and the patient managed accordingly. If liver function tests are consistent with hepatic dysfunction, ACCOLATE therapy should not be resumed. Patients in whom ACCOLATE was withdrawn because of hepatic dysfunction where no other attributable cause is identified should not be re-exposed to ACCOLATE (see PRECAUTIONS, Information for Patients and ADVERSE REACTIONS ). ACCOLATE is not indicated for use in the reversal of bronchospasm in acute asthma attacks, including status asthmaticus. Therapy with ACCOLATE can be continued during acute exacerbations of asthma. Coadministration of zafirlukast with warfarin results in a clinically significant increase in prothrombin time (PT). Patients on oral warfarin anticoagulant therapy and ACCOLATE should have their prothrombin times monitored closely and anticoagulant dose adjusted accordingly (see PRECAUTIONS, Drug Interactions ).</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Zafirlukast is a selective and competitive receptor antagonist of leukotriene D 4 and E 4 (LTD 4 and LTE 4 ), components of slow-reacting substance of anaphylaxis (SRSA). Cysteinyl leukotriene production and receptor occupation have been correlated with the pathophysiology of asthma, including airway edema, smooth muscle constriction, and altered cellular activity associated with the inflammatory process, which contribute to the signs and symptoms of asthma. Patients with asthma were found in one study to be 25-100 times more sensitive to the bronchoconstricting activity of inhaled LTD 4 than nonasthmatic subjects. In vitro studies demonstrated that zafirlukast antagonized the contractile activity of three leukotrienes (LTC 4 , LTD 4 and LTE 4 ) in conducting airway smooth muscle from laboratory animals and humans. Zafirlukast prevented intradermal LTD 4 -induced increases in cutaneous vascular permeability and inhibited inhaled LTD 4 -induced influx of eosinophils into animal lungs. Inhalational challenge studies in sensitized sheep showed that zafirlukast suppressed the airway responses to antigen; this included both the early- and late-phase response and the nonspecific hyperresponsiveness. In humans, zafirlukast inhibited bronchoconstriction caused by several kinds of inhalational challenges. Pretreatment with single oral doses of zafirlukast inhibited the bronchoconstriction caused by sulfur dioxide and cold air in patients with asthma. Pretreatment with single doses of zafirlukast attenuated the early- and late-phase reaction caused by inhalation of various antigens such as grass, cat dander, ragweed, and mixed antigens in patients with asthma. Zafirlukast also attenuated the increase in bronchial hyperresponsiveness to inhaled histamine that followed inhaled allergen challenge. Zafirlukast is rapidly absorbed following oral administration. Peak plasma concentrations are generally achieved 3 hours after oral administration. The absolute bioavailability of zafirlukast is unknown. In two separate studies, one using a high fat and the other a high protein meal, administration of zafirlukast with food reduced the mean bioavailability by approximately 40%. Zafirlukast is more than 99% bound to plasma proteins, predominantly albumin. The degree of binding was independent of concentration in the clinically relevant range. The apparent steady-state volume of distribution (Vss/F) is approximately 70 L, suggesting moderate distribution into tissues. Studies in rats using radiolabeled zafirlukast indicate minimal distribution across the blood-brain barrier. Zafirlukast is extensively metabolized. The most common metabolic products are hydroxylated metabolites which are excreted in the feces. The metabolites of zafirlukast identified in plasma are at least 90 times less potent as LTD 4 receptor antagonists than zafirlukast in a standard in vitro test of activity. In vitro studies using human liver microsomes showed that the hydroxylated metabolites of zafirlukast excreted in the feces are formed through the cytochrome P450 2C9 (CYP2C9) pathway. Additional in vitro studies utilizing human liver microsomes show that zafirlukast inhibits the cytochrome P450 CYP3A4 and CYP2C9 isoenzymes at concentrations close to the clinically achieved total plasma concentrations (see Drug Interactions ). The apparent oral clearance (CL/f) of zafirlukast is approximately 20 L/h. Studies in the rat and dog suggest that biliary excretion is the primary route of excretion. Following oral administration of radiolabeled zafirlukast to volunteers, urinary excretion accounts for approximately 10% of the dose and the remainder is excreted in feces. Zafirlukast is not detected in urine. In the pivotal bioequivalence study, the mean terminal half-life of zafirlukast is approximately 10 hours in both normal adult subjects and patients with asthma. In other studies, the mean plasma half-life of zafirlukast ranged from approximately 8 to 16 hours in both normal subjects and patients with asthma. The pharmacokinetics of zafirlukast are approximately linear over the range from 5 mg to 80 mg. Steady-state plasma concentrations of zafirlukast are proportional to the dose and predictable from single-dose pharmacokinetic data. Accumulation of zafirlukast in the plasma following twice-daily dosing is approximately 45%. The pharmacokinetic parameters of zafirlukast 20 mg administered as a single dose to 36 male volunteers are shown with the table below. Mean (%Coefficient of Variation) pharmacokinetic parameters of zafirlukast following single 20 mg oral dose administration to male volunteers (n=36) C max ng/ml t max Median and range h AUC ng•h/mL t 1/2 h CL/f L/h 326 (31.0) 2 (0.5 - 5.0) 1137 (34) 13.3 (75.6) 19.4 (32) Gender: The pharmacokinetics of zafirlukast are similar in males and females. Weight-adjusted apparent oral clearance does not differ due to gender. Race: No differences in the pharmacokinetics of zafirlukast due to race have been observed. Elderly: The apparent oral clearance of zafirlukast decreases with age. In patients above 65 years of age, there is an approximately 2-3 fold greater C max and AUC compared to young adult patients. Children: Following administration of a single 20 mg dose of zafirlukast to 20 boys and girls between 7 and 11 years of age, and in a second study, to 29 boys and girls between 5 and 6 years of age, the following pharmacokinetic parameters were obtained: Parameter Children age 5-6 years Mean (%Coefficient of Variation) Children age 7-11 years Mean (% Coefficient of Variation) C max (ng/mL) 756 (39%) 601 (45%) AUC (ng•h/mL) 2458 (34%) 2027 (38%) t max (h) 2.1 (61%) 2.5 (55%) CL/f (L/h) 9.2 (37%) 11.4 (42%) Weight unadjusted apparent clearance was 11.4 L/h (42%) in the 7-11 year old children and 9.2 L/h (37%) in the 5-6 year old children, which resulted in greater systemic drug exposures than that obtained in adults for an identical dose. To maintain similar exposure levels in children compared to adults, a dose of 10 mg twice daily is recommended in children 5-11 years of age (see DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION ). Zafirlukast disposition was unchanged after multiple dosing (20 mg twice daily) in children and the degree of accumulation in plasma was similar to that observed in adults. Hepatic Insufficiency: In a study of patients with hepatic impairment (biopsy-proven cirrhosis), there was a reduced clearance of zafirlukast resulting in a 50-60% greater C max and AUC compared to normal subjects. Renal Insufficiency: Based on a cross-study comparison, there are no apparent differences in the pharmacokinetics of zafirlukast between renally-impaired patients and normal subjects. Drug-Drug Interactions: The following drug interaction studies have been conducted with zafirlukast (see PRECAUTIONS, Drug Interactions ). ● Coadministration of multiple doses of zafirlukast (160 mg/day) to steady-state with a single 25 mg dose of warfarin (a substrate of CYP2C9) resulted in a significant increase in the mean AUC (+63%) and half-life (+36%) of S-warfarin. The mean prothrombin time increased by approximately 35%. The pharmacokinetics of zafirlukast were unaffected by coadministration with warfarin. ● Coadministration of zafirlukast (80 mg/day) at steady-state with a single dose of a liquid theophylline preparation (6 mg/kg) in 13 asthmatic patients, 18 to 44 years of age, resulted in decreased mean plasma concentrations of zafirlukast by approximately 30%, but no effect on plasma theophylline concentrations was observed. ● Coadministration of zafirlukast (20 mg/day) or placebo at steady-state with a single dose of sustained release theophylline preparation (16 mg/kg) in 16 healthy boys and girls (6 through 11 years of age) resulted in no significant differences in the pharmacokinetic parameters of theophylline. ● Coadministration of zafirlukast dosed at 40 mg twice daily in a single-blind, parallel-group, 3-week study in 39 healthy female subjects taking oral contraceptives, resulted in no significant effect on ethinyl estradiol plasma concentrations or contraceptive efficacy. ● Coadministration of zafirlukast (40 mg/day) with aspirin (650 mg four times daily) resulted in mean increased plasma concentrations of zafirlukast by approximately 45%. ● Coadministration of a single dose of zafirlukast (40 mg) with erythromycin (500 mg three times daily for 5 days) to steady-state in 11 asthmatic patients resulted in decreased mean plasma concentrations of zafirlukast by approximately 40% due to a decrease in zafirlukast bioavailability. Three U.S. double-blind, randomized, placebo-controlled, 13-week clinical trials in 1380 adults and children 12 years of age and older with mild-to-moderate asthma demonstrated that ACCOLATE improved daytime asthma symptoms, nighttime awakenings, mornings with asthma symptoms, rescue beta 2 -agonist use, FEV 1 , and morning peak expiratory flow rate. In these studies, the patients had a mean baseline FEV 1 of approximately 75% of predicted normal and a mean baseline beta 2 -agonist requirement of approximately 4-5 puffs of albuterol per day. The results of the largest of the trials are shown in the table below. Mean Change from Baseline at Study End Point ACCOLATE 20 mg twice daily N=514 Placebo N=248 Daytime Asthma symptom score (0-3 scale) -0.44 p&amp;lt;0.05, compared to placebo -0.25 Nightime Awakenings (number per week) -1.27 -0.43 Mornings with Asthma Symptoms (days per week) -1.32 -0.75 Rescue β 2 -agonist use (puffs per day) -1.15 -0.24 FEV 1 (L) +0.15 +0.05 Morning PEFR (L/min) +22.06 +7.63 Evening PEFR (L/min) +13.12 +10.14 In a second and smaller study, the effect of ACCOLATE on most efficacy parameters was comparable to the active control (inhaled cromolyn sodium 1600 mcg four times per day) and superior to placebo at end point for decreasing rescue beta 2 -agonist use (figure below). In these trials, improvement in asthma symptoms occurred within one week of initiating treatment with ACCOLATE. The role of ACCOLATE in the management of patients with more severe asthma, patients receiving antiasthma therapy other than as-needed, inhaled beta 2 -agonists, or as an oral or inhaled corticosteroid-sparing agent remains to be fully characterized. Table displaying beta2 agonist use</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="3377" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>ACCOLATE is contraindicated in patients who are hypersensitive to zafirlukast or any of its inactive ingredients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3378" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Because food can reduce the bioavailability of zafirlukast, ACCOLATE should be taken at least 1 hour before or 2 hours after meals.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M1" type="Trigger" span="17 26" str="reduce the bioavailability"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="8 4" str="food" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M3" type="Trigger" span="69 15;101 9;119 5" str="should be taken | before or | after"/>
<Mention id="M4" type="Precipitant" span="125 5" str="meals" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M1" precipitant="M2" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M3" precipitant="M4"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3379" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommended dose of ACCOLATE in adults and children 12 years and older is 20 mg twice daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3380" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommended dose of ACCOLATE in children 5 through 11 years of age is 10 mg twice daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3381" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Elderly Patients: Based on cross-study comparisons, the clearance of zafirlukast is reduced in elderly patients (65 years of age and older), such that Cmax and AUC are approximately twice those of younger adults.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3382" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In clinical trials, a dose of 20 mg twice daily was not associated with an increase in the overall incidence of adverse events or withdrawals because of adverse events in elderly patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3383" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Patients with Hepatic Impairment: The clearance of zafirlukast is reduced in patients with stable alcoholic cirrhosis such that the Cmax and AUC are approximately 50 - 60% greater than those of normal adults.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3384" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>ACCOLATE has not been evaluated in patients with hepatitis or in long-term studies of patients with cirrhosis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3385" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Patients with Renal Impairment: Dosage adjustment is not required for patients with renal impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3386" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>In a drug interaction study in 16 healthy male volunteers, coadministration of multiple doses of zafirlukast (160 mg/day) to steady-state with a single 25 mg dose of warfarin resulted in a significant increase in the mean AUC (+ 63%) and half-life (+36%) of S-warfarin.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M5" type="Trigger" span="201 8;222 3" str="increase | AUC"/>
<Mention id="M8" type="Precipitant" span="166 8" str="warfarin" code="5Q7ZVV76EI | N0000006403"/>
<Mention id="M7" type="Trigger" span="201 8;238 9" str="increase | half-life"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M5" precipitant="M8" effect="C54613"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M7" precipitant="M8" effect="C54611"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3387" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The mean prothrombin time (PT) increased by approximately 35%.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3388" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>This interaction is probably due to an inhibition by zafirlukast of the cytochrome P450 2C9 isoenzyme system.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3389" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Patients on oral warfarin anticoagulant therapy and ACCOLATE should have their prothrombin times monitored closely and anticoagulant dose adjusted accordingly.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M12" type="Trigger" span="97 9" str="monitored"/>
<Mention id="M18" type="Precipitant" span="12 27" str="oral warfarin anticoagulant" code="5Q7ZVV76EI"/>
<Mention id="M14" type="SpecificInteraction" span="79 17" str="prothrombin times" code="165568006: Prothrombin time abnormal (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M20" type="Precipitant" span="17 8" str="warfarin" code="5Q7ZVV76EI | N0000006403"/>
<Mention id="M19" type="Trigger" span="133 13" str="dose adjusted"/>
<Mention id="M16" type="Precipitant" span="26 13" str="anticoagulant" code="N0000175980"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M12" precipitant="M18" effect="M14" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M12" precipitant="M20" effect="M14" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M19" precipitant="M16"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M19" precipitant="M18"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M19" precipitant="M20"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3390" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>No formal drug-drug interaction studies with ACCOLATE and other drugs known to be metabolized by the cytochrome P450 2C9 isoenzyme (eg, tolbutamide, phenytoin, carbamazepine) have been conducted; however, care should be exercised when ACCOLATE is coadministered with these drugs.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M27" type="Trigger" span="205 24" str="care should be exercised"/>
<Mention id="M22" type="Precipitant" span="160 13" str="carbamazepine" code="33CM23913M | N0000007470"/>
<Mention id="M24" type="Precipitant" span="64 66" str="drugs known to be metabolized by the cytochrome P450 2C9 isoenzyme" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M26" type="Precipitant" span="149 9" str="phenytoin" code="6158TKW0C5 | N0000006023"/>
<Mention id="M28" type="Precipitant" span="136 11" str="tolbutamide" code="982XCM1FOI"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M27" precipitant="M22"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M27" precipitant="M24"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M27" precipitant="M26"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M27" precipitant="M28"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3391" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>In a drug interaction study in 11 asthmatic patients, coadministration of a single dose of zafirlukast (40 mg) with erythromycin (500 mg three times daily for 5 days) to steady-state resulted in decreased mean plasma levels of zafirlukast by approximately 40% due to a decrease in zafirlukast bioavailability.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M29" type="Trigger" span="195 28" str="decreased mean plasma levels "/>
<Mention id="M30" type="Trigger" span="195 8;293 15" str=" decrease | bioavailability"/>
<Mention id="M31" type="Precipitant" span="116 12" str="erythromycin" code="N0000007133 | 63937KV33D"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M29;M30" precipitant="M31" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3392" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Coadministration of zafirlukast (20 mg/day) or placebo at steady-state with a single dose of sustained release theophylline preparation (16 mg/kg) in 16 healthy boys and girls (6 through 11 years of age) resulted in no significant differences in the pharmacokinetic parameters of theophylline.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3393" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Coadministration of zafirlukast (80 mg/day) at steady-state with a single dose of a liquid theophylline preparation (6 mg/kg) in 13 asthmatic patients, 18 to 44 years of age, resulted in decreased mean plasma levels of zafirlukast by approximately 30%, but no effect on plasma theophylline levels was observed.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M32" type="Trigger" span="187 28" str="decreased mean plasma levels"/>
<Mention id="M33" type="Precipitant" span="84 19" str="liquid theophylline" code="C137DTR5RG"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M32" precipitant="M33" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3394" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Rare cases of patients experiencing increased theophylline levels with or without clinical signs or symptoms of theophylline toxicity after the addition of ACCOLATE to an existing theophylline regimen have been reported.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M34" type="Trigger" span="36 9;59 6" str="increased | levels"/>
<Mention id="M35" type="Precipitant" span="46 12" str="theophylline" code="N0000007076 | C137DTR5RG"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M34" precipitant="M35" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3395" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The mechanism of the interaction between ACCOLATE and theophylline in these patients is unknown.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M36" type="Trigger" span="21 19" str="interaction between"/>
<Mention id="M37" type="Precipitant" span="54 12" str="theophylline" code="N0000007076 | C137DTR5RG"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M36" precipitant="M37"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3396" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Coadministration of zafirlukast (40 mg/day) with aspirin (650 mg four times daily) resulted in mean increased plasma levels of zafirlukast by approximately 45%.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M38" type="Trigger" span="100 23" str="increased plasma levels"/>
<Mention id="M39" type="Precipitant" span="49 7" str="aspirin" code="N0000006582 | R16CO5Y76E"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M38" precipitant="M39" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3397" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>In a single-blind, parallel-group, 3-week study in 39 healthy female subjects taking oral contraceptives, 40 mg twice daily of zafirlukast had no significant effect on ethinyl estradiol plasma concentrations or contraceptive efficacy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3398" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>No formal drug-drug interaction studies between ACCOLATE and marketed drugs known to be metabolized by the P450 3A4 (CYP3A4) isoenzyme (eg, dihydropyridine calcium-channel blockers, cyclosporin, cisapride) have been conducted.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3399" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>As ACCOLATE is known to be an inhibitor of CYP3A4 in vitro, it is reasonable to employ appropriate clinical monitoring when these drugs are coadministered with ACCOLATE.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M40" type="Trigger" span="30 9" str="inhibitor "/>
<Mention id="M41" type="Trigger" span="108 10" str=" monitoring"/>
<Mention id="M42" type="Precipitant" span="43 6;130 5" str="CYP3A4 | drugs" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M40;M41" precipitant="M42"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3400" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Patients should be told that a rare side effect of ACCOLATE is hepatic dysfunction, and to contact their physician immediately if they experience symptoms of hepatic dysfunction (eg. right upper quadrant abdominal pain, nausea, fatigue, lethargy, pruritus, jaundice, flu-like symptoms, and anorexia).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3401" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Liver failure resulting in liver transplantation and death has occurred in patients taking zafirlukast.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3402" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>ACCOLATE is indicated for the chronic treatment of asthma and should be taken regularly as prescribed, even during symptom-free periods.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3403" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>ACCOLATE is not a bronchodilator and should not be used to treat acute episodes of asthma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3404" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Patients receiving ACCOLATE should be instructed not to decrease the dose or stop taking any other antiasthma medications unless instructed by a physician.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3405" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Patients should be instructed to notify their physician if neuropsychiatric events occur while using ACCOLATE.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3406" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Women who are breast-feeding should be instructed not to take ACCOLATE.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3407" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Alternative antiasthma medication should be considered in such patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3408" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The bioavailability of ACCOLATE may be decreased when taken with food.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M43" type="Trigger" span="4 15;39 9" str="bioavailability | decreased"/>
<Mention id="M44" type="Precipitant" span="65 4" str="food" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M43" precipitant="M44" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3409" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Patients should be instructed to take ACCOLATE at least 1 hour before or 2 hours after meals.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M45" type="Trigger" span="33 4;63 9;81 5" str="take | before or | after"/>
<Mention id="M46" type="Precipitant" span="87 5" str="meals" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M45" precipitant="M46"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3410" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In rare cases, patients on ACCOLATE therapy may present with systemic eosinophilia, eosinophilic pneumonia, or clinical features of vasculitis consistent with Churg-Strauss syndrome, a condition which is often treated with systemic steroid therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3411" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>These events usually, but not always, have been associated with the reduction of oral steroid therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3412" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Physicians should be alert to eosinophilia, vasculitic rash, worsening pulmonary symptoms, cardiac complications, and/or neuropathy presenting in their patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3413" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>A causal association between ACCOLATE and these underlying conditions has not been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3414" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Neuropsychiatric events have been reported in adult, adolescent and pediatric patients taking ACCOLATE.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3415" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Post-marketing reports with ACCOLATE include insomnia and depression.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3416" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The clinical details of some post-marketing reports involving ACCOLATE appear consistent with a drug-induced effect.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3417" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Patients and prescribers should be alert for neuropsychiatric events.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3418" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Patients should be instructed to notify their prescriber if these changes occur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3419" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Prescribers should carefully evaluate the risks and benefits of continuing treatment with ACCOLATE if such events occur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3420" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In two-year carcinogenicity studies, zafirlukast was administered at dietary doses of 10, 100, and 300 mg/kg to mice and 40, 400, and 2000 mg/kg to rats.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3421" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Male mice at an oral dose of 300 mg/kg/day (approximately 30 times the maximum recommended daily oral dose in adults and in children on a mg/m2 basis) showed an increased incidence of hepatocellular adenomas; female mice at this dose showed a greater incidence of whole body histocytic sarcomas.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3422" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Male and female rats at an oral dose of 2000 mg/kg/day (resulting in approximately 160 times the exposure to drug plus metabolites from the maximum recommended daily oral dose in adults and in children based on a comparison of the plasma area-under the curve [AUC] values) of zafirlukast showed an increased incidence of urinary bladder transitional cell papillomas.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3423" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Zafirlukast was not tumorigenic at oral doses up to 100 mg/kg (approximately 10 times the maximum recommended daily oral dose in adults and in children on a mg/m2 basis) in mice and at oral doses up to 400 mg/kg (resulting in approximately 140 times the exposure to drug plus metabolites from the maximum recommended daily oral dose in adults and in children based on a comparison of the plasma AUC values) in rats.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3424" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The clinical significance of these findings for the long-term use of ACCOLATE is unknown.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3425" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Zafirlukast showed no evidence of mutagenic potential in the reverse microbial assay, in 2 forward point mutation (CHO-HGPRT and mouse lymphoma) assays or in two assays for chromosomal aberrations (the in vitro human peripheral blood lymphocyte clastogenic assay and the in vivo rat bone marrow micronucleus assay).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3426" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>No evidence of impairment of fertility and reproduction was seen in male and female rats treated with zafirlukast at oral doses up to 2000 mg/kg (approximately 410 times the maximum recommended daily oral dose in adults on a mg/m2 basis).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3427" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>No teratogenicity was observed at oral doses up to 1600 mg/kg/day in mice (approximately 160 times the maximum recommended daily oral dose in adults on a mg/m2 basis), up to 2000 mg/kg/day in rats (approximately 410 times the maximum recommended daily oral dose in adults on a mg/m2 basis) and up to 2000 mg/kg/day in cynomolgus monkeys (which resulted in approximately 20 times the exposure to drug plus metabolites compared to that from the maximum recommended daily oral dose in adults based on comparison of the AUC values).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3428" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>At an oral dose of 2000 mg/kg/day in rats, maternal toxicity and deaths were seen with increased incidence of early fetal resorption.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3429" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Spontaneous abortions occurred in cynomolgus monkeys at the maternally toxic oral dose of 2000 mg/kg/day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3430" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>There are no adequate and well-controlled trials in pregnant women.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3431" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because animal reproductive studies are not always predictive of human response, ACCOLATE should be used during pregnancy only if clearly needed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3432" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Following repeated 40 mg twice-a-day dosing in healthy women, average steady-state concentrations of zafirlukast in breast milk were 50 ng/mL compared to 255 ng/mL in plasma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3433" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because of the potential for tumorigenicity shown for zafirlukast in mouse and rat studies and the enhanced sensitivity of neonatal rats and dogs to the adverse effects of zafirlukast, ACCOLATE should not be administered to mothers who are breast-feeding.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3434" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The safety of ACCOLATE at doses of 10 mg twice daily has been demonstrated in 205 pediatric patients 5 through 11 years of age in placebo-controlled trials lasting up to six weeks and with 179 patients in this age range participating in 52 weeks of treatment in an open label extension.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3435" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The effectiveness of ACCOLATE for the prophylaxis and chronic treatment of asthma in pediatric patients 5 through 11 years of age is based on an extrapolation of the demonstrated efficacy of ACCOLATE in adults with asthma and the likelihood that the disease course, and pathophysiology and the drug’s effect are substantially similar between the two populations.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3436" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The recommended dose for the patients 5 through 11 years of age is based upon a cross-study comparison of the pharmacokinetics of zafirlukast in adults and pediatric subjects, and on the safety profile of zafirlukast in both adult and pediatric patients at doses equal to or higher than the recommended dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3437" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The safety and effectiveness of zafirlukast for pediatric patients less than 5 years of age has not been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3438" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The effect of ACCOLATE on growth in children has not been determined.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3439" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Based on cross-study comparison, the clearance of zafirlukast is reduced in patients 65 years of age and older such that Cmax and AUC are approximately 2- to 3-fold greater than those of younger patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3440" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>A total of 8094 patients were exposed to zafirlukast in North American and European short-term placebo-controlled clinical trials.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3441" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Of these, 243 patients were elderly (age 65 years and older).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3442" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>No overall difference in adverse events was seen in the elderly patients, except for an increase in the frequency of infections among zafirlukast-treated elderly patients compared to placebo-treated elderly patients (7.0% vs. 2.9%).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3443" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The infections were not severe, occurred mostly in the lower respiratory tract, and did not necessitate withdrawal of therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3444" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>An open-label, uncontrolled, 4-week trial of 3759 asthma patients compared the safety and efficacy of ACCOLATE 20 mg given twice daily in three patient age groups, adolescents (12-17 years), adults (18-65 years), and elderly (greater than 65 years).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3445" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>A higher percentage of elderly patients (n=384) reported adverse events when compared to adults and adolescents.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3446" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>These elderly patients showed less improvement in efficacy measures.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3447" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In the elderly patients, adverse events occurring in greater than 1% of the population included headache (4.7%), diarrhea and nausea (1.8%), and pharyngitis (1.3%).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3448" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The elderly reported the lowest percentage of infections of all three age groups in this study.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3449" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Cases of life-threatening hepatic failure have been reported in patients treated with ACCOLATE.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3450" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Cases of liver injury without other attributable cause have been reported from post-marketing adverse event surveillance of patients who have received the recommended dose of ACCOLATE (40 mg/day).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3451" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>In most, but not all post-marketing reports, the patient’s symptoms abated and the liver enzymes returned to normal or near normal after stopping ACCOLATE.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3452" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>In rare cases, patients have either presented with fulminant hepatitis or progressed to hepatic failure, liver transplantation and death.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3453" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>In extremely rare post-marketing cases, no clinical symptoms or signs suggestive of liver dysfunction were reported to precede the latter observations.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3454" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Physicians may consider the value of liver function testing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3455" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Periodic serum transaminase testing has not proven to prevent serious injury but it is generally believed that early detection of drug-induced hepatic injury along with immediate withdrawal of the suspect drug enhances the likelihood for recovery.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3456" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Patients should be advised to be alert for signs and symptoms of liver dysfunction (eg, right upper quadrant abdominal pain, nausea, fatigue, lethargy, pruritus, jaundice, flu-like symptoms, and anorexia) and to contact their physician immediately if they occur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3457" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Ongoing clinical assessment of patients should govern physician interventions, including diagnostic evaluations and treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3458" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>If liver dysfunction is suspected based upon clinical signs or symptoms (eg, right upper quadrant abdominal pain, nausea, fatigue, lethargy, pruritus, jaundice, flu-like symptoms, anorexia, and enlarged liver), ACCOLATE should be discontinued.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3459" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Liver function tests, in particular serum ALT, should be measured immediately and the patient managed accordingly.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3460" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>If liver function tests are consistent with hepatic dysfunction, ACCOLATE therapy should not be resumed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3461" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Patients in whom ACCOLATE was withdrawn because of hepatic dysfunction where no other attributable cause is identified should not be re-exposed to ACCOLATE.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3462" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>ACCOLATE is not indicated for use in the reversal of bronchospasm in acute asthma attacks, including status asthmaticus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3463" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Therapy with ACCOLATE can be continued during acute exacerbations of asthma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3464" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Coadministration of zafirlukast with warfarin results in a clinically significant increase in prothrombin time (PT).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M47" type="Trigger" span="46 10" str="results in "/>
<Mention id="M48" type="Trigger" span="82 8" str=" increase"/>
<Mention id="M49" type="Precipitant" span="37 8" str="warfarin" code="5Q7ZVV76EI | N0000006403"/>
<Mention id="M50" type="SpecificInteraction" span="82 28" str="increase in prothrombin time" code="409674002: Prothrombin time increased (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M47;M48" precipitant="M49" effect="M50" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3465" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Zafirlukast is a selective and competitive receptor antagonist of leukotriene D4 and E4 (LTD4 and LTE4), components of slow-reacting substance of anaphylaxis (SRSA).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3466" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Cysteinyl leukotriene production and receptor occupation have been correlated with the pathophysiology of asthma, including airway edema, smooth muscle constriction, and altered cellular activity associated with the inflammatory process, which contribute to the signs and symptoms of asthma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3467" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Patients with asthma were found in one study to be 25-100 times more sensitive to the bronchoconstricting activity of inhaled LTD4 than nonasthmatic subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3468" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In vitro studies demonstrated that zafirlukast antagonized the contractile activity of three leukotrienes (LTC4, LTD4 and LTE4) in conducting airway smooth muscle from laboratory animals and humans.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3469" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Zafirlukast prevented intradermal LTD4-induced increases in cutaneous vascular permeability and inhibited inhaled LTD4-induced influx of eosinophils into animal lungs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3470" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Inhalational challenge studies in sensitized sheep showed that zafirlukast suppressed the airway responses to antigen; this included both the early- and late-phase response and the nonspecific hyperresponsiveness.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3471" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In humans, zafirlukast inhibited bronchoconstriction caused by several kinds of inhalational challenges.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3472" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Pretreatment with single oral doses of zafirlukast inhibited the bronchoconstriction caused by sulfur dioxide and cold air in patients with asthma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3473" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Pretreatment with single doses of zafirlukast attenuated the early- and late-phase reaction caused by inhalation of various antigens such as grass, cat dander, ragweed, and mixed antigens in patients with asthma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3474" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Zafirlukast also attenuated the increase in bronchial hyperresponsiveness to inhaled histamine that followed inhaled allergen challenge.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3475" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Zafirlukast is rapidly absorbed following oral administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3476" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Peak plasma concentrations are generally achieved 3 hours after oral administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3477" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The absolute bioavailability of zafirlukast is unknown.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3478" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In two separate studies, one using a high fat and the other a high protein meal, administration of zafirlukast with food reduced the mean bioavailability by approximately 40%.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M51" type="Trigger" span="121 32" str="reduced the mean bioavailability"/>
<Mention id="M52" type="Precipitant" span="116 4" str="food" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M51" precipitant="M52" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3479" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Zafirlukast is more than 99% bound to plasma proteins, predominantly albumin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3480" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The degree of binding was independent of concentration in the clinically relevant range.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3481" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The apparent steady-state volume of distribution (Vss/F) is approximately 70 L, suggesting moderate distribution into tissues.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3482" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Studies in rats using radiolabeled zafirlukast indicate minimal distribution across the blood-brain barrier.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3483" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The most common metabolic products are hydroxylated metabolites which are excreted in the feces.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3484" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The metabolites of zafirlukast identified in plasma are at least 90 times less potent as LTD4 receptor antagonists than zafirlukast in a standard in vitro test of activity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3485" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In vitro studies using human liver microsomes showed that the hydroxylated metabolites of zafirlukast excreted in the feces are formed through the cytochrome P450 2C9 (CYP2C9) pathway.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3486" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Additional in vitro studies utilizing human liver microsomes show that zafirlukast inhibits the cytochrome P450 CYP3A4 and CYP2C9 isoenzymes at concentrations close to the clinically achieved total plasma concentrations.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3487" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The apparent oral clearance (CL/f) of zafirlukast is approximately 20 L/h.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3488" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Studies in the rat and dog suggest that biliary excretion is the primary route of excretion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3489" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following oral administration of radiolabeled zafirlukast to volunteers, urinary excretion accounts for approximately 10% of the dose and the remainder is excreted in feces.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3490" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In the pivotal bioequivalence study, the mean terminal half-life of zafirlukast is approximately 10 hours in both normal adult subjects and patients with asthma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3491" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In other studies, the mean plasma half-life of zafirlukast ranged from approximately 8 to 16 hours in both normal subjects and patients with asthma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3492" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacokinetics of zafirlukast are approximately linear over the range from 5 mg to 80 mg. Steady-state plasma concentrations of zafirlukast are proportional to the dose and predictable from single-dose pharmacokinetic data.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3493" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Accumulation of zafirlukast in the plasma following twice-daily dosing is approximately 45%.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3494" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacokinetic parameters of zafirlukast 20 mg administered as a single dose to 36 male volunteers are shown with the table below.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3495" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Mean (%Coefficient of Variation) pharmacokinetic parameters of zafirlukast following single 20 mg oral dose administration to male volunteers (n=36) Cmax ng/ml tmax Median and range h AUC ngh/mL t1/2 h CL/f L/h 326 (31.0) 2 (0.5 - 5.0) 1137 (34) 13.3 (75.6) 19.4 (32) Gender: The pharmacokinetics of zafirlukast are similar in males and females.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3496" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Weight-adjusted apparent oral clearance does not differ due to gender.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3497" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Race: No differences in the pharmacokinetics of zafirlukast due to race have been observed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3498" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Elderly: The apparent oral clearance of zafirlukast decreases with age.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3499" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In patients above 65 years of age, there is an approximately 2-3 fold greater Cmax and AUC compared to young adult patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3500" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Children: Following administration of a single 20 mg dose of zafirlukast to 20 boys and girls between 7 and 11 years of age, and in a second study, to 29 boys and girls between 5 and 6 years of age, the following pharmacokinetic parameters were obtained: Parameter Children age 5-6 years Mean (%Coefficient of Variation) Children age 7-11 years Mean (% Coefficient of Variation) Cmax (ng/mL) 756 (39%) 601 (45%) AUC (ngh/mL) 2458 (34%) 2027 (38%) tmax (h) 2.1 (61%) 2.5 (55%) CL/f (L/h) 9.2 (37%) 11.4 (42%) Weight unadjusted apparent clearance was 11.4 L/h (42%) in the 7-11 year old children and 9.2 L/h (37%) in the 5-6 year old children, which resulted in greater systemic drug exposures than that obtained in adults for an identical dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3501" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>To maintain similar exposure levels in children compared to adults, a dose of 10 mg twice daily is recommended in children 5-11 years of age.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3502" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Zafirlukast disposition was unchanged after multiple dosing (20 mg twice daily) in children and the degree of accumulation in plasma was similar to that observed in adults.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3503" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Hepatic Insufficiency: In a study of patients with hepatic impairment (biopsy-proven cirrhosis), there was a reduced clearance of zafirlukast resulting in a 50-60% greater Cmax and AUC compared to normal subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3504" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Renal Insufficiency: Based on a cross-study comparison, there are no apparent differences in the pharmacokinetics of zafirlukast between renally-impaired patients and normal subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3505" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Drug-Drug Interactions: The following drug interaction studies have been conducted with zafirlukast.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3506" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>● Coadministration of multiple doses of zafirlukast (160 mg/day) to steady-state with a single 25 mg dose of warfarin (a substrate of CYP2C9) resulted in a significant increase in the mean AUC (+63%) and half-life (+36%) of S-warfarin.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M59" type="Trigger" span="168 8;189 3" str="increase | AUC"/>
<Mention id="M56" type="Precipitant" span="121 19" str="substrate of CYP2C9" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M57" type="Trigger" span="168 8;204 9" str="increase | half-life"/>
<Mention id="M60" type="Precipitant" span="109 8" str="warfarin" code="5Q7ZVV76EI | N0000006403"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M59" precipitant="M56" effect="C54613"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M57" precipitant="M56" effect="C54611"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M57" precipitant="M60" effect="C54611"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M59" precipitant="M60" effect="C54613"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3507" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mean prothrombin time increased by approximately 35%.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3508" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacokinetics of zafirlukast were unaffected by coadministration with warfarin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3509" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>● Coadministration of zafirlukast (80 mg/day) at steady-state with a single dose of a liquid theophylline preparation (6 mg/kg) in 13 asthmatic patients, 18 to 44 years of age, resulted in decreased mean plasma concentrations of zafirlukast by approximately 30%, but no effect on plasma theophylline concentrations was observed.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M61" type="Trigger" span="189 36" str="decreased mean plasma concentrations"/>
<Mention id="M62" type="Precipitant" span="86 19" str="liquid theophylline" code="C137DTR5RG"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M61" precipitant="M62" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3510" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>● Coadministration of zafirlukast (20 mg/day) or placebo at steady-state with a single dose of sustained release theophylline preparation (16 mg/kg) in 16 healthy boys and girls (6 through 11 years of age) resulted in no significant differences in the pharmacokinetic parameters of theophylline.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3511" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>● Coadministration of zafirlukast dosed at 40 mg twice daily in a single-blind, parallel-group, 3-week study in 39 healthy female subjects taking oral contraceptives, resulted in no significant effect on ethinyl estradiol plasma concentrations or contraceptive efficacy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3512" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>● Coadministration of zafirlukast (40 mg/day) with aspirin (650 mg four times daily) resulted in mean increased plasma concentrations of zafirlukast by approximately 45%.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M63" type="Trigger" span="102 31" str="increased plasma concentrations"/>
<Mention id="M64" type="Precipitant" span="51 7" str="aspirin" code="N0000006582 | R16CO5Y76E"/>
<Interaction id="I29" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M63" precipitant="M64" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3513" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>●; Coadministration of a single dose of zafirlukast (40 mg) with erythromycin (500 mg three times daily for 5 days) to steady-state in 11 asthmatic patients resulted in decreased mean plasma concentrations of zafirlukast by approximately 40% due to a decrease in zafirlukast bioavailability.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M65" type="Trigger" span="169 36" str="decreased mean plasma concentrations"/>
<Mention id="M66" type="Trigger" span="169 8;275 15" str=" decrease | bioavailability"/>
<Mention id="M67" type="Precipitant" span="65 12" str="erythromycin" code="N0000007133 | 63937KV33D"/>
<Interaction id="I30" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M65;M66" precipitant="M67" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3514" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Three U.S. double-blind, randomized, placebo-controlled, 13-week clinical trials in 1380 adults and children 12 years of age and older with mild-to-moderate asthma demonstrated that ACCOLATE improved daytime asthma symptoms, nighttime awakenings, mornings with asthma symptoms, rescue beta2-agonist use, FEV1, and morning peak expiratory flow rate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3515" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In these studies, the patients had a mean baseline FEV1 of approximately 75% of predicted normal and a mean baseline beta2-agonist requirement of approximately 4-5 puffs of albuterol per day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3516" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The results of the largest of the trials are shown in the table below.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3517" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Mean Change from Baseline at Study End Point ACCOLATE 20 mg twice daily N=514 Placebo N=248 Daytime Asthma symptom score (0-3 scale) -0.44p&lt;0.05, compared to placebo -0.25 Nightime Awakenings (number per week) -1.27 -0.43 Mornings with Asthma Symptoms (days per week) -1.32 -0.75 Rescue β2-agonist use (puffs per day) -1.15 -0.24 FEV1 (L) +0.15 +0.05 Morning PEFR (L/min) +22.06 +7.63 Evening PEFR (L/min) +13.12 +10.14 In a second and smaller study, the effect of ACCOLATE on most efficacy parameters was comparable to the active control (inhaled cromolyn sodium 1600 mcg four times per day) and superior to placebo at end point for decreasing rescue beta2-agonist use (figure below).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3518" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In these trials, improvement in asthma symptoms occurred within one week of initiating treatment with ACCOLATE.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3519" LabelDrug="ACCOLATE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The role of ACCOLATE in the management of patients with more severe asthma, patients receiving antiasthma therapy other than as-needed, inhaled beta2-agonists, or as an oral or inhaled corticosteroid-sparing agent remains to be fully characterized.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="food" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="meals" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="warfarin" precipitantCode="5Q7ZVV76EI | N0000006403" effect="165568006: Prothrombin time abnormal (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="warfarin" precipitantCode="5Q7ZVV76EI | N0000006403" effect="409674002: Prothrombin time increased (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="warfarin" precipitantCode="5Q7ZVV76EI | N0000006403" effect="C54611"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="warfarin" precipitantCode="5Q7ZVV76EI | N0000006403" effect="C54613"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="warfarin" precipitantCode="5Q7ZVV76EI | N0000006403"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="oral warfarin anticoagulant" precipitantCode="5Q7ZVV76EI" effect="165568006: Prothrombin time abnormal (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="oral warfarin anticoagulant" precipitantCode="5Q7ZVV76EI"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="anticoagulant" precipitantCode="N0000175980"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="carbamazepine" precipitantCode="33CM23913M | N0000007470"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="drugs known to be metabolized by the cytochrome p450 2c9 isoenzyme" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="phenytoin" precipitantCode="6158TKW0C5 | N0000006023"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="tolbutamide" precipitantCode="982XCM1FOI"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="erythromycin" precipitantCode="N0000007133 | 63937KV33D" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="liquid theophylline" precipitantCode="C137DTR5RG" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="theophylline" precipitantCode="N0000007076 | C137DTR5RG" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="theophylline" precipitantCode="N0000007076 | C137DTR5RG"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="aspirin" precipitantCode="N0000006582 | R16CO5Y76E" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="cyp3a4 | drugs" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="substrate of cyp2c9" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54611"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="substrate of cyp2c9" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54613"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>