<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Sandostatin" setid="4e2c9856-1836-49f0-9472-4dbeeb408f39">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
Sensitivity to this drug or any of its components.</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
Sandostatin ® (octreotide acetate) may be administered subcutaneously or intravenously. Subcutaneous injection is the usual route of administration of Sandostatin for control of symptoms. Pain with subcutaneous administration may be reduced by using the smallest volume that will deliver the desired dose. Multiple subcutaneous injections at the same site within short periods of time should be avoided. Sites should be rotated in a systematic manner. Parenteral drug products should be inspected visually for particulate matter and discoloration prior to administration . Do not use if particulates and/or discoloration are observed. Proper sterile technique should be used in the preparation of parenteral admixtures to minimize the possibility of microbial contamination. Sandostatin is not compatible in Total Parenteral Nutrition (TPN) solutions because of the formation of a glycosyl octreotide conjugate which may decrease the efficacy of the product. Sandostatin is stable in sterile isotonic saline solutions or sterile solutions of dextrose 5% in water for 24 hours. It may be diluted in volumes of 50-200 mL and infused intravenously over 15-30 minutes or administered by IV push over 3 minutes. In emergency situations (e.g., carcinoid crisis), it may be given by rapid bolus. The initial dosage is usually 50 mcg administered twice or three times daily. Upward dose titration is frequently required. Dosage information for patients with specific tumors follows. Dosage may be initiated at 50 mcg three times a day. Beginning with this low dose may permit adaptation to adverse gastrointestinal effects for patients who will require higher doses. IGF-I (somatomedin C) levels every 2 weeks can be used to guide titration. Alternatively, multiple growth hormone levels at 0-8 hours after Sandostatin ® (octreotide acetate) administration permit more rapid titration of dose. The goal is to achieve growth hormone levels less than 5 ng/mL or IGF-I (somatomedin C) levels less than 1.9 unit/mL in males and less than 2.2 unit/mL in females. The dose most commonly found to be effective is 100 mcg three times a day, but some patients require up to 500 mcg three times a day for maximum effectiveness. Doses greater than 300 mcg/day seldom result in additional biochemical benefit, and if an increase in dose fails to provide additional benefit, the dose should be reduced. IGF-I (somatomedin C) or growth hormone levels should be reevaluated at 6-month intervals. Sandostatin should be withdrawn yearly for approximately 4 weeks from patients who have received irradiation to assess disease activity. If growth hormone or IGF-I (somatomedin C) levels increase and signs and symptoms recur, Sandostatin therapy may be resumed. The suggested daily dosage of Sandostatin during the first 2 weeks of therapy ranges from 100-600 mcg/day in 2-4 divided doses (mean daily dosage is 300 mcg). In the clinical studies, the median daily maintenance dosage was approximately 450 mcg, but clinical and biochemical benefits were obtained in some patients with as little as 50 mcg, while others required doses up to 1500 mcg/day. However, experience with doses above 750 mcg/day is limited. Daily dosages of 200-300 mcg in 2-4 divided doses are recommended during the initial 2 weeks of therapy (range: 150-750 mcg) to control symptoms of the disease. On an individual basis, dosage may be adjusted to achieve a therapeutic response, but usually doses above 450 mcg/day are not required.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG &amp;amp; OR LABORATORY TEST INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34074-5">
No known interference exists with clinical laboratory tests, including amine or peptide determinations.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
Sandostatin has been associated with alterations in nutrient absorption, so it may have an effect on absorption of orally administered drugs. Concomitant administration of Sandostatin with cyclosporine may decrease blood levels of cyclosporine and result in transplant rejection. Patients receiving insulin, oral hypoglycemic agents, beta blockers, calcium channel blockers, or agents to control fluid and electrolyte balance, may require dose adjustments of these therapeutic agents. Concomitant administration of octreotide and bromocriptine increases the availability of bromocriptine. Limited published data indicate that somatostatin analogs might decrease the metabolic clearance of compounds known to be metabolized by cytochrome P450 enzymes, which may be due to the suppression of growth hormones. Since it cannot be excluded that octreotide may have this effect, other drugs mainly metabolized by CYP3A4 and which have a low therapeutic index (e.g., quinidine, terfenadine) should therefore be used with caution.</Section>
<Section name="PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="42232-9">
Sandostatin ® (octreotide acetate) alters the balance between the counter-regulatory hormones, insulin, glucagon and growth hormone, which may result in hypoglycemia or hyperglycemia. Sandostatin also suppresses secretion of thyroid stimulating hormone, which may result in hypothyroidism. Cardiac conduction abnormalities have also occurred during treatment with Sandostatin. However, the incidence of these adverse events during long-term therapy was determined vigorously only in acromegaly patients who, due to their underlying disease and/or the subsequent treatment they receive, are at an increased risk for the development of diabetes mellitus, hypothyroidism, and cardiovascular disease. Although the degree to which these abnormalities are related to Sandostatin therapy is not clear, new abnormalities of glycemic control, thyroid function and ECG developed during Sandostatin therapy as described below. Risk of Pregnancy with Normalization of IGF-1 and GH Although acromegaly may lead to infertility, there are reports of pregnancy in acromegalic women. In women with active acromegaly who have been unable to become pregnant, normalization of GH and IGF-1 may restore fertility. Female patients of childbearing potential should be advised to use adequate contraception during treatment with octreotide. The hypoglycemia or hyperglycemia which occurs during Sandostatin therapy is usually mild, but may result in overt diabetes mellitus or necessitate dose changes in insulin or other hypoglycemic agents. Hypoglycemia and hyperglycemia occurred on Sandostatin in 3% and 16% of acromegalic patients, respectively. Severe hyperglycemia, subsequent pneumonia, and death following initiation of Sandostatin therapy was reported in one patient with no history of hyperglycemia. In patients with concomitant Type I diabetes mellitus, Sandostatin Injection and Sandostatin LAR® Depot (octreotide acetate for injectable suspension) are likely to affect glucose regulation, and insulin requirements may be reduced. Symptomatic hypoglycemia, which may be severe, has been reported in these patients. In non-diabetics and Type II diabetics with partially intact insulin reserves, Sandostatin Injection or Sandostatin LAR Depot administration may result in decreases in plasma insulin levels and hyperglycemia. It is therefore recommended that glucose tolerance and antidiabetic treatment be periodically monitored during therapy with these drugs. In acromegalic patients, 12% developed biochemical hypothyroidism only, 8% developed goiter, and 4% required initiation of thyroid replacement therapy while receiving Sandostatin. Baseline and periodic assessment of thyroid function (TSH, total and/or free T 4 ) is recommended during chronic therapy. In acromegalics, bradycardia (&amp;lt; 50 bpm) developed in 25%; conduction abnormalities occurred in 10% and arrhythmias occurred in 9% of patients during Sandostatin therapy. Other EKG changes observed included QT prolongation, axis shifts, early repolarization, low voltage, R/S transition, and early R wave progression. These ECG changes are not uncommon in acromegalic patients. Dose adjustments in drugs such as beta-blockers that have bradycardia effects may be necessary. In one acromegalic patient with severe congestive heart failure, initiation of Sandostatin therapy resulted in worsening of CHF with improvement when drug was discontinued. Confirmation of a drug effect was obtained with a positive rechallenge. Several cases of pancreatitis have been reported in patients receiving Sandostatin therapy. Sandostatin may alter absorption of dietary fats in some patients. In patients with severe renal failure requiring dialysis, the half-life of Sandostatin may be increased, necessitating adjustment of the maintenance dosage. Depressed vitamin B 12 levels and abnormal Schilling’s tests have been observed in some patients receiving Sandostatin therapy, and monitoring of vitamin B 12 levels is recommended during chronic Sandostatin therapy. Careful instruction in sterile subcutaneous injection technique should be given to the patients and to other persons who may administer Sandostatin Injection. Laboratory tests that may be helpful as biochemical markers in determining and following patient response depend on the specific tumor. Based on diagnosis, measurement of the following substances may be useful in monitoring the progress of therapy: Acromegaly: Growth Hormone, IGF-I (somatomedin C) Responsiveness to Sandostatin may be evaluated by determining growth hormone levels at 1-4 hour intervals for 8-12 hours post dose. Alternatively, a single measurement of IGF-I (somatomedin C) level may be made two weeks after drug initiation or dosage change. Carcinoid: 5-HIAA (urinary 5-hydroxyindole acetic acid), plasma serotonin, plasma Substance P VIPoma: VIP (plasma vasoactive intestinal peptide) Baseline and periodic total and/or free T 4 measurements should be performed during chronic therapy ( see PRECAUTIONS – General ). Sandostatin has been associated with alterations in nutrient absorption, so it may have an effect on absorption of orally administered drugs. Concomitant administration of Sandostatin with cyclosporine may decrease blood levels of cyclosporine and result in transplant rejection. Patients receiving insulin, oral hypoglycemic agents, beta blockers, calcium channel blockers, or agents to control fluid and electrolyte balance, may require dose adjustments of these therapeutic agents. Concomitant administration of octreotide and bromocriptine increases the availability of bromocriptine. Limited published data indicate that somatostatin analogs might decrease the metabolic clearance of compounds known to be metabolized by cytochrome P450 enzymes, which may be due to the suppression of growth hormones. Since it cannot be excluded that octreotide may have this effect, other drugs mainly metabolized by CYP3A4 and which have a low therapeutic index (e.g., quinidine, terfenadine) should therefore be used with caution. No known interference exists with clinical laboratory tests, including amine or peptide determinations. Studies in laboratory animals have demonstrated no mutagenic potential of Sandostatin. No carcinogenic potential was demonstrated in mice treated subcutaneously for 85-99 weeks at doses up to 2000 mcg/kg/day (8 x the human exposure based on body surface area). In a 116-week subcutaneous study in rats, a 27% and 12% incidence of injection site sarcomas or squamous cell carcinomas was observed in males and females, respectively, at the highest dose level of 1250 mcg/kg/day (10 x the human exposure based on body surface area) compared to an incidence of 8%-10% in the vehicle-control groups. The increased incidence of injection site tumors was most probably caused by irritation and the high sensitivity of the rat to repeated subcutaneous injections at the same site. Rotating injection sites would prevent chronic irritation in humans. There have been no reports of injection site tumors in patients treated with Sandostatin for up to 5 years. There was also a 15% incidence of uterine adenocarcinomas in the 1250 mcg/kg/day females compared to 7% in the saline-control females and 0% in the vehicle-control females. The presence of endometritis coupled with the absence of corpora lutea, the reduction in mammary fibroadenomas, and the presence of uterine dilatation suggest that the uterine tumors were associated with estrogen dominance in the aged female rats which does not occur in humans. Sandostatin did not impair fertility in rats at doses up to 1000 mcg/kg/day, which represents 7x the human exposure based on body surface area. There are no adequate and well-controlled studies of octreotide use in pregnant women. Reproduction studies have been performed in rats and rabbits at doses up to 16 times the highest recommended human dose based on body surface area and revealed no evidence of harm to the fetus due to octreotide. However, because animal reproduction studies are not always predictive of human response, this drug should be used during pregnancy only if clearly needed. In postmarketing data, a limited number of exposed pregnancies have been reported in patients with acromegaly. Most women were exposed to octreotide during the first trimester of pregnancy at doses ranging from 100-300 mcg/day of Sandostatin s.c. or 20-30 mg/month of Sandostatin LAR, however some women elected to continue octreotide therapy throughout pregnancy. In cases with a known outcome, no congenital malformations were reported. It is not known whether octreotide is excreted into human milk. Because many drugs are excreted in human milk, caution should be exercised when octreotide is administered to a nursing woman. Safety and efficacy of Sandostatin Injection in the pediatric population have not been demonstrated. No formal controlled clinical trials have been performed to evaluate the safety and effectiveness of Sandostatin in pediatric patients under age 6 years. In post-marketing reports, serious adverse events, including hypoxia, necrotizing enterocolitis, and death, have been reported with Sandostatin use in children, most notably in children under 2 years of age. The relationship of these events to octreotide has not been established as the majority of these pediatric patients had serious underlying co-morbid conditions. The efficacy and safety of Sandostatin using the Sandostatin LAR Depot formulation was examined in a single randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, six month pharmacokinetics study in 60 pediatric patient's age 6-17 years with hypothalamic obesity resulting from cranial insult. The mean octreotide concentration after 6 doses of 40 mg Sandostatin LAR Depot administered by IM injection every four weeks was approximately 3 ng/ml. Steady-state concentrations was achieved after 3 injections of a 40 mg dose. Mean BMI increased 0.1 kg/m 2 in Sandostatin LAR Depot-treated subjects compared to 0.0 kg/m 2 in saline control-treated subjects. Efficacy was not demonstrated. Diarrhea occurred in 11 of 30 (37%) patients treated with Sandostatin LAR Depot. No unexpected adverse events were observed. However, with Sandostatin LAR Depot 40 mg once a month, the incidence of new cholelithiasis in this pediatric population (33%) was higher than that seen in other adults indications such as acromegaly (22%) or malignant carcinoid syndrome (24%), where Sandostatin LAR Depot was 10 to 30 mg once a month. Clinical studies of Sandostatin did not include sufficient numbers of subjects aged 65 and over to determine whether they respond differently from younger subjects. Other reported clinical experience has not identified differences in responses between the elderly and younger patients. In general, dose selection for an elderly patient should be cautious, usually starting at the low end of the dosing range, reflecting the greater frequency of decreased hepatic, renal, or cardiac function, and of concomitant disease or other drug therapy.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS SECTION" id="34071-1">
Single doses of Sandostatin ® (octreotide acetate) have been shown to inhibit gallbladder contractility and decrease bile secretion in normal volunteers. In clinical trials (primarily patients with acromegaly or psoriasis), the incidence of biliary tract abnormalities was 63% (27% gallstones, 24% sludge without stones, 12% biliary duct dilatation). The incidence of stones or sludge in patients who received Sandostatin for 12 months or longer was 52%. Less than 2% of patients treated with Sandostatin for 1 month or less developed gallstones. The incidence of gallstones did not appear related to age, sex or dose. Like patients without gallbladder abnormalities, the majority of patients developing gallbladder abnormalities on ultrasound had gastrointestinal symptoms. The symptoms were not specific for gallbladder disease. A few patients developed acute cholecystitis, ascending cholangitis, biliary obstruction, cholestatic hepatitis, or pancreatitis during Sandostatin therapy or following its withdrawal. One patient developed ascending cholangitis during Sandostatin therapy and died.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Sandostatin ® (octreotide acetate) exerts pharmacologic actions similar to the natural hormone, somatostatin. It is an even more potent inhibitor of growth hormone, glucagon, and insulin than somatostatin. Like somatostatin, it also suppresses LH response to GnRH, decreases splanchnic blood flow, and inhibits release of serotonin, gastrin, vasoactive intestinal peptide, secretin, motilin, and pancreatic polypeptide. By virtue of these pharmacological actions, Sandostatin has been used to treat the symptoms associated with metastatic carcinoid tumors (flushing and diarrhea), and Vasoactive Intestinal Peptide (VIP) secreting adenomas (watery diarrhea). Sandostatin substantially reduces growth hormone and/or IGF-I (somatomedin C) levels in patients with acromegaly. Single doses of Sandostatin have been shown to inhibit gallbladder contractility and to decrease bile secretion in normal volunteers. In controlled clinical trials, the incidence of gallstone or biliary sludge formation was markedly increased ( see WARNINGS ). Sandostatin suppresses secretion of thyroid stimulating hormone (TSH). After subcutaneous injection, octreotide is absorbed rapidly and completely from the injection site. Peak concentrations of 5.2 ng/mL (100-mcg dose) were reached 0.4 hours after dosing. Using a specific radioimmunoassay, intravenous and subcutaneous doses were found to be bioequivalent. Peak concentrations and area under the curve (AUC) values were dose proportional after intravenous single doses up to 200 mcg and subcutaneous single doses up to 500 mcg and after subcutaneous multiple doses up to 500 mcg three times a day (1500 mcg/day). In healthy volunteers, the distribution of octreotide from plasma was rapid (tα1/2 = 0.2 h), the volume of distribution (V dss ) was estimated to be 13.6 L, and the total body clearance ranged from 7 L/hr to 10 L/hr. In blood, the distribution into the erythrocytes was found to be negligible and about 65% was bound in the plasma in a concentration-independent manner. Binding was mainly to lipoprotein and, to a lesser extent, to albumin. The elimination of octreotide from plasma had an apparent half-life of 1.7 to 1.9 hours compared with 1-3 minutes with the natural hormone. The duration of action of Sandostatin is variable but extends up to 12 hours depending upon the type of tumor. About 32% of the dose is excreted unchanged into the urine. In an elderly population, dose adjustments may be necessary due to a significant increase in the half-life (46%) and a significant decrease in the clearance (26%) of the drug. In patients with acromegaly, the pharmacokinetics differs somewhat from those in healthy volunteers. A mean peak concentration of 2.8 ng/mL (100-mcg dose) was reached in 0.7 hours after subcutaneous dosing. The volume of distribution (V dss ) was estimated to be 21.6 ± 8.5 L, and the total body clearance was increased to 18 L/h. The mean percent of the drug bound was 41.2%. The disposition and elimination half-lives were similar to normals. In patients with renal impairment, the elimination of octreotide from plasma was prolonged and total body clearance reduced. In mild renal impairment (CL CR 40-60 mL/min), octreotide t 1/2 was 2.4 hours and total body clearance was 8.8 L/hr, in moderate impairment (CL CR 10-39 mL/min) t 1/2 was 3.0 hours and total body clearance 7.3 L/hr, and in severely renally impaired patients not requiring dialysis (CL CR &amp;lt; 10 mL/min) t 1/2 was 3.1 hours and total body clearance was 7.6 L/hr. In patients with severe renal failure requiring dialysis, total body clearance was reduced to about half that found in healthy subjects (from approximately 10 L/hr to 4.5 L/hr). Patients with liver cirrhosis showed prolonged elimination of drug, with octreotide t 1/2 increasing to 3.7 hr and total body clearance decreasing to 5.9 L/hr, whereas patients with fatty liver disease showed t 1/2 increased to 3.4 hr and total body clearance of 8.2 L/hr.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="914" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Sensitivity to this drug or any of its components.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="915" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Sandostatin® (octreotide acetate) may be administered subcutaneously or intravenously.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="916" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Subcutaneous injection is the usual route of administration of Sandostatin for control of symptoms.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="917" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Pain with subcutaneous administration may be reduced by using the smallest volume that will deliver the desired dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="918" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Multiple subcutaneous injections at the same site within short periods of time should be avoided.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="919" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Sites should be rotated in a systematic manner.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="920" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Parenteral drug products should be inspected visually for particulate matter and discoloration prior to administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="921" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not use if particulates and/or discoloration are observed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="922" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Proper sterile technique should be used in the preparation of parenteral admixtures to minimize the possibility of microbial contamination.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="923" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Sandostatin is not compatible in Total Parenteral Nutrition (TPN) solutions because of the formation of a glycosyl octreotide conjugate which may decrease the efficacy of the product.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M9" type="Trigger" span="15 14" str="not compatible "/>
<Mention id="M10" type="Trigger" span="146 21" str=" decrease the efficacy"/>
<Mention id="M3" type="Precipitant" span="33 42" str="Total Parenteral Nutrition (TPN) solutions" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M12" type="SpecificInteraction" span="146 21" str="decrease the efficacy" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M7" type="Precipitant" span="33 26;66 9" str="Total Parenteral Nutrition | solutions" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M11" type="Precipitant" span="61 3;66 9" str="TPN | solutions" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M9;M10" precipitant="M3" effect="M12" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M9;M10" precipitant="M7" effect="M12" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M9;M10" precipitant="M11" effect="M12" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="924" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Sandostatin is stable in sterile isotonic saline solutions or sterile solutions of dextrose 5% in water for 24 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="925" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>It may be diluted in volumes of 50-200 mL and infused intravenously over 15-30 minutes or administered by IV push over 3 minutes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="926" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In emergency situations (e.g., carcinoid crisis), it may be given by rapid bolus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="927" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The initial dosage is usually 50 mcg administered twice or three times daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="928" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Upward dose titration is frequently required.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="929" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dosage information for patients with specific tumors follows.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="930" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dosage may be initiated at 50 mcg three times a day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="931" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Beginning with this low dose may permit adaptation to adverse gastrointestinal effects for patients who will require higher doses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="932" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>IGF-I (somatomedin C) levels every 2 weeks can be used to guide titration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="933" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Alternatively, multiple growth hormone levels at 0-8 hours after Sandostatin® (octreotide acetate) administration permit more rapid titration of dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="934" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The goal is to achieve growth hormone levels less than 5 ng/mL or IGF-I (somatomedin C) levels less than 1.9 unit/mL in males and less than 2.2 unit/mL in females.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="935" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The dose most commonly found to be effective is 100 mcg three times a day, but some patients require up to 500 mcg three times a day for maximum effectiveness.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="936" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Doses greater than 300 mcg/day seldom result in additional biochemical benefit, and if an increase in dose fails to provide additional benefit, the dose should be reduced.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="937" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>IGF-I (somatomedin C) or growth hormone levels should be reevaluated at 6-month intervals.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="938" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Sandostatin should be withdrawn yearly for approximately 4 weeks from patients who have received irradiation to assess disease activity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="939" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If growth hormone or IGF-I (somatomedin C) levels increase and signs and symptoms recur, Sandostatin therapy may be resumed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="940" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The suggested daily dosage of Sandostatin during the first 2 weeks of therapy ranges from 100-600 mcg/day in 2-4 divided doses (mean daily dosage is 300 mcg).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="941" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In the clinical studies, the median daily maintenance dosage was approximately 450 mcg, but clinical and biochemical benefits were obtained in some patients with as little as 50 mcg, while others required doses up to 1500 mcg/day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="942" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>However, experience with doses above 750 mcg/day is limited.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="943" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Daily dosages of 200-300 mcg in 2-4 divided doses are recommended during the initial 2 weeks of therapy (range: 150-750 mcg) to control symptoms of the disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="944" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>On an individual basis, dosage may be adjusted to achieve a therapeutic response, but usually doses above 450 mcg/day are not required.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="945" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34074-5">
<SentenceText>No known interference exists with clinical laboratory tests, including amine or peptide determinations.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="946" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Sandostatin has been associated with alterations in nutrient absorption, so it may have an effect on absorption of orally administered drugs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="947" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant administration of Sandostatin with cyclosporine may decrease blood levels of cyclosporine and result in transplant rejection.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M13" type="Trigger" span="106 9" str="result in"/>
<Mention id="M17" type="Precipitant" span="47 12" str="cyclosporine" code="83HN0GTJ6D | N0000007346"/>
<Mention id="M15" type="SpecificInteraction" span="116 20" str="transplant rejection" code="213148006: Transplanted organ rejection (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M16" type="Trigger" span="64 21" str="decrease blood levels"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M13" precipitant="M17" effect="M15" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M16" precipitant="M17" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="948" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Patients receiving insulin, oral hypoglycemic agents, beta blockers, calcium channel blockers, or agents to control fluid and electrolyte balance, may require dose adjustments of these therapeutic agents.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M26" type="Trigger" span="159 16" str="dose adjustments"/>
<Mention id="M19" type="Precipitant" span="98 47" str="agents to control fluid and electrolyte balance" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M21" type="Precipitant" span="54 13" str="beta blockers" code="N0000000161 | N0000175556"/>
<Mention id="M23" type="Precipitant" span="69 24" str="calcium channel blockers" code="N0000175566 | N0000000069 | N0000029119"/>
<Mention id="M25" type="Precipitant" span="19 7" str="insulin" code="N0000004931 | N0000175944"/>
<Mention id="M27" type="Precipitant" span="28 24" str="oral hypoglycemic agents" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M26" precipitant="M19"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M26" precipitant="M21"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M26" precipitant="M23"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M26" precipitant="M25"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M26" precipitant="M27"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="949" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant administration of octreotide and bromocriptine increases the availability of bromocriptine.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M28" type="Trigger" span="59 26" str="increases the availability"/>
<Mention id="M29" type="Precipitant" span="45 13" str="bromocriptine" code="3A64E3G5ZO"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M28" precipitant="M29" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="950" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Limited published data indicate that somatostatin analogs might decrease the metabolic clearance of compounds known to be metabolized by cytochrome P450 enzymes, which may be due to the suppression of growth hormones.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M30" type="Trigger" span="64 32" str="decrease the metabolic clearance"/>
<Mention id="M31" type="Precipitant" span="100 60" str="compounds known to be metabolized by cytochrome P450 enzymes" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M30" precipitant="M31" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="951" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Since it cannot be excluded that octreotide may have this effect, other drugs mainly metabolized by CYP3A4 and which have a low therapeutic index (e.g., quinidine, terfenadine) should therefore be used with caution.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M36" type="Trigger" span="207 7" str="caution"/>
<Mention id="M33" type="Precipitant" span="72 73" str="drugs mainly metabolized by CYP3A4 and which have a low therapeutic index" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M35" type="Precipitant" span="153 9" str="quinidine" code="N0000007728 | ITX08688JL"/>
<Mention id="M37" type="Precipitant" span="164 11" str="terfenadine" code="7BA5G9Y06Q"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M36" precipitant="M33"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M36" precipitant="M35"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M36" precipitant="M37"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="952" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Sandostatin® (octreotide acetate) alters the balance between the counter-regulatory hormones, insulin, glucagon and growth hormone, which may result in hypoglycemia or hyperglycemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="953" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Sandostatin also suppresses secretion of thyroid stimulating hormone, which may result in hypothyroidism.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="954" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Cardiac conduction abnormalities have also occurred during treatment with Sandostatin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="955" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>However, the incidence of these adverse events during long-term therapy was determined vigorously only in acromegaly patients who, due to their underlying disease and/or the subsequent treatment they receive, are at an increased risk for the development of diabetes mellitus, hypothyroidism, and cardiovascular disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="956" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Although the degree to which these abnormalities are related to Sandostatin therapy is not clear, new abnormalities of glycemic control, thyroid function and ECG developed during Sandostatin therapy as described below.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="957" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Risk of Pregnancy with Normalization of IGF-1 and GH Although acromegaly may lead to infertility, there are reports of pregnancy in acromegalic women.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="958" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In women with active acromegaly who have been unable to become pregnant, normalization of GH and IGF-1 may restore fertility.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="959" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Female patients of childbearing potential should be advised to use adequate contraception during treatment with octreotide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="960" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The hypoglycemia or hyperglycemia which occurs during Sandostatin therapy is usually mild, but may result in overt diabetes mellitus or necessitate dose changes in insulin or other hypoglycemic agents.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M40" type="Trigger" span="148 12" str="dose changes"/>
<Mention id="M39" type="Precipitant" span="181 19" str="hypoglycemic agents" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M41" type="Precipitant" span="164 7" str="insulin" code="N0000004931 | N0000175944"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M40" precipitant="M39"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M40" precipitant="M41"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="961" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Hypoglycemia and hyperglycemia occurred on Sandostatin in 3% and 16% of acromegalic patients, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="962" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Severe hyperglycemia, subsequent pneumonia, and death following initiation of Sandostatin therapy was reported in one patient with no history of hyperglycemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="963" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In patients with concomitant Type I diabetes mellitus, Sandostatin Injection and Sandostatin LAR® Depot (octreotide acetate for injectable suspension) are likely to affect glucose regulation, and insulin requirements may be reduced.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M42" type="Trigger" span="204 27" str="requirements may be reduced"/>
<Mention id="M43" type="Precipitant" span="196 7" str="insulin" code="N0000004931 | N0000175944"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M42" precipitant="M43"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="964" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Symptomatic hypoglycemia, which may be severe, has been reported in these patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="965" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In non-diabetics and Type II diabetics with partially intact insulin reserves, Sandostatin Injection or Sandostatin LAR Depot administration may result in decreases in plasma insulin levels and hyperglycemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="966" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>It is therefore recommended that glucose tolerance and antidiabetic treatment be periodically monitored during therapy with these drugs.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M44" type="Trigger" span="68 9;94 9" str="treatment | monitored"/>
<Mention id="M45" type="Precipitant" span="55 12" str="antidiabetic" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M44" precipitant="M45"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="967" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In acromegalic patients, 12% developed biochemical hypothyroidism only, 8% developed goiter, and 4% required initiation of thyroid replacement therapy while receiving Sandostatin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="968" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Baseline and periodic assessment of thyroid function (TSH, total and/or free T4) is recommended during chronic therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="969" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In acromegalics, bradycardia (&lt; 50 bpm) developed in 25%; conduction abnormalities occurred in 10% and arrhythmias occurred in 9% of patients during Sandostatin therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="970" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Other EKG changes observed included QT prolongation, axis shifts, early repolarization, low voltage, R/S transition, and early R wave progression.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="971" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>These ECG changes are not uncommon in acromegalic patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="972" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Dose adjustments in drugs such as beta-blockers that have bradycardia effects may be necessary.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M48" type="Trigger" span="0 16" str="Dose adjustments"/>
<Mention id="M47" type="Precipitant" span="34 13" str="beta-blockers" code="N0000000161 | N0000175556"/>
<Mention id="M49" type="Precipitant" span="20 5;48 29" str="drugs | that have bradycardia effects" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M48" precipitant="M47"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M48" precipitant="M49"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="973" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In one acromegalic patient with severe congestive heart failure, initiation of Sandostatin therapy resulted in worsening of CHF with improvement when drug was discontinued.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="974" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Confirmation of a drug effect was obtained with a positive rechallenge.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="975" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Several cases of pancreatitis have been reported in patients receiving Sandostatin therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="976" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Sandostatin may alter absorption of dietary fats in some patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="977" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In patients with severe renal failure requiring dialysis, the half-life of Sandostatin may be increased, necessitating adjustment of the maintenance dosage.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="978" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Depressed vitamin B12 levels and abnormal Schilling’s tests have been observed in some patients receiving Sandostatin therapy, and monitoring of vitamin B12 levels is recommended during chronic Sandostatin therapy.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M50" type="Trigger" span="0 9;22 6" str="Depressed | levels"/>
<Mention id="M51" type="Precipitant" span="10 11" str="vitamin B12" code="P6YC3EG204"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M50" precipitant="M51" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="979" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Careful instruction in sterile subcutaneous injection technique should be given to the patients and to other persons who may administer Sandostatin Injection.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="980" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Laboratory tests that may be helpful as biochemical markers in determining and following patient response depend on the specific tumor.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="981" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Based on diagnosis, measurement of the following substances may be useful in monitoring the progress of therapy: Acromegaly: Growth Hormone, IGF-I (somatomedin C) Responsiveness to Sandostatin may be evaluated by determining growth hormone levels at 1-4 hour intervals for 8-12 hours post dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="982" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Alternatively, a single measurement of IGF-I (somatomedin C) level may be made two weeks after drug initiation or dosage change.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="983" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Carcinoid: 5-HIAA (urinary 5-hydroxyindole acetic acid), plasma serotonin, plasma Substance P VIPoma: VIP (plasma vasoactive intestinal peptide) Baseline and periodic total and/or free T4 measurements should be performed during chronic therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="984" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Studies in laboratory animals have demonstrated no mutagenic potential of Sandostatin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="985" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>No carcinogenic potential was demonstrated in mice treated subcutaneously for 85-99 weeks at doses up to 2000 mcg/kg/day (8 x the human exposure based on body surface area).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="986" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In a 116-week subcutaneous study in rats, a 27% and 12% incidence of injection site sarcomas or squamous cell carcinomas was observed in males and females, respectively, at the highest dose level of 1250 mcg/kg/day (10 x the human exposure based on body surface area) compared to an incidence of 8%-10% in the vehicle-control groups.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="987" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The increased incidence of injection site tumors was most probably caused by irritation and the high sensitivity of the rat to repeated subcutaneous injections at the same site.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="988" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Rotating injection sites would prevent chronic irritation in humans.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="989" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>There have been no reports of injection site tumors in patients treated with Sandostatin for up to 5 years.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="990" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>There was also a 15% incidence of uterine adenocarcinomas in the 1250 mcg/kg/day females compared to 7% in the saline-control females and 0% in the vehicle-control females.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="991" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The presence of endometritis coupled with the absence of corpora lutea, the reduction in mammary fibroadenomas, and the presence of uterine dilatation suggest that the uterine tumors were associated with estrogen dominance in the aged female rats which does not occur in humans.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="992" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Sandostatin did not impair fertility in rats at doses up to 1000 mcg/kg/day, which represents 7x the human exposure based on body surface area.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="993" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>There are no adequate and well-controlled studies of octreotide use in pregnant women.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="994" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Reproduction studies have been performed in rats and rabbits at doses up to 16 times the highest recommended human dose based on body surface area and revealed no evidence of harm to the fetus due to octreotide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="995" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>However, because animal reproduction studies are not always predictive of human response, this drug should be used during pregnancy only if clearly needed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="996" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In postmarketing data, a limited number of exposed pregnancies have been reported in patients with acromegaly.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="997" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Most women were exposed to octreotide during the first trimester of pregnancy at doses ranging from 100-300 mcg/day of Sandostatin s.c. or 20-30 mg/month of Sandostatin LAR, however some women elected to continue octreotide therapy throughout pregnancy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="998" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In cases with a known outcome, no congenital malformations were reported.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="999" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>It is not known whether octreotide is excreted into human milk.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1000" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because many drugs are excreted in human milk, caution should be exercised when octreotide is administered to a nursing woman.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1001" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Safety and efficacy of Sandostatin Injection in the pediatric population have not been demonstrated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1002" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>No formal controlled clinical trials have been performed to evaluate the safety and effectiveness of Sandostatin in pediatric patients under age 6 years.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1003" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In post-marketing reports, serious adverse events, including hypoxia, necrotizing enterocolitis, and death, have been reported with Sandostatin use in children, most notably in children under 2 years of age.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1004" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The relationship of these events to octreotide has not been established as the majority of these pediatric patients had serious underlying co-morbid conditions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1005" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The efficacy and safety of Sandostatin using the Sandostatin LAR Depot formulation was examined in a single randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, six month pharmacokinetics study in 60 pediatric patient's age 6-17 years with hypothalamic obesity resulting from cranial insult.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1006" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The mean octreotide concentration after 6 doses of 40 mg Sandostatin LAR Depot administered by IM injection every four weeks was approximately 3 ng/ml.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1007" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Steady-state concentrations was achieved after 3 injections of a 40 mg dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1008" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Mean BMI increased 0.1 kg/m2 in Sandostatin LAR Depot-treated subjects compared to 0.0 kg/m2 in saline control-treated subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1009" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Diarrhea occurred in 11 of 30 (37%) patients treated with Sandostatin LAR Depot.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1010" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>No unexpected adverse events were observed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1011" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>However, with Sandostatin LAR Depot 40 mg once a month, the incidence of new cholelithiasis in this pediatric population (33%) was higher than that seen in other adults indications such as acromegaly (22%) or malignant carcinoid syndrome (24%), where Sandostatin LAR Depot was 10 to 30 mg once a month.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1012" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Clinical studies of Sandostatin did not include sufficient numbers of subjects aged 65 and over to determine whether they respond differently from younger subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1013" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Other reported clinical experience has not identified differences in responses between the elderly and younger patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1014" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In general, dose selection for an elderly patient should be cautious, usually starting at the low end of the dosing range, reflecting the greater frequency of decreased hepatic, renal, or cardiac function, and of concomitant disease or other drug therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1015" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Single doses of Sandostatin® (octreotide acetate) have been shown to inhibit gallbladder contractility and decrease bile secretion in normal volunteers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1016" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>In clinical trials (primarily patients with acromegaly or psoriasis), the incidence of biliary tract abnormalities was 63% (27% gallstones, 24% sludge without stones, 12% biliary duct dilatation).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1017" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The incidence of stones or sludge in patients who received Sandostatin for 12 months or longer was 52%.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1018" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Less than 2% of patients treated with Sandostatin for 1 month or less developed gallstones.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1019" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The incidence of gallstones did not appear related to age, sex or dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1020" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Like patients without gallbladder abnormalities, the majority of patients developing gallbladder abnormalities on ultrasound had gastrointestinal symptoms.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1021" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The symptoms were not specific for gallbladder disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1022" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>A few patients developed acute cholecystitis, ascending cholangitis, biliary obstruction, cholestatic hepatitis, or pancreatitis during Sandostatin therapy or following its withdrawal.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1023" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>One patient developed ascending cholangitis during Sandostatin therapy and died.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1024" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Sandostatin® (octreotide acetate) exerts pharmacologic actions similar to the natural hormone, somatostatin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1025" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>It is an even more potent inhibitor of growth hormone, glucagon, and insulin than somatostatin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1026" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Like somatostatin, it also suppresses LH response to GnRH, decreases splanchnic blood flow, and inhibits release of serotonin, gastrin, vasoactive intestinal peptide, secretin, motilin, and pancreatic polypeptide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1027" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>By virtue of these pharmacological actions, Sandostatin has been used to treat the symptoms associated with metastatic carcinoid tumors (flushing and diarrhea), and Vasoactive Intestinal Peptide (VIP) secreting adenomas (watery diarrhea).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1028" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Sandostatin substantially reduces growth hormone and/or IGF-I (somatomedin C) levels in patients with acromegaly.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1029" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Single doses of Sandostatin have been shown to inhibit gallbladder contractility and to decrease bile secretion in normal volunteers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1030" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In controlled clinical trials, the incidence of gallstone or biliary sludge formation was markedly increased.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1031" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Sandostatin suppresses secretion of thyroid stimulating hormone (TSH).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1032" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>After subcutaneous injection, octreotide is absorbed rapidly and completely from the injection site.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1033" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Peak concentrations of 5.2 ng/mL (100-mcg dose) were reached 0.4 hours after dosing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1034" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Using a specific radioimmunoassay, intravenous and subcutaneous doses were found to be bioequivalent.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1035" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Peak concentrations and area under the curve (AUC) values were dose proportional after intravenous single doses up to 200 mcg and subcutaneous single doses up to 500 mcg and after subcutaneous multiple doses up to 500 mcg three times a day (1500 mcg/day).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1036" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In healthy volunteers, the distribution of octreotide from plasma was rapid (tα1/2 = 0.2 h), the volume of distribution (Vdss) was estimated to be 13.6 L, and the total body clearance ranged from 7 L/hr to 10 L/hr.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1037" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In blood, the distribution into the erythrocytes was found to be negligible and about 65% was bound in the plasma in a concentration-independent manner.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1038" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Binding was mainly to lipoprotein and, to a lesser extent, to albumin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1039" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The elimination of octreotide from plasma had an apparent half-life of 1.7 to 1.9 hours compared with 1-3 minutes with the natural hormone.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1040" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The duration of action of Sandostatin is variable but extends up to 12 hours depending upon the type of tumor.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1041" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>About 32% of the dose is excreted unchanged into the urine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1042" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In an elderly population, dose adjustments may be necessary due to a significant increase in the half-life (46%) and a significant decrease in the clearance (26%) of the drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1043" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In patients with acromegaly, the pharmacokinetics differs somewhat from those in healthy volunteers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1044" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A mean peak concentration of 2.8 ng/mL (100-mcg dose) was reached in 0.7 hours after subcutaneous dosing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1045" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The volume of distribution (Vdss) was estimated to be 21.6 ± 8.5 L, and the total body clearance was increased to 18 L/h.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1046" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mean percent of the drug bound was 41.2%.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1047" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The disposition and elimination half-lives were similar to normals.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1048" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In patients with renal impairment, the elimination of octreotide from plasma was prolonged and total body clearance reduced.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1049" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In mild renal impairment (CLCR 40-60 mL/min), octreotide t1/2 was 2.4 hours and total body clearance was 8.8 L/hr, in moderate impairment (CLCR 10-39 mL/min) t1/2 was 3.0 hours and total body clearance 7.3 L/hr, and in severely renally impaired patients not requiring dialysis (CLCR &lt; 10 mL/min) t1/2 was 3.1 hours and total body clearance was 7.6 L/hr.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1050" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In patients with severe renal failure requiring dialysis, total body clearance was reduced to about half that found in healthy subjects (from approximately 10 L/hr to 4.5 L/hr).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1051" LabelDrug="Sandostatin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Patients with liver cirrhosis showed prolonged elimination of drug, with octreotide t1/2 increasing to 3.7 hr and total body clearance decreasing to 5.9 L/hr, whereas patients with fatty liver disease showed t1/2 increased to 3.4 hr and total body clearance of 8.2 L/hr.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="total parenteral nutrition (tpn) solutions" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="total parenteral nutrition | solutions" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="tpn | solutions" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cyclosporine" precipitantCode="83HN0GTJ6D | N0000007346" effect="213148006: Transplanted organ rejection (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cyclosporine" precipitantCode="83HN0GTJ6D | N0000007346" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="agents to control fluid and electrolyte balance" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="beta blockers" precipitantCode="N0000000161 | N0000175556"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="calcium channel blockers" precipitantCode="N0000175566 | N0000000069 | N0000029119"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="insulin" precipitantCode="N0000004931 | N0000175944"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="oral hypoglycemic agents" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="bromocriptine" precipitantCode="3A64E3G5ZO" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="compounds known to be metabolized by cytochrome p450 enzymes" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="drugs mainly metabolized by cyp3a4 and which have a low therapeutic index" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="quinidine" precipitantCode="N0000007728 | ITX08688JL"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="terfenadine" precipitantCode="7BA5G9Y06Q"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="hypoglycemic agents" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="antidiabetic" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="beta-blockers" precipitantCode="N0000000161 | N0000175556"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="drugs | that have bradycardia effects" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="vitamin b12" precipitantCode="P6YC3EG204" effect="C54358"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>