<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Toviaz" setid="4f01dced-195a-4712-a614-d68012bc29df">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
Toviaz is contraindicated in patients with urinary retention, gastric retention, or uncontrolled narrow-angle glaucoma. Toviaz is also contraindicated in patients with known hypersensitivity to the drug or its ingredients, or to tolterodine tartrate tablets or tolterodine tartrate extended-release capsules [ see Clinical Pharmacology (12.1) ]. Toviaz is contraindicated in patients with urinary retention, gastric retention, or uncontrolled narrow-angle glaucoma. Toviaz is also contraindicated in patients with known hypersensitivity to the drug or its ingredients or to tolterodine tartrate tablets or tolterodine tartrate extended-release capsules. ( 4 )</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
The recommended starting dose of Toviaz is 4 mg once daily. Based upon individual response and tolerability, the dose may be increased to 8 mg once daily. The daily dose of Toviaz should not exceed 4 mg in the following populations: Patients with severe renal impairment (CL CR &amp;lt;30 mL/min). Patients taking potent CYP3A4 inhibitors, such as ketoconazole, itraconazole, and clarithromycin. Toviaz is not recommended for use in patients with severe hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh C) [ see Warnings and Precautions (5.6 , 5.8 , 5.9) ; Use in Specific Populations (8.6 , 8.7) ; and Drug Interactions (7.2) ]. Toviaz should be taken with liquid and swallowed whole. Toviaz can be administered with or without food, and should not be chewed, divided, or crushed. The recommended starting dose of Toviaz is 4 mg once daily. Based upon individual response and tolerability, the dose may be increased to 8 mg once daily. ( 2 ) The daily dose of Toviaz should not exceed 4 mg in the following populations: Patients with severe renal impairment (CL CR &amp;lt;30 mL/min) ( 2 ) Patients taking potent CYP3A4 inhibitors, such as ketoconazole, itraconazole, and clarithromycin. ( 2 ) Toviaz is not recommended for use in patients with severe hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh C). ( 2 ) Toviaz should be taken with liquid and swallowed whole. Toviaz can be administered with or without food, and should not be chewed, divided, or crushed. ( 2 )</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
Coadministration of Toviaz with other antimuscarinic agents that produce dry mouth, constipation, urinary retention, and other anticholinergic pharmacological effects may increase the frequency and/or severity of such effects. Anticholinergic agents may potentially alter the absorption of some concomitantly administered drugs due to anticholinergic effects on gastrointestinal motility. Doses of Toviaz greater than 4 mg are not recommended in patients taking potent CYP3A4 inhibitors, such as ketoconazole, itraconazole, and clarithromycin. Coadministration of the potent CYP3A4 inhibitor ketoconazole with fesoterodine led to approximately a doubling of the maximum concentration (C max ) and area under the concentration versus time curve (AUC) of 5-hydroxymethyl tolterodine (5-HMT), the active metabolite of fesoterodine. Compared with CYP2D6 extensive metabolizers not taking ketoconazole, further increases in the exposure to 5-HMT were observed in subjects who were CYP2D6 poor metabolizers taking ketoconazole [ see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3) , Warnings and Precautions (5.8) , and Dosage and Administration (2) ]. There is no clinically relevant effect of moderate CYP3A4 inhibitors on the pharmacokinetics of fesoterodine. Following blockade of CYP3A4 by coadministration of the moderate CYP3A4 inhibitor fluconazole 200 mg twice a day for 2 days, the average (90% confidence interval) increase in C max and AUC of the active metabolite of fesoterodine was approximately 19% (11% – 28%) and 27% (18% – 36%) respectively. No dosing adjustments are recommended in the presence of moderate CYP3A4 inhibitors (e.g., erythromycin, fluconazole, diltiazem, verapamil and grapefruit juice). The effect of weak CYP3A4 inhibitors (e.g. cimetidine) was not examined; it is not expected to be in excess of the effect of moderate inhibitors [ see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3) , Warnings and Precautions (5.8) , and Dosage and Administration (2) ]. No dosing adjustments are recommended in the presence of CYP3A4 inducers, such as rifampin and carbamazepine. Following induction of CYP3A4 by coadministration of rifampin 600 mg once a day, C max and AUC of the active metabolite of fesoterodine decreased by approximately 70% and 75%, respectively, after oral administration of Toviaz 8 mg. The terminal half-life of the active metabolite was not changed. The interaction with CYP2D6 inhibitors was not tested clinically. In poor metabolizers for CYP2D6, representing a maximum CYP2D6 inhibition, C max and AUC of the active metabolite are increased 1.7- and 2-fold, respectively. No dosing adjustments are recommended in the presence of CYP2D6 inhibitors. In vitro data indicate that at therapeutic concentrations, the active metabolite of fesoterodine does not have the potential to inhibit or induce Cytochrome P450 enzyme systems [ see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3) ]. In the presence of fesoterodine, there are no clinically significant changes in the plasma concentrations of combined oral contraceptives containing ethinyl estradiol and levonorgestrel [ see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3) ]. A clinical study has shown that fesoterodine 8 mg once daily has no significant effect on the pharmacokinetics or the anticoagulant activity (PT/INR) of warfarin 25 mg. Standard therapeutic monitoring for warfarin should be continued [ see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3) ]. Interactions between Toviaz and laboratory tests have not been studied.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
Angioedema of the face, lips, tongue, and/or larynx has been reported with fesoterodine. ( 5.1 ). Toviaz should be administered with caution to patients with clinically significant bladder outlet obstruction because of the risk of urinary retention. ( 5.2 ) Toviaz, like other antimuscarinic drugs, should be used with caution in patients with decreased gastrointestinal motility, such as those with severe constipation. ( 5.3 ) Toviaz should be used with caution in patients being treated for narrow-angle glaucoma, and only where the potential benefits outweigh the risks ( 5.4 ) Central Nervous System Effects: Somnolence has been reported with Toviaz. Advise patients not to drive or operate heavy machinery until they know how Toviaz affects them ( 5.5 ) Toviaz should be used with caution in patients with myasthenia gravis, a disease characterized by decreased cholinergic activity at the neuromuscular junction. ( 5.9 ) Angioedema of the face, lips, tongue, and/or larynx has been reported with fesoterodine. In some cases angioedema occurred after the first dose. Angioedema associated with upper airway swelling may be life-threatening. If involvement of the tongue, hypopharynx, or larynx occurs, fesoterodine should be promptly discontinued and appropriate therapy and/or measures to ensure a patent airway should be promptly provided. Toviaz should be administered with caution to patients with clinically significant bladder outlet obstruction because of the risk of urinary retention [ see Contraindications (4) ]. Toviaz, like other antimuscarinic drugs, should be used with caution in patients with decreased gastrointestinal motility, such as those with severe constipation. Toviaz should be used with caution in patients being treated for narrow-angle glaucoma, and only where the potential benefits outweigh the risks [ see Contraindications (4) ]. Toviaz is associated with anticholinergic central nervous sytem (CNS) effects [see Adverse Reactions (6.2) ]. A variety of CNS anticholinergic effects have been reported, including headache, dizziness, and somnolence. Patients should be monitored for signs of anticholinergic CNS effects, particularly after beginning treatment or increasing the dose. Advise patients not to drive or operate heavy machinery until they know how Toviaz affects them. If a patient experiences anticholinergic CNS effects, dose reduction or drug discontinuation should be considered. Toviaz has not been studied in patients with severe hepatic impairment and therefore is not recommended for use in this patient population [ see Use in Specific Populations (8.7) and Dosage and Administration (2) ]. Doses of Toviaz greater than 4 mg are not recommended in patients with severe renal impairment [ see Use In Specific Populations (8.6) and Dosage and Administration (2) ]. Doses of Toviaz greater than 4 mg are not recommended in patients taking a potent CYP3A4 inhibitor (e.g., ketoconazole, itraconazole, clarithromycin). No dosing adjustments are recommended in the presence of moderate CYP3A4 inhibitors (e.g., erythromycin, fluconazole, diltiazem, verapamil and grapefruit juice). While the effect of weak CYP3A4 inhibitors (e.g. cimetidine) was not examined by clinical study, some pharmacokinetic interaction is expected, albeit less than that observed with moderate CYP3A4 inhibitors [ see Drug Interactions (7.2) and Dosage and Administration (2) ]. Toviaz should be used with caution in patients with myasthenia gravis, a disease characterized by decreased cholinergic activity at the neuromuscular junction.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Fesoterodine is a competitive muscarinic receptor antagonist. After oral administration, fesoterodine is rapidly and extensively hydrolyzed by nonspecific esterases to its active metabolite, 5-hydroxymethyl tolterodine, which is responsible for the antimuscarinic activity of fesoterodine and is also one of the active moieties of tolterodine tartrate tablets and tolterodine tartrate extended-release capsules. Muscarinic receptors play a role in contractions of urinary bladder smooth muscle and stimulation of salivary secretion. Inhibition of these receptors in the bladder is presumed to be the mechanism by which fesoterodine produces its effects. In a urodynamic study involving patients with involuntary detrusor contractions, the effects after the administration of fesoterodine on the volume at first detrusor contraction and bladder capacity were assessed. Administration of fesoterodine increased the volume at first detrusor contraction and bladder capacity in a dose-dependent manner. These findings are consistent with an antimuscarinic effect on the bladder. Cardiac Electrophysiology: The effect of fesoterodine 4 mg and 28 mg on the QT interval was evaluated in a double-blind, randomized, placebo- and positive-controlled (moxifloxacin 400 mg once a day) parallel trial with once-daily treatment over a period of 3 days in 261 male and female subjects aged 44 to 65 years. Electrocardiographic parameters were measured over a 24-hour period at pre-dose, after the first administration, and after the third administration of study medication. Fesoterodine 28 mg was chosen because this dose, when administered to CYP2D6 extensive metabolizers, results in an exposure to the active metabolite that is similar to the exposure in a CYP2D6 poor metabolizer receiving fesoterodine 8 mg together with CYP3A4 blockade. Corrected QT intervals (QTc) were calculated using Fridericia's correction and a linear individual correction method. Analyses of 24-hour average QTc, time-matched baseline-corrected QTc, and time-matched placebo-subtracted QTc intervals indicate that fesoterodine at doses of 4 and 28 mg/day did not prolong the QT interval. The sensitivity of the study was confirmed by positive QTc prolongation by moxifloxacin. Toviaz is associated with an increase in heart rate that correlates with increasing dose. In the study described above, when compared to placebo, the mean increase in heart rate associated with a dose of 4 mg/day and 28 mg/day of fesoterodine was 3 beats/minute and 11 beats/minute, respectively. In the two, phase 3, placebo-controlled studies in patients with overactive bladder, the mean increase in heart rate compared to placebo was approximately 3–4 beats/minute in the 4 mg/day group and 3–5 beats/minute in the 8 mg/day group. Absorption: After oral administration, fesoterodine is well absorbed. Due to rapid and extensive hydrolysis by nonspecific esterases to its active metabolite 5-hydroxymethyl tolterodine, fesoterodine cannot be detected in plasma. Bioavailability of the active metabolite is 52%. After single or multiple-dose oral administration of fesoterodine in doses from 4 mg to 28 mg, plasma concentrations of the active metabolite are proportional to the dose. Maximum plasma levels are reached after approximately 5 hours. No accumulation occurs after multiple-dose administration. A summary of pharmacokinetic parameters for the active metabolite after a single dose of Toviaz 4 mg and 8 mg in extensive and poor metabolizers of CYP2D6 is provided in Table 2. Table 2: Summary of geometric mean [CV] pharmacokinetic parameters for the active metabolite after a single dose of Toviaz 4 mg and 8 mg in extensive and poor CYP2D6 metabolizers Toviaz 4 mg Toviaz 8 mg Parameter EM (n=16) PM (n=8) EM (n=16) PM (n=8) EM = extensive CYP2D6 metabolizer, PM = poor CYP2D6 metabolizer, CV = coefficient of variation C max = maximum plasma concentration, AUC 0–tz = area under the concentration time curve from zero up to the last measurable plasma concentration, t max = time to reach C max , t ½ = terminal half-life C max (ng/mL) 1.89 [43%] 3.45 [54%] 3.98 [28%] 6.90 [39%] AUC 0–tz (ng*h/mL) 21.2 [38%] 40.5 [31%] 45.3 [32%] 88.7 [36%] t max (h) Data presented as median (range) 5 [2–6] 5 [5–6] 5 [3–6] 5 [5–6] t ½ (h) 7.31 [27%] 7.31 [30%] 8.59 [41%] 7.66 [21%] Effect of Food: There is no clinically relevant effect of food on the pharmacokinetics of fesoterodine. In a study of the effects of food on the pharmacokinetics of fesoterodine in 16 healthy male volunteers, concomitant food intake increased the active metabolite of fesoterodine AUC by approximately 19% and C max by 18% [ see Dosage and Administration (2) ]. Distribution: Plasma protein binding of the active metabolite is low (approximately 50%) and is primarily bound to albumin and alpha-1-acid glycoprotein. The mean steady-state volume of distribution following intravenous infusion of the active metabolite is 169 L. Metabolism: After oral administration, fesoterodine is rapidly and extensively hydrolyzed to its active metabolite. The active metabolite is further metabolized in the liver to its carboxy, carboxy-N-desisopropyl, and N-desisopropyl metabolites via two major pathways involving CYP2D6 and CYP3A4. None of these metabolites contribute significantly to the antimuscarinic activity of fesoterodine. Variability in CYP2D6 Metabolism: A subset of individuals (approximately 7% of Caucasians and approximately 2% of African Americans) are poor metabolizers for CYP2D6. C max and AUC of the active metabolite are increased 1.7- and 2-fold, respectively, in CYP2D6 poor metabolizers, as compared to extensive metabolizers. Excretion: Hepatic metabolism and renal excretion contribute significantly to the elimination of the active metabolite. After oral administration of fesoterodine, approximately 70% of the administered dose was recovered in urine as the active metabolite (16%), carboxy metabolite (34%), carboxy-N-desisopropyl metabolite (18%), or N-desisopropyl metabolite (1%), and a smaller amount (7%) was recovered in feces. The terminal half-life of the active metabolite is approximately 4 hours following an intravenous administration. The apparent terminal half-life following oral administration is approximately 7 hours. Pharmacokinetics in Specific Populations: Geriatric Patients: Following a single 8 mg oral dose of fesoterodine, the mean (±SD) AUC and C max for the active metabolite 5-hydroxymethyl tolterodine in 12 elderly men (mean age 67 years) were 51.8 ± 26.1 h*ng/mL and 3.8 ± 1.7 ng/mL, respectively. In the same study, the mean (±SD) AUC and C max in 12 young men (mean age 30 years) were 52.0 ± 31.5 h*ng/mL and 4.1 ± 2.1 ng/mL, respectively. The pharmacokinetics of fesoterodine were not significantly influenced by age [ see Use in Specific Populations (8.5) ]. Pediatric Patients: The pharmacokinetics of fesoterodine have not been evaluated in pediatric patients [ see Use in Specific Populations (8.4) ]. Gender: Following a single 8 mg oral dose of fesoterodine, the mean (±SD) AUC and C max for the active metabolite 5-hydroxymethyl tolterodine in 12 elderly men (mean age 67 years) were 51.8 ± 26.1 h*ng/mL and 3.8 ± 1.7 ng/mL, respectively. In the same study, the mean (±SD) AUC and C max in 12 elderly women (mean age 68 years) were 56.0 ± 28.8 h*ng/mL and 4.6 ± 2.3 ng/mL, respectively. The pharmacokinetics of fesoterodine were not significantly influenced by gender [ see Use in Specific Populations (8.8) ]. Race: The effects of Caucasian or Black race on the pharmacokinetics of fesoterodine were examined in a study of 12 Caucasian and 12 Black African young male volunteers. Each subject received a single oral dose of 8 mg fesoterodine. The mean (±SD) AUC and C max for the active metabolite 5-hydroxymethyl tolterodine in Caucasian males were 73.0 ± 27.8 h*ng/mL and 6.1 ± 2.7 ng/mL, respectively. The mean (±SD) AUC and C max in Black males were 65.8 ± 23.2 h*ng/mL and 5.5 ± 1.9 ng/mL, respectively . The pharmacokinetics of fesoterodine were not significantly influenced by race [ see Use in Specific Populations (8.9) ]. Renal Impairment: In patients with mild or moderate renal impairment (CL CR ranging from 30–80 mL/min), C max and AUC of the active metabolite are increased up to 1.5- and 1.8-fold, respectively, as compared to healthy subjects. In patients with severe renal impairment (CL CR &amp;lt; 30 mL/min), C max and AUC are increased 2.0- and 2.3-fold, respectively. [ see Use in Specific Populations (8.6) , Warnings and Precautions (5.7) , and Dosage and Administration (2) ]. Hepatic Impairment: In patients with moderate (Child-Pugh B) hepatic impairment, C max and AUC of the active metabolite are increased 1.4- and 2.1-fold, respectively, as compared to healthy subjects. Subjects with severe hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh C) have not been studied [ see Use in Specific Populations (8.7) , Warnings and Precautions (5.6) , and Dosage and Administration (2) ]. Drug-Drug Interactions: Drugs Metabolized by Cytochrome P450: At therapeutic concentrations, the active metabolite of fesoterodine does not inhibit CYP1A2, 2B6, 2C8, 2C9, 2C19, 2D6, 2E1, or 3A4, or induce CYP1A2, 2B6, 2C9, 2C19, or 3A4 in vitro [ see Drug Interactions (7.5) ]. CYP3A4 Inhibitors: Following blockade of CYP3A4 by coadministration of the potent CYP3A4 inhibitor ketoconazole 200 mg twice a day for 5 days, C max and AUC of the active metabolite of fesoterodine increased 2.0- and 2.3-fold, respectively, after oral administration of Toviaz 8 mg to CYP2D6 extensive metabolizers. In CYP2D6 poor metabolizers, C max and AUC of the active metabolite of fesoterodine increased 2.1- and 2.5-fold, respectively, during coadministration of ketoconazole 200 mg twice a day for 5 days. C max and AUC were 4.5- and 5.7-fold higher, respectively, in subjects who were CYP2D6 poor metabolizers and taking ketoconazole compared to subjects who were CYP2D6 extensive metabolizers and not taking ketoconazole. In a separate study coadministering fesoterodine with ketoconazole 200 mg once a day for 5 days, the C max and AUC values of the active metabolite of fesoterodine were increased 2.2-fold in CYP2D6 extensive metabolizers and 1.5- and 1.9-fold, respectively, in CYP2D6 poor metabolizers. C max and AUC were 3.4- and 4.2-fold higher, respectively, in subjects who were CYP2D6 poor metabolizers and taking ketoconazole compared to subjects who were CYP2D6 extensive metabolizers and not taking ketoconazole. There is no clinically relevant effect of moderate CYP3A4 inhibitors on the pharmacokinetics of fesoterodine. In a drug-drug interaction study evaluating the coadministration of the moderate CYP3A4 inhibitor fluconazole 200 mg twice a day for 2 days, a single 8 mg dose of fesoterodine was administered 1 hour following the first dose of fluconazole on day 1 of the study. The average (90% confidence interval) for the increase in Cmax and AUC of the active metabolite of fesoterodine was approximately 19% (11% – 28%) and 27% (18% – 36%) respectively. The effect of weak CYP3A4 inhibitors (e.g. cimetidine) was not examined; it is not expected to be in excess of the effect of moderate inhibitors [ see Drug Interactions (7.2) ], Warnings and Precautions (5.8) , and Dosage and Administration (2) ]. CYP3A4 Inducers: Following induction of CYP3A4 by coadministration of rifampicin 600 mg once a day, C max and AUC of the active metabolite of fesoterodine decreased by approximately 70% and 75%, respectively, after oral administration of Toviaz 8 mg. The terminal half-life of the active metabolite was not changed. Induction of CYP3A4 may lead to reduced plasma levels. No dosing adjustments are recommended in the presence of CYP3A4 inducers [ see Drug Interactions (7.3) ]. CYP2D6 Inhibitors: The interaction with CYP2D6 inhibitors was not studied. In poor metabolizers for CYP2D6, representing a maximum CYP2D6 inhibition, C max and AUC of the active metabolite are increased 1.7- and 2-fold, respectively. [ see Drug Interactions (7.4) ]. Oral Contraceptives: Thirty healthy female subjects taking an oral contraceptive containing 0.03 mg ethinyl estradiol and 0.15 mg levonorgestrel were evaluated in a 2-period crossover study. Each subject was randomized to receive concomitant administration of either placebo or fesoterodine 8 mg once daily on days 1 – 14 of hormone cycle for 2 consecutive cycles. Pharmacokinetics of ethinyl estradiol and levonorgestrel were assessed on day 13 of each cycle. Fesoterodine increased the AUC and C max of ethinyl estradiol by 1 – 3% and decreased the AUC and C max of levonorgestrel by 11 – 13% [ see Drug Interactions (7.6) ]. Warfarin: In a cross-over study in 14 healthy male volunteers (18–55 years), a single oral dose of warfarin 25 mg was given either alone or on day 3 of once daily dosing for 9 days with fesoterodine 8 mg. Compared to warfarin alone dosing, the C max and AUC of S-warfarin were lower by ~ 4 %, while the Cmax and AUC of R-warfarin were lower by approximately 8 % and 6% for the co-administration, suggesting absence of a significant pharmacokinetic interaction. There were no statistically significant changes in the measured pharmacodynamic parameters for anti-coagulant activity of warfarin (INR max , AUC INR ), with only a small decrease noted in INR max of ~ 3 % with the co-administration relative to warfarin alone. INR versus time profiles across individual subjects in the study suggested some differences following co-administration with fesoterodine, although there was no definite trend with regard to the changes noted [ see Drug Interactions (7.7) ].</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="4218" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Toviaz is contraindicated in patients with urinary retention, gastric retention, or uncontrolled narrow-angle glaucoma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4219" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Toviaz is also contraindicated in patients with known hypersensitivity to the drug or its ingredients, or to tolterodine tartrate tablets or tolterodine tartrate extended-release capsules.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4220" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Toviaz is also contraindicated in patients with known hypersensitivity to the drug or its ingredients or to tolterodine tartrate tablets or tolterodine tartrate extended-release capsules.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4221" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommended starting dose of Toviaz is 4 mg once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4222" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Based upon individual response and tolerability, the dose may be increased to 8 mg once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4223" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The daily dose of Toviaz should not exceed 4 mg in the following populations: Patients with severe renal impairment (CLCR &lt;30 mL/min).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4224" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Patients taking potent CYP3A4 inhibitors, such as ketoconazole, itraconazole, and clarithromycin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4225" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Toviaz is not recommended for use in patients with severe hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh C).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4226" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Toviaz should be taken with liquid and swallowed whole.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4227" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Toviaz can be administered with or without food, and should not be chewed, divided, or crushed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4228" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The daily dose of Toviaz should not exceed 4 mg in the following populations: Patients with severe renal impairment (CLCR &lt;30 mL/min) (2) Patients taking potent CYP3A4 inhibitors, such as ketoconazole, itraconazole, and clarithromycin.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M7" type="Trigger" span="10 4;25 17" str="dose | should not exceed"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="220 14" str="clarithromycin" code="H1250JIK0A | N0000007316"/>
<Mention id="M4" type="Precipitant" span="202 12" str="itraconazole" code="304NUG5GF4 | N0000006753"/>
<Mention id="M6" type="Precipitant" span="188 12" str="ketoconazole" code="N0000007319 | R9400W927I"/>
<Mention id="M8" type="Precipitant" span="154 24" str="potent CYP3A4 inhibitors" code="N0000182141"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M7" precipitant="M2" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M7" precipitant="M4" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M7" precipitant="M6" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M7" precipitant="M8" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4229" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Coadministration of Toviaz with other antimuscarinic agents that produce dry mouth, constipation, urinary retention, and other anticholinergic pharmacological effects may increase the frequency and/or severity of such effects.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M24" type="Trigger" span="65 7" str="produce "/>
<Mention id="M25" type="Trigger" span="171 22" str=" increase the frequency "/>
<Mention id="M26" type="Trigger" span="171 8;201 8" str=" increase | severity"/>
<Mention id="M27" type="Precipitant" span="38 21" str="antimuscarinic agents" code="N0000000125"/>
<Mention id="M13" type="SpecificInteraction" span="127 15;159 7" str="anticholinergic | effects" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M18" type="SpecificInteraction" span="84 12" str="constipation" code="14760008: Constipation (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M23" type="SpecificInteraction" span="73 9" str="dry mouth" code="87715008: Xerostomia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M28" type="SpecificInteraction" span="98 17" str="urinary retention" code="267064002: Retention of urine (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M24;M25;M26" precipitant="M27" effect="M13" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M24;M25;M26" precipitant="M27" effect="M18" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M24;M25;M26" precipitant="M27" effect="M23" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M24;M25;M26" precipitant="M27" effect="M28" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4230" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Anticholinergic agents may potentially alter the absorption of some concomitantly administered drugs due to anticholinergic effects on gastrointestinal motility.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4231" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Doses of Toviaz greater than 4 mg are not recommended in patients taking potent CYP3A4 inhibitors, such as ketoconazole, itraconazole, and clarithromycin.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M35" type="Trigger" span="38 15" str="not recommended"/>
<Mention id="M30" type="Precipitant" span="139 14" str="clarithromycin" code="H1250JIK0A | N0000007316"/>
<Mention id="M32" type="Precipitant" span="121 12" str="itraconazole" code="304NUG5GF4 | N0000006753"/>
<Mention id="M34" type="Precipitant" span="107 12" str="ketoconazole" code="N0000007319 | R9400W927I"/>
<Mention id="M36" type="Precipitant" span="73 24" str="potent CYP3A4 inhibitors" code="N0000182141"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M30"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M32"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M34"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M36"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4232" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Coadministration of the potent CYP3A4 inhibitor ketoconazole with fesoterodine led to approximately a doubling of the maximum concentration (Cmax) and area under the concentration versus time curve (AUC) of 5-hydroxymethyl tolterodine (5-HMT), the active metabolite of fesoterodine.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M51" type="Trigger" span="102 8;151 14;192 5" str="doubling | area under the | curve"/>
<Mention id="M44" type="Precipitant" span="48 12" str="ketoconazole" code="N0000007319 | R9400W927I"/>
<Mention id="M49" type="Trigger" span="102 8;199 3" str="doubling | AUC"/>
<Mention id="M47" type="Trigger" span="102 37" str="doubling of the maximum concentration"/>
<Mention id="M45" type="Trigger" span="102 8;141 4" str="doubling | Cmax"/>
<Mention id="M52" type="Precipitant" span="24 23" str="potent CYP3A4 inhibitor" code="N0000182141"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M51" precipitant="M44" effect="C54605"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M49" precipitant="M44" effect="C54605"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M47" precipitant="M44" effect="C54602"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M45" precipitant="M44" effect="C54602"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M45" precipitant="M52" effect="C54602"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M47" precipitant="M52" effect="C54602"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M49" precipitant="M52" effect="C54605"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M51" precipitant="M52" effect="C54605"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4233" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Compared with CYP2D6 extensive metabolizers not taking ketoconazole, further increases in the exposure to 5-HMT were observed in subjects who were CYP2D6 poor metabolizers taking ketoconazole.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M53" type="Trigger" span="77 25" str="increases in the exposure"/>
<Mention id="M54" type="Precipitant" span="55 12" str="ketoconazole" code="N0000007319 | R9400W927I"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M53" precipitant="M54" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4234" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>There is no clinically relevant effect of moderate CYP3A4 inhibitors on the pharmacokinetics of fesoterodine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4235" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Following blockade of CYP3A4 by coadministration of the moderate CYP3A4 inhibitor fluconazole 200 mg twice a day for 2 days, the average (90% confidence interval) increase in Cmax and AUC of the active metabolite of fesoterodine was approximately 19% (11% – 28%) and 27% (18% – 36%) respectively.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M61" type="Trigger" span="163 8;184 3" str="increase | AUC"/>
<Mention id="M58" type="Precipitant" span="82 11" str="fluconazole" code="N0000006331 | 8VZV102JFY"/>
<Mention id="M59" type="Trigger" span="163 16" str="increase in Cmax"/>
<Mention id="M62" type="Precipitant" span="56 25" str="moderate CYP3A4 inhibitor" code="N0000182141"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M61" precipitant="M58" effect="C54605"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M59" precipitant="M58" effect="C54602"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M59" precipitant="M62" effect="C54602"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M61" precipitant="M62" effect="C54605"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4236" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>No dosing adjustments are recommended in the presence of moderate CYP3A4 inhibitors (e.g., erythromycin, fluconazole, diltiazem, verapamil and grapefruit juice).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4237" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The effect of weak CYP3A4 inhibitors (e.g. cimetidine) was not examined; it is not expected to be in excess of the effect of moderate inhibitors.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4238" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>No dosing adjustments are recommended in the presence of CYP3A4 inducers, such as rifampin and carbamazepine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4239" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Following induction of CYP3A4 by coadministration of rifampin 600 mg once a day, Cmax and AUC of the active metabolite of fesoterodine decreased by approximately 70% and 75%, respectively, after oral administration of Toviaz 8 mg.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M63" type="Trigger" span="90 3;135 9" str="AUC | decreased"/>
<Mention id="M66" type="Precipitant" span="53 8" str="rifampin" code="VJT6J7R4TR | N0000006026"/>
<Mention id="M65" type="Trigger" span="81 4;135 9" str="Cmax | decreased"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M63" precipitant="M66" effect="C54609"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M65" precipitant="M66" effect="C54606"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4240" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The terminal half-life of the active metabolite was not changed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4241" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The interaction with CYP2D6 inhibitors was not tested clinically.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4242" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>In poor metabolizers for CYP2D6, representing a maximum CYP2D6 inhibition, Cmax and AUC of the active metabolite are increased 1.7- and 2-fold, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4243" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>No dosing adjustments are recommended in the presence of CYP2D6 inhibitors.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4244" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>In vitro data indicate that at therapeutic concentrations, the active metabolite of fesoterodine does not have the potential to inhibit or induce Cytochrome P450 enzyme systems.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4245" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>In the presence of fesoterodine, there are no clinically significant changes in the plasma concentrations of combined oral contraceptives containing ethinyl estradiol and levonorgestrel.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4246" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>A clinical study has shown that fesoterodine 8 mg once daily has no significant effect on the pharmacokinetics or the anticoagulant activity (PT/INR) of warfarin 25 mg. Standard therapeutic monitoring for warfarin should be continued.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4247" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Interactions between Toviaz and laboratory tests have not been studied.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4248" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Angioedema of the face, lips, tongue, and/or larynx has been reported with fesoterodine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4249" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Toviaz should be administered with caution to patients with clinically significant bladder outlet obstruction because of the risk of urinary retention.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4250" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Toviaz, like other antimuscarinic drugs, should be used with caution in patients with decreased gastrointestinal motility, such as those with severe constipation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4251" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Toviaz should be used with caution in patients being treated for narrow-angle glaucoma, and only where the potential benefits outweigh the risks (5.4) Central Nervous System Effects: Somnolence has been reported with Toviaz.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4252" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Advise patients not to drive or operate heavy machinery until they know how Toviaz affects them (5.5) Toviaz should be used with caution in patients with myasthenia gravis, a disease characterized by decreased cholinergic activity at the neuromuscular junction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4253" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In some cases angioedema occurred after the first dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4254" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Angioedema associated with upper airway swelling may be life-threatening.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4255" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If involvement of the tongue, hypopharynx, or larynx occurs, fesoterodine should be promptly discontinued and appropriate therapy and/or measures to ensure a patent airway should be promptly provided.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4256" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Toviaz should be used with caution in patients being treated for narrow-angle glaucoma, and only where the potential benefits outweigh the risks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4257" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Toviaz is associated with anticholinergic central nervous sytem (CNS) effects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4258" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>A variety of CNS anticholinergic effects have been reported, including headache, dizziness, and somnolence.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4259" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients should be monitored for signs of anticholinergic CNS effects, particularly after beginning treatment or increasing the dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4260" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Advise patients not to drive or operate heavy machinery until they know how Toviaz affects them.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4261" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If a patient experiences anticholinergic CNS effects, dose reduction or drug discontinuation should be considered.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4262" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Toviaz has not been studied in patients with severe hepatic impairment and therefore is not recommended for use in this patient population.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4263" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Doses of Toviaz greater than 4 mg are not recommended in patients with severe renal impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4264" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Doses of Toviaz greater than 4 mg are not recommended in patients taking a potent CYP3A4 inhibitor (e.g., ketoconazole, itraconazole, clarithromycin).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M73" type="Trigger" span="38 15" str="not recommended"/>
<Mention id="M68" type="Precipitant" span="134 14" str="clarithromycin" code="H1250JIK0A | N0000007316"/>
<Mention id="M70" type="Precipitant" span="120 12" str="itraconazole" code="304NUG5GF4 | N0000006753"/>
<Mention id="M72" type="Precipitant" span="106 12" str="ketoconazole" code="N0000007319 | R9400W927I"/>
<Mention id="M74" type="Precipitant" span="75 23" str="potent CYP3A4 inhibitor" code="N0000182141"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M73" precipitant="M68"/>
<Interaction id="I29" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M73" precipitant="M70"/>
<Interaction id="I30" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M73" precipitant="M72"/>
<Interaction id="I31" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M73" precipitant="M74"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4265" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>While the effect of weak CYP3A4 inhibitors (e.g. cimetidine) was not examined by clinical study, some pharmacokinetic interaction is expected, albeit less than that observed with moderate CYP3A4 inhibitors.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M79" type="Trigger" span="102 27" str="pharmacokinetic interaction"/>
<Mention id="M76" type="Precipitant" span="49 10" str="cimetidine" code="80061L1WGD"/>
<Mention id="M78" type="Precipitant" span="179 26" str="moderate CYP3A4 inhibitors" code="N0000182141"/>
<Mention id="M80" type="Precipitant" span="20 22" str="weak CYP3A4 inhibitors" code="N0000182141"/>
<Interaction id="I32" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M79" precipitant="M76"/>
<Interaction id="I33" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M79" precipitant="M78"/>
<Interaction id="I34" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M79" precipitant="M80"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4266" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Toviaz should be used with caution in patients with myasthenia gravis, a disease characterized by decreased cholinergic activity at the neuromuscular junction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4267" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Fesoterodine is a competitive muscarinic receptor antagonist.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4268" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>After oral administration, fesoterodine is rapidly and extensively hydrolyzed by nonspecific esterases to its active metabolite, 5-hydroxymethyl tolterodine, which is responsible for the antimuscarinic activity of fesoterodine and is also one of the active moieties of tolterodine tartrate tablets and tolterodine tartrate extended-release capsules.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4269" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Muscarinic receptors play a role in contractions of urinary bladder smooth muscle and stimulation of salivary secretion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4270" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Inhibition of these receptors in the bladder is presumed to be the mechanism by which fesoterodine produces its effects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4271" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In a urodynamic study involving patients with involuntary detrusor contractions, the effects after the administration of fesoterodine on the volume at first detrusor contraction and bladder capacity were assessed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4272" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Administration of fesoterodine increased the volume at first detrusor contraction and bladder capacity in a dose-dependent manner.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4273" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>These findings are consistent with an antimuscarinic effect on the bladder.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4274" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Cardiac Electrophysiology: The effect of fesoterodine 4 mg and 28 mg on the QT interval was evaluated in a double-blind, randomized, placebo- and positive-controlled (moxifloxacin 400 mg once a day) parallel trial with once-daily treatment over a period of 3 days in 261 male and female subjects aged 44 to 65 years.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4275" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Electrocardiographic parameters were measured over a 24-hour period at pre-dose, after the first administration, and after the third administration of study medication.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4276" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Fesoterodine 28 mg was chosen because this dose, when administered to CYP2D6 extensive metabolizers, results in an exposure to the active metabolite that is similar to the exposure in a CYP2D6 poor metabolizer receiving fesoterodine 8 mg together with CYP3A4 blockade.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4277" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Corrected QT intervals (QTc) were calculated using Fridericia's correction and a linear individual correction method.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4278" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Analyses of 24-hour average QTc, time-matched baseline-corrected QTc, and time-matched placebo-subtracted QTc intervals indicate that fesoterodine at doses of 4 and 28 mg/day did not prolong the QT interval.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4279" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The sensitivity of the study was confirmed by positive QTc prolongation by moxifloxacin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4280" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Toviaz is associated with an increase in heart rate that correlates with increasing dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4281" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In the study described above, when compared to placebo, the mean increase in heart rate associated with a dose of 4 mg/day and 28 mg/day of fesoterodine was 3 beats/minute and 11 beats/minute, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4282" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In the two, phase 3, placebo-controlled studies in patients with overactive bladder, the mean increase in heart rate compared to placebo was approximately 3–4 beats/minute in the 4 mg/day group and 3–5 beats/minute in the 8 mg/day group.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4283" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Absorption: After oral administration, fesoterodine is well absorbed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4284" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Due to rapid and extensive hydrolysis by nonspecific esterases to its active metabolite 5-hydroxymethyl tolterodine, fesoterodine cannot be detected in plasma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4285" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Bioavailability of the active metabolite is 52%.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4286" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>After single or multiple-dose oral administration of fesoterodine in doses from 4 mg to 28 mg, plasma concentrations of the active metabolite are proportional to the dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4287" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Maximum plasma levels are reached after approximately 5 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4288" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No accumulation occurs after multiple-dose administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4289" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A summary of pharmacokinetic parameters for the active metabolite after a single dose of Toviaz 4 mg and 8 mg in extensive and poor metabolizers of CYP2D6 is provided in Table 2.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4290" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Table 2: Summary of geometric mean [CV] pharmacokinetic parameters for the active metabolite after a single dose of Toviaz 4 mg and 8 mg in extensive and poor CYP2D6 metabolizers Toviaz 4 mg Toviaz 8 mg Parameter EM (n=16) PM (n=8) EM (n=16) PM (n=8) EM = extensive CYP2D6 metabolizer, PM = poor CYP2D6 metabolizer, CV = coefficient of variation Cmax = maximum plasma concentration, AUC0–tz = area under the concentration time curve from zero up to the last measurable plasma concentration, tmax = time to reach Cmax, t½ = terminal half-life Cmax (ng/mL) 1.89 [43%] 3.45 [54%] 3.98 [28%] 6.90 [39%] AUC0–tz (ng*h/mL) 21.2 [38%] 40.5 [31%] 45.3 [32%] 88.7 [36%] tmax (h)Data presented as median (range) 5 [2–6] 5 [5–6] 5 [3–6] 5 [5–6] t½ (h) 7.31 [27%] 7.31 [30%] 8.59 [41%] 7.66 [21%] Effect of Food: There is no clinically relevant effect of food on the pharmacokinetics of fesoterodine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4291" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In a study of the effects of food on the pharmacokinetics of fesoterodine in 16 healthy male volunteers, concomitant food intake increased the active metabolite of fesoterodine AUC by approximately 19% and Cmax by 18%.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M81" type="Trigger" span="129 9;177 3" str="increased | AUC"/>
<Mention id="M84" type="Precipitant" span="29 4" str="food" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M83" type="Trigger" span="129 9;206 4" str="increased | Cmax"/>
<Interaction id="I35" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M81" precipitant="M84" effect="C54605"/>
<Interaction id="I36" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M83" precipitant="M84" effect="C54602"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4292" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Distribution: Plasma protein binding of the active metabolite is low (approximately 50%) and is primarily bound to albumin and alpha-1-acid glycoprotein.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4293" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mean steady-state volume of distribution following intravenous infusion of the active metabolite is 169 L. Metabolism: After oral administration, fesoterodine is rapidly and extensively hydrolyzed to its active metabolite.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4294" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The active metabolite is further metabolized in the liver to its carboxy, carboxy-N-desisopropyl, and N-desisopropyl metabolites via two major pathways involving CYP2D6 and CYP3A4.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4295" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>None of these metabolites contribute significantly to the antimuscarinic activity of fesoterodine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4296" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Variability in CYP2D6 Metabolism: A subset of individuals (approximately 7% of Caucasians and approximately 2% of African Americans) are poor metabolizers for CYP2D6.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4297" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Cmax and AUC of the active metabolite are increased 1.7- and 2-fold, respectively, in CYP2D6 poor metabolizers, as compared to extensive metabolizers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4298" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Excretion: Hepatic metabolism and renal excretion contribute significantly to the elimination of the active metabolite.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4299" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>After oral administration of fesoterodine, approximately 70% of the administered dose was recovered in urine as the active metabolite (16%), carboxy metabolite (34%), carboxy-N-desisopropyl metabolite (18%), or N-desisopropyl metabolite (1%), and a smaller amount (7%) was recovered in feces.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4300" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The terminal half-life of the active metabolite is approximately 4 hours following an intravenous administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4301" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The apparent terminal half-life following oral administration is approximately 7 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4302" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Pharmacokinetics in Specific Populations: Geriatric Patients: Following a single 8 mg oral dose of fesoterodine, the mean (±SD) AUC and Cmax for the active metabolite 5-hydroxymethyl tolterodine in 12 elderly men (mean age 67 years) were 51.8 ± 26.1 h*ng/mL and 3.8 ± 1.7 ng/mL, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4303" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In the same study, the mean (±SD) AUC and Cmax in 12 young men (mean age 30 years) were 52.0 ± 31.5 h*ng/mL and 4.1 ± 2.1 ng/mL, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4304" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacokinetics of fesoterodine were not significantly influenced by age.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4305" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Pediatric Patients: The pharmacokinetics of fesoterodine have not been evaluated in pediatric patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4306" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Gender: Following a single 8 mg oral dose of fesoterodine, the mean (±SD) AUC and Cmax for the active metabolite 5-hydroxymethyl tolterodine in 12 elderly men (mean age 67 years) were 51.8 ± 26.1 h*ng/mL and 3.8 ± 1.7 ng/mL, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4307" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In the same study, the mean (±SD) AUC and Cmax in 12 elderly women (mean age 68 years) were 56.0 ± 28.8 h*ng/mL and 4.6 ± 2.3 ng/mL, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4308" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacokinetics of fesoterodine were not significantly influenced by gender.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4309" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Race: The effects of Caucasian or Black race on the pharmacokinetics of fesoterodine were examined in a study of 12 Caucasian and 12 Black African young male volunteers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4310" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Each subject received a single oral dose of 8 mg fesoterodine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4311" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mean (±SD) AUC and Cmax for the active metabolite 5-hydroxymethyl tolterodine in Caucasian males were 73.0 ± 27.8 h*ng/mL and 6.1 ± 2.7 ng/mL, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4312" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mean (±SD) AUC and Cmax in Black males were 65.8 ± 23.2 h*ng/mL and 5.5 ± 1.9 ng/mL, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4313" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacokinetics of fesoterodine were not significantly influenced by race.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4314" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Renal Impairment: In patients with mild or moderate renal impairment (CLCR ranging from 30–80 mL/min), Cmax and AUC of the active metabolite are increased up to 1.5- and 1.8-fold, respectively, as compared to healthy subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4315" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In patients with severe renal impairment (CLCR &lt; 30 mL/min), Cmax and AUC are increased 2.0- and 2.3-fold, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4316" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Hepatic Impairment: In patients with moderate (Child-Pugh B) hepatic impairment, Cmax and AUC of the active metabolite are increased 1.4- and 2.1-fold, respectively, as compared to healthy subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4317" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Subjects with severe hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh C) have not been studied.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4318" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Drug-Drug Interactions: Drugs Metabolized by Cytochrome P450: At therapeutic concentrations, the active metabolite of fesoterodine does not inhibit CYP1A2, 2B6, 2C8, 2C9, 2C19, 2D6, 2E1, or 3A4, or induce CYP1A2, 2B6, 2C9, 2C19, or 3A4 in vitro.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4319" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>CYP3A4 Inhibitors: Following blockade of CYP3A4 by coadministration of the potent CYP3A4 inhibitor ketoconazole 200 mg twice a day for 5 days, Cmax and AUC of the active metabolite of fesoterodine increased 2.0- and 2.3-fold, respectively, after oral administration of Toviaz 8 mg to CYP2D6 extensive metabolizers.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M91" type="Trigger" span="152 3;197 9" str="AUC | increased"/>
<Mention id="M88" type="Precipitant" span="99 12" str="ketoconazole" code="N0000007319 | R9400W927I"/>
<Mention id="M89" type="Trigger" span="143 4;197 9" str="Cmax | increased"/>
<Mention id="M92" type="Precipitant" span="75 23" str="potent CYP3A4 inhibitor" code="N0000182141"/>
<Interaction id="I37" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M91" precipitant="M88" effect="C54605"/>
<Interaction id="I38" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M89" precipitant="M88" effect="C54602"/>
<Interaction id="I39" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M89" precipitant="M92" effect="C54602"/>
<Interaction id="I40" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M91" precipitant="M92" effect="C54605"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4320" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In CYP2D6 poor metabolizers, Cmax and AUC of the active metabolite of fesoterodine increased 2.1- and 2.5-fold, respectively, during coadministration of ketoconazole 200 mg twice a day for 5 days.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M93" type="Trigger" span="38 3;83 9" str="AUC | increased"/>
<Mention id="M96" type="Precipitant" span="153 12" str="ketoconazole" code="N0000007319 | R9400W927I"/>
<Mention id="M95" type="Trigger" span="29 4;83 9" str="Cmax | increased"/>
<Interaction id="I41" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M93" precipitant="M96" effect="C54605"/>
<Interaction id="I42" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M95" precipitant="M96" effect="C54602"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4321" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Cmax and AUC were 4.5- and 5.7-fold higher, respectively, in subjects who were CYP2D6 poor metabolizers and taking ketoconazole compared to subjects who were CYP2D6 extensive metabolizers and not taking ketoconazole.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M97" type="Trigger" span="9 3;36 6" str="AUC | higher"/>
<Mention id="M100" type="Precipitant" span="115 12" str="ketoconazole" code="N0000007319 | R9400W927I"/>
<Mention id="M99" type="Trigger" span="0 4;36 6" str="Cmax | higher"/>
<Interaction id="I43" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M97" precipitant="M100" effect="C54605"/>
<Interaction id="I44" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M99" precipitant="M100" effect="C54602"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4322" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In a separate study coadministering fesoterodine with ketoconazole 200 mg once a day for 5 days, the Cmax and AUC values of the active metabolite of fesoterodine were increased 2.2-fold in CYP2D6 extensive metabolizers and 1.5- and 1.9-fold, respectively, in CYP2D6 poor metabolizers.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M101" type="Trigger" span="110 3;167 9" str="AUC | increased"/>
<Mention id="M104" type="Precipitant" span="54 12" str="ketoconazole" code="N0000007319 | R9400W927I"/>
<Mention id="M103" type="Trigger" span="101 4;167 9" str="Cmax | increased"/>
<Interaction id="I45" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M101" precipitant="M104" effect="C54605"/>
<Interaction id="I46" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M103" precipitant="M104" effect="C54602"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4323" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Cmax and AUC were 3.4- and 4.2-fold higher, respectively, in subjects who were CYP2D6 poor metabolizers and taking ketoconazole compared to subjects who were CYP2D6 extensive metabolizers and not taking ketoconazole.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M105" type="Trigger" span="9 3;36 6" str="AUC | higher"/>
<Mention id="M108" type="Precipitant" span="115 12" str="ketoconazole" code="N0000007319 | R9400W927I"/>
<Mention id="M107" type="Trigger" span="0 4;36 6" str="Cmax | higher"/>
<Interaction id="I47" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M105" precipitant="M108" effect="C54605"/>
<Interaction id="I48" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M107" precipitant="M108" effect="C54602"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4324" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In a drug-drug interaction study evaluating the coadministration of the moderate CYP3A4 inhibitor fluconazole 200 mg twice a day for 2 days, a single 8 mg dose of fesoterodine was administered 1 hour following the first dose of fluconazole on day 1 of the study.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4325" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The average (90% confidence interval) for the increase in Cmax and AUC of the active metabolite of fesoterodine was approximately 19% (11% – 28%) and 27% (18% – 36%) respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4326" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The effect of weak CYP3A4 inhibitors (e.g. cimetidine) was not examined; it is not expected to be in excess of the effect of moderate inhibitors, Warnings and Precautions (5.8), and Dosage and Administration (2) ].</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4327" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>CYP3A4 Inducers: Following induction of CYP3A4 by coadministration of rifampicin 600 mg once a day, Cmax and AUC of the active metabolite of fesoterodine decreased by approximately 70% and 75%, respectively, after oral administration of Toviaz 8 mg.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M115" type="Trigger" span="109 3;154 9" str="AUC | decreased"/>
<Mention id="M112" type="Precipitant" span="0 15" str="CYP3A4 Inducers" code="N0000185506"/>
<Mention id="M113" type="Trigger" span="100 4;154 9" str="Cmax | decreased"/>
<Mention id="M116" type="Precipitant" span="70 10" str="rifampicin" code="VJT6J7R4TR"/>
<Interaction id="I49" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M115" precipitant="M112" effect="C54609"/>
<Interaction id="I50" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M113" precipitant="M112" effect="C54606"/>
<Interaction id="I51" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M113" precipitant="M116" effect="C54606"/>
<Interaction id="I52" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M115" precipitant="M116" effect="C54609"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4328" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Induction of CYP3A4 may lead to reduced plasma levels.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M117" type="Trigger" span="32 21" str="reduced plasma levels"/>
<Mention id="M118" type="Precipitant" span="0 19" str="Induction of CYP3A4" code="N0000185506"/>
<Interaction id="I53" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M117" precipitant="M118" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4329" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No dosing adjustments are recommended in the presence of CYP3A4 inducers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4330" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>CYP2D6 Inhibitors: The interaction with CYP2D6 inhibitors was not studied.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4331" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Oral Contraceptives: Thirty healthy female subjects taking an oral contraceptive containing 0.03 mg ethinyl estradiol and 0.15 mg levonorgestrel were evaluated in a 2-period crossover study.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4332" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Each subject was randomized to receive concomitant administration of either placebo or fesoterodine 8 mg once daily on days 1 – 14 of hormone cycle for 2 consecutive cycles.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4333" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Pharmacokinetics of ethinyl estradiol and levonorgestrel were assessed on day 13 of each cycle.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4334" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Fesoterodine increased the AUC and Cmax of ethinyl estradiol by 1 – 3% and decreased the AUC and Cmax of levonorgestrel by 11 – 13%.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M119" type="Trigger" span="13 9;35 4" str="increased | Cmax"/>
<Mention id="M122" type="Precipitant" span="43 17" str="ethinyl estradiol" code="423D2T571U"/>
<Mention id="M121" type="Trigger" span="13 17" str="increased the AUC"/>
<Mention id="M123" type="Trigger" span="75 9;35 4" str="decreased | Cmax"/>
<Mention id="M126" type="Precipitant" span="105 14" str="levonorgestrel" code="5W7SIA7YZW"/>
<Mention id="M125" type="Trigger" span="75 17" str="decreased the AUC"/>
<Interaction id="I54" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M119" precipitant="M122" effect="C54610"/>
<Interaction id="I55" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M121" precipitant="M122" effect="C54613"/>
<Interaction id="I56" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M123" precipitant="M126" effect="C54615"/>
<Interaction id="I57" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M125" precipitant="M126" effect="C54614"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4335" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Warfarin: In a cross-over study in 14 healthy male volunteers (18–55 years), a single oral dose of warfarin 25 mg was given either alone or on day 3 of once daily dosing for 9 days with fesoterodine 8 mg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4336" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Compared to warfarin alone dosing, the Cmax and AUC of S-warfarin were lower by ~ 4 %, while the Cmax and AUC of R-warfarin were lower by approximately 8 % and 6% for the co-administration, suggesting absence of a significant pharmacokinetic interaction.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M127" type="Trigger" span="48 3;71 5" str="AUC | lower"/>
<Mention id="M130" type="Precipitant" span="12 8" str="warfarin" code="5Q7ZVV76EI | N0000006403"/>
<Mention id="M129" type="Trigger" span="39 4;71 5" str="Cmax | lower"/>
<Interaction id="I58" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M127" precipitant="M130" effect="C54614"/>
<Interaction id="I59" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M129" precipitant="M130" effect="C54615"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4337" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There were no statistically significant changes in the measured pharmacodynamic parameters for anti-coagulant activity of warfarin (INRmax, AUCINR), with only a small decrease noted in INRmax of ~ 3 % with the co-administration relative to warfarin alone.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M131" type="Trigger" span="167 8" str="decrease"/>
<Mention id="M132" type="Precipitant" span="122 8" str="warfarin" code="5Q7ZVV76EI | N0000006403"/>
<Mention id="M133" type="SpecificInteraction" span="167 8;132 6" str="decrease | INRmax" code="165583001: International normalized ratio abnormal (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I60" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M131" precipitant="M132" effect="M133" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="4338" LabelDrug="Toviaz" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>INR versus time profiles across individual subjects in the study suggested some differences following co-administration with fesoterodine, although there was no definite trend with regard to the changes noted.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="clarithromycin" precipitantCode="H1250JIK0A | N0000007316" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="clarithromycin" precipitantCode="H1250JIK0A | N0000007316"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="itraconazole" precipitantCode="304NUG5GF4 | N0000006753" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="itraconazole" precipitantCode="304NUG5GF4 | N0000006753"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="ketoconazole" precipitantCode="N0000007319 | R9400W927I" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="ketoconazole" precipitantCode="N0000007319 | R9400W927I" effect="C54602"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="ketoconazole" precipitantCode="N0000007319 | R9400W927I" effect="C54605"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="ketoconazole" precipitantCode="N0000007319 | R9400W927I"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="potent cyp3a4 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000182141" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="potent cyp3a4 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000182141"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="antimuscarinic agents" precipitantCode="N0000000125" effect="14760008: Constipation (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="antimuscarinic agents" precipitantCode="N0000000125" effect="267064002: Retention of urine (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="antimuscarinic agents" precipitantCode="N0000000125" effect="87715008: Xerostomia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="antimuscarinic agents" precipitantCode="N0000000125" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="potent cyp3a4 inhibitor" precipitantCode="N0000182141" effect="C54602"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="potent cyp3a4 inhibitor" precipitantCode="N0000182141" effect="C54605"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="potent cyp3a4 inhibitor" precipitantCode="N0000182141"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="fluconazole" precipitantCode="N0000006331 | 8VZV102JFY" effect="C54602"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="fluconazole" precipitantCode="N0000006331 | 8VZV102JFY" effect="C54605"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="moderate cyp3a4 inhibitor" precipitantCode="N0000182141" effect="C54602"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="moderate cyp3a4 inhibitor" precipitantCode="N0000182141" effect="C54605"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="rifampin" precipitantCode="VJT6J7R4TR | N0000006026" effect="C54606"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="rifampin" precipitantCode="VJT6J7R4TR | N0000006026" effect="C54609"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="cimetidine" precipitantCode="80061L1WGD"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="moderate cyp3a4 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000182141"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="weak cyp3a4 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000182141"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="food" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54602"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="food" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54605"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cyp3a4 inducers" precipitantCode="N0000185506" effect="C54606"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cyp3a4 inducers" precipitantCode="N0000185506" effect="C54609"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="rifampicin" precipitantCode="VJT6J7R4TR" effect="C54606"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="rifampicin" precipitantCode="VJT6J7R4TR" effect="C54609"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="induction of cyp3a4" precipitantCode="N0000185506" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="ethinyl estradiol" precipitantCode="423D2T571U" effect="C54610"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="ethinyl estradiol" precipitantCode="423D2T571U" effect="C54613"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="levonorgestrel" precipitantCode="5W7SIA7YZW" effect="C54614"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="levonorgestrel" precipitantCode="5W7SIA7YZW" effect="C54615"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="warfarin" precipitantCode="5Q7ZVV76EI | N0000006403" effect="165583001: International normalized ratio abnormal (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="warfarin" precipitantCode="5Q7ZVV76EI | N0000006403" effect="C54614"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="warfarin" precipitantCode="5Q7ZVV76EI | N0000006403" effect="C54615"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>