<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Starlix" setid="5cbda9bc-3c0d-4d75-a37a-994844680c8c">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
STARLIX is contraindicated in patients with a history of hypersensitivity to STARLIX or its inactive ingredients. History of hypersensitivity to nateglinide or its inactive ingredients ( 4 )</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
The recommended dose of STARLIX is 120 mg orally three times daily before meals. The recommended dose of STARLIX is 60 mg orally three times daily before meals in patients who are near glycemic goal when treatment is initiated. Instruct patients to take STARLIX 1 to 30 minutes before meals. In patients who skip meals, instruct patients to skip the scheduled dose of STARLIX to reduce the risk of hypoglycemia [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)] . Recommended dose is 120 mg three times daily ( 2 ) In patients who are near glycemic goal when treatment is initiated, 60 mg three times daily may be administered. ( 2 ) Administer 1 to 30 minutes before meals ( 2 ) If a meal is skipped, skip the scheduled dose to reduce the risk of hypoglycemia. ( 2 , 5.1 )</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
Table 2 includes a list of drugs with clinically important drug interactions when concomitantly administered or withdrawn with STARLIX and instructions for managing or preventing them. Table 2: Clinically Significant Drug Interactions with STARLIX Drugs That May Increase the Blood-Glucose-Lowering Effect of STARLIX and Susceptibility to Hypoglycemia Drugs: Nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), salicylates, monoamine oxidase inhibitors, non-selective beta-adrenergic-blocking agents, anabolic hormones (e.g., methandrostenolone), guanethidine, gymnema sylvestre, glucomannan, thioctic acid, and inhibitors of CYP2C9 (e.g., amiodarone, fluconazole, voriconazole, sulfinpyrazone) or in patients known to be poor metabolizers of CYP2C9 substrates, alcohol. Intervention: Dose reductions and increased frequency of glucose monitoring may be required when STARLIX is coadministered with these drugs. Drugs and Herbals That May Reduce the Blood-Glucose-Lowering Effect of STARLIX and Increase Susceptibility to Hyperglycemia Drugs: Thiazides, corticosteroids, thyroid products, sympathomimetics, somatropin, somatostatin analogues (e.g., lanreotide, octreotide), and CYP inducers (e.g., rifampin, phenytoin and St John’s Wort). Intervention: Dose increases and increased frequency of glucose monitoring may be required when STARLIX is coadministered with these drugs. Drugs That May Blunt Signs and Symptoms of Hypoglycemia Drugs: beta-blockers, clonidine, guanethidine, and reserpine Intervention: Increased frequency of glucose monitoring may be required when STARLIX is coadministered with these drugs. Drugs That May Increase the Potential for Hypoglycemia: STARLIX dose reductions and increased frequency of glucose monitoring may be required when co-administered ( 7 ) Drugs That May Increase the Potential for Hyperglycemia: STARLIX dose increases and increased frequency of glucose monitoring may be required when co-administered ( 7 ) Drugs That May Blunt Signs and Symptoms of Hypoglycemia: Increased frequency of glucose monitoring may be required when co-administered ( 7 )</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
Hypoglycemia: STARLIX may cause hypoglycemia. Administer before meals to reduce the risk of hypoglycemia. Skip the scheduled dose of STARLIX if a meal is skipped to reduce the risk of hypoglycemia. ( 5.1 ) Macrovascular Outcomes: There have been no clinical studies establishing conclusive evidence of macrovascular risk reduction with STARLIX. ( 5.2 ) All glinides, including STARLIX, can cause hypoglycemia [see Adverse Reactions (6.1) ]. Severe hypoglycemia can cause seizures, may be life-threatening, or cause death. Hypoglycemia can impair concentration ability and reaction time; this may place an individual and others at risk in situations where these abilities are important (e.g., driving or operating other machinery). Hypoglycemia can happen suddenly and symptoms may differ in each individual and change over time in the same individual. Symptomatic awareness of hypoglycemia may be less pronounced in patients with longstanding diabetes, in patients with diabetic neuropathy (nerve disease), in patients using medications that block the sympathetic nervous system (e.g., beta-blockers) [see Drug Interactions (7)] , or in patients who experience recurrent hypoglycemia. Factors which may increase the risk of hypoglycemia include changes in meal pattern (e.g., macronutrient content), changes in level of physical activity, changes to coadministered medication [see Drug Interactions (7)], and concomitant use with other antidiabetic agents. Patients with renal or hepatic impairment may be at higher risk of hypoglycemia [see Use in Specific Populations (8.6, 8.7), Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)] . Patients should take STARLIX before meals and be instructed to skip the dose of STARLIX if a meal is skipped [see Dosage and Administration (2)] . Patients and caregivers must be educated to recognize and manage hypoglycemia. Self-monitoring of blood glucose plays an essential role in the prevention and management of hypoglycemia. In patients at higher risk for hypoglycemia and patients who have reduced symptomatic awareness of hypoglycemia, increased frequency of blood glucose monitoring is recommended. There have been no clinical studies establishing conclusive evidence of macrovascular risk reduction with STARLIX.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Nateglinide lowers blood glucose levels by stimulating insulin secretion from the pancreas. This action is dependent upon functioning beta-cells in the pancreatic islets. Nateglinide interacts with the ATP-sensitive potassium (K+ ATP ) channel on pancreatic beta-cells. The subsequent depolarization of the beta cell opens the calcium channel, producing calcium influx and insulin secretion. The extent of insulin release is glucose dependent and diminishes at low glucose levels. Nateglinide is highly tissue selective with low affinity for heart and skeletal muscle. STARLIX stimulates pancreatic insulin secretion within 20 minutes of oral administration. When STARLIX is dosed before meals, the peak rise in plasma insulin occurs approximately 1 hour after dosing and falls to baseline by 4 hours after dosing. In patients with Type 2 diabetes, multiple dose administration of nateglinide over the dosage range of 60 mg to 240 mg shows linear pharmacokinetics for both area under the curve (AUC) and C max . In patients with Type 2 diabetes, there is no apparent accumulation of nateglinide upon multiple dosing of up to 240 mg three times daily for 7 days. Absorption Absolute bioavailability of nateglinide is approximately 73%. Plasma profiles are characterized by multiple plasma concentration peaks when nateglinide is administered under fasting conditions. This effect is diminished when nateglinide is taken prior to a meal. Following oral administration immediately prior to a meal, the mean peak plasma nateglinide concentrations (C max ) generally occur within 1 hour (T max ) after dosing. T max is independent of dose. The pharmacokinetics of nateglinide are not affected by the composition of a meal (high protein, fat, or carbohydrate). However, peak plasma levels are significantly reduced when STARLIX is administered 10 minutes prior to a liquid meal as compared to solid meal. When given with or after meals, the extent of nateglinide absorption (AUC) remains unaffected. However, there is a delay in the rate of absorption characterized by a decrease in C max and a delay in time to peak plasma concentration (T max ). STARLIX did not have any effect on gastric emptying in healthy subjects as assessed by acetaminophen testing. Distribution Following intravenous (IV) administration of nateglinide, the steady-state volume of distribution of nateglinide is estimated to be approximately 10 L in healthy subjects. Nateglinide is extensively bound (98%) to serum proteins, primarily serum albumin, and to a lesser extent α1 acid glycoprotein. The extent of serum protein binding is independent of drug concentration over the test range of 0.1 to 10 mcg/mL. Elimination In healthy volunteers and patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus, nateglinide plasma concentrations declined with an average elimination half-life of approximately 1.5 hours. Metabolism In vitro drug metabolism studies indicate that STARLIX is predominantly metabolized by the cytochrome P450 isozyme CYP2C9 (70%) and to a lesser extent CYP3A4 (30%). The major routes of metabolism are hydroxylation followed by glucuronide conjugation. The major metabolites are less potent antidiabetic agents than nateglinide. The isoprene minor metabolite possesses potency similar to that of the parent compound nateglinide. Excretion Nateglinide and its metabolites are rapidly and completely eliminated following oral administration. Eighty-three percent of the 14 C -nateglinide was excreted in the urine with an additional 10% eliminated in the feces. Approximately 16% of the 14 C -nateglinide was excreted in the urine as parent compound. Specific Populations Renal Impairment No pharmacokinetic data are available in subjects with mild renal impairment (CrCl 60 to 89 mL/min). Compared to healthy matched subjects, patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus and moderate and severe renal impairment (CrCl 15-50 mL/min) not on dialysis displayed similar apparent clearance, AUC, and Cmax. Patients with type 2 diabetes and renal failure on dialysis exhibited reduced overall drug exposure (Cmax decreased by 49%; not statistically significant). However, hemodialysis patients also experienced reductions in plasma protein binding compared to the matched healthy volunteers. In a cohort of 8 patients with type 2 diabetes and end-stage renal disease (ESRD) (eGFR &amp;lt; 15 mL/min/1.73m 2 ) M1 metabolite accumulation up to 1.2 ng/mL occurred with a dosage of 90 mg once daily for 1 to 3 months. In another cohort of 8 patients with type 2 diabetes on hemodialysis, M1 concentration decreased after a single session of hemodialysis. Although the hypoglycemic activity of the M1 metabolite is approximately 5 times lower than nateglinide, metabolite accumulation may increase the hypoglycemic effect of the administered dose. Hepatic Impairment In patients with mild hepatic impairment, the mean increase in Cmax and AUC of nateglinide were 37% and 30 % respectively, as compared to healthy matched control subjects. There is no data on pharmacokinetics of STARLIX in patients with moderate-to-severe hepatic impairment. Gender No clinically significant differences in nateglinide pharmacokinetics were observed between men and women. Race Results of a population pharmacokinetic analysis including subjects of Caucasian, Black, and other ethnic origins suggest that race has little influence on the pharmacokinetics of nateglinide. Age Age does not influence the pharmacokinetic properties of nateglinide. Drug Interactions: In vitro assessment of drug interactions STARLIX is a potential inhibitor of the CYP2C9 isoenzyme in vivo as indicated by its ability to inhibit the in vitro metabolism of tolbutamide. Inhibition of CYP3A4 metabolic reactions was not detected in in vitro experiments. In vitro displacement studies with highly protein-bound drugs such as furosemide, propranolol, captopril, nicardipine, pravastatin, glyburide, warfarin, phenytoin, acetylsalicylic acid, tolbutamide, and metformin showed no influence on the extent of nateglinide protein binding. Similarly, nateglinide had no influence on the serum protein binding of propranolol, glyburide, nicardipine, warfarin, phenytoin, acetylsalicylic acid, and tolbutamide in vitro. However, prudent evaluation of individual cases is warranted in the clinical setting. In vivo assessment of drug interactions The effect of coadministered drugs on the pharmacokinetics of nateglinide and the effect of nateglinide on pharmacokinetics of coadministered drugs are shown in Tables 3 and 4. No clinically relevant change in pharmacokinetic parameters of either agent was reported when nateglinide was coadministered with glyburide, metformin, digoxin, warfarin, and diclofenac. Table 3: Effect of Coadministered Drugs on Pharmacokinetics of Nateglinide AM: after morning dose; PM: after evening dose; * after second dose; ↑: increase in the parameter; ↓: decrease in the parameter Coadministered drug Dosing regimen of coadministered drug Dosing regimen of nateglinide Change in C max Change in AUC Glyburide 10 mg once daily for 3 weeks 120 mg three times a day, single dose 8.78% ↓ 3.53 % ↓ Metformin 500 mg three times a day for 3 weeks 120 mg three times a day, single dose AM: 7.14% ↑ PM: 11.4% ↓ AM: 1.51% ↑ PM: 5.97% ↑ Digoxin 1 mg, single dose 120 mg three times a day, single dose AM: 2.17% ↓ PM: 3.19% ↑ AM: 7.62% ↑ PM: 2.22% ↑ Warfarin 30 mg, single dose 120 mg three times a day for 4 days 2.65% ↑ 3.72% ↓ Diclofenac 75 mg, single dose 120 mg twice daily, single dose AM: 13.23% ↓ *PM: 3.76% ↑ AM: 2.2% ↓ *PM: 7.5% ↑ Table 4: Effect of Nateglinide on Pharmacokinetics of Coadministered Drugs AM: after morning dose; PM: after evening dose; SD: single dose; ↑: increase in the parameter; ↓: decrease in the parameter Coadministered drug Dosing regimen of coadministered drug Dosing regimen of nateglinide Change in C max Change in AUC Glyburide 10 mg once daily for 3 weeks 120 mg three times a day, single dose 3.18% ↓ 7.34% ↓ Metformin 500 mg three times a day for 3 weeks 120 mg three times a day, single dose AM: 10.7% ↑ PM: 0.40% ↑ AM: 13.3% ↑ PM: 2.27% ↓ Digoxin 1 mg, single dose 120 mg three times a day, single dose 5.41% ↓ 6.58 % ↑ Warfarin 30 mg, single dose 120 mg three times a day for 4 days R-warfarin: 1.03% ↓ S-warfarin: 0.85% ↓ R-warfarin: 0.74% ↑ S-warfarin: 7.23% ↑ Diclofenac 75 mg, single dose 120 mg twice daily, single dose 2.19% ↑ 7.97% ↑</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="6728" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>STARLIX is contraindicated in patients with a history of hypersensitivity to STARLIX or its inactive ingredients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6729" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>History of hypersensitivity to nateglinide or its inactive ingredients (4)</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6730" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommended dose of STARLIX is 120 mg orally three times daily before meals.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6731" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommended dose of STARLIX is 60 mg orally three times daily before meals in patients who are near glycemic goal when treatment is initiated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6732" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Instruct patients to take STARLIX 1 to 30 minutes before meals.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6733" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In patients who skip meals, instruct patients to skip the scheduled dose of STARLIX to reduce the risk of hypoglycemia.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M1" type="Trigger" span="87 15" str="reduce the risk"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="21 5" str="meals" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M3" type="SpecificInteraction" span="106 12" str="hypoglycemia" code="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M1" precipitant="M2" effect="M3" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6734" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Recommended dose is 120 mg three times daily (2) In patients who are near glycemic goal when treatment is initiated, 60 mg three times daily may be administered.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6735" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Administer 1 to 30 minutes before meals (2) If a meal is skipped, skip the scheduled dose to reduce the risk of hypoglycemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6736" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Table 2 includes a list of drugs with clinically important drug interactions when concomitantly administered or withdrawn with STARLIX and instructions for managing or preventing them.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6737" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Table 2: Clinically Significant Drug Interactions with STARLIX Drugs That May Increase the Blood-Glucose-Lowering Effect of STARLIX and Susceptibility to Hypoglycemia Drugs: Nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), salicylates, monoamine oxidase inhibitors, non-selective beta-adrenergic-blocking agents, anabolic hormones (e.g., methandrostenolone), guanethidine, gymnema sylvestre, glucomannan, thioctic acid, and inhibitors of CYP2C9 (e.g., amiodarone, fluconazole, voriconazole, sulfinpyrazone) or in patients known to be poor metabolizers of CYP2C9 substrates, alcohol.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M112" type="Trigger" span="78 8;136 14" str="Increase | Susceptibility"/>
<Mention id="M8" type="Precipitant" span="572 7" str="alcohol" code="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M"/>
<Mention id="M114" type="SpecificInteraction" span="154 12" str="hypoglycemia" code="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M115" type="Trigger" span="78 8;114 6" str="Increase | Effect"/>
<Mention id="M117" type="SpecificInteraction" span="78 53" str="Increase the Blood-Glucose-Lowering Effect of STARLIX" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M14" type="Precipitant" span="450 10" str="amiodarone" code="N0000005761 | N3RQ532IUT"/>
<Mention id="M20" type="Precipitant" span="311 17" str="anabolic hormones" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M26" type="Precipitant" span="278 31" str="beta-adrenergic-blocking agents" code="N0000000161 | N0000175556"/>
<Mention id="M32" type="Precipitant" span="553 17" str="CYP2C9 substrates" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M38" type="Precipitant" span="462 11" str="fluconazole" code="N0000006331 | 8VZV102JFY"/>
<Mention id="M44" type="Precipitant" span="390 11" str="glucomannan" code="36W3E5TAMG"/>
<Mention id="M50" type="Precipitant" span="357 12" str="guanethidine" code="ZTI6C33Q2Q"/>
<Mention id="M56" type="Precipitant" span="371 17" str="gymnema sylvestre" code="E95LRW83Y9"/>
<Mention id="M62" type="Precipitant" span="422 20" str="inhibitors of CYP2C9" code="N0000185504"/>
<Mention id="M68" type="Precipitant" span="336 18" str="methandrostenolone" code="COZ1R7EOCC"/>
<Mention id="M74" type="Precipitant" span="234 28" str="monoamine oxidase inhibitors" code="N0000000184 | N0000175744"/>
<Mention id="M80" type="Precipitant" span="264 45" str="non-selective beta-adrenergic-blocking agents" code="N0000175953"/>
<Mention id="M86" type="Precipitant" span="174 36" str="Nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M92" type="Precipitant" span="212 6" str="NSAIDs" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M98" type="Precipitant" span="221 11" str="salicylates" code="N0000006035 | O414PZ4LPZ"/>
<Mention id="M104" type="Precipitant" span="489 14" str="sulfinpyrazone" code="V6OFU47K3W"/>
<Mention id="M110" type="Precipitant" span="403 13" str="thioctic acid" code="73Y7P0K73Y"/>
<Mention id="M116" type="Precipitant" span="475 12" str="voriconazole" code="N0000010191 | JFU09I87TR"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M112" precipitant="M8" effect="M114" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M115" precipitant="M8" effect="M117" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M112" precipitant="M14" effect="M114" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M115" precipitant="M14" effect="M117" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M112" precipitant="M20" effect="M114" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M115" precipitant="M20" effect="M117" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M112" precipitant="M26" effect="M114" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M115" precipitant="M26" effect="M117" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M112" precipitant="M32" effect="M114" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M115" precipitant="M32" effect="M117" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M112" precipitant="M38" effect="M114" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M115" precipitant="M38" effect="M117" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M112" precipitant="M44" effect="M114" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M115" precipitant="M44" effect="M117" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M112" precipitant="M50" effect="M114" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M115" precipitant="M50" effect="M117" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M112" precipitant="M56" effect="M114" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M115" precipitant="M56" effect="M117" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M112" precipitant="M62" effect="M114" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M115" precipitant="M62" effect="M117" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M112" precipitant="M68" effect="M114" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M115" precipitant="M68" effect="M117" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M112" precipitant="M74" effect="M114" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M115" precipitant="M74" effect="M117" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M112" precipitant="M80" effect="M114" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M115" precipitant="M80" effect="M117" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M112" precipitant="M86" effect="M114" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I29" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M115" precipitant="M86" effect="M117" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I30" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M112" precipitant="M92" effect="M114" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I31" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M115" precipitant="M92" effect="M117" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I32" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M112" precipitant="M98" effect="M114" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I33" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M115" precipitant="M98" effect="M117" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I34" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M112" precipitant="M104" effect="M114" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I35" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M115" precipitant="M104" effect="M117" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I36" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M112" precipitant="M110" effect="M114" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I37" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M115" precipitant="M110" effect="M117" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I38" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M112" precipitant="M116" effect="M114" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I39" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M115" precipitant="M116" effect="M117" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6738" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Intervention: Dose reductions and increased frequency of glucose monitoring may be required when STARLIX is coadministered with these drugs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6739" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Drugs and Herbals That May Reduce the Blood-Glucose-Lowering Effect of STARLIX and Increase Susceptibility to Hyperglycemia Drugs: Thiazides, corticosteroids, thyroid products, sympathomimetics, somatropin, somatostatin analogues (e.g., lanreotide, octreotide), and CYP inducers (e.g., rifampin, phenytoin and St John’s Wort).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M184" type="Trigger" span="27 6;61 6" str="Reduce | Effect"/>
<Mention id="M122" type="Precipitant" span="142 15" str="corticosteroids" code="N0000011309 | N0000175576"/>
<Mention id="M186" type="SpecificInteraction" span="38 40" str="Blood-Glucose-Lowering Effect of STARLIX" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M187" type="Trigger" span="83 23" str="Increase Susceptibility"/>
<Mention id="M189" type="SpecificInteraction" span="110 13" str="Hyperglycemia" code="80394007: Hyperglycemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M128" type="Precipitant" span="266 12" str="CYP inducers" code="N0000185505"/>
<Mention id="M134" type="Precipitant" span="237 10" str="lanreotide" code="0G3DE8943Y"/>
<Mention id="M140" type="Precipitant" span="249 10" str="octreotide" code="RWM8CCW8GP"/>
<Mention id="M146" type="Precipitant" span="296 9" str="phenytoin" code="6158TKW0C5 | N0000006023"/>
<Mention id="M152" type="Precipitant" span="286 8" str="rifampin" code="VJT6J7R4TR | N0000006026"/>
<Mention id="M158" type="Precipitant" span="207 22" str="somatostatin analogues" code="N0000175904"/>
<Mention id="M164" type="Precipitant" span="195 10" str="somatropin" code="NQX9KB6PCL"/>
<Mention id="M170" type="Precipitant" span="310 14" str="St John’s Wort" code="N0000022261 | UFH8805FKA"/>
<Mention id="M176" type="Precipitant" span="177 16" str="sympathomimetics" code="N0000029104 | N0000175651"/>
<Mention id="M182" type="Precipitant" span="131 9" str="Thiazides" code="N0000175419"/>
<Mention id="M188" type="Precipitant" span="159 16" str="thyroid products" code="0B4FDL9I6P"/>
<Interaction id="I40" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M184" precipitant="M122" effect="M186" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I41" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M187" precipitant="M122" effect="M189" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I42" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M184" precipitant="M128" effect="M186" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I43" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M187" precipitant="M128" effect="M189" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I44" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M184" precipitant="M134" effect="M186" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I45" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M187" precipitant="M134" effect="M189" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I46" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M184" precipitant="M140" effect="M186" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I47" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M187" precipitant="M140" effect="M189" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I48" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M184" precipitant="M146" effect="M186" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I49" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M187" precipitant="M146" effect="M189" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I50" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M184" precipitant="M152" effect="M186" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I51" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M187" precipitant="M152" effect="M189" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I52" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M184" precipitant="M158" effect="M186" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I53" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M187" precipitant="M158" effect="M189" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I54" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M184" precipitant="M164" effect="M186" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I55" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M187" precipitant="M164" effect="M189" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I56" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M184" precipitant="M170" effect="M186" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I57" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M187" precipitant="M170" effect="M189" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I58" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M184" precipitant="M176" effect="M186" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I59" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M187" precipitant="M176" effect="M189" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I60" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M184" precipitant="M182" effect="M186" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I61" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M187" precipitant="M182" effect="M189" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I62" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M184" precipitant="M188" effect="M186" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I63" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M187" precipitant="M188" effect="M189" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6740" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Intervention: Dose increases and increased frequency of glucose monitoring may be required when STARLIX is coadministered with these drugs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6741" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Drugs That May Blunt Signs and Symptoms of Hypoglycemia Drugs: beta-blockers, clonidine, guanethidine, and reserpine Intervention: Increased frequency of glucose monitoring may be required when STARLIX is coadministered with these drugs.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M214" type="Trigger" span="15 24" str="Blunt Signs and Symptoms"/>
<Mention id="M194" type="Precipitant" span="63 13" str="beta-blockers" code="N0000000161 | N0000175556"/>
<Mention id="M216" type="SpecificInteraction" span="15 40" str="Blunt Signs and Symptoms of Hypoglycemia" code="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M217" type="Trigger" span="131 9;162 10" str="Increased | monitoring"/>
<Mention id="M219" type="SpecificInteraction" span="154 7" str="glucose" code="166922008: Blood glucose abnormal (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M200" type="Precipitant" span="78 9" str="clonidine" code="N0000006505 | MN3L5RMN02"/>
<Mention id="M206" type="Precipitant" span="0 55" str="Drugs That May Blunt Signs and Symptoms of Hypoglycemia" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M212" type="Precipitant" span="89 12" str="guanethidine" code="ZTI6C33Q2Q"/>
<Mention id="M218" type="Precipitant" span="107 9" str="reserpine" code="8B1QWR724A"/>
<Interaction id="I64" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M214" precipitant="M194" effect="M216" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I65" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M217" precipitant="M194" effect="M219" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I66" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M214" precipitant="M200" effect="M216" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I67" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M217" precipitant="M200" effect="M219" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I68" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M214" precipitant="M206" effect="M216" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I69" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M217" precipitant="M206" effect="M219" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I70" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M214" precipitant="M212" effect="M216" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I71" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M217" precipitant="M212" effect="M219" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I72" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M214" precipitant="M218" effect="M216" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I73" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M217" precipitant="M218" effect="M219" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6742" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Drugs That May Increase the Potential for Hypoglycemia: STARLIX dose reductions and increased frequency of glucose monitoring may be required when co-administered (7) Drugs That May Increase the Potential for Hyperglycemia: STARLIX dose increases and increased frequency of glucose monitoring may be required when co-administered (7) Drugs That May Blunt Signs and Symptoms of Hypoglycemia: Increased frequency of glucose monitoring may be required when co-administered (7)</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M220" type="Trigger" span="349 24" str="Blunt Signs and Symptoms"/>
<Mention id="M224" type="Precipitant" span="334 55" str="Drugs That May Blunt Signs and Symptoms of Hypoglycemia" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M222" type="SpecificInteraction" span="349 40" str="Blunt Signs and Symptoms of Hypoglycemia" code="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M240" type="Trigger" span="84 9;115 10" str="increased | monitoring"/>
<Mention id="M242" type="SpecificInteraction" span="107 7" str="glucose" code="166922008: Blood glucose abnormal (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M234" type="Precipitant" span="167 55" str="Drugs That May Increase the Potential for Hyperglycemia" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M229" type="Trigger" span="232 14" str="dose increases "/>
<Mention id="M237" type="Trigger" span="84 9;115 10" str=" increased | monitoring"/>
<Mention id="M243" type="Trigger" span="15 22" str="Increase the Potential"/>
<Mention id="M235" type="SpecificInteraction" span="209 13" str="Hyperglycemia" code="80394007: Hyperglycemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M236" type="Trigger" span="64 15" str="dose reductions "/>
<Mention id="M244" type="Precipitant" span="0 54" str="Drugs That May Increase the Potential for Hypoglycemia" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M245" type="SpecificInteraction" span="42 12" str="hypoglycemia" code="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I74" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M220" precipitant="M224" effect="M222" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I75" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M240" precipitant="M224" effect="M242" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I76" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M240" precipitant="M234" effect="M242" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I77" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M229;M237" precipitant="M234" effect="M242" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I78" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M243" precipitant="M234" effect="M235" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I79" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M236;M237" precipitant="M244" effect="M242" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I80" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M240" precipitant="M244" effect="M242" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I81" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M243" precipitant="M244" effect="M245" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6743" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hypoglycemia: STARLIX may cause hypoglycemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6744" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Administer before meals to reduce the risk of hypoglycemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6745" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Skip the scheduled dose of STARLIX if a meal is skipped to reduce the risk of hypoglycemia.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M246" type="Trigger" span="0 4;56 18" str="Skip | to reduce the risk"/>
<Mention id="M247" type="Precipitant" span="40 4" str="meal" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M248" type="SpecificInteraction" span="78 12" str="hypoglycemia" code="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I82" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M246" precipitant="M247" effect="M248" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6746" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Macrovascular Outcomes: There have been no clinical studies establishing conclusive evidence of macrovascular risk reduction with STARLIX.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6747" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>All glinides, including STARLIX, can cause hypoglycemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6748" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Severe hypoglycemia can cause seizures, may be life-threatening, or cause death.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6749" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hypoglycemia can impair concentration ability and reaction time; this may place an individual and others at risk in situations where these abilities are important (e.g., driving or operating other machinery).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6750" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hypoglycemia can happen suddenly and symptoms may differ in each individual and change over time in the same individual.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6751" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Symptomatic awareness of hypoglycemia may be less pronounced in patients with longstanding diabetes, in patients with diabetic neuropathy (nerve disease), in patients using medications that block the sympathetic nervous system (e.g., beta-blockers), or in patients who experience recurrent hypoglycemia.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M253" type="Trigger" span="0 11" str="Symptomatic "/>
<Mention id="M254" type="Trigger" span="45 15" str=" less pronounced"/>
<Mention id="M251" type="Precipitant" span="234 13" str="beta-blockers" code="N0000000161 | N0000175556"/>
<Mention id="M256" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 60" str="Symptomatic awareness of hypoglycemia may be less pronounced" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M255" type="Precipitant" span="173 53" str="medications that block the sympathetic nervous system" code="N0000175650"/>
<Interaction id="I83" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M253;M254" precipitant="M251" effect="M256" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I84" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M253;M254" precipitant="M255" effect="M256" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6752" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Factors which may increase the risk of hypoglycemia include changes in meal pattern (e.g., macronutrient content), changes in level of physical activity, changes to coadministered medication, and concomitant use with other antidiabetic agents.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M260" type="Trigger" span="18 17" str="increase the risk"/>
<Mention id="M258" type="Precipitant" span="223 19" str="antidiabetic agents" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M262" type="SpecificInteraction" span="39 12" str="hypoglycemia" code="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M261" type="Precipitant" span="91 13" str="macronutrient" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I85" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M260" precipitant="M258" effect="M262" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I86" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M260" precipitant="M261" effect="M262" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6753" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients with renal or hepatic impairment may be at higher risk of hypoglycemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6754" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients should take STARLIX before meals and be instructed to skip the dose of STARLIX if a meal is skipped.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6755" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients and caregivers must be educated to recognize and manage hypoglycemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6756" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Self-monitoring of blood glucose plays an essential role in the prevention and management of hypoglycemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6757" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In patients at higher risk for hypoglycemia and patients who have reduced symptomatic awareness of hypoglycemia, increased frequency of blood glucose monitoring is recommended.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6758" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There have been no clinical studies establishing conclusive evidence of macrovascular risk reduction with STARLIX.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6759" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Nateglinide lowers blood glucose levels by stimulating insulin secretion from the pancreas.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6760" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This action is dependent upon functioning beta-cells in the pancreatic islets.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6761" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Nateglinide interacts with the ATP-sensitive potassium (K+ATP) channel on pancreatic beta-cells.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6762" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The subsequent depolarization of the beta cell opens the calcium channel, producing calcium influx and insulin secretion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6763" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The extent of insulin release is glucose dependent and diminishes at low glucose levels.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6764" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Nateglinide is highly tissue selective with low affinity for heart and skeletal muscle.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6765" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>STARLIX stimulates pancreatic insulin secretion within 20 minutes of oral administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6766" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>When STARLIX is dosed before meals, the peak rise in plasma insulin occurs approximately 1 hour after dosing and falls to baseline by 4 hours after dosing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6767" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In patients with Type 2 diabetes, multiple dose administration of nateglinide over the dosage range of 60 mg to 240 mg shows linear pharmacokinetics for both area under the curve (AUC) and Cmax.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6768" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In patients with Type 2 diabetes, there is no apparent accumulation of nateglinide upon multiple dosing of up to 240 mg three times daily for 7 days.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6769" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Absorption Absolute bioavailability of nateglinide is approximately 73%.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6770" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Plasma profiles are characterized by multiple plasma concentration peaks when nateglinide is administered under fasting conditions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6771" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This effect is diminished when nateglinide is taken prior to a meal.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M263" type="Trigger" span="5 25;46 14" str="effect is diminished when | taken prior to"/>
<Mention id="M264" type="Precipitant" span="63 4" str="meal" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I87" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M264"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6772" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following oral administration immediately prior to a meal, the mean peak plasma nateglinide concentrations (Cmax) generally occur within 1 hour (Tmax) after dosing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6773" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacokinetics of nateglinide are not affected by the composition of a meal (high protein, fat, or carbohydrate).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6774" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>However, peak plasma levels are significantly reduced when STARLIX is administered 10 minutes prior to a liquid meal as compared to solid meal.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M265" type="Trigger" span="9 18;46 7" str="peak plasma levels | reduced"/>
<Mention id="M266" type="Precipitant" span="105 11" str="liquid meal" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I88" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M265" precipitant="M266" effect="C54606"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6775" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>When given with or after meals, the extent of nateglinide absorption (AUC) remains unaffected.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6776" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>However, there is a delay in the rate of absorption characterized by a decrease in Cmax and a delay in time to peak plasma concentration (Tmax).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6777" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>STARLIX did not have any effect on gastric emptying in healthy subjects as assessed by acetaminophen testing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6778" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Distribution Following intravenous (IV) administration of nateglinide, the steady-state volume of distribution of nateglinide is estimated to be approximately 10 L in healthy subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6779" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Nateglinide is extensively bound (98%) to serum proteins, primarily serum albumin, and to a lesser extent α1 acid glycoprotein.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6780" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The extent of serum protein binding is independent of drug concentration over the test range of 0.1 to 10 mcg/mL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6781" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Elimination In healthy volunteers and patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus, nateglinide plasma concentrations declined with an average elimination half-life of approximately 1.5 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6782" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Metabolism In vitro drug metabolism studies indicate that STARLIX is predominantly metabolized by the cytochrome P450 isozyme CYP2C9 (70%) and to a lesser extent CYP3A4 (30%).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6783" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The major routes of metabolism are hydroxylation followed by glucuronide conjugation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6784" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The major metabolites are less potent antidiabetic agents than nateglinide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6785" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The isoprene minor metabolite possesses potency similar to that of the parent compound nateglinide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6786" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Excretion Nateglinide and its metabolites are rapidly and completely eliminated following oral administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6787" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Eighty-three percent of the 14C-nateglinide was excreted in the urine with an additional 10% eliminated in the feces.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6788" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Approximately 16% of the 14C-nateglinide was excreted in the urine as parent compound.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6789" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Specific Populations Renal Impairment No pharmacokinetic data are available in subjects with mild renal impairment (CrCl 60 to 89 mL/min).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6790" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Compared to healthy matched subjects, patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus and moderate and severe renal impairment (CrCl 15-50 mL/min) not on dialysis displayed similar apparent clearance, AUC, and Cmax.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6791" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Patients with type 2 diabetes and renal failure on dialysis exhibited reduced overall drug exposure (Cmax decreased by 49%; not statistically significant).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6792" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>However, hemodialysis patients also experienced reductions in plasma protein binding compared to the matched healthy volunteers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6793" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In a cohort of 8 patients with type 2 diabetes and end-stage renal disease (ESRD) (eGFR &lt; 15 mL/min/1.73m2) M1 metabolite accumulation up to 1.2 ng/mL occurred with a dosage of 90 mg once daily for 1 to 3 months.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6794" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In another cohort of 8 patients with type 2 diabetes on hemodialysis, M1 concentration decreased after a single session of hemodialysis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6795" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Although the hypoglycemic activity of the M1 metabolite is approximately 5 times lower than nateglinide, metabolite accumulation may increase the hypoglycemic effect of the administered dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6796" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Hepatic Impairment In patients with mild hepatic impairment, the mean increase in Cmax and AUC of nateglinide were 37% and 30 % respectively, as compared to healthy matched control subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6797" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There is no data on pharmacokinetics of STARLIX in patients with moderate-to-severe hepatic impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6798" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Gender No clinically significant differences in nateglinide pharmacokinetics were observed between men and women.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6799" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Race Results of a population pharmacokinetic analysis including subjects of Caucasian, Black, and other ethnic origins suggest that race has little influence on the pharmacokinetics of nateglinide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6800" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Age Age does not influence the pharmacokinetic properties of nateglinide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6801" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Drug Interactions: In vitro assessment of drug interactions STARLIX is a potential inhibitor of the CYP2C9 isoenzyme in vivo as indicated by its ability to inhibit the in vitro metabolism of tolbutamide.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M267" type="Trigger" span="83 7;177 10" str="inhibit | metabolism"/>
<Mention id="M268" type="Precipitant" span="191 11" str="tolbutamide" code="982XCM1FOI"/>
<Interaction id="I89" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M267" precipitant="M268" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6802" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Inhibition of CYP3A4 metabolic reactions was not detected in in vitro experiments.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6803" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In vitro displacement studies with highly protein-bound drugs such as furosemide, propranolol, captopril, nicardipine, pravastatin, glyburide, warfarin, phenytoin, acetylsalicylic acid, tolbutamide, and metformin showed no influence on the extent of nateglinide protein binding.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6804" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Similarly, nateglinide had no influence on the serum protein binding of propranolol, glyburide, nicardipine, warfarin, phenytoin, acetylsalicylic acid, and tolbutamide in vitro.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6805" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>However, prudent evaluation of individual cases is warranted in the clinical setting.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6806" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In vivo assessment of drug interactions The effect of coadministered drugs on the pharmacokinetics of nateglinide and the effect of nateglinide on pharmacokinetics of coadministered drugs are shown in Tables 3 and 4.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6807" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No clinically relevant change in pharmacokinetic parameters of either agent was reported when nateglinide was coadministered with glyburide, metformin, digoxin, warfarin, and diclofenac.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="6808" LabelDrug="Starlix" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Table 3: Effect of Coadministered Drugs on Pharmacokinetics of Nateglinide AM: after morning dose; PM: after evening dose; *after second dose; ↑: increase in the parameter; ↓: decrease in the parameter Coadministered drug Dosing regimen of coadministered drug Dosing regimen of nateglinide Change in Cmax Change in AUC Glyburide 10 mg once daily for 3 weeks 120 mg three times a day, single dose 8.78% ↓ 3.53 % ↓ Metformin 500 mg three times a day for 3 weeks 120 mg three times a day, single dose AM: 7.14% ↑PM: 11.4% ↓ AM: 1.51% ↑PM: 5.97% ↑ Digoxin 1 mg, single dose 120 mg three times a day, single dose AM: 2.17% ↓PM: 3.19% ↑ AM: 7.62% ↑PM: 2.22% ↑ Warfarin 30 mg, single dose 120 mg three times a day for 4 days 2.65% ↑ 3.72% ↓ Diclofenac 75 mg, single dose 120 mg twice daily, single dose AM: 13.23% ↓*PM: 3.76% ↑ AM: 2.2% ↓*PM: 7.5% ↑ Table 4: Effect of Nateglinide on Pharmacokinetics of Coadministered Drugs AM: after morning dose; PM: after evening dose; SD: single dose; ↑: increase in the parameter; ↓: decrease in the parameter Coadministered drug Dosing regimen of coadministered drug Dosing regimen of nateglinide Change in Cmax Change in AUC Glyburide 10 mg once daily for 3 weeks 120 mg three times a day, single dose 3.18% ↓ 7.34% ↓ Metformin 500 mg three times a day for 3 weeks 120 mg three times a day, single dose AM: 10.7% ↑PM: 0.40% ↑ AM: 13.3% ↑PM: 2.27% ↓ Digoxin 1 mg, single dose 120 mg three times a day, single dose 5.41% ↓ 6.58 % ↑ Warfarin 30 mg, single dose 120 mg three times a day for 4 days R-warfarin: 1.03% ↓S-warfarin: 0.85% ↓ R-warfarin: 0.74% ↑S-warfarin: 7.23% ↑ Diclofenac 75 mg, single dose 120 mg twice daily, single dose 2.19% ↑ 7.97% ↑</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="meals" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="alcohol" precipitantCode="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="alcohol" precipitantCode="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="amiodarone" precipitantCode="N0000005761 | N3RQ532IUT" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="amiodarone" precipitantCode="N0000005761 | N3RQ532IUT" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="anabolic hormones" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="anabolic hormones" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="beta-adrenergic-blocking agents" precipitantCode="N0000000161 | N0000175556" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="beta-adrenergic-blocking agents" precipitantCode="N0000000161 | N0000175556" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cyp2c9 substrates" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cyp2c9 substrates" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="fluconazole" precipitantCode="N0000006331 | 8VZV102JFY" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="fluconazole" precipitantCode="N0000006331 | 8VZV102JFY" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="glucomannan" precipitantCode="36W3E5TAMG" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="glucomannan" precipitantCode="36W3E5TAMG" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="guanethidine" precipitantCode="ZTI6C33Q2Q" effect="166922008: Blood glucose abnormal (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="guanethidine" precipitantCode="ZTI6C33Q2Q" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="guanethidine" precipitantCode="ZTI6C33Q2Q" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="gymnema sylvestre" precipitantCode="E95LRW83Y9" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="gymnema sylvestre" precipitantCode="E95LRW83Y9" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="inhibitors of cyp2c9" precipitantCode="N0000185504" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="inhibitors of cyp2c9" precipitantCode="N0000185504" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="methandrostenolone" precipitantCode="COZ1R7EOCC" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="methandrostenolone" precipitantCode="COZ1R7EOCC" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="monoamine oxidase inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000000184 | N0000175744" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="monoamine oxidase inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000000184 | N0000175744" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="non-selective beta-adrenergic-blocking agents" precipitantCode="N0000175953" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="non-selective beta-adrenergic-blocking agents" precipitantCode="N0000175953" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nsaids" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nsaids" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="salicylates" precipitantCode="N0000006035 | O414PZ4LPZ" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="salicylates" precipitantCode="N0000006035 | O414PZ4LPZ" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sulfinpyrazone" precipitantCode="V6OFU47K3W" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sulfinpyrazone" precipitantCode="V6OFU47K3W" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="thioctic acid" precipitantCode="73Y7P0K73Y" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="thioctic acid" precipitantCode="73Y7P0K73Y" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="voriconazole" precipitantCode="N0000010191 | JFU09I87TR" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="voriconazole" precipitantCode="N0000010191 | JFU09I87TR" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="corticosteroids" precipitantCode="N0000011309 | N0000175576" effect="80394007: Hyperglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="corticosteroids" precipitantCode="N0000011309 | N0000175576" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cyp inducers" precipitantCode="N0000185505" effect="80394007: Hyperglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cyp inducers" precipitantCode="N0000185505" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="lanreotide" precipitantCode="0G3DE8943Y" effect="80394007: Hyperglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="lanreotide" precipitantCode="0G3DE8943Y" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="octreotide" precipitantCode="RWM8CCW8GP" effect="80394007: Hyperglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="octreotide" precipitantCode="RWM8CCW8GP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="phenytoin" precipitantCode="6158TKW0C5 | N0000006023" effect="80394007: Hyperglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="phenytoin" precipitantCode="6158TKW0C5 | N0000006023" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="rifampin" precipitantCode="VJT6J7R4TR | N0000006026" effect="80394007: Hyperglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="rifampin" precipitantCode="VJT6J7R4TR | N0000006026" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="somatostatin analogues" precipitantCode="N0000175904" effect="80394007: Hyperglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="somatostatin analogues" precipitantCode="N0000175904" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="somatropin" precipitantCode="NQX9KB6PCL" effect="80394007: Hyperglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="somatropin" precipitantCode="NQX9KB6PCL" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="st john’s wort" precipitantCode="N0000022261 | UFH8805FKA" effect="80394007: Hyperglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="st john’s wort" precipitantCode="N0000022261 | UFH8805FKA" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sympathomimetics" precipitantCode="N0000029104 | N0000175651" effect="80394007: Hyperglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sympathomimetics" precipitantCode="N0000029104 | N0000175651" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="thiazides" precipitantCode="N0000175419" effect="80394007: Hyperglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="thiazides" precipitantCode="N0000175419" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="thyroid products" precipitantCode="0B4FDL9I6P" effect="80394007: Hyperglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="thyroid products" precipitantCode="0B4FDL9I6P" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="beta-blockers" precipitantCode="N0000000161 | N0000175556" effect="166922008: Blood glucose abnormal (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="beta-blockers" precipitantCode="N0000000161 | N0000175556" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="beta-blockers" precipitantCode="N0000000161 | N0000175556" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="clonidine" precipitantCode="N0000006505 | MN3L5RMN02" effect="166922008: Blood glucose abnormal (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="clonidine" precipitantCode="N0000006505 | MN3L5RMN02" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="drugs that may blunt signs and symptoms of hypoglycemia" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="166922008: Blood glucose abnormal (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="drugs that may blunt signs and symptoms of hypoglycemia" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="reserpine" precipitantCode="8B1QWR724A" effect="166922008: Blood glucose abnormal (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="reserpine" precipitantCode="8B1QWR724A" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="drugs that may increase the potential for hyperglycemia" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="166922008: Blood glucose abnormal (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="drugs that may increase the potential for hyperglycemia" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="80394007: Hyperglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="drugs that may increase the potential for hypoglycemia" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="166922008: Blood glucose abnormal (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="drugs that may increase the potential for hypoglycemia" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="meal" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="meal" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="medications that block the sympathetic nervous system" precipitantCode="N0000175650" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="antidiabetic agents" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="macronutrient" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="liquid meal" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54606"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="tolbutamide" precipitantCode="982XCM1FOI" effect="C54357"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>