<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" setid="6025e8d4-5083-4c3a-58a0-050e7b0b6150">
<Text><Section name="BOXED WARNING SECTION" id="34066-1">
Serious, life-threatening, or fatal respiratory depression may occur with use of Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection, particularly when used concomitantly with other opioids or central nervous system depressants. Monitor for respiratory depression, especially during initiation of Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection or following a dose increase [see WARNINGS ]. Concomitant use of opioids with benzodiazepines or other central nervous system (CNS) depressants, including alcohol, may result in profound sedation, respiratory depression, coma, and death [see WARNINGS , PRECAUTIONS; Drug Interactions ]. Reserve concomitant prescribing of nalbuphine hydrochloride and benzodiazepines or other CNS depressants for use in patients for whom alternative treatment options are inadequate. Limit dosages and durations to the minimum required. Follow patients for signs and symptoms of respiratory depression and sedation.</Section>
<Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection is contraindicated in patients with: Significant respiratory depression [see WARNINGS ] Acute or severe bronchial asthma in an unmonitored setting or in the absence of resuscitative equipment [see WARNINGS ] Known or suspected gastrointestinal obstruction, including paralytic ileus [see WARNINGS ] Hypersensitivity to nalbuphine or to any of the other ingredients in Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection.</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection should be administered as a supplement to general anesthesia only by persons specifically trained in the use of intravenous anesthetics and management of the respiratory effects of potent opioids. Naloxone, resuscitative and intubation equipment and oxygen should be readily available. Initiate the dosing regimen for each patient individually, taking into account the patient's severity of pain, patient response, prior analgesic treatment experience, and risk factors for addiction, abuse, and misuse [see WARNINGS ]. Monitor patients closely for respiratory depression, especially within the first 24 to 72 hours of initiating therapy and following dosage increases with Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection and adjust the dosage accordingly [see WARNINGS ]. Parenteral drug products should be inspected visually for particulate matter and discoloration prior to administration whenever solution and container permit. The usual recommended adult dose is 10 mg for a 70 kg individual administered subcutaneously, intramuscularly, or intravenously; this dose may be repeated every 3 to 6 hours as necessary. Dosage should be adjusted according to the severity of the pain, physical status of the patient, and other medications which the patient may be receiving [see WARNINGS; Risks from Concomitant Use with Benzodiazepines or Other CNS Depressants ]. In nontolerant individuals, the recommended single maximum dose is 20 mg with a maximum total daily dose of 160 mg. The use of Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection as a supplement to balanced anesthesia requires larger doses than those recommended for analgesia. Induction doses of nalbuphine hydrochloride range from 0.3 mg/kg to 3 mg/kg intravenously to be administered over a 10 to 15 minute period with maintenance doses of 0.25 to 0.5 mg/kg in single intravenous administrations as required. The use of Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection may be followed by respiratory depression which can be reversed with the opioid antagonist naloxone hydrochloride. Individually titrate Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection to a dose that provides adequate analgesia and minimizes adverse reactions. Continually reevaluate patients receiving nalbuphine hydrochloride to assess the maintenance of pain control and the relative incidence of adverse reactions, as well as monitoring for the development of addiction, abuse, or misuse [see WARNINGS ]. Frequent communication is important among the prescriber, other members of the healthcare team, the patient, and the caregiver/family during periods of changing analgesic requirements, including initial titration. If the level of pain increases after dosage stabilization, attempt to identify the source of increased pain before increasing the nalbuphine hydrochloride dosage. If unacceptable opioid-related adverse reactions are observed, consider reducing the dosage. Adjust the dosage to obtain an appropriate balance between management of pain and opioid-related adverse events. When a patient who has been taking Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection regularly and may be physically dependent no longer requires therapy with Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection, taper the dose gradually, by 25% to 50% every 2 to 4 days, while monitoring carefully for signs and symptoms of withdrawal. If the patient develops these signs or symptoms, raise the dose to the previous level and taper more slowly, either by increasing the interval between decreases, decreasing the amount of change in dose, or both. Do not abruptly discontinue Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection in a physically-dependent patient [see WARNINGS , DRUG ABUSE AND DEPENDENCE ].</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
Although Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection possesses opioid antagonist activity, there is evidence that in nondependent patients it will not antagonize an opioid analgesic administered just before, concurrently, or just after an injection of Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection. Therefore, due to additive pharmacologic effects, the concomitant use of other opioid analgesics, benzodiazepines or other CNS depressants such as alcohol, other sedatives/hypnotics, anxiolytics, tranquilizers, muscle relaxants, general anesthetics, antipsychotics, and other opioids, can increase the risk of respiratory depression, profound sedation, coma, and death. Reserve concomitant prescribing of these drugs for use in patients for whom alternative treatment options are inadequate. Limit dosages and durations to the minimum required. Follow patients closely for signs of respiratory depression and sedation [see WARNINGS ]. The concomitant use of opioids with other drugs that affect the serotonergic neurotransmitter system, such as selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs), serotonin and norepinephrine reuptake inhibitors (SNRIs), tricyclic antidepressants (TCAs), triptans, 5-HT3 receptor antagonists, drugs that affect the serotonin neurotransmitter system (e.g., mirtazapine, trazodone, tramadol), and monoamine oxidase (MAO) inhibitors (those intended to treat psychiatric disorders and also others, such as linezolid and intravenous methylene blue), has resulted in serotonin syndrome [see PRECAUTIONS; Information for Patients ]. If concomitant use is warranted, carefully observe the patient, particularly during treatment initiation and dose adjustment. Discontinue Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection if serotonin syndrome is suspected. MAOI (e.g., phenelzine, tranylcypromine, linezolid) interactions with opioids may manifest as serotonin syndrome [see Drug Interactions ] or opioid toxicity (e.g., respiratory depression, coma [see Warnings ]). The use of Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection is not recommended for patients taking MAOIs or within 14 days of stopping such treatment. If urgent use of an opioid is necessary, use test doses and frequent titration of small doses to treat pain while closely monitoring blood pressure and signs and symptoms of CNS and respiratory depression.</Section>
<Section name="PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="42232-9">
Because nalbuphine is metabolized in the liver and excreted by the kidneys, Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection should be used with caution in patients with renal or liver dysfunction and administered in reduced amounts. As with all potent analgesics, Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection should be used with caution in patients with myocardial infarction who have nausea or vomiting. As with all opioid analgesics, Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection should be used with caution in patients about to undergo surgery of the biliary tract since it may cause spasm of the sphincter of Oddi. During evaluation of Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection in anesthesia, a higher incidence of bradycardia has been reported in patients who did not receive atropine pre-operatively. Patients should be advised of the following information: Inform patients that opioids could cause a rare but potentially life-threatening condition resulting from concomitant administration of serotonergic drugs. Warn patients of the symptoms of serotonin syndrome and to seek medical attention right away if symptoms develop. Instruct patients to inform their physicians if they are taking, or plan to take serotonergic medications [see PRECAUTIONS; Drug Interactions ]. Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection is associated with sedation and may impair mental and physical abilities required for the performance of potentially dangerous tasks such as driving a car or operating machinery. Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection is to be used as prescribed by a physician. Dose or frequency should not be increased without first consulting with a physician since Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection may cause psychological or physical dependence. The use of Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection with other opioids can cause signs and symptoms of withdrawal. Abrupt discontinuation of Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection after prolonged usage may cause signs and symptoms of withdrawal. Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection may interfere with enzymatic methods for the detection of opioids depending on the specificity/sensitivity of the test. Consult the test manufacturer for specific details. Although Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection possesses opioid antagonist activity, there is evidence that in nondependent patients it will not antagonize an opioid analgesic administered just before, concurrently, or just after an injection of Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection. Therefore, due to additive pharmacologic effects, the concomitant use of other opioid analgesics, benzodiazepines or other CNS depressants such as alcohol, other sedatives/hypnotics, anxiolytics, tranquilizers, muscle relaxants, general anesthetics, antipsychotics, and other opioids, can increase the risk of respiratory depression, profound sedation, coma, and death. Reserve concomitant prescribing of these drugs for use in patients for whom alternative treatment options are inadequate. Limit dosages and durations to the minimum required. Follow patients closely for signs of respiratory depression and sedation [see WARNINGS ]. The concomitant use of opioids with other drugs that affect the serotonergic neurotransmitter system, such as selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs), serotonin and norepinephrine reuptake inhibitors (SNRIs), tricyclic antidepressants (TCAs), triptans, 5-HT3 receptor antagonists, drugs that affect the serotonin neurotransmitter system (e.g., mirtazapine, trazodone, tramadol), and monoamine oxidase (MAO) inhibitors (those intended to treat psychiatric disorders and also others, such as linezolid and intravenous methylene blue), has resulted in serotonin syndrome [see PRECAUTIONS; Information for Patients ]. If concomitant use is warranted, carefully observe the patient, particularly during treatment initiation and dose adjustment. Discontinue Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection if serotonin syndrome is suspected. MAOI (e.g., phenelzine, tranylcypromine, linezolid) interactions with opioids may manifest as serotonin syndrome [see Drug Interactions ] or opioid toxicity (e.g., respiratory depression, coma [see Warnings ]). The use of Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection is not recommended for patients taking MAOIs or within 14 days of stopping such treatment. If urgent use of an opioid is necessary, use test doses and frequent titration of small doses to treat pain while closely monitoring blood pressure and signs and symptoms of CNS and respiratory depression. Long term carcinogenicity studies were performed in rats (24 months) and mice (19 months) by oral administration at doses up to 200 mg/kg (1180 mg/m2) and 200 mg/kg (600 mg/m2) per day, respectively. There was no evidence of an increase in tumors in either species related to Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection administration. The maximum recommend human dose (MRHD) in a day is 160 mg subcutaneously, intramuscularly or intravenously, or approximately 100 mg/m2/day for a 60 kg subject. Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection did not have mutagenic activity in the AMES test with four bacterial strains, in the Chinese Hamster Ovary HGPRT assays or in the Sister Chromatids Exchange Assay. However, Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection induced an increased frequency of mutation in the mouse lymphoma assay. Clastogenic activity was not observed in the mouse micronucleus test of the cytogenicity bone marrow assay in rats. A reproduction study was performed in male and female rats at subcutaneous doses up to 56 mg/kg/day or 330 mg/m2/day. Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection did not affect either male or female fertility rats. Reproduction studies have been performed in rats by subcutaneous administration of nalbuphine up to 100 mg/kg/day, or 590 mg/m2/day which is approximately 6 times the MRHD, and in rabbits by intravenous administration of nalbuphine up to 32 mg/kg/day, or 378 mg/m2/day which is approximately 4 times the MRHD. The results did not reveal evidence of developmental toxicity, including teratogenicity, or harm to the fetus. There are, however, no adequate and well-controlled studies in pregnant women. Because animal reproduction studies are not always predictive of human response, this drug should be used during pregnancy only if clearly needed. Neonatal body weight and survival rates were reduced at birth and during lactation when nalbuphine was subcutaneously administered to female and male rats prior to mating and throughout gestation and lactation or to pregnant rats during the last third of gestation and throughout lactation at doses approximately 4 times the maximum recommended human dose. Severe fetal bradycardia has been reported when nalbuphine hydrochloride is administered during labor. Naloxone may reverse these effects. Although there are no reports of fetal bradycardia earlier in pregnancy, it is possible that this may occur. This drug should be used in pregnancy only if clearly needed, if the potential benefit outweighs the risk to the fetus, and if appropriate measures such as fetal monitoring are taken to detect and manage any potential adverse effect on the fetus. Opioids cross the placenta and may produce respiratory depression and psycho-physiologic effects in neonates. An opioid antagonist, such as naloxone, must be available for reversal of opioid-induced respiratory depression in the neonate. Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection is not recommended for use in pregnant women during or immediately prior to labor, when other analgesic techniques are more appropriate. Opioid analgesics, including Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection, can prolong labor through actions which temporarily reduce the strength, duration, and frequency of uterine contractions. However, this effect is not consistent and may be offset by an increased rate of cervical dilation, which tends to shorten labor. Monitor neonates exposed to opioid analgesics during labor for signs of excess sedation and respiratory depression. Limited data suggest that Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection is excreted in maternal milk but only in a small amount (less than 1% of the administered dose) and with a clinically insignificant effect. Infants exposed to Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection through breast milk should be monitored for excess sedation and respiratory depression. Withdrawal symptoms can occur in breastfed infants when maternal administration of an opioid analgesic is stopped, or when breast-feeding is stopped. Safety and effectiveness in pediatric patients below the age of 18 years have not been established. Elderly patients (aged 65 years or older) may have increased sensitivity to Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection. In general, use caution when selecting a dosage for an elderly patient, usually starting at the low end of the dosing range, reflecting the greater frequency of decreased hepatic, renal, or cardiac function and of concomitant disease or other drug therapy. Respiratory depression is the chief risk for elderly patients treated with opioids, and has occurred after large initial doses were administered to patients who were not opioid-tolerant or when opioids were co-administered with other agents that depress respiration. Titrate the dosage of Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection slowly in geriatric patients [see WARNINGS ].</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS SECTION" id="34071-1">
Serious, life-threatening, or fatal respiratory depression has been reported with the use of opioids, even when used as recommended. Respiratory depression, if not immediately recognized and treated, may lead to respiratory arrest and death. Management of respiratory depression may include close observation, supportive measures, and use of opioid antagonists, depending on the patient's clinical status [see OVERDOSAGE ]. Carbon dioxide (CO 2 ) retention from opioid-induced respiratory depression can exacerbate the sedating effects of opioids. While serious, life-threatening, or fatal respiratory depression can occur at any time during the use of Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection, the risk is greatest during the initiation of therapy or following a dosage increase. Monitor patients closely for respiratory depression, especially within the first 24 to 72 hours of initiating therapy with and following dosage increases of Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection. To reduce the risk of respiratory depression, proper dosing and titration of Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection is essential [see DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION ]. Overestimating the Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection dosage when converting patients from another opioid product can result in a fatal overdose with the first dose. Profound sedation, respiratory depression, coma, and death may result from the concomitant use of Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection with benzodiazepines or other CNS depressants (e.g., non-benzodiazepine sedatives/hypnotics, anxiolytics, tranquilizers, muscle relaxants, general anesthetics, antipsychotics, other opioids, alcohol). Because of these risks, reserve concomitant prescribing of these drugs for use in patients for whom alternative treatment options are inadequate. Observational studies have demonstrated that concomitant use of opioid analgesics and benzodiazepines increases the risk of drug-related mortality compared to use of opioid analgesics alone. Because of similar pharmacological properties, it is reasonable to expect similar risk with the concomitant use of other CNS depressant drugs with opioid analgesics [see PRECAUTIONS; Drug Interactions ]. If the decision is made to prescribe a benzodiazepine or other CNS depressant concomitantly with an opioid analgesic, prescribe the lowest effective dosages and minimum durations of concomitant use. In patients already receiving an opioid analgesic, prescribe a lower initial dose of the benzodiazepine or other CNS depressant than indicated in the absence of an opioid, and titrate based on clinical response. If an opioid analgesic is initiated in a patient already taking a benzodiazepine or other CNS depressant, prescribe a lower initial dose of the opioid analgesic, and titrate based on clinical response. Follow patients closely for signs and symptoms of respiratory depression and sedation. Advise both patients and caregivers about the risks of respiratory depression and sedation when Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection is used with benzodiazepines or other CNS depressants (including alcohol and illicit drugs). Advise patients not to drive or operate heavy machinery until the effects of concomitant use of the benzodiazepine or other CNS depressant have been determined. Screen patients for risk of substance use disorders, including opioid abuse and misuse, and warn them of the risk for overdose and death associated with the use of additional CNS depressants including alcohol and illicit drugs [see PRECAUTIONS; Drug Interactions and Information for Patients ]. The use of Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection in patients with acute or severe bronchial asthma in an unmonitored setting or in the absence of resuscitative equipment is contraindicated. Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection-treated patients with significant chronic obstructive pulmonary disease or cor pulmonale, and those with a substantially decreased respiratory reserve, hypoxia, hypercapnia, or pre-existing respiratory depression are at increased risk of decreased respiratory drive including apnea, even at recommended dosages of use of Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection [see WARNINGS ]. Life-threatening respiratory depression is more likely to occur in elderly, cachectic, or debilitated patients because they may have altered pharmacokinetics or altered clearance compared to younger, healthier patients [see WARNINGS ]. Monitor such patients closely, particularly when initiating and titrating Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection and when Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection is given concomitantly with other drugs that depress respiration [see WARNINGS ]. Alternatively, consider the use of non-opioid analgesics in these patients. Cases of adrenal insufficiency have been reported with opioid use, more often following greater than 1 month of use. Presentation of adrenal insufficiency may include non-specific symptoms and signs including nausea, vomiting, anorexia, fatigue, weakness, dizziness, and low blood pressure. If adrenal insufficiency is suspected, confirm the diagnosis with diagnostic testing as soon as possible. If adrenal insufficiency is diagnosed, treat with physiologic replacement doses of corticosteroids. Wean the patient off of the opioid to allow adrenal function to recover and continue corticosteroid treatment until adrenal function recovers. Other opioids may be tried as some cases reported use of a different opioid without recurrence of adrenal insufficiency. The information available does not identify any particular opioids as being more likely to be associated with adrenal insufficiency. The possible respiratory depressant effects and the potential of potent analgesics to elevate cerebrospinal fluid pressure (resulting from vasodilation following CO 2 retention) may be markedly exaggerated in the presence of head injury, intracranial lesions or a pre-existing increase in intracranial pressure. Furthermore, potent analgesics can produce effects which may obscure the clinical course of patients with head injuries. Therefore, Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection should be used in these circumstances only when essential, and then should be administered with extreme caution. Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection may impair the mental or physical abilities required for the performance of potentially dangerous tasks such as driving a car or operating machinery. Therefore, Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection should be administered with caution to ambulatory patients who should be warned to avoid such hazards. Maintain patient under observation until recovered from Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection effects that would affect driving or other potentially dangerous tasks. Severe fetal bradycardia has been reported when Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection is administered during labor. Naloxone may reverse these effects. Although there are no reports of fetal bradycardia earlier in pregnancy, it is possible that this may occur. Avoid the use of Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection in pregnant women unless the potential benefit outweighs the risk to the fetus, and if appropriate measures such as fetal monitoring are taken to detect and manage any potential adverse effect on the fetus. The placental transfer of nalbuphine is high, rapid, and variable with a maternal to fetal ratio ranging from 1:0.37 to 1:6. Fetal and neonatal adverse effects that have been reported following the administration of nalbuphine to the mother during labor include fetal bradycardia, respiratory depression at birth, apnea, cyanosis, and hypotonia. Some of these events have been life-threatening. Maternal administration of naloxone during labor has normalized these effects in some cases. Severe and prolonged fetal bradycardia has been reported. Permanent neurological damage attributed to fetal bradycardia has occurred. A sinusoidal fetal heart rate pattern associated with the use of nalbuphine has also been reported. Nalbuphine should be used during labor and delivery only if clearly indicated and only if the potential benefit outweighs the risk to the infant. Newborns should be monitored for respiratory depression, apnea, bradycardia and arrhythmias if nalbuphine has been used. Nalbuphine hydrochloride is a synthetic opioid agonist-antagonist analgesic. As an opioid, Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection exposes users to the risks of addiction, abuse, and misuse [see DRUG ABUSE AND DEPENDENCE ]. Although the risk of addiction in any individual is unknown, it can occur in patients appropriately prescribed Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection. Addiction can occur at recommended dosages and if the drug is misused or abused. Assess each patient's risk for opioid addiction, abuse, or misuse. Risks are increased in patients with a personal or family history of substance abuse (including drug or alcohol abuse or addiction) or mental illness (e.g., major depression). The potential for these risks should not, however, prevent the proper management of pain in any given patient. Opioids are sought by drug abusers and people with addiction disorders and are subject to criminal diversion. Consider these risks when prescribing or dispensing Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection. Strategies to reduce these risks include prescribing the drug in the smallest appropriate quantity. Contact local state professional licensing board or state controlled substances authority for information on how to prevent and detect abuse or diversion of this product.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Chronic use of opioids may influence the hypothalamic-pituitary-gonadal axis, leading to androgen deficiency that may manifest as low libido, impotence, erectile dysfunction, amenorrhea, or infertility. The causal role of opioids in the clinical syndrome of hypogonadism is unknown because the various medical, physical, lifestyle, and psychological stressors that may influence gonadal hormone levels have not been adequately controlled for in studies conducted to date. Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection is a potent analgesic. Its analgesic potency is essentially equivalent to that of morphine on a milligram basis. Receptor studies show that nalbuphine hydrochloride binds to mu, kappa, and delta receptors, but not to sigma receptors. Nalbuphine hydrochloride is primarily a kappa agonist/partial mu antagonist analgesic. The onset of action of nalbuphine hydrochloride occurs within 2 to 3 minutes after intravenous administration, and in less than 15 minutes following subcutaneous or intramuscular injection. The plasma half-life of nalbuphine is 5 hours, and in clinical studies the duration of analgesic activity has been reported to range from 3 to 6 hours. The opioid antagonist activity of nalbuphine hydrochloride is one-fourth as potent as nalorphine and 10 times that of pentazocine. Nalbuphine hydrochloride may produce the same degree of respiratory depression as equianalgesic doses of morphine. However, Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection exhibits a ceiling effect such that increases in dose greater than 30 mg do not produce further respiratory depression in the absence of other CNS active medications affecting respiration. Nalbuphine hydrochloride by itself has potent opioid antagonist activity at doses equal to or lower than its analgesic dose. When administered following or concurrent with mµ agonist opioid analgesics (e.g., morphine, oxymorphone, fentanyl), nalbuphine hydrochloride may partially reverse or block opioid-induced respiratory depression from the mµ agonist analgesic. Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection may precipitate withdrawal in patients dependent on opioid drugs. Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection should be used with caution in patients who have been receiving mu opioid analgesics on a regular basis.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="1981" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Serious, life-threatening, or fatal respiratory depression may occur with use of Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection, particularly when used concomitantly with other opioids or central nervous system depressants.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M4" type="Trigger" span="63 5" str="occur"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="176 34" str="central nervous system depressants" code="N0000175758"/>
<Mention id="M6" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 58" str="Serious, life-threatening, or fatal respiratory depression" code="80954004: Decreased respiratory function (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M5" type="Precipitant" span="165 7" str="opioids" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M4" precipitant="M2" effect="M6" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M4" precipitant="M5" effect="M6" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1982" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Monitor for respiratory depression, especially during initiation of Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection or following a dose increase.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1983" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Concomitant use of opioids with benzodiazepines or other central nervous system (CNS) depressants, including alcohol, may result in profound sedation, respiratory depression, coma, and death.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M64" type="Trigger" span="122 9" str="result in"/>
<Mention id="M17" type="Precipitant" span="109 7" str="alcohol" code="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M"/>
<Mention id="M57" type="SpecificInteraction" span="175 4" str="coma" code="371632003: Coma (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M60" type="SpecificInteraction" span="185 5" str="death" code="419620001: Death (event)"/>
<Mention id="M63" type="SpecificInteraction" span="132 17" str="Profound sedation" code="17971005: Sedated (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M66" type="SpecificInteraction" span="151 22" str="respiratory depression" code="80954004: Decreased respiratory function (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M29" type="Precipitant" span="32 15" str="benzodiazepines" code="N0000007542 | N0000175694"/>
<Mention id="M41" type="Precipitant" span="57 40" str="central nervous system (CNS) depressants" code="N0000175758"/>
<Mention id="M53" type="Precipitant" span="57 22;86 11" str="central nervous system | depressants" code="N0000175758"/>
<Mention id="M65" type="Precipitant" span="81 3;86 11" str="CNS | depressants" code="N0000175758"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M64" precipitant="M17" effect="M57" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M64" precipitant="M17" effect="M60" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M64" precipitant="M17" effect="M63" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M64" precipitant="M17" effect="M66" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M64" precipitant="M29" effect="M57" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M64" precipitant="M29" effect="M60" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M64" precipitant="M29" effect="M63" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M64" precipitant="M29" effect="M66" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M64" precipitant="M41" effect="M57" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M64" precipitant="M41" effect="M60" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M64" precipitant="M41" effect="M63" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M64" precipitant="M41" effect="M66" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M64" precipitant="M53" effect="M57" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M64" precipitant="M53" effect="M60" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M64" precipitant="M53" effect="M63" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M64" precipitant="M53" effect="M66" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M64" precipitant="M65" effect="M57" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M64" precipitant="M65" effect="M60" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M64" precipitant="M65" effect="M63" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M64" precipitant="M65" effect="M66" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1984" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Reserve concomitant prescribing of nalbuphine hydrochloride and benzodiazepines or other CNS depressants for use in patients for whom alternative treatment options are inadequate.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M69" type="Trigger" span="0 7" str="Reserve"/>
<Mention id="M68" type="Precipitant" span="64 15" str="benzodiazepines" code="N0000007542 | N0000175694"/>
<Mention id="M70" type="Precipitant" span="89 15" str="CNS depressants" code="N0000175758"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M69" precipitant="M68"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M69" precipitant="M70"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1985" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Limit dosages and durations to the minimum required.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1986" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Follow patients for signs and symptoms of respiratory depression and sedation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1987" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection is contraindicated in patients with: Significant respiratory depression Acute or severe bronchial asthma in an unmonitored setting or in the absence of resuscitative equipment Known or suspected gastrointestinal obstruction, including paralytic ileus Hypersensitivity to nalbuphine or to any of the other ingredients in Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1988" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection should be administered as a supplement to general anesthesia only by persons specifically trained in the use of intravenous anesthetics and management of the respiratory effects of potent opioids.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1989" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Naloxone, resuscitative and intubation equipment and oxygen should be readily available.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1990" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Initiate the dosing regimen for each patient individually, taking into account the patient's severity of pain, patient response, prior analgesic treatment experience, and risk factors for addiction, abuse, and misuse.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1991" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor patients closely for respiratory depression, especially within the first 24 to 72 hours of initiating therapy and following dosage increases with Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection and adjust the dosage accordingly.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1992" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Parenteral drug products should be inspected visually for particulate matter and discoloration prior to administration whenever solution and container permit.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1993" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The usual recommended adult dose is 10 mg for a 70 kg individual administered subcutaneously, intramuscularly, or intravenously; this dose may be repeated every 3 to 6 hours as necessary.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1994" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dosage should be adjusted according to the severity of the pain, physical status of the patient, and other medications which the patient may be receiving.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1995" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In nontolerant individuals, the recommended single maximum dose is 20 mg with a maximum total daily dose of 160 mg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1996" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The use of Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection as a supplement to balanced anesthesia requires larger doses than those recommended for analgesia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1997" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Induction doses of nalbuphine hydrochloride range from 0.3 mg/kg to 3 mg/kg intravenously to be administered over a 10 to 15 minute period with maintenance doses of 0.25 to 0.5 mg/kg in single intravenous administrations as required.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1998" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The use of Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection may be followed by respiratory depression which can be reversed with the opioid antagonist naloxone hydrochloride.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1999" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Individually titrate Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection to a dose that provides adequate analgesia and minimizes adverse reactions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2000" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Continually reevaluate patients receiving nalbuphine hydrochloride to assess the maintenance of pain control and the relative incidence of adverse reactions, as well as monitoring for the development of addiction, abuse, or misuse.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2001" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Frequent communication is important among the prescriber, other members of the healthcare team, the patient, and the caregiver/family during periods of changing analgesic requirements, including initial titration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2002" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If the level of pain increases after dosage stabilization, attempt to identify the source of increased pain before increasing the nalbuphine hydrochloride dosage.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2003" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If unacceptable opioid-related adverse reactions are observed, consider reducing the dosage.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2004" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Adjust the dosage to obtain an appropriate balance between management of pain and opioid-related adverse events.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2005" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>When a patient who has been taking Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection regularly and may be physically dependent no longer requires therapy with Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection, taper the dose gradually, by 25% to 50% every 2 to 4 days, while monitoring carefully for signs and symptoms of withdrawal.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2006" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If the patient develops these signs or symptoms, raise the dose to the previous level and taper more slowly, either by increasing the interval between decreases, decreasing the amount of change in dose, or both.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2007" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not abruptly discontinue Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection in a physically-dependent patient.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2008" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Although Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection possesses opioid antagonist activity, there is evidence that in nondependent patients it will not antagonize an opioid analgesic administered just before, concurrently, or just after an injection of Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M71" type="Trigger" span="61 10" str="antagonist"/>
<Mention id="M72" type="Precipitant" span="54 6" str="opioid" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M73" type="SpecificInteraction" span="54 26" str="opioid antagonist activity" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M71" precipitant="M72" effect="M73" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2009" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Therefore, due to additive pharmacologic effects, the concomitant use of other opioid analgesics, benzodiazepines or other CNS depressants such as alcohol, other sedatives/hypnotics, anxiolytics, tranquilizers, muscle relaxants, general anesthetics, antipsychotics, and other opioids, can increase the risk of respiratory depression, profound sedation, coma, and death.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M263" type="Trigger" span="289 17" str="increase the risk"/>
<Mention id="M84" type="Precipitant" span="147 7" str="alcohol" code="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M"/>
<Mention id="M256" type="SpecificInteraction" span="353 4" str="coma" code="371632003: Coma (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M259" type="SpecificInteraction" span="363 5" str="death" code="419620001: Death (event)"/>
<Mention id="M262" type="SpecificInteraction" span="334 17" str="profound sedation" code="17971005: Sedated (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M265" type="SpecificInteraction" span="310 22" str="respiratory depression" code="80954004: Decreased respiratory function (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M253" type="SpecificInteraction" span="18 30" str="additive pharmacologic effects" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M99" type="Precipitant" span="250 14" str="antipsychotics" code="N0000029150 | N0000178316"/>
<Mention id="M114" type="Precipitant" span="183 11" str="anxiolytics" code="N0000193818"/>
<Mention id="M129" type="Precipitant" span="98 15" str="benzodiazepines" code="N0000007542 | N0000175694"/>
<Mention id="M144" type="Precipitant" span="123 15" str="CNS depressants" code="N0000175758"/>
<Mention id="M159" type="Precipitant" span="229 19" str="general anesthetics" code="N0000175681"/>
<Mention id="M174" type="Precipitant" span="172 9" str="hypnotics" code="N0000029424 | N0000193842"/>
<Mention id="M189" type="Precipitant" span="211 16" str="muscle relaxants" code="N0000175737"/>
<Mention id="M204" type="Precipitant" span="79 17" str="opioid analgesics" code="N0000175440"/>
<Mention id="M219" type="Precipitant" span="276 7" str="opioids" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M234" type="Precipitant" span="162 9" str="sedatives" code="N0000029143 | N0000193842"/>
<Mention id="M249" type="Precipitant" span="162 19" str="sedatives/hypnotics" code="n0000029143 | N0000193842"/>
<Mention id="M264" type="Precipitant" span="196 13" str="tranquilizers" code="N0000029143 | N0000193842"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M84" effect="M256" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M84" effect="M259" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M84" effect="M262" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I29" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M84" effect="M265" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I30" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M253" precipitant="M99" effect="M253" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I31" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M99" effect="M256" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I32" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M99" effect="M259" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I33" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M99" effect="M262" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I34" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M99" effect="M265" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I35" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M253" precipitant="M114" effect="M253" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I36" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M114" effect="M256" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I37" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M114" effect="M259" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I38" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M114" effect="M262" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I39" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M114" effect="M265" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I40" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M253" precipitant="M129" effect="M253" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I41" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M129" effect="M256" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I42" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M129" effect="M259" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I43" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M129" effect="M262" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I44" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M129" effect="M265" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I45" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M253" precipitant="M144" effect="M253" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I46" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M144" effect="M256" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I47" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M144" effect="M259" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I48" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M144" effect="M262" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I49" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M144" effect="M265" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I50" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M253" precipitant="M159" effect="M253" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I51" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M159" effect="M256" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I52" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M159" effect="M259" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I53" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M159" effect="M262" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I54" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M159" effect="M265" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I55" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M253" precipitant="M174" effect="M253" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I56" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M174" effect="M256" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I57" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M174" effect="M259" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I58" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M174" effect="M262" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I59" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M174" effect="M265" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I60" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M253" precipitant="M189" effect="M253" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I61" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M189" effect="M256" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I62" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M189" effect="M259" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I63" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M189" effect="M262" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I64" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M189" effect="M265" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I65" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M253" precipitant="M204" effect="M253" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I66" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M204" effect="M256" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I67" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M204" effect="M259" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I68" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M204" effect="M262" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I69" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M204" effect="M265" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I70" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M253" precipitant="M219" effect="M253" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I71" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M219" effect="M256" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I72" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M219" effect="M259" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I73" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M219" effect="M262" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I74" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M219" effect="M265" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I75" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M253" precipitant="M234" effect="M253" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I76" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M234" effect="M256" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I77" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M234" effect="M259" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I78" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M234" effect="M262" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I79" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M234" effect="M265" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I80" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M253" precipitant="M249" effect="M253" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I81" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M249" effect="M256" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I82" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M249" effect="M259" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I83" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M249" effect="M262" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I84" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M249" effect="M265" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I85" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M253" precipitant="M264" effect="M253" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I86" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M264" effect="M256" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I87" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M264" effect="M259" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I88" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M264" effect="M262" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I89" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M263" precipitant="M264" effect="M265" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2010" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Reserve concomitant prescribing of these drugs for use in patients for whom alternative treatment options are inadequate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2011" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Follow patients closely for signs of respiratory depression and sedation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2012" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The concomitant use of opioids with other drugs that affect the serotonergic neurotransmitter system, such as selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs), serotonin and norepinephrine reuptake inhibitors (SNRIs), tricyclic antidepressants (TCAs), triptans, 5-HT3 receptor antagonists, drugs that affect the serotonin neurotransmitter system (e.g., mirtazapine, trazodone, tramadol), and monoamine oxidase (MAO) inhibitors (those intended to treat psychiatric disorders and also others, such as linezolid and intravenous methylene blue), has resulted in serotonin syndrome.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M317" type="Trigger" span="545 11" str="resulted in"/>
<Mention id="M267" type="Precipitant" span="261 26" str="5-HT3 receptor antagonists" code="N0000175817 | N0000000090"/>
<Mention id="M319" type="SpecificInteraction" span="557 18" str="serotonin syndrome" code="371089000: Serotonin syndrome (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M270" type="Precipitant" span="42 58" str="drugs that affect the serotonergic neurotransmitter system" code="N0000009844"/>
<Mention id="M273" type="Precipitant" span="289 55" str="drugs that affect the serotonin neurotransmitter system" code="N0000009844"/>
<Mention id="M276" type="Precipitant" span="512 26" str="intravenous methylene blue" code="N0000007449 | T42P99266K"/>
<Mention id="M279" type="Precipitant" span="498 9" str="linezolid" code="ISQ9I6J12J"/>
<Mention id="M282" type="Precipitant" span="410 3;139 10" str="MAO | inhibitors" code="N0000000184 | N0000175744"/>
<Mention id="M285" type="Precipitant" span="352 11" str="mirtazapine" code="A051Q2099Q"/>
<Mention id="M288" type="Precipitant" span="391 34" str="monoamine oxidase (MAO) inhibitors" code="N0000000184 | N0000175744"/>
<Mention id="M291" type="Precipitant" span="391 17;139 10" str="monoamine oxidase | inhibitors" code="N0000000184 | N0000175744"/>
<Mention id="M294" type="Precipitant" span="110 39" str="selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors" code="N0000175696"/>
<Mention id="M297" type="Precipitant" span="159 48" str="serotonin and norepinephrine reuptake inhibitors" code="N0000175749"/>
<Mention id="M300" type="Precipitant" span="209 5" str="SNRIs" code="N0000175749"/>
<Mention id="M303" type="Precipitant" span="151 5" str="SSRIs" code="N0000175696"/>
<Mention id="M306" type="Precipitant" span="244 4" str="TCAs" code="N0000029148 | N0000175752"/>
<Mention id="M309" type="Precipitant" span="376 8" str="tramadol" code="39J1LGJ30J"/>
<Mention id="M312" type="Precipitant" span="365 9" str="trazodone" code="YBK48BXK30"/>
<Mention id="M315" type="Precipitant" span="217 25" str="tricyclic antidepressants" code="N0000029148 | N0000175752"/>
<Mention id="M318" type="Precipitant" span="251 8" str="triptans" code="40V943JDGR"/>
<Interaction id="I90" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M317" precipitant="M267" effect="M319" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I91" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M317" precipitant="M270" effect="M319" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I92" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M317" precipitant="M273" effect="M319" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I93" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M317" precipitant="M276" effect="M319" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I94" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M317" precipitant="M279" effect="M319" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I95" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M317" precipitant="M282" effect="M319" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I96" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M317" precipitant="M285" effect="M319" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I97" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M317" precipitant="M288" effect="M319" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I98" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M317" precipitant="M291" effect="M319" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I99" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M317" precipitant="M294" effect="M319" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I100" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M317" precipitant="M297" effect="M319" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I101" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M317" precipitant="M300" effect="M319" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I102" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M317" precipitant="M303" effect="M319" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I103" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M317" precipitant="M306" effect="M319" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I104" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M317" precipitant="M309" effect="M319" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I105" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M317" precipitant="M312" effect="M319" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I106" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M317" precipitant="M315" effect="M319" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I107" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M317" precipitant="M318" effect="M319" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2013" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>If concomitant use is warranted, carefully observe the patient, particularly during treatment initiation and dose adjustment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2014" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Discontinue Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection if serotonin syndrome is suspected.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2015" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>MAOI (e.g., phenelzine, tranylcypromine, linezolid) interactions with opioids may manifest as serotonin syndrome or opioid toxicity (e.g., respiratory depression, coma ).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M365" type="Trigger" span="52 12;82 11" str="interactions | manifest as"/>
<Mention id="M330" type="Precipitant" span="41 9" str="linezolid" code="ISQ9I6J12J"/>
<Mention id="M358" type="SpecificInteraction" span="163 4" str="coma" code="371632003: Coma (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M361" type="SpecificInteraction" span="116 15" str="opioid toxicity" code="77721001: Opioid intoxication (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M364" type="SpecificInteraction" span="139 22" str="respiratory depression" code="80954004: Decreased respiratory function (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M367" type="SpecificInteraction" span="94 18" str="serotonin syndrome" code="371089000: Serotonin syndrome (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M342" type="Precipitant" span="0 4" str="MAOI" code="N0000000184"/>
<Mention id="M354" type="Precipitant" span="12 10" str="phenelzine" code="O408N561GF"/>
<Mention id="M366" type="Precipitant" span="24 15" str="tranylcypromine" code="3E3V44J4Z9"/>
<Interaction id="I108" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M365" precipitant="M330" effect="M358" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I109" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M365" precipitant="M330" effect="M361" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I110" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M365" precipitant="M330" effect="M364" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I111" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M365" precipitant="M330" effect="M367" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I112" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M365" precipitant="M342" effect="M358" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I113" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M365" precipitant="M342" effect="M361" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I114" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M365" precipitant="M342" effect="M364" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I115" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M365" precipitant="M342" effect="M367" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I116" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M365" precipitant="M354" effect="M358" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I117" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M365" precipitant="M354" effect="M361" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I118" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M365" precipitant="M354" effect="M364" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I119" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M365" precipitant="M354" effect="M367" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I120" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M365" precipitant="M366" effect="M358" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I121" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M365" precipitant="M366" effect="M361" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I122" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M365" precipitant="M366" effect="M364" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I123" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M365" precipitant="M366" effect="M367" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2016" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The use of Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection is not recommended for patients taking MAOIs or within 14 days of stopping such treatment.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M368" type="Trigger" span="49 15" str="not recommended"/>
<Mention id="M369" type="Precipitant" span="85 5" str="MAOIs" code="N0000000184"/>
<Interaction id="I124" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M368" precipitant="M369"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2017" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>If urgent use of an opioid is necessary, use test doses and frequent titration of small doses to treat pain while closely monitoring blood pressure and signs and symptoms of CNS and respiratory depression.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2018" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because nalbuphine is metabolized in the liver and excreted by the kidneys, Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection should be used with caution in patients with renal or liver dysfunction and administered in reduced amounts.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2019" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>As with all potent analgesics, Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection should be used with caution in patients with myocardial infarction who have nausea or vomiting.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2020" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>As with all opioid analgesics, Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection should be used with caution in patients about to undergo surgery of the biliary tract since it may cause spasm of the sphincter of Oddi.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2021" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>During evaluation of Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection in anesthesia, a higher incidence of bradycardia has been reported in patients who did not receive atropine pre-operatively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2022" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Patients should be advised of the following information: Inform patients that opioids could cause a rare but potentially life-threatening condition resulting from concomitant administration of serotonergic drugs.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M370" type="Trigger" span="92 5" str="cause"/>
<Mention id="M371" type="Precipitant" span="193 18" str="serotonergic drugs" code="N0000000256"/>
<Mention id="M372" type="SpecificInteraction" span="121 26" str="life-threatening condition" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I125" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M370" precipitant="M371" effect="M372" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2023" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Warn patients of the symptoms of serotonin syndrome and to seek medical attention right away if symptoms develop.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2024" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Instruct patients to inform their physicians if they are taking, or plan to take serotonergic medications.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M373" type="Trigger" span="21 23" str="inform their physicians"/>
<Mention id="M374" type="Precipitant" span="81 24" str="serotonergic medications" code="N0000000256"/>
<Interaction id="I126" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M373" precipitant="M374"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2025" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection is associated with sedation and may impair mental and physical abilities required for the performance of potentially dangerous tasks such as driving a car or operating machinery.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2026" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection is to be used as prescribed by a physician.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2027" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Dose or frequency should not be increased without first consulting with a physician since Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection may cause psychological or physical dependence.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2028" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The use of Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection with other opioids can cause signs and symptoms of withdrawal.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M375" type="Trigger" span="69 24" str="cause signs and symptoms"/>
<Mention id="M376" type="Precipitant" span="57 7" str="opioids" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M377" type="SpecificInteraction" span="75 32" str="signs and symptoms of withdrawal" code="363101005: Drug withdrawal (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I127" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M375" precipitant="M376" effect="M377" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2029" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Abrupt discontinuation of Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection after prolonged usage may cause signs and symptoms of withdrawal.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2030" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection may interfere with enzymatic methods for the detection of opioids depending on the specificity/sensitivity of the test.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2031" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Consult the test manufacturer for specific details.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2032" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Long term carcinogenicity studies were performed in rats (24 months) and mice (19 months) by oral administration at doses up to 200 mg/kg (1180 mg/m2) and 200 mg/kg (600 mg/m2) per day, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2033" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>There was no evidence of an increase in tumors in either species related to Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2034" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The maximum recommend human dose (MRHD) in a day is 160 mg subcutaneously, intramuscularly or intravenously, or approximately 100 mg/m2/day for a 60 kg subject.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2035" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection did not have mutagenic activity in the AMES test with four bacterial strains, in the Chinese Hamster Ovary HGPRT assays or in the Sister Chromatids Exchange Assay.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2036" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>However, Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection induced an increased frequency of mutation in the mouse lymphoma assay.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2037" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Clastogenic activity was not observed in the mouse micronucleus test of the cytogenicity bone marrow assay in rats.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2038" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>A reproduction study was performed in male and female rats at subcutaneous doses up to 56 mg/kg/day or 330 mg/m2/day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2039" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection did not affect either male or female fertility rats.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2040" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Reproduction studies have been performed in rats by subcutaneous administration of nalbuphine up to 100 mg/kg/day, or 590 mg/m2/day which is approximately 6 times the MRHD, and in rabbits by intravenous administration of nalbuphine up to 32 mg/kg/day, or 378 mg/m2/day which is approximately 4 times the MRHD.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2041" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The results did not reveal evidence of developmental toxicity, including teratogenicity, or harm to the fetus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2042" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>There are, however, no adequate and well-controlled studies in pregnant women.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2043" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because animal reproduction studies are not always predictive of human response, this drug should be used during pregnancy only if clearly needed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2044" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Neonatal body weight and survival rates were reduced at birth and during lactation when nalbuphine was subcutaneously administered to female and male rats prior to mating and throughout gestation and lactation or to pregnant rats during the last third of gestation and throughout lactation at doses approximately 4 times the maximum recommended human dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2045" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Severe fetal bradycardia has been reported when nalbuphine hydrochloride is administered during labor.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2046" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Although there are no reports of fetal bradycardia earlier in pregnancy, it is possible that this may occur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2047" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>This drug should be used in pregnancy only if clearly needed, if the potential benefit outweighs the risk to the fetus, and if appropriate measures such as fetal monitoring are taken to detect and manage any potential adverse effect on the fetus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2048" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Opioids cross the placenta and may produce respiratory depression and psycho-physiologic effects in neonates.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2049" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>An opioid antagonist, such as naloxone, must be available for reversal of opioid-induced respiratory depression in the neonate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2050" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection is not recommended for use in pregnant women during or immediately prior to labor, when other analgesic techniques are more appropriate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2051" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Opioid analgesics, including Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection, can prolong labor through actions which temporarily reduce the strength, duration, and frequency of uterine contractions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2052" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>However, this effect is not consistent and may be offset by an increased rate of cervical dilation, which tends to shorten labor.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2053" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Monitor neonates exposed to opioid analgesics during labor for signs of excess sedation and respiratory depression.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2054" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Limited data suggest that Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection is excreted in maternal milk but only in a small amount (less than 1% of the administered dose) and with a clinically insignificant effect.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2055" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Infants exposed to Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection through breast milk should be monitored for excess sedation and respiratory depression.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2056" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Withdrawal symptoms can occur in breastfed infants when maternal administration of an opioid analgesic is stopped, or when breast-feeding is stopped.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2057" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Safety and effectiveness in pediatric patients below the age of 18 years have not been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2058" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Elderly patients (aged 65 years or older) may have increased sensitivity to Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2059" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In general, use caution when selecting a dosage for an elderly patient, usually starting at the low end of the dosing range, reflecting the greater frequency of decreased hepatic, renal, or cardiac function and of concomitant disease or other drug therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2060" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Respiratory depression is the chief risk for elderly patients treated with opioids, and has occurred after large initial doses were administered to patients who were not opioid-tolerant or when opioids were co-administered with other agents that depress respiration.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M378" type="Trigger" span="36 4" str="risk "/>
<Mention id="M379" type="Trigger" span="92 8" str=" occurred"/>
<Mention id="M380" type="Precipitant" span="234 31" str="agents that depress respiration" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M381" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 22" str="Respiratory depression" code="80954004: Decreased respiratory function (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I128" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M378;M379" precipitant="M380" effect="M381" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2061" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Titrate the dosage of Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection slowly in geriatric patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2062" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Serious, life-threatening, or fatal respiratory depression has been reported with the use of opioids, even when used as recommended.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2063" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Respiratory depression, if not immediately recognized and treated, may lead to respiratory arrest and death.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2064" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Management of respiratory depression may include close observation, supportive measures, and use of opioid antagonists, depending on the patient's clinical status.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2065" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Carbon dioxide (CO2) retention from opioid-induced respiratory depression can exacerbate the sedating effects of opioids.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2066" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>While serious, life-threatening, or fatal respiratory depression can occur at any time during the use of Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection, the risk is greatest during the initiation of therapy or following a dosage increase.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2067" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Monitor patients closely for respiratory depression, especially within the first 24 to 72 hours of initiating therapy with and following dosage increases of Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2068" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>To reduce the risk of respiratory depression, proper dosing and titration of Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection is essential.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2069" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Overestimating the Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection dosage when converting patients from another opioid product can result in a fatal overdose with the first dose.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M382" type="Trigger" span="66 10;118 9" str="converting | result in"/>
<Mention id="M383" type="Precipitant" span="99 14" str="opioid product" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M384" type="SpecificInteraction" span="130 14" str="fatal overdose" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I129" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M382" precipitant="M383" effect="M384" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2070" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Profound sedation, respiratory depression, coma, and death may result from the concomitant use of Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection with benzodiazepines or other CNS depressants (e.g., non-benzodiazepine sedatives/hypnotics, anxiolytics, tranquilizers, muscle relaxants, general anesthetics, antipsychotics, other opioids, alcohol).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M526" type="Trigger" span="63 11" str="result from"/>
<Mention id="M395" type="Precipitant" span="324 7" str="alcohol" code="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M"/>
<Mention id="M519" type="SpecificInteraction" span="43 4" str="coma" code="371632003: Coma (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M522" type="SpecificInteraction" span="53 5" str="death" code="419620001: Death (event)"/>
<Mention id="M525" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 17" str="Profound sedation" code="17971005: Sedated (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M528" type="SpecificInteraction" span="19 22" str="respiratory depression" code="80954004: Decreased respiratory function (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M407" type="Precipitant" span="293 14" str="antipsychotics" code="N0000029150 | N0000178316"/>
<Mention id="M419" type="Precipitant" span="226 11" str="anxiolytics" code="N0000193818"/>
<Mention id="M431" type="Precipitant" span="138 15" str="benzodiazepines" code="N0000007542 | N0000175694"/>
<Mention id="M443" type="Precipitant" span="163 15" str="CNS depressants" code="N0000175758"/>
<Mention id="M455" type="Precipitant" span="272 19" str="general anesthetics" code="N0000175681"/>
<Mention id="M467" type="Precipitant" span="254 16" str="muscle relaxants" code="N0000175737"/>
<Mention id="M479" type="Precipitant" span="186 18;215 9" str="non-benzodiazepine | hypnotics" code="N0000193842"/>
<Mention id="M491" type="Precipitant" span="186 28" str="non-benzodiazepine sedatives" code="N0000193842"/>
<Mention id="M503" type="Precipitant" span="186 38" str="non-benzodiazepine sedatives/hypnotics" code="N0000193842"/>
<Mention id="M515" type="Precipitant" span="315 7" str="opioids" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M527" type="Precipitant" span="239 13" str="tranquilizers" code="N0000029143 | N0000193842"/>
<Interaction id="I130" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M395" effect="M519" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I131" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M395" effect="M522" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I132" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M395" effect="M525" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I133" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M395" effect="M528" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I134" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M407" effect="M519" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I135" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M407" effect="M522" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I136" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M407" effect="M525" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I137" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M407" effect="M528" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I138" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M419" effect="M519" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I139" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M419" effect="M522" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I140" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M419" effect="M525" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I141" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M419" effect="M528" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I142" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M431" effect="M519" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I143" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M431" effect="M522" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I144" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M431" effect="M525" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I145" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M431" effect="M528" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I146" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M443" effect="M519" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I147" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M443" effect="M522" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I148" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M443" effect="M525" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I149" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M443" effect="M528" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I150" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M455" effect="M519" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I151" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M455" effect="M522" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I152" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M455" effect="M525" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I153" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M455" effect="M528" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I154" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M467" effect="M519" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I155" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M467" effect="M522" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I156" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M467" effect="M525" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I157" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M467" effect="M528" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I158" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M479" effect="M519" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I159" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M479" effect="M522" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I160" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M479" effect="M525" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I161" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M479" effect="M528" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I162" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M491" effect="M519" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I163" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M491" effect="M522" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I164" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M491" effect="M525" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I165" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M491" effect="M528" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I166" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M503" effect="M519" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I167" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M503" effect="M522" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I168" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M503" effect="M525" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I169" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M503" effect="M528" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I170" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M515" effect="M519" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I171" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M515" effect="M522" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I172" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M515" effect="M525" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I173" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M515" effect="M528" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I174" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M527" effect="M519" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I175" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M527" effect="M522" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I176" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M527" effect="M525" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I177" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M526" precipitant="M527" effect="M528" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2071" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Because of these risks, reserve concomitant prescribing of these drugs for use in patients for whom alternative treatment options are inadequate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2072" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Observational studies have demonstrated that concomitant use of opioid analgesics and benzodiazepines increases the risk of drug-related mortality compared to use of opioid analgesics alone.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M529" type="Trigger" span="102 18" str="increases the risk"/>
<Mention id="M530" type="Precipitant" span="86 15" str="benzodiazepines" code="N0000007542 | N0000175694"/>
<Mention id="M531" type="SpecificInteraction" span="124 22" str="drug-related mortality" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I178" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M529" precipitant="M530" effect="M531" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2073" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Because of similar pharmacological properties, it is reasonable to expect similar risk with the concomitant use of other CNS depressant drugs with opioid analgesics.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M532" type="Trigger" span="82 4" str="risk"/>
<Mention id="M533" type="Precipitant" span="121 20" str="CNS depressant drugs" code="N0000175758"/>
<Interaction id="I179" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M532" precipitant="M533"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2074" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>If the decision is made to prescribe a benzodiazepine or other CNS depressant concomitantly with an opioid analgesic, prescribe the lowest effective dosages and minimum durations of concomitant use.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M537" type="Trigger" span="132 24" str="lowest effective dosages "/>
<Mention id="M538" type="Trigger" span="161 17" str=" minimum durations"/>
<Mention id="M536" type="Precipitant" span="39 14" str="benzodiazepine" code="N0000175694 | M0Q7802G2B"/>
<Mention id="M539" type="Precipitant" span="63 14" str="CNS depressant" code="N0000175758"/>
<Interaction id="I180" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M537;M538" precipitant="M536"/>
<Interaction id="I181" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M537;M538" precipitant="M539"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2075" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>In patients already receiving an opioid analgesic, prescribe a lower initial dose of the benzodiazepine or other CNS depressant than indicated in the absence of an opioid, and titrate based on clinical response.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M542" type="Trigger" span="63 18" str="lower initial dose"/>
<Mention id="M541" type="Precipitant" span="89 14" str="benzodiazepine" code="N0000175694 | M0Q7802G2B"/>
<Mention id="M543" type="Precipitant" span="113 14" str="CNS depressant" code="N0000175758"/>
<Interaction id="I182" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M542" precipitant="M541"/>
<Interaction id="I183" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M542" precipitant="M543"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2076" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>If an opioid analgesic is initiated in a patient already taking a benzodiazepine or other CNS depressant, prescribe a lower initial dose of the opioid analgesic, and titrate based on clinical response.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M546" type="Trigger" span="118 18" str="lower initial dose"/>
<Mention id="M545" type="Precipitant" span="66 14" str="benzodiazepine" code="N0000175694 | M0Q7802G2B"/>
<Mention id="M547" type="Precipitant" span="90 14" str="CNS depressant" code="N0000175758"/>
<Interaction id="I184" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M546" precipitant="M545"/>
<Interaction id="I185" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M546" precipitant="M547"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2077" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Follow patients closely for signs and symptoms of respiratory depression and sedation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2078" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Advise both patients and caregivers about the risks of respiratory depression and sedation when Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection is used with benzodiazepines or other CNS depressants (including alcohol and illicit drugs).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M569" type="Trigger" span="46 8" str="risks of"/>
<Mention id="M552" type="Precipitant" span="196 7" str="alcohol" code="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M"/>
<Mention id="M568" type="SpecificInteraction" span="55 22" str="respiratory depression" code="80954004: Decreased respiratory function (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M571" type="SpecificInteraction" span="82 8" str="sedation" code="17971005: Sedated (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M558" type="Precipitant" span="144 15" str="benzodiazepines" code="N0000007542 | N0000175694"/>
<Mention id="M564" type="Precipitant" span="169 15" str="CNS depressants" code="N0000175758"/>
<Mention id="M570" type="Precipitant" span="208 13" str="illicit drugs" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I186" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M569" precipitant="M552" effect="M568" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I187" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M569" precipitant="M552" effect="M571" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I188" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M569" precipitant="M558" effect="M568" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I189" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M569" precipitant="M558" effect="M571" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I190" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M569" precipitant="M564" effect="M568" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I191" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M569" precipitant="M564" effect="M571" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I192" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M569" precipitant="M570" effect="M568" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I193" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M569" precipitant="M570" effect="M571" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2079" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Advise patients not to drive or operate heavy machinery until the effects of concomitant use of the benzodiazepine or other CNS depressant have been determined.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M575" type="Trigger" span="0 6" str="Advise "/>
<Mention id="M576" type="Trigger" span="66 7" str=" effects"/>
<Mention id="M574" type="Precipitant" span="100 14" str="benzodiazepine" code="N0000175694 | M0Q7802G2B"/>
<Mention id="M577" type="Precipitant" span="124 14" str="CNS depressant" code="N0000175758"/>
<Interaction id="I194" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M575;M576" precipitant="M574"/>
<Interaction id="I195" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M575;M576" precipitant="M577"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2080" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Screen patients for risk of substance use disorders, including opioid abuse and misuse, and warn them of the risk for overdose and death associated with the use of additional CNS depressants including alcohol and illicit drugs.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M598" type="Trigger" span="109 8" str="risk for "/>
<Mention id="M599" type="Trigger" span="137 15" str=" associated with"/>
<Mention id="M584" type="Precipitant" span="201 7" str="alcohol" code="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M"/>
<Mention id="M597" type="SpecificInteraction" span="131 5" str="death" code="419620001: Death (event)"/>
<Mention id="M601" type="SpecificInteraction" span="118 8" str="overdose" code="55680006: Drug overdose (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M592" type="Precipitant" span="175 15" str="CNS depressants" code="N0000175758"/>
<Mention id="M600" type="Precipitant" span="213 13" str="illicit drugs" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I196" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M598;M599" precipitant="M584" effect="M597" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I197" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M598;M599" precipitant="M584" effect="M601" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I198" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M598;M599" precipitant="M592" effect="M597" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I199" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M598;M599" precipitant="M592" effect="M601" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I200" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M598;M599" precipitant="M600" effect="M597" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I201" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M598;M599" precipitant="M600" effect="M601" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2081" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The use of Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection in patients with acute or severe bronchial asthma in an unmonitored setting or in the absence of resuscitative equipment is contraindicated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2082" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection-treated patients with significant chronic obstructive pulmonary disease or cor pulmonale, and those with a substantially decreased respiratory reserve, hypoxia, hypercapnia, or pre-existing respiratory depression are at increased risk of decreased respiratory drive including apnea, even at recommended dosages of use of Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2083" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Life-threatening respiratory depression is more likely to occur in elderly, cachectic, or debilitated patients because they may have altered pharmacokinetics or altered clearance compared to younger, healthier patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2084" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Monitor such patients closely, particularly when initiating and titrating Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection and when Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection is given concomitantly with other drugs that depress respiration.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M602" type="Trigger" span="0 7" str="Monitor"/>
<Mention id="M603" type="Precipitant" span="187 30" str="drugs that depress respiration" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I202" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M602" precipitant="M603"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2085" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Alternatively, consider the use of non-opioid analgesics in these patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2086" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Cases of adrenal insufficiency have been reported with opioid use, more often following greater than 1 month of use.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2087" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Presentation of adrenal insufficiency may include non-specific symptoms and signs including nausea, vomiting, anorexia, fatigue, weakness, dizziness, and low blood pressure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2088" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>If adrenal insufficiency is suspected, confirm the diagnosis with diagnostic testing as soon as possible.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2089" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>If adrenal insufficiency is diagnosed, treat with physiologic replacement doses of corticosteroids.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2090" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Wean the patient off of the opioid to allow adrenal function to recover and continue corticosteroid treatment until adrenal function recovers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2091" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Other opioids may be tried as some cases reported use of a different opioid without recurrence of adrenal insufficiency.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2092" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The information available does not identify any particular opioids as being more likely to be associated with adrenal insufficiency.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2093" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The possible respiratory depressant effects and the potential of potent analgesics to elevate cerebrospinal fluid pressure (resulting from vasodilation following CO2 retention) may be markedly exaggerated in the presence of head injury, intracranial lesions or a pre-existing increase in intracranial pressure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2094" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Furthermore, potent analgesics can produce effects which may obscure the clinical course of patients with head injuries.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2095" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Therefore, Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection should be used in these circumstances only when essential, and then should be administered with extreme caution.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2096" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection may impair the mental or physical abilities required for the performance of potentially dangerous tasks such as driving a car or operating machinery.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2097" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Therefore, Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection should be administered with caution to ambulatory patients who should be warned to avoid such hazards.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2098" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Maintain patient under observation until recovered from Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection effects that would affect driving or other potentially dangerous tasks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2099" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Severe fetal bradycardia has been reported when Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection is administered during labor.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2100" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Avoid the use of Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection in pregnant women unless the potential benefit outweighs the risk to the fetus, and if appropriate measures such as fetal monitoring are taken to detect and manage any potential adverse effect on the fetus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2101" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The placental transfer of nalbuphine is high, rapid, and variable with a maternal to fetal ratio ranging from 1:0.37 to 1:6.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2102" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Fetal and neonatal adverse effects that have been reported following the administration of nalbuphine to the mother during labor include fetal bradycardia, respiratory depression at birth, apnea, cyanosis, and hypotonia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2103" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Some of these events have been life-threatening.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2104" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Maternal administration of naloxone during labor has normalized these effects in some cases.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2105" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Severe and prolonged fetal bradycardia has been reported.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2106" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Permanent neurological damage attributed to fetal bradycardia has occurred.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2107" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>A sinusoidal fetal heart rate pattern associated with the use of nalbuphine has also been reported.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2108" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Nalbuphine should be used during labor and delivery only if clearly indicated and only if the potential benefit outweighs the risk to the infant.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2109" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Newborns should be monitored for respiratory depression, apnea, bradycardia and arrhythmias if nalbuphine has been used.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2110" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Nalbuphine hydrochloride is a synthetic opioid agonist-antagonist analgesic.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2111" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>As an opioid, Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection exposes users to the risks of addiction, abuse, and misuse.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2112" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Although the risk of addiction in any individual is unknown, it can occur in patients appropriately prescribed Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2113" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Addiction can occur at recommended dosages and if the drug is misused or abused.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2114" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Assess each patient's risk for opioid addiction, abuse, or misuse.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2115" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Risks are increased in patients with a personal or family history of substance abuse (including drug or alcohol abuse or addiction) or mental illness (e.g., major depression).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2116" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The potential for these risks should not, however, prevent the proper management of pain in any given patient.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2117" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Opioids are sought by drug abusers and people with addiction disorders and are subject to criminal diversion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2118" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Consider these risks when prescribing or dispensing Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2119" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Strategies to reduce these risks include prescribing the drug in the smallest appropriate quantity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2120" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Contact local state professional licensing board or state controlled substances authority for information on how to prevent and detect abuse or diversion of this product.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2121" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Chronic use of opioids may influence the hypothalamic-pituitary-gonadal axis, leading to androgen deficiency that may manifest as low libido, impotence, erectile dysfunction, amenorrhea, or infertility.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2122" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The causal role of opioids in the clinical syndrome of hypogonadism is unknown because the various medical, physical, lifestyle, and psychological stressors that may influence gonadal hormone levels have not been adequately controlled for in studies conducted to date.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2123" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection is a potent analgesic.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2124" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Its analgesic potency is essentially equivalent to that of morphine on a milligram basis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2125" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Receptor studies show that nalbuphine hydrochloride binds to mu, kappa, and delta receptors, but not to sigma receptors.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2126" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Nalbuphine hydrochloride is primarily a kappa agonist/partial mu antagonist analgesic.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2127" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The onset of action of nalbuphine hydrochloride occurs within 2 to 3 minutes after intravenous administration, and in less than 15 minutes following subcutaneous or intramuscular injection.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2128" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The plasma half-life of nalbuphine is 5 hours, and in clinical studies the duration of analgesic activity has been reported to range from 3 to 6 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2129" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The opioid antagonist activity of nalbuphine hydrochloride is one-fourth as potent as nalorphine and 10 times that of pentazocine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2130" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Nalbuphine hydrochloride may produce the same degree of respiratory depression as equianalgesic doses of morphine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2131" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>However, Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection exhibits a ceiling effect such that increases in dose greater than 30 mg do not produce further respiratory depression in the absence of other CNS active medications affecting respiration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2132" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Nalbuphine hydrochloride by itself has potent opioid antagonist activity at doses equal to or lower than its analgesic dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2133" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>When administered following or concurrent with mµ agonist opioid analgesics (e.g., morphine, oxymorphone, fentanyl), nalbuphine hydrochloride may partially reverse or block opioid-induced respiratory depression from the mµ agonist analgesic.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2134" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection may precipitate withdrawal in patients dependent on opioid drugs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2135" LabelDrug="Nalbuphine Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Nalbuphine Hydrochloride Injection should be used with caution in patients who have been receiving mu opioid analgesics on a regular basis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="central nervous system depressants" precipitantCode="N0000175758" effect="80954004: Decreased respiratory function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="opioids" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="17971005: Sedated (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="opioids" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="363101005: Drug withdrawal (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="opioids" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="371632003: Coma (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="opioids" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="419620001: Death (event)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="opioids" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="80954004: Decreased respiratory function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="opioids" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="alcohol" precipitantCode="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M" effect="17971005: Sedated (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="alcohol" precipitantCode="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M" effect="371632003: Coma (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="alcohol" precipitantCode="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M" effect="419620001: Death (event)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="alcohol" precipitantCode="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M" effect="55680006: Drug overdose (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="alcohol" precipitantCode="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M" effect="80954004: Decreased respiratory function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="benzodiazepines" precipitantCode="N0000007542 | N0000175694" effect="17971005: Sedated (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="benzodiazepines" precipitantCode="N0000007542 | N0000175694" effect="371632003: Coma (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="benzodiazepines" precipitantCode="N0000007542 | N0000175694" effect="419620001: Death (event)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="benzodiazepines" precipitantCode="N0000007542 | N0000175694" effect="80954004: Decreased respiratory function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="benzodiazepines" precipitantCode="N0000007542 | N0000175694" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="benzodiazepines" precipitantCode="N0000007542 | N0000175694"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="central nervous system (cns) depressants" precipitantCode="N0000175758" effect="17971005: Sedated (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="central nervous system (cns) depressants" precipitantCode="N0000175758" effect="371632003: Coma (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="central nervous system (cns) depressants" precipitantCode="N0000175758" effect="419620001: Death (event)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="central nervous system (cns) depressants" precipitantCode="N0000175758" effect="80954004: Decreased respiratory function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="central nervous system | depressants" precipitantCode="N0000175758" effect="17971005: Sedated (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="central nervous system | depressants" precipitantCode="N0000175758" effect="371632003: Coma (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="central nervous system | depressants" precipitantCode="N0000175758" effect="419620001: Death (event)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="central nervous system | depressants" precipitantCode="N0000175758" effect="80954004: Decreased respiratory function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cns | depressants" precipitantCode="N0000175758" effect="17971005: Sedated (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cns | depressants" precipitantCode="N0000175758" effect="371632003: Coma (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cns | depressants" precipitantCode="N0000175758" effect="419620001: Death (event)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cns | depressants" precipitantCode="N0000175758" effect="80954004: Decreased respiratory function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cns depressants" precipitantCode="N0000175758" effect="17971005: Sedated (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cns depressants" precipitantCode="N0000175758" effect="371632003: Coma (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cns depressants" precipitantCode="N0000175758" effect="419620001: Death (event)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cns depressants" precipitantCode="N0000175758" effect="55680006: Drug overdose (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cns depressants" precipitantCode="N0000175758" effect="80954004: Decreased respiratory function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cns depressants" precipitantCode="N0000175758" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="cns depressants" precipitantCode="N0000175758"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="opioid" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="antipsychotics" precipitantCode="N0000029150 | N0000178316" effect="17971005: Sedated (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="antipsychotics" precipitantCode="N0000029150 | N0000178316" effect="371632003: Coma (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="antipsychotics" precipitantCode="N0000029150 | N0000178316" effect="419620001: Death (event)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="antipsychotics" precipitantCode="N0000029150 | N0000178316" effect="80954004: Decreased respiratory function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="antipsychotics" precipitantCode="N0000029150 | N0000178316" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="anxiolytics" precipitantCode="N0000193818" effect="17971005: Sedated (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="anxiolytics" precipitantCode="N0000193818" effect="371632003: Coma (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="anxiolytics" precipitantCode="N0000193818" effect="419620001: Death (event)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="anxiolytics" precipitantCode="N0000193818" effect="80954004: Decreased respiratory function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="anxiolytics" precipitantCode="N0000193818" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="general anesthetics" precipitantCode="N0000175681" effect="17971005: Sedated (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="general anesthetics" precipitantCode="N0000175681" effect="371632003: Coma (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="general anesthetics" precipitantCode="N0000175681" effect="419620001: Death (event)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="general anesthetics" precipitantCode="N0000175681" effect="80954004: Decreased respiratory function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="general anesthetics" precipitantCode="N0000175681" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="hypnotics" precipitantCode="N0000029424 | N0000193842" effect="17971005: Sedated (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="hypnotics" precipitantCode="N0000029424 | N0000193842" effect="371632003: Coma (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="hypnotics" precipitantCode="N0000029424 | N0000193842" effect="419620001: Death (event)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="hypnotics" precipitantCode="N0000029424 | N0000193842" effect="80954004: Decreased respiratory function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="hypnotics" precipitantCode="N0000029424 | N0000193842" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="muscle relaxants" precipitantCode="N0000175737" effect="17971005: Sedated (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="muscle relaxants" precipitantCode="N0000175737" effect="371632003: Coma (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="muscle relaxants" precipitantCode="N0000175737" effect="419620001: Death (event)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="muscle relaxants" precipitantCode="N0000175737" effect="80954004: Decreased respiratory function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="muscle relaxants" precipitantCode="N0000175737" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="opioid analgesics" precipitantCode="N0000175440" effect="17971005: Sedated (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="opioid analgesics" precipitantCode="N0000175440" effect="371632003: Coma (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="opioid analgesics" precipitantCode="N0000175440" effect="419620001: Death (event)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="opioid analgesics" precipitantCode="N0000175440" effect="80954004: Decreased respiratory function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="opioid analgesics" precipitantCode="N0000175440" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sedatives" precipitantCode="N0000029143 | N0000193842" effect="17971005: Sedated (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sedatives" precipitantCode="N0000029143 | N0000193842" effect="371632003: Coma (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sedatives" precipitantCode="N0000029143 | N0000193842" effect="419620001: Death (event)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sedatives" precipitantCode="N0000029143 | N0000193842" effect="80954004: Decreased respiratory function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sedatives" precipitantCode="N0000029143 | N0000193842" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sedatives/hypnotics" precipitantCode="n0000029143 | N0000193842" effect="17971005: Sedated (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sedatives/hypnotics" precipitantCode="n0000029143 | N0000193842" effect="371632003: Coma (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sedatives/hypnotics" precipitantCode="n0000029143 | N0000193842" effect="419620001: Death (event)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sedatives/hypnotics" precipitantCode="n0000029143 | N0000193842" effect="80954004: Decreased respiratory function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sedatives/hypnotics" precipitantCode="n0000029143 | N0000193842" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="tranquilizers" precipitantCode="N0000029143 | N0000193842" effect="17971005: Sedated (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="tranquilizers" precipitantCode="N0000029143 | N0000193842" effect="371632003: Coma (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="tranquilizers" precipitantCode="N0000029143 | N0000193842" effect="419620001: Death (event)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="tranquilizers" precipitantCode="N0000029143 | N0000193842" effect="80954004: Decreased respiratory function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="tranquilizers" precipitantCode="N0000029143 | N0000193842" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="5-ht3 receptor antagonists" precipitantCode="N0000175817 | N0000000090" effect="371089000: Serotonin syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="drugs that affect the serotonergic neurotransmitter system" precipitantCode="N0000009844" effect="371089000: Serotonin syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="drugs that affect the serotonin neurotransmitter system" precipitantCode="N0000009844" effect="371089000: Serotonin syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="intravenous methylene blue" precipitantCode="N0000007449 | T42P99266K" effect="371089000: Serotonin syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="linezolid" precipitantCode="ISQ9I6J12J" effect="371089000: Serotonin syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="linezolid" precipitantCode="ISQ9I6J12J" effect="371632003: Coma (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="linezolid" precipitantCode="ISQ9I6J12J" effect="77721001: Opioid intoxication (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="linezolid" precipitantCode="ISQ9I6J12J" effect="80954004: Decreased respiratory function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="mao | inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000000184 | N0000175744" effect="371089000: Serotonin syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="mirtazapine" precipitantCode="A051Q2099Q" effect="371089000: Serotonin syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="monoamine oxidase (mao) inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000000184 | N0000175744" effect="371089000: Serotonin syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="monoamine oxidase | inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000000184 | N0000175744" effect="371089000: Serotonin syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175696" effect="371089000: Serotonin syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="serotonin and norepinephrine reuptake inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175749" effect="371089000: Serotonin syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="snris" precipitantCode="N0000175749" effect="371089000: Serotonin syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ssris" precipitantCode="N0000175696" effect="371089000: Serotonin syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="tcas" precipitantCode="N0000029148 | N0000175752" effect="371089000: Serotonin syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="tramadol" precipitantCode="39J1LGJ30J" effect="371089000: Serotonin syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="trazodone" precipitantCode="YBK48BXK30" effect="371089000: Serotonin syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="tricyclic antidepressants" precipitantCode="N0000029148 | N0000175752" effect="371089000: Serotonin syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="triptans" precipitantCode="40V943JDGR" effect="371089000: Serotonin syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="maoi" precipitantCode="N0000000184" effect="371089000: Serotonin syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="maoi" precipitantCode="N0000000184" effect="371632003: Coma (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="maoi" precipitantCode="N0000000184" effect="77721001: Opioid intoxication (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="maoi" precipitantCode="N0000000184" effect="80954004: Decreased respiratory function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="phenelzine" precipitantCode="O408N561GF" effect="371089000: Serotonin syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="phenelzine" precipitantCode="O408N561GF" effect="371632003: Coma (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="phenelzine" precipitantCode="O408N561GF" effect="77721001: Opioid intoxication (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="phenelzine" precipitantCode="O408N561GF" effect="80954004: Decreased respiratory function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="tranylcypromine" precipitantCode="3E3V44J4Z9" effect="371089000: Serotonin syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="tranylcypromine" precipitantCode="3E3V44J4Z9" effect="371632003: Coma (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="tranylcypromine" precipitantCode="3E3V44J4Z9" effect="77721001: Opioid intoxication (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="tranylcypromine" precipitantCode="3E3V44J4Z9" effect="80954004: Decreased respiratory function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="maois" precipitantCode="N0000000184"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="serotonergic drugs" precipitantCode="N0000000256" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="serotonergic medications" precipitantCode="N0000000256"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="agents that depress respiration" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="80954004: Decreased respiratory function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="opioid product" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="non-benzodiazepine | hypnotics" precipitantCode="N0000193842" effect="17971005: Sedated (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="non-benzodiazepine | hypnotics" precipitantCode="N0000193842" effect="371632003: Coma (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="non-benzodiazepine | hypnotics" precipitantCode="N0000193842" effect="419620001: Death (event)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="non-benzodiazepine | hypnotics" precipitantCode="N0000193842" effect="80954004: Decreased respiratory function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="non-benzodiazepine sedatives" precipitantCode="N0000193842" effect="17971005: Sedated (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="non-benzodiazepine sedatives" precipitantCode="N0000193842" effect="371632003: Coma (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="non-benzodiazepine sedatives" precipitantCode="N0000193842" effect="419620001: Death (event)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="non-benzodiazepine sedatives" precipitantCode="N0000193842" effect="80954004: Decreased respiratory function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="non-benzodiazepine sedatives/hypnotics" precipitantCode="N0000193842" effect="17971005: Sedated (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="non-benzodiazepine sedatives/hypnotics" precipitantCode="N0000193842" effect="371632003: Coma (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="non-benzodiazepine sedatives/hypnotics" precipitantCode="N0000193842" effect="419620001: Death (event)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="non-benzodiazepine sedatives/hypnotics" precipitantCode="N0000193842" effect="80954004: Decreased respiratory function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="cns depressant drugs" precipitantCode="N0000175758"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="benzodiazepine" precipitantCode="N0000175694 | M0Q7802G2B"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="cns depressant" precipitantCode="N0000175758"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="illicit drugs" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="17971005: Sedated (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="illicit drugs" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="419620001: Death (event)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="illicit drugs" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="55680006: Drug overdose (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="illicit drugs" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="80954004: Decreased respiratory function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="drugs that depress respiration" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>