<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Avita" setid="6bb07b84-68bd-4513-b0cf-e2e949eaa964">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
The product should not be used if there is hypersensitivity to any of the ingredients.</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
AVITA ® Gel should be applied once a day, in the evening, to the skin where acne lesions appear, using enough to cover the entire affected area lightly. Application may cause a transient feeling of warmth or slight stinging. In cases where it has been necessary to temporarily discontinue therapy or reduce the frequency of application, therapy may be resumed or frequency of application increased when the patients become able to tolerate the treatment. Alterations of dose frequency should be closely monitored by careful observation of the clinical therapeutic response and skin tolerance. Efficacy has not been established for less than once-daily dosing frequencies. During the early weeks of therapy, an apparent increase in number and exacerbation of inflammatory acne lesions may occur. This is due, in part, to the action of the medication on deep, previously unseen lesions and should not be considered a reason to discontinue therapy. Therapeutic results should be noticed after two to three weeks, but more than six weeks of therapy may be required before definite beneficial effects are seen. Patients treated with AVITA ® Gel may use cosmetics, but the areas to be treated should be cleansed thoroughly before the medication is applied (see Precautions Section).</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
Concomitant topical medication, medicated or abrasive soaps and cleansers, soaps and cosmetics that have a strong drying effect, and products with high concentrations of alcohol, astringents, spices or lime should be used with caution because of possible interaction with tretinoin. Particular caution should be exercised in using preparations containing sulfur, resorcinol, or salicylic acid with AVITA ® Gel. It also is advisable to “rest” a patient’s skin until the effects of such preparations subside before use of AVITA ® Gel is begun.</Section>
<Section name="PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="42232-9">
If a reaction suggesting sensitivity or chemical irritation occurs, use of the medication should be discontinued. Exposure to sunlight, including sunlamps or artificial sunlight should be minimized during the use of AVITA ® Gel, and patients with sunburn should be advised not to use the product until fully recovered because of heightened susceptibility to sunlight as a result of the use of tretinoin. Patients who may be required to have considerable sun exposure due to occupation and those with inherent sensitivity to the sun should exercise particular caution. Use of sunscreen products and protective clothing over treated areas is recommended when exposure cannot be avoided. Weather extremes, such as wind or cold, also may be irritating to patients under treatment with tretinoin. AVITA ® (tretinoin gel) Gel, 0.025% should be kept away from the eyes, the mouth, the paranasal creases, and mucous membranes.Topical use may induce severe local erythema and peeling at the site of application. If the degree of local irritation warrants, patients should be directed to temporarily use the medication less frequently, discontinue use temporarily, or discontinue use altogether. Efficacy at reduced frequencies of application has not been established. Tretinoin has been reported to cause severe irritation on eczematous skin and should be used with utmost caution in patients with this condition. See attached Patient Package Insert . Concomitant topical medication, medicated or abrasive soaps and cleansers, soaps and cosmetics that have a strong drying effect, and products with high concentrations of alcohol, astringents, spices or lime should be used with caution because of possible interaction with tretinoin. Particular caution should be exercised in using preparations containing sulfur, resorcinol, or salicylic acid with AVITA ® Gel. It also is advisable to “rest” a patient’s skin until the effects of such preparations subside before use of AVITA ® Gel is begun. In a dermal mouse carcinogenicity study with AVITA® Gel, tretinoin was administered to CD-1 mice at topical doses of 0.027 mg/kg (0.003% gel), 0.072 mg/kg (0.008% gel), and 0.225 mg/kg (0.025% gel) for 2 years (5 doses/week). No drug-related tumors were noted in this mouse carcinogenicity study up to the highest dose evaluated in this study of 0.225 mg/kg in both male and female mice, which was 2.6 times the recommended human topical clinical dose (based on weekly dose BSA comparison). For purposes of comparisons of the animal exposure to human exposure, the “recommended human topical clinical dose” is defined as 1.0 g of 0.025% AVITA® Gel applied daily to a 50 kg person. In a chronic, two-year bioassay of vitamin A acid in mice performed by Tsubura and Yamamoto, generalized amyloid deposition was reported in all vitamin A treated groups in the basal layer of the skin. In CD-1 mice, a similar study reported hyalinization at the treated skin sites and the incidence of this finding was 0/50, 3/50, 3/50, and 2/50 in male mice and 1/50, 0/50, 4/50, and 2/50 in female mice from the vehicle control, 0.25 mg/kg, 0.5 mg/kg, and 1 mg/kg groups, respectively. Studies in hairless albino mice suggest that tretinoin may enhance the tumorigenic potential of carcinogenic doses of UVA and UVB light from a solar simulator. In other studies, when lightly pigmented hairless mice treated with tretinoin were exposed to carcinogenic doses of UVA/UVB light, the incidence and rate of development of skin tumors were either reduced or no effect was seen. Due to significantly different experimental conditions, no strict comparison of these disparate data is possible at this time. Although the significance of these studies to humans is not clear, patients should minimize exposure to sun. The mutagenic potential of tretinoin was evaluated in the Ames assay and in the in vivo mouse micronucleus assay, both of which were negative. Dermal Segment I and III studies with AVITA ® Gel have not been performed in any species. In oral Segment I and Segment III studies in rats with tretinoin, decreased survival of neonates and growth retardation were observed at doses in excess of 2 mg/kg/day (&amp;gt; 400 times the average recommended human topical clinical dose). Oral tretinoin has been shown to be teratogenic in rats, mice, rabbits, hamsters, and subhuman primates. It was teratogenic and fetotoxic in rats when given orally in doses 1000 times the average recommended human topical clinical dose. However, variations in teratogenic doses among various strains of rats have been reported. In the cynomolgus monkey, which metabolically is closer to humans for tretinoin than other species examined, fetal malformations were reported at oral doses of 10 mg/kg/day or greater, but none were observed at 5 mg/kg/day (1000 times the average recommended human topical clinical dose), although increased skeletal variations were observed at all doses. Dose-related increased embryolethality and abortion were reported. Similar results have also been reported in pigtail macaques. Topical tretinoin in animal teratogenicity tests has generated equivocal results. There is evidence for teratogenicity (shortened or kinked tail) of topical tretinoin in Wistar rats at doses greater than 1 mg/kg/day (200 times the recommended human topical clinical dose). Anomalies (humerus: short 13%, bent 6%; os parietal incompletely ossified 14%) have also been reported in rats when 10 mg/kg/day was dermally applied. Topical tretinoin (AVITA ® Gel, 0.025%) has been shown to be teratogenic in rabbits when given in doses 364 times the topical human dose for gel (assuming a 50 kg adult applies 1.0 g of 0.025% gel topically). In this study, increased incidence of cleft palate and hydrocephaly was reported in the tretinoin-treated animals. There are other reports, in New Zealand White rabbits with doses of approximately 80 times the recommended human topical clinical dose, of an increased incidence of domed head and hydrocephaly, typical of retinoid-induced fetal malformations in this species. When given subcutaneously to rabbits, tretinoin was teratogenic at 2 mg/kg/day but not at 1 mg/kg/day. These doses are approximately 400 and 200 times, respectively, the human topical dose of tretinoin gel, 0.025% (assuming a 50 kg adult applies 1.0 g of 0.025% gel topically). In contrast, several well-controlled animal studies have shown that dermally applied tretinoin was not teratogenic at doses of 100 and 200 times the recommended human topical clinical dose, in rats and rabbits, respectively. With widespread use of any drug, a small number of birth defect reports associated temporally with the administration of the drug would be expected by chance alone. Thirty cases of temporally associated congenital malformations have been reported during two decades of clinical use of another formulation of topical tretinoin (Retin-A). Although no definite pattern of teratogenicity and no causal association have been established from these cases, 5 of the reports describe the rare birth defect category, holoprosencephaly (defects associated with incomplete midline development of the forebrain). The significance of these spontaneous reports in terms of risk to the fetus is not known. Dermal tretinoin has been shown to be fetotoxic in rabbits when administered in doses 100 times the recommended topical human clinical dose. Oral tretinoin has been shown to be fetotoxic in rats when administered in doses 500 times the recommended topical human clinical dose. There are, however, no adequate and well-controlled studies in pregnant women.  AVITA ® (tretinoin gel) Gel, 0.025% should not be used during pregnancy. It is not known whether this drug is excreted in human milk, caution should be exercised when AVITA ® Gel is administered to a nursing woman.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS SECTION" id="34071-1">
GELS ARE FLAMMABLE. Note: Keep away from heat and flame. Keep tube tightly closed.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Although the exact mode of action of tretinoin is unknown, current evidence suggests that topical tretinoin decreases cohesiveness of follicular epithelial cells with decreased microcomedo formation. Additionally, tretinoin stimulates mitotic activity and increased turnover of follicular epithelial cells causing extrusion of the comedones. In vitro and in vivo pharmacokinetic studies with AVITA ® Gel indicate that less than 0.3% of the topically applied dose is bioavailable. Circulating plasma levels of both tretinoin and isotretinoin are only slightly elevated above those found in healthy normal controls. In two large vehicle-controlled clinical trials, AVITA ® (tretinoin gel) Gel 0.025%, applied once daily was more effective than vehicle in the treatment of facial acne vulgaris of mild to moderate severity . Percent reductions in lesion counts after treatment for 12 weeks in these studies are shown in the following Tables: Study 1 AVITA ® Gel, 0.025% Vehicle Gel N = 198 N = 204 Noninflammatory Lesions -36% -27% Inflammatory Lesions -35% -25% Total Lesions -36% -27% Study 2 AVITA ® Gel, 0.025% Vehicle Gel N = 58 N = 58 N = Number of Subjects Noninflammatory Lesions -42% -26% Inflammatory Lesions -38% -23% Total Lesions -41% -26%</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="7243" LabelDrug="Avita" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>The product should not be used if there is hypersensitivity to any of the ingredients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7244" LabelDrug="Avita" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>AVITA® Gel should be applied once a day, in the evening, to the skin where acne lesions appear, using enough to cover the entire affected area lightly.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7245" LabelDrug="Avita" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Application may cause a transient feeling of warmth or slight stinging.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7246" LabelDrug="Avita" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In cases where it has been necessary to temporarily discontinue therapy or reduce the frequency of application, therapy may be resumed or frequency of application increased when the patients become able to tolerate the treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7247" LabelDrug="Avita" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Alterations of dose frequency should be closely monitored by careful observation of the clinical therapeutic response and skin tolerance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7248" LabelDrug="Avita" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Efficacy has not been established for less than once-daily dosing frequencies.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7249" LabelDrug="Avita" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>During the early weeks of therapy, an apparent increase in number and exacerbation of inflammatory acne lesions may occur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7250" LabelDrug="Avita" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>This is due, in part, to the action of the medication on deep, previously unseen lesions and should not be considered a reason to discontinue therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7251" LabelDrug="Avita" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Therapeutic results should be noticed after two to three weeks, but more than six weeks of therapy may be required before definite beneficial effects are seen.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7252" LabelDrug="Avita" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Patients treated with AVITA® Gel may use cosmetics, but the areas to be treated should be cleansed thoroughly before the medication is applied.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7253" LabelDrug="Avita" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant topical medication, medicated or abrasive soaps and cleansers, soaps and cosmetics that have a strong drying effect, and products with high concentrations of alcohol, astringents, spices or lime should be used with caution because of possible interaction with tretinoin.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M34" type="Trigger" span="227 7" str="caution "/>
<Mention id="M35" type="Trigger" span="246 20" str=" possible interaction"/>
<Mention id="M3" type="Precipitant" span="45 8;64 9" str="abrasive | cleansers" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M6" type="Precipitant" span="45 14" str="abrasive soaps" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M9" type="Precipitant" span="170 7" str="alcohol" code="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M"/>
<Mention id="M12" type="Precipitant" span="179 11" str="astringents" code="N0000008301"/>
<Mention id="M15" type="Precipitant" span="85 42" str="cosmetics that have a strong drying effect" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M18" type="Precipitant" span="202 4" str="lime" code="C7X2M0VVNH"/>
<Mention id="M21" type="Precipitant" span="32 9;64 9" str="medicated | cleansers" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M24" type="Precipitant" span="32 9;54 5" str="medicated | soaps" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M27" type="Precipitant" span="133 44" str="products with high concentrations of alcohol" code="3K9958V90M"/>
<Mention id="M30" type="Precipitant" span="54 5;95 32" str="soaps | that have a strong drying effect" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M33" type="Precipitant" span="192 6" str="spices" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M36" type="Precipitant" span="12 18" str="topical medication" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M34;M35" precipitant="M3"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M34;M35" precipitant="M6"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M34;M35" precipitant="M9"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M34;M35" precipitant="M12"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M34;M35" precipitant="M15"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M34;M35" precipitant="M18"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M34;M35" precipitant="M21"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M34;M35" precipitant="M24"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M34;M35" precipitant="M27"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M34;M35" precipitant="M30"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M34;M35" precipitant="M33"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M34;M35" precipitant="M36"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7254" LabelDrug="Avita" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Particular caution should be exercised in using preparations containing sulfur, resorcinol, or salicylic acid with AVITA® Gel.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M49" type="Trigger" span="11 7" str="caution"/>
<Mention id="M38" type="Precipitant" span="48 23;80 10" str="preparations containing | resorcinol" code="YUL4LO94HK"/>
<Mention id="M40" type="Precipitant" span="48 23;95 14" str="preparations containing | salicylic acid" code="O414PZ4LPZ"/>
<Mention id="M42" type="Precipitant" span="48 30" str="preparations containing sulfur" code="70FD1KFU70"/>
<Mention id="M44" type="Precipitant" span="48 61" str="preparations containing sulfur, resorcinol, or salicylic acid" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M46" type="Precipitant" span="80 10" str="resorcinol" code="YUL4LO94HK"/>
<Mention id="M48" type="Precipitant" span="95 14" str="salicylic acid" code="O414PZ4LPZ"/>
<Mention id="M50" type="Precipitant" span="72 6" str="sulfur" code="70FD1KFU70"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M49" precipitant="M38"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M49" precipitant="M40"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M49" precipitant="M42"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M49" precipitant="M44"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M49" precipitant="M46"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M49" precipitant="M48"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M49" precipitant="M50"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7255" LabelDrug="Avita" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>It also is advisable to “rest” a patient’s skin until the effects of such preparations subside before use of AVITA® Gel is begun.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7256" LabelDrug="Avita" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>If a reaction suggesting sensitivity or chemical irritation occurs, use of the medication should be discontinued.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7257" LabelDrug="Avita" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Exposure to sunlight, including sunlamps or artificial sunlight should be minimized during the use of AVITA® Gel, and patients with sunburn should be advised not to use the product until fully recovered because of heightened susceptibility to sunlight as a result of the use of tretinoin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7258" LabelDrug="Avita" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Patients who may be required to have considerable sun exposure due to occupation and those with inherent sensitivity to the sun should exercise particular caution.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7259" LabelDrug="Avita" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Use of sunscreen products and protective clothing over treated areas is recommended when exposure cannot be avoided.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7260" LabelDrug="Avita" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Weather extremes, such as wind or cold, also may be irritating to patients under treatment with tretinoin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7261" LabelDrug="Avita" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>AVITA® (tretinoin gel) Gel, 0.025% should be kept away from the eyes, the mouth, the paranasal creases, and mucous membranes.Topical use may induce severe local erythema and peeling at the site of application.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7262" LabelDrug="Avita" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>If the degree of local irritation warrants, patients should be directed to temporarily use the medication less frequently, discontinue use temporarily, or discontinue use altogether.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7263" LabelDrug="Avita" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Efficacy at reduced frequencies of application has not been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7264" LabelDrug="Avita" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Tretinoin has been reported to cause severe irritation on eczematous skin and should be used with utmost caution in patients with this condition.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7265" LabelDrug="Avita" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In a dermal mouse carcinogenicity study with AVITA® Gel, tretinoin was administered to CD-1 mice at topical doses of 0.027 mg/kg (0.003% gel), 0.072 mg/kg (0.008% gel), and 0.225 mg/kg (0.025% gel) for 2 years (5 doses/week).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7266" LabelDrug="Avita" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>No drug-related tumors were noted in this mouse carcinogenicity study up to the highest dose evaluated in this study of 0.225 mg/kg in both male and female mice, which was 2.6 times the recommended human topical clinical dose (based on weekly dose BSA comparison).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7267" LabelDrug="Avita" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>For purposes of comparisons of the animal exposure to human exposure, the “recommended human topical clinical dose” is defined as 1.0 g of 0.025% AVITA® Gel applied daily to a 50 kg person.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7268" LabelDrug="Avita" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In a chronic, two-year bioassay of vitamin A acid in mice performed by Tsubura and Yamamoto, generalized amyloid deposition was reported in all vitamin A treated groups in the basal layer of the skin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7269" LabelDrug="Avita" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In CD-1 mice, a similar study reported hyalinization at the treated skin sites and the incidence of this finding was 0/50, 3/50, 3/50, and 2/50 in male mice and 1/50, 0/50, 4/50, and 2/50 in female mice from the vehicle control, 0.25 mg/kg, 0.5 mg/kg, and 1 mg/kg groups, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7270" LabelDrug="Avita" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Studies in hairless albino mice suggest that tretinoin may enhance the tumorigenic potential of carcinogenic doses of UVA and UVB light from a solar simulator.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7271" LabelDrug="Avita" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In other studies, when lightly pigmented hairless mice treated with tretinoin were exposed to carcinogenic doses of UVA/UVB light, the incidence and rate of development of skin tumors were either reduced or no effect was seen.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7272" LabelDrug="Avita" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Due to significantly different experimental conditions, no strict comparison of these disparate data is possible at this time.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7273" LabelDrug="Avita" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Although the significance of these studies to humans is not clear, patients should minimize exposure to sun.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7274" LabelDrug="Avita" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The mutagenic potential of tretinoin was evaluated in the Ames assay and in the in vivo mouse micronucleus assay, both of which were negative.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7275" LabelDrug="Avita" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Dermal Segment I and III studies with AVITA® Gel have not been performed in any species.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7276" LabelDrug="Avita" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In oral Segment I and Segment III studies in rats with tretinoin, decreased survival of neonates and growth retardation were observed at doses in excess of 2 mg/kg/day (&gt; 400 times the average recommended human topical clinical dose).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7277" LabelDrug="Avita" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Oral tretinoin has been shown to be teratogenic in rats, mice, rabbits, hamsters, and subhuman primates.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7278" LabelDrug="Avita" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>It was teratogenic and fetotoxic in rats when given orally in doses 1000 times the average recommended human topical clinical dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7279" LabelDrug="Avita" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>However, variations in teratogenic doses among various strains of rats have been reported.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7280" LabelDrug="Avita" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In the cynomolgus monkey, which metabolically is closer to humans for tretinoin than other species examined, fetal malformations were reported at oral doses of 10 mg/kg/day or greater, but none were observed at 5 mg/kg/day (1000 times the average recommended human topical clinical dose), although increased skeletal variations were observed at all doses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7281" LabelDrug="Avita" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Dose-related increased embryolethality and abortion were reported.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7282" LabelDrug="Avita" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Similar results have also been reported in pigtail macaques.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7283" LabelDrug="Avita" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Topical tretinoin in animal teratogenicity tests has generated equivocal results.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7284" LabelDrug="Avita" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>There is evidence for teratogenicity (shortened or kinked tail) of topical tretinoin in Wistar rats at doses greater than 1 mg/kg/day (200 times the recommended human topical clinical dose).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7285" LabelDrug="Avita" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Anomalies (humerus: short 13%, bent 6%; os parietal incompletely ossified 14%) have also been reported in rats when 10 mg/kg/day was dermally applied.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7286" LabelDrug="Avita" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Topical tretinoin (AVITA® Gel, 0.025%) has been shown to be teratogenic in rabbits when given in doses 364 times the topical human dose for gel (assuming a 50 kg adult applies 1.0 g of 0.025% gel topically).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7287" LabelDrug="Avita" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In this study, increased incidence of cleft palate and hydrocephaly was reported in the tretinoin-treated animals.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7288" LabelDrug="Avita" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>There are other reports, in New Zealand White rabbits with doses of approximately 80 times the recommended human topical clinical dose, of an increased incidence of domed head and hydrocephaly, typical of retinoid-induced fetal malformations in this species.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7289" LabelDrug="Avita" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>When given subcutaneously to rabbits, tretinoin was teratogenic at 2 mg/kg/day but not at 1 mg/kg/day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7290" LabelDrug="Avita" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>These doses are approximately 400 and 200 times, respectively, the human topical dose of tretinoin gel, 0.025% (assuming a 50 kg adult applies 1.0 g of 0.025% gel topically).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7291" LabelDrug="Avita" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In contrast, several well-controlled animal studies have shown that dermally applied tretinoin was not teratogenic at doses of 100 and 200 times the recommended human topical clinical dose, in rats and rabbits, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7292" LabelDrug="Avita" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>With widespread use of any drug, a small number of birth defect reports associated temporally with the administration of the drug would be expected by chance alone.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7293" LabelDrug="Avita" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Thirty cases of temporally associated congenital malformations have been reported during two decades of clinical use of another formulation of topical tretinoin (Retin-A).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7294" LabelDrug="Avita" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Although no definite pattern of teratogenicity and no causal association have been established from these cases, 5 of the reports describe the rare birth defect category, holoprosencephaly (defects associated with incomplete midline development of the forebrain).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7295" LabelDrug="Avita" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The significance of these spontaneous reports in terms of risk to the fetus is not known.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7296" LabelDrug="Avita" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Dermal tretinoin has been shown to be fetotoxic in rabbits when administered in doses 100 times the recommended topical human clinical dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7297" LabelDrug="Avita" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Oral tretinoin has been shown to be fetotoxic in rats when administered in doses 500 times the recommended topical human clinical dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7298" LabelDrug="Avita" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>There are, however, no adequate and well-controlled studies in pregnant women.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7299" LabelDrug="Avita" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>AVITA® (tretinoin gel) Gel, 0.025% should not be used during pregnancy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7300" LabelDrug="Avita" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>It is not known whether this drug is excreted in human milk, caution should be exercised when AVITA® Gel is administered to a nursing woman.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7301" LabelDrug="Avita" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Although the exact mode of action of tretinoin is unknown, current evidence suggests that topical tretinoin decreases cohesiveness of follicular epithelial cells with decreased microcomedo formation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7302" LabelDrug="Avita" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Additionally, tretinoin stimulates mitotic activity and increased turnover of follicular epithelial cells causing extrusion of the comedones.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7303" LabelDrug="Avita" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In vitro and in vivo pharmacokinetic studies with AVITA® Gel indicate that less than 0.3% of the topically applied dose is bioavailable.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7304" LabelDrug="Avita" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Circulating plasma levels of both tretinoin and isotretinoin are only slightly elevated above those found in healthy normal controls.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7305" LabelDrug="Avita" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In two large vehicle-controlled clinical trials, AVITA® (tretinoin gel) Gel 0.025%, applied once daily was more effective than vehicle in the treatment of facial acne vulgaris of mild to moderate severity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7306" LabelDrug="Avita" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Percent reductions in lesion counts after treatment for 12 weeks in these studies are shown in the following Tables: Study 1 AVITA® Gel,0.025% VehicleGel N = 198 N = 204 Noninflammatory Lesions -36% -27% Inflammatory Lesions -35% -25% Total Lesions -36% -27% Study 2 AVITA® Gel,0.025% VehicleGel N = 58 N = 58 N = Number of Subjects Noninflammatory Lesions -42% -26% Inflammatory Lesions -38% -23% Total Lesions -41% -26%</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="abrasive | cleansers" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="abrasive soaps" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="alcohol" precipitantCode="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="astringents" precipitantCode="N0000008301"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="cosmetics that have a strong drying effect" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="lime" precipitantCode="C7X2M0VVNH"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="medicated | cleansers" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="medicated | soaps" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="products with high concentrations of alcohol" precipitantCode="3K9958V90M"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="soaps | that have a strong drying effect" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="spices" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="topical medication" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="preparations containing | resorcinol" precipitantCode="YUL4LO94HK"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="preparations containing | salicylic acid" precipitantCode="O414PZ4LPZ"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="preparations containing sulfur" precipitantCode="70FD1KFU70"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="preparations containing sulfur, resorcinol, or salicylic acid" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="resorcinol" precipitantCode="YUL4LO94HK"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="salicylic acid" precipitantCode="O414PZ4LPZ"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="sulfur" precipitantCode="70FD1KFU70"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>