<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Triacin-C" setid="6cc01bb7-27c5-43c4-8e21-64ecbfbb4fa2">
<Text><Section name="Boxed Warning section" id="34066-1">
WARNING: Death Related to Ultra-Rapid Metabolism of Codeine to Morphine Respiratory depression and death have occurred in children who received codeine following tonsillectomy and/or adenoidectomy and had evidence of being ultra-rapid metabolizers of codeine due to a CYP2D6 polymorphism (see WARNINGS - Codeine Phosphate - Death Related to Ultra-Rapid Metabolism of Codeine to Morphine ).</Section>
<Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
Triacin-C is contraindicated under the following conditions: Codeine sulfate is contraindicated for postoperative pain management in children who have undergone tonsillectomy and/or adenoidectomy. This drug should not be used in newborn or premature infants. Antihistamines should not be used to treat lower respiratory tract symptoms, including asthma. Hypersensitivity To (1) codeine phosphate or other narcotics; (2) triprolidine hydrochloride or other antihistamines of similar chemical structure; or (3) sympathomimetic amines, including pseudoephedrine. Sympathomimetic amines are contraindicated in patients with severe hypertension, severe coronary artery disease and in patients on monoamine oxidase (MAO) inhibitor therapy (see PRECAUTIONS - Drug Interactions ) .</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
DOSAGE SHOULD BE INDIVIDUALIZED ACCORDING TO THE NEEDS AND RESPONSE OF THE PATIENT. Usual Dose: Teaspoonfuls (5 mL) Adults and children 12 years and older 2 teaspoonfuls (10 mL) every 4 to 6 hours, not to exceed 8 teaspoonfuls (40 mL) in 24 hours. Children 6 to under 12 years 1 teaspoonful (5 mL) every 4 to 6 hours, not to exceed 4 teaspoonfuls (20 mL) in 24 hours. Children 2 to under 6 years ½ teaspoonful (2.5 mL) every 4 to 6 hours, not to exceed 2 teaspoonfuls</Section>
<Section name="PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="42232-9">
General : Triacin-C should be prescribed with caution for certain special-risk patients, such as the elderly or debilitated, and for those with severe impairment of renal or hepatic function, gallbladder disease or gallstones, respiratory impairment, cardiac arrhythmias, history of bronchial asthma, prostatic hypertrophy or urethral stricture, and in patients known to be taking other antitussive, antihistamine or decongestant medications. Patients’ self-medication habits should be investigated to determine their use of such medications. Triacin-C is intended for short-term use only. Information For Patients : Advise patients that some people have a genetic variation that results in codeine changing into morphine more rapidly and completely than other people. Most people are unaware of whether they are an ultra-rapid codeine metabolizer or not. These higher-than-normal levels of morphine in the blood may lead to life-threatening or fatal respiratory depression or signs of overdose such as extreme sleepiness, confusion, or shallow breathing. Children with this genetic variation who were prescribed codeine after tonsillectomy and/or adenoidectomy for obstructive sleep apnea may be at greatest risk based on reports of several deaths in this population due to respiratory depression. As a result, codeine is contraindicated in all children who undergo tonsillectomy and/or adenoidectomy. Advise caregivers of children receiving codeine for other reasons to monitor for signs of respiratory depression (see WARNINGS – Death Related to Ultra-Rapid metabolism of Codeine to Morphine). 1. Patients should be warned about engaging in activities requiring mental alertness such as driving a car, operating dangerous machinery or hazardous appliances. 2. Patients with a history of glaucoma, peptic ulcer, urinary retention or pregnancy should be cautioned before starting this product. 3. Patients should be told not to take alcohol, sleeping pills, sedatives or tranquilizers while taking Triacin-C. 4. Antihistamines may cause dizziness, drowsiness, dry mouth, blurred vision, weakness, nausea, headache or nervousness in some patients. 5. Patients should be told to store this medicine in a tightly closed container in a dry, cool place away from heat or direct sunlight and out of the reach of children. 6. Nursing Mothers – refer to following section titled “Nursing Mothers.” (see WARNINGS – Death Related to Ultra-Rapid Metabolism of Codeine to Morphine ). This product should not be used by persons intolerant to sympathomimetics used for the relief of nasal or sinus congestion. Such drugs include ephedrine, epinephrine, phenylephrine and phenylpropanolamine. Symptoms of intolerance include drowsiness, dizziness, weakness, difficulty in breathing, tenseness, muscle tremors or palpitations. Codeine may be habit-forming when used over long periods or in high doses. Patients should take the drug only for as long, in the amounts, and as frequently as prescribed. Drug Interactions : Triacin-C may enhance the effects of: 1. Monoamine oxidase (MAO) inhibitors; 2. other narcotic analgesics, alcohol, general anesthetics, tranquilizers, sedative-hypnotics, surgical skeletal muscle relaxants, or other CNS depressants, by causing increased CNS depression. This product may diminish the antihypertensive effects of guanethidine, bethanidine, methyldopa and reserpine. Drug/Laboratory Test Interactions : Codeine: Narcotic administration may increase serum amylase levels. Carcinogenesis, Mutagenesis, Impairment Of Fertility : No adequate studies have been conducted in animals to determine whether the components of Triacin-C have a potential for carcinogenesis, mutagenesis or impairment of fertility. Pregnancy : Teratogenic Effects – Pregnancy category C. Animal reproduction studies have not been conducted with Triacin-C. It is also not known whether this product can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman or can affect reproduction capacity. This product should be given to a pregnant woman only if clearly needed. Teratology studies have been conducted with the three ingredients of Triacin-C. Pseudoephedrine studies were conducted in rats at doses up to 150 times the human dose; triprolidine was studied in rats and rabbits at doses up to 125 times the human dose, and codeine studies were conducted in rats and rabbits at doses up to 150 times the human dose. No evidence of teratogenic harm to the fetus was revealed in any of these studies. However, overt signs of toxicity were observed in the dams which received pseudoephedrine. This was reflected in reduced average weight and length and rate of skeletal ossification in their fetuses. Nursing Mothers: The components of Triacin-C are excreted in breast milk in small amounts, but the significance of their effects on nursing infants is not known. Because of the potential for serious adverse reactions in nursing infants from maternal ingestion of this product, a decision should be made whether to discontinue nursing or to discontinue the drug, taking into account the importance of the drug to the mother. (see WARNINGS – Death Related to Ultra-Rapid Metabolism of Codeine to Morphine ). Pediatric Use: Respiratory depression and death have occurred in children with obstructive sleep apnea who received codeine in the post-operative period following tonsillectomy and/or adenoidectomy and had evidence of being ultra-rapid metabolizers of codeine (i.e., multiple copies of the gene for cytochrome P450 isoenzyme CYP2D6 or high morphine concentrations). These children may be particularly sensitive to the respiratory depressant effects of codeine that has been rapidly metabolized to morphine. Codeine is contraindicated for post-operative pain management in these patients (see WARNINGS - Death Related to Ultra-Rapid Metabolism of Codeine to Morphine and CONTRAINDICATIONS) As in adults, the combination of an antihistamine, sympathomimetic amine and codeine can elicit either mild stimulation or mild sedation in pediatric patients. In pediatric patients particularly, the ingredients in this drug product in overdosage may produce hallucinations, convulsions and death. Symptoms of toxicity in pediatric patients may include fixed dilated pupils, flushed face, dry mouth, fever, excitation, hallucinations, ataxia, incoordination, athetosis, tonic clonic convulsions and postictal depression, (see CONTRAINDICATIONS and OVERDOSAGE sections). Use In Elderly (Approximately 60 Years Or Older): The ingredients in Triacin-C are more likely to cause adverse reactions in elderly patients.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS SECTION" id="34071-1">
Respiratory depression and death have occurred in children who received codeine in the post­operative period following tonsillectomy and/or adenoidectomy and had evidence of being ultra­rapid metabolizers of codeine (i.e., multiple copies of the gene for cytochrome P450 isoenzyme 2D6 or high morphine concentrations). Deaths have also occurred in nursing infants who were exposed to high levels of morphine in breast milk because their mothers were ultra-rapid metabolizers of codeine (see PRECAUTIONS-Nursing Mothers ). Some individuals may be ultra-rapid metabolizers because of a specific CYP2D6 genotype (gene duplications denoted as *1/*1xN or *1/*2xN). The prevalence of this CYP2D6 phenotype varies widely and has been estimated at 0.5 to 1% in Chinese and Japanese, 0.5 to 1% in Hispanics, 1 to 10% in Caucasians, 3% in African Americans, and 16 to 28% in North Africans, Ethiopians, and Arabs. Data are not available for other ethnic groups. These individuals convert codeine into its active metabolite, morphine, more rapidly and completely than other people. This rapid conversion results in higher than expected serum morphine levels. Even at labeled dosage regimens, individuals who are ultra-rapid metabolizers may have life-threatening or fatal respiratory depression or experience signs of overdose (such as extreme sleepiness, confusion, or shallow breathing) (see OVERDOSAGE ). Children with obstructive sleep apnea who are treated with codeine for post-tonsillectomy and/or adenoidectomy pain may be particularly sensitive to the respiratory depressant effects of codeine that has been rapidly metabolized to morphine. Codeine is contraindicated for post-operative pain management in all pediatric patients undergoing tonsillectomy and/or adenoidectomy (see CONTRAINDICATIONS ). When prescribing codeine-containing drugs, healthcare providers should choose the lowest effective dose for the shortest period of time and inform patients and caregivers about these risks and the signs of morphine overdose. Triacin-C should be used with considerable caution in patients with increased intraocular pressure (narrow angle glaucoma), stenosing peptic ulcer, pyloroduodenal obstruction, symptomatic prostatic hypertrophy, bladder neck obstruction, hypertension, diabetes mellitus, ischemic heart disease, and hyperthyroidism. In the presence of head injury or other intracranial lesions, the respiratory depressant effects of codeine and other narcotics may be markedly enhanced, as well as their capacity for elevating cerebrospinal fluid pressure. Narcotics also produce other CNS depressant effects, such as drowsiness, that may further obscure the clinical course of patients with head injuries. Codeine or other narcotics may obscure signs on which to judge the diagnosis or clinical course of patients with acute abdominal conditions.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Codeine: Codeine probably exerts its antitussive activity by depressing the medullary (brain) cough center, thereby raising its threshold for incoming cough impulses. Codeine is readily absorbed from the gastrointestinal tract, with a therapeutic dose reaching peak antitussive effectiveness in about 2 hours and persisting for 4 to 6 hours. Codeine is rapidly distributed from blood to body tissues and taken up preferentially by parenchymatous organs such as liver, spleen and kidney. It passes the blood brain barrier and is found in fetal tissue and breast milk. The drug is not bound by plasma proteins nor is it accumulated in body tissues. Codeine is metabolized in the liver to morphine and norcodeine, each representing about 10 percent of the administered codeine dose. About 90 percent of the dose is excreted within 24 hours, primarily through the kidneys. Urinary excretion products are free and glucuronide-conjugated codeine (about 70%), free and conjugated norcodeine (about 10%), free and conjugated morphine (about 10%), normorphine (under 4%) and hydrocodone (&amp;lt;1%). The remainder of the dose appears in the feces. Triprolidine: Antihistamines such as triprolidine hydrochloride act as antagonists of the H1 histamine receptor. Consequently, they prevent histamine from eliciting typical immediate hypersensitivity responses in the nose, eyes, lungs and skin. Animal distribution studies have shown localization of triprolidine in lung, spleen and kidney tissue. Liver microsome studies have revealed the presence of several metabolites with an oxidized product of the toluene methyl group predominating. Pseudoephedrine: Pseudoephedrine acts as an indirect sympathomimetic agent by stimulating sympathetic (adrenergic) nerve endings to release norepinephrine. Norepinephrine in turn stimulates alpha and beta receptors throughout the body. The action of pseudoephedrine hydrochloride is apparently more specific for the blood vessels of the upper respiratory tract and less specific for the blood vessels of the systemic circulation. The vasoconstriction elicited at these sites results in the shrinkage of swollen tissues in the sinuses and nasal passages. Pseudoephedrine is rapidly and almost completely absorbed from the gastrointestinal tract. Considerable variation in half-life has been observed (from about 4½ to 10 hours), which is attributed to individual differences in absorption and excretion. Excretion rates are also altered by urine pH, increasing with acidification and decreasing with alkalinization. As a result, mean half-life falls to about 4 hours at pH 5 and increases to 12 to 13 hours at pH 8. After administration of a 60 mg tablet, 87 to 96% of the pseudoephedrine is cleared from the body within 24 hours. The drug is distributed to body tissues and fluids, including fetal tissue, breast milk and the central nervous system (CNS). About 55 to 75% of an administered dose is excreted unchanged in the urine; the remainder is apparently metabolized in the liver to inactive compounds by N-demethylation, parahydroxylation and oxidative deamination.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="10653" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>WARNING: Death Related to Ultra-Rapid Metabolism of Codeine to Morphine Respiratory depression and death have occurred in children who received codeine following tonsillectomy and/or adenoidectomy and had evidence of being ultra-rapid metabolizers of codeine due to a CYP2D6 polymorphism.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10654" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Triacin-C is contraindicated under the following conditions: Codeine sulfate is contraindicated for postoperative pain management in children who have undergone tonsillectomy and/or adenoidectomy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10655" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>This drug should not be used in newborn or premature infants.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10656" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Antihistamines should not be used to treat lower respiratory tract symptoms, including asthma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10657" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Hypersensitivity To (1) codeine phosphate or other narcotics; (2) triprolidine hydrochloride or other antihistamines of similar chemical structure; or (3) sympathomimetic amines, including pseudoephedrine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10658" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Sympathomimetic amines are contraindicated in patients with severe hypertension, severe coronary artery disease and in patients on monoamine oxidase (MAO) inhibitor therapy.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M5" type="Trigger" span="27 15" str="contraindicated"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="150 3;155 9" str="MAO | inhibitor" code="N0000000184"/>
<Mention id="M4" type="Precipitant" span="131 33" str="monoamine oxidase (MAO) inhibitor" code="N0000000184"/>
<Mention id="M6" type="Precipitant" span="131 17;155 9" str="monoamine oxidase | inhibitor" code="N0000000184 | N0000175744"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M5" precipitant="M2"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M5" precipitant="M4"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M5" precipitant="M6"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10659" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>DOSAGE SHOULD BE INDIVIDUALIZED ACCORDING TO THE NEEDS AND RESPONSE OF THE PATIENT.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10660" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Usual Dose: Teaspoonfuls (5 mL) Adults and children 12 years and older 2 teaspoonfuls (10 mL) every 4 to 6 hours, not to exceed 8 teaspoonfuls (40 mL) in 24 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10661" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Children 6 to under 12 years 1 teaspoonful (5 mL) every 4 to 6 hours, not to exceed 4 teaspoonfuls (20 mL) in 24 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10662" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Children 2 to under 6 years ½ teaspoonful (2.5 mL) every 4 to 6 hours, not to exceed 2 teaspoonfuls</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10663" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>General: Triacin-C should be prescribed with caution for certain special-risk patients, such as the elderly or debilitated, and for those with severe impairment of renal or hepatic function, gallbladder disease or gallstones, respiratory impairment, cardiac arrhythmias, history of bronchial asthma, prostatic hypertrophy or urethral stricture, and in patients known to be taking other antitussive, antihistamine or decongestant medications.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M11" type="Trigger" span="45 7" str="caution"/>
<Mention id="M8" type="Precipitant" span="399 13" str="antihistamine" code="N0000175750"/>
<Mention id="M10" type="Precipitant" span="386 11" str="antitussive" code="N0000178319"/>
<Mention id="M12" type="Precipitant" span="416 12" str="decongestant" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M11" precipitant="M8"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M11" precipitant="M10"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M11" precipitant="M12"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10664" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Patients’ self-medication habits should be investigated to determine their use of such medications.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10665" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Triacin-C is intended for short-term use only.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10666" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Information For Patients:Advise patients that some people have a genetic variation that results in codeine changing into morphine more rapidly and completely than other people.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10667" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Most people are unaware of whether they are an ultra-rapid codeine metabolizer or not.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10668" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>These higher-than-normal levels of morphine in the blood may lead to life-threatening or fatal respiratory depression or signs of overdose such as extreme sleepiness, confusion, or shallow breathing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10669" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Children with this genetic variation who were prescribed codeine after tonsillectomy and/or adenoidectomy for obstructive sleep apnea may be at greatest risk based on reports of several deaths in this population due to respiratory depression.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10670" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>As a result, codeine is contraindicated in all children who undergo tonsillectomy and/or adenoidectomy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10671" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Advise caregivers of children receiving codeine for other reasons to monitor for signs of respiratory depression.1.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10672" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Patients should be warned about engaging in activities requiring mental alertness such as driving a car, operating dangerous machinery or hazardous appliances.2.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10673" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Patients with a history of glaucoma, peptic ulcer, urinary retention or pregnancy should be cautioned before starting this product.3.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10674" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Patients should be told not to take alcohol, sleeping pills, sedatives or tranquilizers while taking Triacin-C.4.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M19" type="Trigger" span="24 11" str="not to take"/>
<Mention id="M14" type="Precipitant" span="36 7" str="alcohol" code="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M"/>
<Mention id="M16" type="Precipitant" span="61 9" str="sedatives" code="N0000029143 | N0000193842"/>
<Mention id="M18" type="Precipitant" span="45 14" str="sleeping pills" code="N0000193842"/>
<Mention id="M20" type="Precipitant" span="74 13" str="tranquilizers" code="N0000029143 | N0000193842"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M19" precipitant="M14"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M19" precipitant="M16"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M19" precipitant="M18"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M19" precipitant="M20"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10675" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Antihistamines may cause dizziness, drowsiness, dry mouth, blurred vision, weakness, nausea, headache or nervousness in some patients.5.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10676" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Patients should be told to store this medicine in a tightly closed container in a dry, cool place away from heat or direct sunlight and out of the reach of children.6.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10677" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Nursing Mothers – refer to following section titled “Nursing Mothers.”.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10678" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>This product should not be used by persons intolerant to sympathomimetics used for the relief of nasal or sinus congestion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10679" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Such drugs include ephedrine, epinephrine, phenylephrine and phenylpropanolamine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10680" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Symptoms of intolerance include drowsiness, dizziness, weakness, difficulty in breathing, tenseness, muscle tremors or palpitations.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10681" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Codeine may be habit-forming when used over long periods or in high doses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10682" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Patients should take the drug only for as long, in the amounts, and as frequently as prescribed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10683" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Drug Interactions: Triacin-C may enhance the effects of: 1.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10684" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Monoamine oxidase (MAO) inhibitors;2. other narcotic analgesics, alcohol, general anesthetics, tranquilizers, sedative-hypnotics, surgical skeletal muscle relaxants, or other CNS depressants, by causing increased CNS depression.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M48" type="Trigger" span="195 7" str="causing"/>
<Mention id="M22" type="Precipitant" span="65 7" str="alcohol" code="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M"/>
<Mention id="M50" type="SpecificInteraction" span="203 24" str="increased CNS depression" code="418072004: Central nervous system depression (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M25" type="Precipitant" span="175 15" str="CNS depressants" code="N0000175758"/>
<Mention id="M28" type="Precipitant" span="74 19" str="general anesthetics" code="N0000175681"/>
<Mention id="M31" type="Precipitant" span="19 3;24 10" str="MAO | inhibitors" code="N0000000184 | N0000175744"/>
<Mention id="M34" type="Precipitant" span="0 34" str="Monoamine oxidase (MAO) inhibitors" code="N0000000184 | N0000175744"/>
<Mention id="M37" type="Precipitant" span="0 17;24 10" str="Monoamine oxidase | inhibitors" code="N0000000184 | N0000175744"/>
<Mention id="M40" type="Precipitant" span="44 19" str="narcotic analgesics" code="N0000175440"/>
<Mention id="M43" type="Precipitant" span="110 18" str="sedative-hypnotics" code="n0000029143 | N0000193842"/>
<Mention id="M46" type="Precipitant" span="130 34" str="surgical skeletal muscle relaxants" code="N0000175738"/>
<Mention id="M49" type="Precipitant" span="95 13" str="tranquilizers" code="N0000029143 | N0000193842"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M48" precipitant="M22" effect="M50" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M48" precipitant="M25" effect="M50" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M48" precipitant="M28" effect="M50" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M48" precipitant="M31" effect="M50" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M48" precipitant="M34" effect="M50" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M48" precipitant="M37" effect="M50" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M48" precipitant="M40" effect="M50" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M48" precipitant="M43" effect="M50" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M48" precipitant="M46" effect="M50" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M48" precipitant="M49" effect="M50" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10685" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>This product may diminish the antihypertensive effects of guanethidine, bethanidine, methyldopa and reserpine.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M60" type="Trigger" span="17 8;47 7" str="diminish | effects"/>
<Mention id="M52" type="Precipitant" span="72 11" str="bethanidine" code="W8S3YM7AUU"/>
<Mention id="M62" type="SpecificInteraction" span="17 37" str="diminish the antihypertensive effects" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M55" type="Precipitant" span="58 12" str="guanethidine" code="ZTI6C33Q2Q"/>
<Mention id="M58" type="Precipitant" span="85 10" str="methyldopa" code="56LH93261Y"/>
<Mention id="M61" type="Precipitant" span="100 9" str="reserpine" code="8B1QWR724A"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M60" precipitant="M52" effect="M62" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M60" precipitant="M55" effect="M62" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M60" precipitant="M58" effect="M62" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M60" precipitant="M61" effect="M62" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10686" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Drug/Laboratory Test Interactions: Codeine: Narcotic administration may increase serum amylase levels.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10687" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Carcinogenesis, Mutagenesis, Impairment Of Fertility: No adequate studies have been conducted in animals to determine whether the components of Triacin-C have a potential for carcinogenesis, mutagenesis or impairment of fertility.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10688" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Pregnancy: Teratogenic Effects – Pregnancy category C. Animal reproduction studies have not been conducted with Triacin-C.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10689" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>It is also not known whether this product can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman or can affect reproduction capacity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10690" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>This product should be given to a pregnant woman only if clearly needed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10691" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Teratology studies have been conducted with the three ingredients of Triacin-C. Pseudoephedrine studies were conducted in rats at doses up to 150 times the human dose; triprolidine was studied in rats and rabbits at doses up to 125 times the human dose, and codeine studies were conducted in rats and rabbits at doses up to 150 times the human dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10692" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>No evidence of teratogenic harm to the fetus was revealed in any of these studies.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10693" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>However, overt signs of toxicity were observed in the dams which received pseudoephedrine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10694" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>This was reflected in reduced average weight and length and rate of skeletal ossification in their fetuses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10695" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Nursing Mothers: The components of Triacin-C are excreted in breast milk in small amounts, but the significance of their effects on nursing infants is not known.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10696" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because of the potential for serious adverse reactions in nursing infants from maternal ingestion of this product, a decision should be made whether to discontinue nursing or to discontinue the drug, taking into account the importance of the drug to the mother.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10697" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Pediatric Use: Respiratory depression and death have occurred in children with obstructive sleep apnea who received codeine in the post-operative period following tonsillectomy and/or adenoidectomy and had evidence of being ultra-rapid metabolizers of codeine (i.e., multiple copies of the gene for cytochrome P450 isoenzyme CYP2D6 or high morphine concentrations).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10698" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>These children may be particularly sensitive to the respiratory depressant effects of codeine that has been rapidly metabolized to morphine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10699" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Codeine is contraindicated for post-operative pain management in these patients As in adults, the combination of an antihistamine, sympathomimetic amine and codeine can elicit either mild stimulation or mild sedation in pediatric patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10700" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In pediatric patients particularly, the ingredients in this drug product in overdosage may produce hallucinations, convulsions and death.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10701" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Symptoms of toxicity in pediatric patients may include fixed dilated pupils, flushed face, dry mouth, fever, excitation, hallucinations, ataxia, incoordination, athetosis, tonic clonic convulsions and postictal depression,.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10702" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Use In Elderly (Approximately 60 Years Or Older): The ingredients in Triacin-C are more likely to cause adverse reactions in elderly patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10703" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Respiratory depression and death have occurred in children who received codeine in the post­operative period following tonsillectomy and/or adenoidectomy and had evidence of being ultra­rapid metabolizers of codeine (i.e., multiple copies of the gene for cytochrome P450 isoenzyme 2D6 or high morphine concentrations).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10704" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Deaths have also occurred in nursing infants who were exposed to high levels of morphine in breast milk because their mothers were ultra-rapid metabolizers of codeine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10705" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Some individuals may be ultra-rapid metabolizers because of a specific CYP2D6 genotype (gene duplications denoted as *1/*1xN or *1/*2xN).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10706" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The prevalence of this CYP2D6 phenotype varies widely and has been estimated at 0.5 to 1% in Chinese and Japanese, 0.5 to 1% in Hispanics, 1 to 10% in Caucasians, 3% in African Americans, and 16 to 28% in North Africans, Ethiopians, and Arabs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10707" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Data are not available for other ethnic groups.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10708" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>These individuals convert codeine into its active metabolite, morphine, more rapidly and completely than other people.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10709" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>This rapid conversion results in higher than expected serum morphine levels.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10710" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Even at labeled dosage regimens, individuals who are ultra-rapid metabolizers may have life-threatening or fatal respiratory depression or experience signs of overdose (such as extreme sleepiness, confusion, or shallow breathing).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10711" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Children with obstructive sleep apnea who are treated with codeine for post-tonsillectomy and/or adenoidectomy pain may be particularly sensitive to the respiratory depressant effects of codeine that has been rapidly metabolized to morphine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10712" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Codeine is contraindicated for post-operative pain management in all pediatric patients undergoing tonsillectomy and/or adenoidectomy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10713" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>When prescribing codeine-containing drugs, healthcare providers should choose the lowest effective dose for the shortest period of time and inform patients and caregivers about these risks and the signs of morphine overdose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10714" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Triacin-C should be used with considerable caution in patients with increased intraocular pressure (narrow angle glaucoma), stenosing peptic ulcer, pyloroduodenal obstruction, symptomatic prostatic hypertrophy, bladder neck obstruction, hypertension, diabetes mellitus, ischemic heart disease, and hyperthyroidism.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10715" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>In the presence of head injury or other intracranial lesions, the respiratory depressant effects of codeine and other narcotics may be markedly enhanced, as well as their capacity for elevating cerebrospinal fluid pressure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10716" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Narcotics also produce other CNS depressant effects, such as drowsiness, that may further obscure the clinical course of patients with head injuries.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10717" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Codeine or other narcotics may obscure signs on which to judge the diagnosis or clinical course of patients with acute abdominal conditions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10718" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Codeine: Codeine probably exerts its antitussive activity by depressing the medullary (brain) cough center, thereby raising its threshold for incoming cough impulses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10719" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Codeine is readily absorbed from the gastrointestinal tract, with a therapeutic dose reaching peak antitussive effectiveness in about 2 hours and persisting for 4 to 6 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10720" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Codeine is rapidly distributed from blood to body tissues and taken up preferentially by parenchymatous organs such as liver, spleen and kidney.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10721" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>It passes the blood brain barrier and is found in fetal tissue and breast milk.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10722" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The drug is not bound by plasma proteins nor is it accumulated in body tissues.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10723" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Codeine is metabolized in the liver to morphine and norcodeine, each representing about 10 percent of the administered codeine dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10724" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>About 90 percent of the dose is excreted within 24 hours, primarily through the kidneys.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10725" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Urinary excretion products are free and glucuronide-conjugated codeine (about 70%), free and conjugated norcodeine (about 10%), free and conjugated morphine (about 10%), normorphine (under 4%) and hydrocodone (&lt;1%).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10726" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The remainder of the dose appears in the feces.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10727" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Triprolidine: Antihistamines such as triprolidine hydrochloride act as antagonists of the H1 histamine receptor.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10728" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Consequently, they prevent histamine from eliciting typical immediate hypersensitivity responses in the nose, eyes, lungs and skin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10729" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Animal distribution studies have shown localization of triprolidine in lung, spleen and kidney tissue.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10730" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Liver microsome studies have revealed the presence of several metabolites with an oxidized product of the toluene methyl group predominating.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10731" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Pseudoephedrine: Pseudoephedrine acts as an indirect sympathomimetic agent by stimulating sympathetic (adrenergic) nerve endings to release norepinephrine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10732" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Norepinephrine in turn stimulates alpha and beta receptors throughout the body.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10733" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The action of pseudoephedrine hydrochloride is apparently more specific for the blood vessels of the upper respiratory tract and less specific for the blood vessels of the systemic circulation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10734" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The vasoconstriction elicited at these sites results in the shrinkage of swollen tissues in the sinuses and nasal passages.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10735" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Pseudoephedrine is rapidly and almost completely absorbed from the gastrointestinal tract.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10736" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Considerable variation in half-life has been observed (from about 4½ to 10 hours), which is attributed to individual differences in absorption and excretion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10737" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Excretion rates are also altered by urine pH, increasing with acidification and decreasing with alkalinization.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10738" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>As a result, mean half-life falls to about 4 hours at pH 5 and increases to 12 to 13 hours at pH 8.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10739" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>After administration of a 60 mg tablet, 87 to 96% of the pseudoephedrine is cleared from the body within 24 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10740" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The drug is distributed to body tissues and fluids, including fetal tissue, breast milk and the central nervous system (CNS).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10741" LabelDrug="Triacin-C" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>About 55 to 75% of an administered dose is excreted unchanged in the urine; the remainder is apparently metabolized in the liver to inactive compounds by N-demethylation, parahydroxylation and oxidative deamination.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="mao | inhibitor" precipitantCode="N0000000184"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="monoamine oxidase (mao) inhibitor" precipitantCode="N0000000184"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="monoamine oxidase | inhibitor" precipitantCode="N0000000184 | N0000175744"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="antihistamine" precipitantCode="N0000175750"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="antitussive" precipitantCode="N0000178319"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="decongestant" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="alcohol" precipitantCode="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M" effect="418072004: Central nervous system depression (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="alcohol" precipitantCode="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="sedatives" precipitantCode="N0000029143 | N0000193842"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="sleeping pills" precipitantCode="N0000193842"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="tranquilizers" precipitantCode="N0000029143 | N0000193842" effect="418072004: Central nervous system depression (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="tranquilizers" precipitantCode="N0000029143 | N0000193842"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cns depressants" precipitantCode="N0000175758" effect="418072004: Central nervous system depression (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="general anesthetics" precipitantCode="N0000175681" effect="418072004: Central nervous system depression (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="mao | inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000000184 | N0000175744" effect="418072004: Central nervous system depression (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="monoamine oxidase (mao) inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000000184 | N0000175744" effect="418072004: Central nervous system depression (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="monoamine oxidase | inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000000184 | N0000175744" effect="418072004: Central nervous system depression (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="narcotic analgesics" precipitantCode="N0000175440" effect="418072004: Central nervous system depression (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sedative-hypnotics" precipitantCode="n0000029143 | N0000193842" effect="418072004: Central nervous system depression (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="surgical skeletal muscle relaxants" precipitantCode="N0000175738" effect="418072004: Central nervous system depression (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="bethanidine" precipitantCode="W8S3YM7AUU" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="guanethidine" precipitantCode="ZTI6C33Q2Q" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="methyldopa" precipitantCode="56LH93261Y" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="reserpine" precipitantCode="8B1QWR724A" effect="NO MAP"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>