<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Neomycin Sulfate" setid="777dbfab-f83e-4738-ae1e-78619a9f82a7">
<Text><Section name="BOXED WARNING SECTION" id="34066-1">
SYSTEMIC ABSORPTION OF NEOMYCIN OCCURS FOLLOWING ORAL ADMINISTRATION AND TOXIC REACTIONS MAY OCCUR. Patients treated with neomycin should be under close clinical observation because of the potential toxicity associated with their use. NEUROTOXICITY (INCLUDING OTOTOXICITY) AND NEPHROTOXICITY FOLLOWING THE ORAL USE OF NEOMYCIN SULFATE HAVE BEEN REPORTED, EVEN WHEN USED IN RECOMMENDED DOSES. THE POTENTIAL FOR NEPHROTOXICITY, PERMANENT BILATERAL AUDITORY OTOTOXICITY AND SOMETIMES VESTIBULAR TOXICITY IS PRESENT IN PATIENTS WITH NORMAL RENAL FUNCTION WHEN TREATED WITH HIGHER DOSES OF NEOMYCIN AND/OR FOR LONGER PERIODS THAN RECOMMENDED. Serial, vestibular and audiometric tests, as well as tests of renal function, should be performed (especially in high-risk patients). THE RISK OF NEPHROTOXICITY AND OTOTOXICITY IS GREATER IN PATIENTS WITH IMPAIRED RENAL FUNCTION. Ototoxicity is often delayed in onset and patients developing cochlear damage will not have symptoms during therapy to warn them of developing eighth nerve destruction and total or partial deafness may occur long after neomycin has been discontinued. Neuromuscular blockage and respiratory paralysis have been reported following the oral use of neomycin. The possibility of the occurrence of neuromuscular blockage and respiratory paralysis should be considered if neomycin is administered, especially to patients receiving anesthetics, neuromuscular blocking agents such as tubocurarine, succinylcholine, decamethonium, or in patients receiving massive transfusions of citrate anticoagulated blood. If blockage occurs, calcium salts may reverse these phenomena but mechanical respiratory assistance may be necessary. Concurrent and/or sequential systemic, oral or topical use of other aminoglycosides, including paromomycin and other potentially nephrotoxic and/or neurotoxic drugs such as bacitracin, cisplatin, vancomycin, amphotericin B, polymyxin B, colistin and viomycin, should be avoided because the toxicity may be additive. Other factors which increase the risk of toxicity are advanced age and dehydration. The concurrent use of neomycin with potent diuretics such as ethacrynic acid or furosemide should be avoided, since certain diuretics by themselves may cause ototoxicity. In addition, when administered intravenously, diuretics may enhance neomycin toxicity by altering the antibiotic concentration in serum and tissue.</Section>
<Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
Neomycin sulfate oral preparations are contraindicated in the presence of intestinal obstruction and in individuals with a history of hypersensitivity to the drug. Patients with a history of hypersensitivity or serious toxic reaction to other aminoglycosides may have a cross-sensitivity to neomycin. Neomycin sulfate oral preparations are contraindicated in patients with inflammatory or ulcerative gastrointestinal disease because of the potential for enhanced gastrointestinal absorption of neomycin.</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
To minimize the risk of toxicity, use the lowest possible dose and the shortest possible treatment period to control the condition. Treatment for periods longer than two weeks is not recommended. For use as an adjunct in the management of hepatic coma, the recommended dose is 4 to 12 grams per day given in the following regimen: Withdraw protein from diet. Avoid use of diuretic agents. Give supportive therapy, including blood products, as indicated. Give neomycin sulfate tablets in doses of 4 to 12 grams of neomycin sulfate per day (eight to 24 tablets) in divided doses. Treatment should be continued over a period of five to six days, during which time protein should be returned incrementally to the diet. If less potentially toxic drugs cannot be used for chronic hepatic insufficiency, neomycin in doses of up to four grams daily (eight tablets per day) may be necessary. The risk for the development of neomycin-induced toxicity progressively increases when treatment must be extended to preserve the life of a patient with hepatic encephalopathy who has failed to fully respond. Frequent periodic monitoring of these patients to ascertain the presence of drug toxicity is mandatory (see PRECAUTIONS ). Also, neomycin serum concentrations should be monitored to avoid potentially toxic levels. The benefits to the patient should be weighed against the risks of nephrotoxicity, permanent ototoxicity and neuromuscular blockade following the accumulation of neomycin in the tissues. Listed below is an example of a recommended bowel preparation regimen. A proposed surgery time of 8:00 a.m. has been used. Pre-op Day 3: Minimum residue or clear liquid diet. Bisacodyl, 1 tablet orally at 6:00 p.m. Pre-op Day 2: Minimum residue or clear liquid diet. Magnesium sulfate, 30 mL, 50% solution (15 g) orally at 10:00 a.m., 2:00 p.m., and 6:00 p.m. Enema at 7:00 p.m. and 8:00 p.m. Pre-op Day 1: Clear liquid diet. Supplemental (IV) fluids as needed. Magnesium sulfate, 30 mL, 50% solution (15 g) orally at 10:00 a.m., and 2:00 p.m. Neomycin sulfate (1 g) and erythromycin base (1 g) orally at 1:00 p.m., 2:00 p.m. and 11:00 p.m. No enema. Day of Operation: Patient evacuates rectum at 6:30 a.m. for scheduled operation at 8:00 a.m.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
Caution should be taken in concurrent or serial use of other neurotoxic and/or nephrotoxic drugs because of possible enhancement of the nephrotoxicity and/or ototoxicity of neomycin (see boxed WARNINGS ). Caution should also be taken in concurrent or serial use of other amino-glycosides and polymyxins because they may enhance neomycin’s nephrotoxicity and/or ototoxicity and potentiate neomycin sulfate’s neuromuscular blocking effects. Oral neomycin inhibits the gastrointestinal absorption of penicillin V, oral vitamin B-12, methotrexate and 5-fluorouracil. The gastrointestinal absorption of digoxin also appears to be inhibited. Therefore, digoxin serum levels should be monitored. Oral neomycin sulfate may enhance the effect of coumarin in anticoagulants by decreasing vitamin K availability.</Section>
<Section name="PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="42232-9">
Prescribing Neomycin Sulfate Tablets USP in the absence of a proven or strongly suspected bacterial infection or a prophylactic indication is unlikely to provide benefit to the patient and increases the risk of the development of drug-resistant bacteria. As with other antibiotics, use of oral neomycin may result in overgrowth of nonsusceptible organisms, particularly fungi. If this occurs, appropriate therapy should be instituted. Neomycin is quickly and almost totally absorbed from body surfaces (except the urinary bladder) after local irrigation and when applied topically in association with surgical procedures. Delayed-onset irreversible deafness, renal failure and death due to neuromuscular blockade (regardless of the status of renal function) have been reported following irrigation of both small and large surgical fields with minute quantities of neomycin. Cross-allergenicity among amino-glycosides has been demonstrated. Aminoglycosides should be used with caution in patients with muscular disorders such as myasthenia gravis or parkinsonism since these drugs may aggravate muscle weakness because of their potential curare-like effect on the neuromuscular junction. Small amounts of orally administered neomycin are absorbed through intact intestinal mucosa. There have been many reports in the literature of nephrotoxicity and/or ototoxicity with oral use of neomycin. If renal insufficiency develops during oral therapy, consideration should be given to reducing the drug dosage or discontinuing therapy. An oral neomycin dose of 12 grams per day produces a malabsorption syndrome for a variety of substances, including fat, nitrogen, cholesterol, carotene, glucose, xylose, lactose, sodium, calcium, cyanocobalamin and iron. Orally administered neomycin increases fecal bile acid excretion and reduces intestinal lactase activity. Patients should be counseled that antibacterial drugs including Neomycin Sulfate Tablets USP should only be used to treat bacterial infections. They do not treat viral infections (e.g., the common cold). When Neomycin Sulfate Tablets USP are prescribed to treat a bacterial infection, patients should be told that although it is common to feel better early in the course of therapy, the medication should be taken exactly as directed. Skipping doses or not completing the full course of therapy may (1) decrease the effectiveness of the immediate treatment and (2) increase the likelihood that bacteria will develop resistance and will not be treatable by Neomycin Sulfate Tablets USP or other antibacterial drugs in the future. Before administering the drug, patients or members of their families should be informed of possible toxic effects on the eighth nerve. The possibility of acute toxicity increases in premature infants and neonates. Patients with renal insufficiency may develop toxic neomycin blood levels unless doses are properly regulated. If renal insufficiency develops during treatment, the dosage should be reduced or the antibiotic discontinued. To avoid nephrotoxicity and eighth nerve damage associated with high doses and prolonged treatment, the following should be performed prior to and periodically during therapy: urinalysis for increased excretion of protein, decreased specific gravity, casts and cells; renal function tests such as serum creatinine, BUN or creatinine clearance; tests of the vestibulocochlearis nerve (eighth cranial nerve) function. Serial, vestibular and audiometric tests should be performed (especially in high-risk patients). Since elderly patients may have reduced renal function which may not be evident in the results of routine screening tests such as BUN or serum creatinine, a creatinine clearance determination may be more useful. Caution should be taken in concurrent or serial use of other neurotoxic and/or nephrotoxic drugs because of possible enhancement of the nephrotoxicity and/or ototoxicity of neomycin (see boxed WARNINGS ). Caution should also be taken in concurrent or serial use of other amino-glycosides and polymyxins because they may enhance neomycin’s nephrotoxicity and/or ototoxicity and potentiate neomycin sulfate’s neuromuscular blocking effects. Oral neomycin inhibits the gastrointestinal absorption of penicillin V, oral vitamin B-12, methotrexate and 5-fluorouracil. The gastrointestinal absorption of digoxin also appears to be inhibited. Therefore, digoxin serum levels should be monitored. Oral neomycin sulfate may enhance the effect of coumarin in anticoagulants by decreasing vitamin K availability. No long-term animal studies have been performed with neomycin sulfate to evaluate carcinogenic or mutagenic potential or impairment of fertility. (See Warnings section.) It is not known whether neomycin is excreted in human milk, but it has been shown to be excreted in cow milk following a single intramuscular injection. Other aminoglycosides have been shown to be excreted in human milk. Because of the potential for serious adverse reactions from the aminoglycosides in nursing infants, a decision should be made whether to discontinue nursing or to discontinue the drug, taking into account the importance of the drug to the mother. The safety and efficacy of oral neomycin sulfate in patients less than 18 years of age have not been established. If treatment of a patient less than 18 years of age is necessary, neomycin should be used with caution and the period of treatment should not exceed two weeks because of absorption from the gastrointestinal tract.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS SECTION" id="34071-1">
Additional manifestations of neurotoxicity may include numbness, skin tingling, muscle twitching and convulsions. The risk of hearing loss continues after drug withdrawal. Aminoglycosides can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. Aminoglycoside antibiotics cross the placenta and there have been several reports of total irreversible bilateral congenital deafness in children whose mothers received streptomycin during pregnancy. Although serious side effects to fetus or newborn have not been reported in the treatment of pregnant women with other aminoglycosides, the potential for harm exists. Animal reproduction studies of neomycin have not been conducted. If neomycin is used during pregnancy, or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking this drug, the patient should be apprised of the potential hazard to the fetus.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Neomycin sulfate is poorly absorbed from the normal gastrointestinal tract. The small absorbed fraction is rapidly distributed in the tissues and is excreted by the kidney in keeping with the degree of kidney function. The unabsorbed portion of the drug (approximately 97%) is eliminated unchanged in the feces. Growth of most intestinal bacteria is rapidly suppressed following oral administration of neomycin sulfate, with the suppression persisting for 48 to 72 hours. Nonpathogenic yeasts and occasionally resistant strains of Enterobacter aerogenes (formerly Aerobacter aerogenes ) replace the intestinal bacteria. As with other aminoglycosides, the amount of systemically absorbed neomycin transferred to the tissues increases cumulatively with each repeated dose administered until a steady state is achieved. The kidney functions as the primary excretory path as well as the tissue binding site, with the highest concentration found in the renal cortex. With repeated dosings, progressive accumulation also occurs in the inner ear. Release of tissue-bound neomycin occurs slowly over a period of several weeks after dosing has been discontinued. Protein binding studies have shown that the degree of aminoglycoside protein binding is low and, depending upon the methods used for testing, this may be between 0% and 30%. In vitro tests have demonstrated that neomycin is bactericidal and acts by inhibiting the synthesis of protein in susceptible bacterial cells. It is effective primarily against gram-negative bacilli but does have some activity against gram-positive organisms. Neomycin is active in vitro against Escherichia coli and the Klebsiella-Enterobacter group. Neomycin is not active against anaerobic bowel flora. Susceptibility Testing For specific information regarding susceptibility test interpretive criteria and associated test methods and quality control standards recognized by FDA for this drug, please see: https://www.fda.gov/STIC.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="2523" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>SYSTEMIC ABSORPTION OF NEOMYCIN OCCURS FOLLOWING ORAL ADMINISTRATION AND TOXIC REACTIONS MAY OCCUR.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2524" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Patients treated with neomycin should be under close clinical observation because of the potential toxicity associated with their use.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2525" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>NEUROTOXICITY (INCLUDING OTOTOXICITY) AND NEPHROTOXICITY FOLLOWING THE ORAL USE OF NEOMYCIN SULFATE HAVE BEEN REPORTED, EVEN WHEN USED IN RECOMMENDED DOSES.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2526" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>THE POTENTIAL FOR NEPHROTOXICITY, PERMANENT BILATERAL AUDITORY OTOTOXICITY AND SOMETIMES VESTIBULAR TOXICITY IS PRESENT IN PATIENTS WITH NORMAL RENAL FUNCTION WHEN TREATED WITH HIGHER DOSES OF NEOMYCIN AND/OR FOR LONGER PERIODS THAN RECOMMENDED.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2527" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Serial, vestibular and audiometric tests, as well as tests of renal function, should be performed (especially in high-risk patients).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2528" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>THE RISK OF NEPHROTOXICITY AND OTOTOXICITY IS GREATER IN PATIENTS WITH IMPAIRED RENAL FUNCTION.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2529" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Ototoxicity is often delayed in onset and patients developing cochlear damage will not have symptoms during therapy to warn them of developing eighth nerve destruction and total or partial deafness may occur long after neomycin has been discontinued.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2530" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Neuromuscular blockage and respiratory paralysis have been reported following the oral use of neomycin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2531" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>The possibility of the occurrence of neuromuscular blockage and respiratory paralysis should be considered if neomycin is administered, especially to patients receiving anesthetics, neuromuscular blocking agents such as tubocurarine, succinylcholine, decamethonium, or in patients receiving massive transfusions of citrate anticoagulated blood.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M45" type="Trigger" span="4 11" str="possibility "/>
<Mention id="M46" type="Trigger" span="23 10" str=" occurrence"/>
<Mention id="M7" type="Precipitant" span="169 11" str="anesthetics" code="N0000029138 | N0000175681"/>
<Mention id="M44" type="SpecificInteraction" span="37 22" str="neuromuscular blockage" code="397785000: Neuromuscular block problem (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M48" type="SpecificInteraction" span="64 21" str="respiratory paralysis" code="95430002: Respiratory tract paralysis (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M15" type="Precipitant" span="251 13" str="decamethonium" code="C1CG1S3T2W"/>
<Mention id="M23" type="Precipitant" span="291 52" str="massive transfusions of citrate anticoagulated blood" code="N0000193821"/>
<Mention id="M31" type="Precipitant" span="182 29" str="neuromuscular blocking agents" code="N0000175731"/>
<Mention id="M39" type="Precipitant" span="234 15" str="succinylcholine" code="N0000006153 | J2R869A8YF"/>
<Mention id="M47" type="Precipitant" span="220 12" str="tubocurarine" code="N0000006051 | W9YXS298BM"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M45;M46" precipitant="M7" effect="M44" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M45;M46" precipitant="M7" effect="M48" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M45;M46" precipitant="M15" effect="M44" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M45;M46" precipitant="M15" effect="M48" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M45;M46" precipitant="M23" effect="M44" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M45;M46" precipitant="M23" effect="M48" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M45;M46" precipitant="M31" effect="M44" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M45;M46" precipitant="M31" effect="M48" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M45;M46" precipitant="M39" effect="M44" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M45;M46" precipitant="M39" effect="M48" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M45;M46" precipitant="M47" effect="M44" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M45;M46" precipitant="M47" effect="M48" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2532" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>If blockage occurs, calcium salts may reverse these phenomena but mechanical respiratory assistance may be necessary.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2533" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Concurrent and/or sequential systemic, oral or topical use of other aminoglycosides, including paromomycin and other potentially nephrotoxic and/or neurotoxic drugs such as bacitracin, cisplatin, vancomycin, amphotericin B, polymyxin B, colistin and viomycin, should be avoided because the toxicity may be additive.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M79" type="Trigger" span="260 25" str="should be avoided because"/>
<Mention id="M50" type="Precipitant" span="68 15" str="aminoglycosides" code="N0000175929"/>
<Mention id="M81" type="SpecificInteraction" span="290 24" str="toxicity may be additive" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M53" type="Precipitant" span="208 14" str="amphotericin B" code="7XU7A7DROE"/>
<Mention id="M56" type="Precipitant" span="173 10" str="bacitracin" code="58H6RWO52I"/>
<Mention id="M59" type="Precipitant" span="185 9" str="cisplatin" code="N0000007062 | Q20Q21Q62J"/>
<Mention id="M62" type="Precipitant" span="237 8" str="colistin" code="Z67X93HJG1"/>
<Mention id="M65" type="Precipitant" span="95 11" str="paromomycin" code="61JJC8N5ZK"/>
<Mention id="M68" type="Precipitant" span="224 11" str="polymyxin B" code="J2VZ07J96K"/>
<Mention id="M71" type="Precipitant" span="117 11;148 16" str="potentially | neurotoxic drugs" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M74" type="Precipitant" span="117 23;159 5" str="potentially nephrotoxic | drugs" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M77" type="Precipitant" span="196 10" str="vancomycin" code="6Q205EH1VU"/>
<Mention id="M80" type="Precipitant" span="250 8" str="viomycin" code="YVU35998K5"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M79" precipitant="M50" effect="M81" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M79" precipitant="M53" effect="M81" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M79" precipitant="M56" effect="M81" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M79" precipitant="M59" effect="M81" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M79" precipitant="M62" effect="M81" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M79" precipitant="M65" effect="M81" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M79" precipitant="M68" effect="M81" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M79" precipitant="M71" effect="M81" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M79" precipitant="M74" effect="M81" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M79" precipitant="M77" effect="M81" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M79" precipitant="M80" effect="M81" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2534" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Other factors which increase the risk of toxicity are advanced age and dehydration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2535" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>The concurrent use of neomycin with potent diuretics such as ethacrynic acid or furosemide should be avoided, since certain diuretics by themselves may cause ototoxicity.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M88" type="Trigger" span="91 17;152 5" str="should be avoided | cause"/>
<Mention id="M83" type="Precipitant" span="61 15" str="ethacrynic acid" code="M5DP350VZV | N0000007304"/>
<Mention id="M90" type="SpecificInteraction" span="158 11" str="ototoxicity" code="9062008: Ototoxicity (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M86" type="Precipitant" span="80 10" str="furosemide" code="7LXU5N7ZO5 | N0000007175"/>
<Mention id="M89" type="Precipitant" span="36 16" str="potent diuretics" code="N0000175359"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M88" precipitant="M83" effect="M90" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M88" precipitant="M86" effect="M90" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M88" precipitant="M89" effect="M90" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2536" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>In addition, when administered intravenously, diuretics may enhance neomycin toxicity by altering the antibiotic concentration in serum and tissue.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M91" type="Trigger" span="60 7;77 20;113 13" str="enhance | toxicity by altering | concentration"/>
<Mention id="M92" type="Precipitant" span="31 11;46 9" str="intravenous | diuretics" code="N0000175359"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M91" precipitant="M92" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2537" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Neomycin sulfate oral preparations are contraindicated in the presence of intestinal obstruction and in individuals with a history of hypersensitivity to the drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2538" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Patients with a history of hypersensitivity or serious toxic reaction to other aminoglycosides may have a cross-sensitivity to neomycin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2539" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Neomycin sulfate oral preparations are contraindicated in patients with inflammatory or ulcerative gastrointestinal disease because of the potential for enhanced gastrointestinal absorption of neomycin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2540" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>To minimize the risk of toxicity, use the lowest possible dose and the shortest possible treatment period to control the condition.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2541" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Treatment for periods longer than two weeks is not recommended.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2542" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For use as an adjunct in the management of hepatic coma, the recommended dose is 4 to 12 grams per day given in the following regimen: Withdraw protein from diet.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M93" type="Trigger" span="135 8" str="Withdraw"/>
<Mention id="M94" type="Precipitant" span="144 7" str="protein" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M93" precipitant="M94"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2543" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Give supportive therapy, including blood products, as indicated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2544" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Give neomycin sulfate tablets in doses of 4 to 12 grams of neomycin sulfate per day (eight to 24 tablets) in divided doses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2545" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Treatment should be continued over a period of five to six days, during which time protein should be returned incrementally to the diet.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2546" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If less potentially toxic drugs cannot be used for chronic hepatic insufficiency, neomycin in doses of up to four grams daily (eight tablets per day) may be necessary.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2547" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The risk for the development of neomycin-induced toxicity progressively increases when treatment must be extended to preserve the life of a patient with hepatic encephalopathy who has failed to fully respond.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2548" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Frequent periodic monitoring of these patients to ascertain the presence of drug toxicity is mandatory.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2549" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Also, neomycin serum concentrations should be monitored to avoid potentially toxic levels.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2550" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The benefits to the patient should be weighed against the risks of nephrotoxicity, permanent ototoxicity and neuromuscular blockade following the accumulation of neomycin in the tissues.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2551" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Listed below is an example of a recommended bowel preparation regimen.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2552" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>A proposed surgery time of 8:00 a.m. has been used.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2553" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Pre-op Day 3: Minimum residue or clear liquid diet.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2554" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Bisacodyl, 1 tablet orally at 6:00 p.m. Pre-op Day 2: Minimum residue or clear liquid diet.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2555" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Magnesium sulfate, 30 mL, 50% solution (15 g) orally at 10:00 a.m., 2:00 p.m., and 6:00 p.m. Enema at 7:00 p.m. and 8:00 p.m. Pre-op Day 1: Clear liquid diet.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2556" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Magnesium sulfate, 30 mL, 50% solution (15 g) orally at 10:00 a.m., and 2:00 p.m. Neomycin sulfate (1 g) and erythromycin base (1 g) orally at 1:00 p.m., 2:00 p.m. and 11:00 p.m. No enema.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2557" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Day of Operation: Patient evacuates rectum at 6:30 a.m. for scheduled operation at 8:00 a.m.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2558" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Caution should be taken in concurrent or serial use of other neurotoxic and/or nephrotoxic drugs because of possible enhancement of the nephrotoxicity and/or ototoxicity of neomycin.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M98" type="Trigger" span="117 11" str="enhancement"/>
<Mention id="M96" type="Precipitant" span="79 17" str="nephrotoxic drugs" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M97" type="SpecificInteraction" span="136 14" str="nephrotoxicity" code="236514003: Toxic nephropathy (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M99" type="Precipitant" span="61 10;91 5" str="neurotoxic | drugs" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M100" type="SpecificInteraction" span="158 11" str="ototoxicity" code="9062008: Ototoxicity (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I29" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M98" precipitant="M96" effect="M97" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I30" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M98" precipitant="M99" effect="M100" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2559" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Caution should also be taken in concurrent or serial use of other amino-glycosides and polymyxins because they may enhance neomycin’s nephrotoxicity and/or ototoxicity and potentiate neomycin sulfate’s neuromuscular blocking effects.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M116" type="Trigger" span="115 7" str="enhance"/>
<Mention id="M108" type="Precipitant" span="66 16" str="amino-glycosides" code="N0000175929"/>
<Mention id="M112" type="SpecificInteraction" span="134 14" str="nephrotoxicity" code="236514003: Toxic nephropathy (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M113" type="Trigger" span="172 10" str="potentiate"/>
<Mention id="M115" type="SpecificInteraction" span="202 30" str="neuromuscular blocking effects" code="397785000: Neuromuscular block problem (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M118" type="SpecificInteraction" span="156 11" str="ototoxicity" code="9062008: Ototoxicity (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M117" type="Precipitant" span="87 10" str="polymyxins" code="N0000175499"/>
<Interaction id="I31" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M116" precipitant="M108" effect="M112" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I32" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M113" precipitant="M108" effect="M115" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I33" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M116" precipitant="M108" effect="M118" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I34" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M116" precipitant="M117" effect="M112" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I35" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M113" precipitant="M117" effect="M115" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I36" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M116" precipitant="M117" effect="M118" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2560" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Oral neomycin inhibits the gastrointestinal absorption of penicillin V, oral vitamin B-12, methotrexate and 5-fluorouracil.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M125" type="Trigger" span="14 8;44 10" str="inhibits | absorption"/>
<Mention id="M120" type="Precipitant" span="108 14" str="5-fluorouracil" code="U3P01618RT"/>
<Mention id="M122" type="Precipitant" span="91 12" str="methotrexate" code="N0000007370 | YL5FZ2Y5U1"/>
<Mention id="M124" type="Precipitant" span="72 17" str="oral vitamin B-12" code="P6YC3EG204"/>
<Mention id="M126" type="Precipitant" span="58 12" str="penicillin V" code="Z61I075U2W"/>
<Interaction id="I37" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M125" precipitant="M120" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I38" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M125" precipitant="M122" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I39" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M125" precipitant="M124" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I40" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M125" precipitant="M126" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2561" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The gastrointestinal absorption of digoxin also appears to be inhibited.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M127" type="Trigger" span="21 10;62 9" str="absorption | inhibited"/>
<Mention id="M128" type="Precipitant" span="35 7" str="digoxin" code="73K4184T59 | N0000005903"/>
<Interaction id="I41" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M127" precipitant="M128" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2562" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Therefore, digoxin serum levels should be monitored.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M129" type="Trigger" span="19 32" str="serum levels should be monitored"/>
<Mention id="M130" type="Precipitant" span="11 7" str="digoxin" code="73K4184T59 | N0000005903"/>
<Interaction id="I42" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M129" precipitant="M130"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2563" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Oral neomycin sulfate may enhance the effect of coumarin in anticoagulants by decreasing vitamin K availability.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M134" type="Trigger" span="26 18" str="enhance the effect"/>
<Mention id="M132" type="Precipitant" span="60 14" str="anticoagulants" code="N0000029110 | N0000175980"/>
<Mention id="M133" type="SpecificInteraction" span="26 21;60 14" str="enhance the effect of | anticoagulants" code="10191004: Anticoagulant effect (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M135" type="Precipitant" span="48 8" str="coumarin" code="A4VZ22K1WT"/>
<Mention id="M136" type="SpecificInteraction" span="26 30" str="enhance the effect of coumarin" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M137" type="Trigger" span="78 10" str="decreasing"/>
<Mention id="M138" type="Precipitant" span="89 9" str="vitamin K" code="A034SE7857"/>
<Interaction id="I43" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M134" precipitant="M132" effect="M133" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I44" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M134" precipitant="M135" effect="M136" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I45" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M137" precipitant="M138" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2564" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Prescribing Neomycin Sulfate Tablets USP in the absence of a proven or strongly suspected bacterial infection or a prophylactic indication is unlikely to provide benefit to the patient and increases the risk of the development of drug-resistant bacteria.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2565" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>As with other antibiotics, use of oral neomycin may result in overgrowth of nonsusceptible organisms, particularly fungi.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2566" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>If this occurs, appropriate therapy should be instituted.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2567" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Neomycin is quickly and almost totally absorbed from body surfaces (except the urinary bladder) after local irrigation and when applied topically in association with surgical procedures.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2568" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Delayed-onset irreversible deafness, renal failure and death due to neuromuscular blockade (regardless of the status of renal function) have been reported following irrigation of both small and large surgical fields with minute quantities of neomycin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2569" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Cross-allergenicity among amino-glycosides has been demonstrated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2570" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Aminoglycosides should be used with caution in patients with muscular disorders such as myasthenia gravis or parkinsonism since these drugs may aggravate muscle weakness because of their potential curare-like effect on the neuromuscular junction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2571" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Small amounts of orally administered neomycin are absorbed through intact intestinal mucosa.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2572" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>There have been many reports in the literature of nephrotoxicity and/or ototoxicity with oral use of neomycin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2573" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>If renal insufficiency develops during oral therapy, consideration should be given to reducing the drug dosage or discontinuing therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2574" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>An oral neomycin dose of 12 grams per day produces a malabsorption syndrome for a variety of substances, including fat, nitrogen, cholesterol, carotene, glucose, xylose, lactose, sodium, calcium, cyanocobalamin and iron.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M169" type="Trigger" span="42 8" str="produces"/>
<Mention id="M140" type="Precipitant" span="187 7" str="calcium" code="SY7Q814VUP"/>
<Mention id="M171" type="SpecificInteraction" span="53 22" str="malabsorption syndrome" code="32230006: Malabsorption syndrome (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M143" type="Precipitant" span="143 8" str="carotene" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M146" type="Precipitant" span="130 11" str="cholesterol" code="97C5T2UQ7J"/>
<Mention id="M149" type="Precipitant" span="196 14" str="cyanocobalamin" code="P6YC3EG204"/>
<Mention id="M152" type="Precipitant" span="115 3" str="fat" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M155" type="Precipitant" span="153 7" str="glucose" code="5SL0G7R0OK"/>
<Mention id="M158" type="Precipitant" span="215 4" str="iron" code="E1UOL152H7"/>
<Mention id="M161" type="Precipitant" span="170 7" str="lactose" code="J2B2A4N98G"/>
<Mention id="M164" type="Precipitant" span="120 8" str="nitrogen" code="N762921K75"/>
<Mention id="M167" type="Precipitant" span="179 6" str="sodium" code="9NEZ333N27"/>
<Mention id="M170" type="Precipitant" span="162 6" str="xylose" code="A1TA934AKO"/>
<Interaction id="I46" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M169" precipitant="M140" effect="M171" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I47" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M169" precipitant="M143" effect="M171" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I48" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M169" precipitant="M146" effect="M171" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I49" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M169" precipitant="M149" effect="M171" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I50" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M169" precipitant="M152" effect="M171" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I51" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M169" precipitant="M155" effect="M171" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I52" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M169" precipitant="M158" effect="M171" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I53" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M169" precipitant="M161" effect="M171" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I54" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M169" precipitant="M164" effect="M171" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I55" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M169" precipitant="M167" effect="M171" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I56" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M169" precipitant="M170" effect="M171" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2575" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Orally administered neomycin increases fecal bile acid excretion and reduces intestinal lactase activity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2576" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Patients should be counseled that antibacterial drugs including Neomycin Sulfate Tablets USP should only be used to treat bacterial infections.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2577" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>They do not treat viral infections (e.g., the common cold).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2578" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>When Neomycin Sulfate Tablets USP are prescribed to treat a bacterial infection, patients should be told that although it is common to feel better early in the course of therapy, the medication should be taken exactly as directed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2579" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Skipping doses or not completing the full course of therapy may (1) decrease the effectiveness of the immediate treatment and (2) increase the likelihood that bacteria will develop resistance and will not be treatable by Neomycin Sulfate Tablets USP or other antibacterial drugs in the future.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2580" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Before administering the drug, patients or members of their families should be informed of possible toxic effects on the eighth nerve.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2581" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The possibility of acute toxicity increases in premature infants and neonates.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2582" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Patients with renal insufficiency may develop toxic neomycin blood levels unless doses are properly regulated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2583" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>If renal insufficiency develops during treatment, the dosage should be reduced or the antibiotic discontinued.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2584" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>To avoid nephrotoxicity and eighth nerve damage associated with high doses and prolonged treatment, the following should be performed prior to and periodically during therapy: urinalysis for increased excretion of protein, decreased specific gravity, casts and cells; renal function tests such as serum creatinine, BUN or creatinine clearance; tests of the vestibulocochlearis nerve (eighth cranial nerve) function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2585" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Serial, vestibular and audiometric tests should be performed (especially in high-risk patients).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2586" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Since elderly patients may have reduced renal function which may not be evident in the results of routine screening tests such as BUN or serum creatinine, a creatinine clearance determination may be more useful.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2587" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>No long-term animal studies have been performed with neomycin sulfate to evaluate carcinogenic or mutagenic potential or impairment of fertility.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2588" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>It is not known whether neomycin is excreted in human milk, but it has been shown to be excreted in cow milk following a single intramuscular injection.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2589" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Other aminoglycosides have been shown to be excreted in human milk.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2590" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because of the potential for serious adverse reactions from the aminoglycosides in nursing infants, a decision should be made whether to discontinue nursing or to discontinue the drug, taking into account the importance of the drug to the mother.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2591" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The safety and efficacy of oral neomycin sulfate in patients less than 18 years of age have not been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2592" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>If treatment of a patient less than 18 years of age is necessary, neomycin should be used with caution and the period of treatment should not exceed two weeks because of absorption from the gastrointestinal tract.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2593" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Additional manifestations of neurotoxicity may include numbness, skin tingling, muscle twitching and convulsions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2594" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The risk of hearing loss continues after drug withdrawal.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2595" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Aminoglycosides can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2596" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Aminoglycoside antibiotics cross the placenta and there have been several reports of total irreversible bilateral congenital deafness in children whose mothers received streptomycin during pregnancy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2597" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Although serious side effects to fetus or newborn have not been reported in the treatment of pregnant women with other aminoglycosides, the potential for harm exists.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2598" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Animal reproduction studies of neomycin have not been conducted.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2599" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>If neomycin is used during pregnancy, or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking this drug, the patient should be apprised of the potential hazard to the fetus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2600" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Neomycin sulfate is poorly absorbed from the normal gastrointestinal tract.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2601" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The small absorbed fraction is rapidly distributed in the tissues and is excreted by the kidney in keeping with the degree of kidney function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2602" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The unabsorbed portion of the drug (approximately 97%) is eliminated unchanged in the feces.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2603" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Growth of most intestinal bacteria is rapidly suppressed following oral administration of neomycin sulfate, with the suppression persisting for 48 to 72 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2604" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Nonpathogenic yeasts and occasionally resistant strains of Enterobacter aerogenes (formerly Aerobacter aerogenes) replace the intestinal bacteria.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2605" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>As with other aminoglycosides, the amount of systemically absorbed neomycin transferred to the tissues increases cumulatively with each repeated dose administered until a steady state is achieved.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2606" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The kidney functions as the primary excretory path as well as the tissue binding site, with the highest concentration found in the renal cortex.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2607" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>With repeated dosings, progressive accumulation also occurs in the inner ear.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2608" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Release of tissue-bound neomycin occurs slowly over a period of several weeks after dosing has been discontinued.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2609" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Protein binding studies have shown that the degree of aminoglycoside protein binding is low and, depending upon the methods used for testing, this may be between 0% and 30%.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2610" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In vitro tests have demonstrated that neomycin is bactericidal and acts by inhibiting the synthesis of protein in susceptible bacterial cells.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2611" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>It is effective primarily against gram-negative bacilli but does have some activity against gram-positive organisms.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2612" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Neomycin is active in vitro against Escherichia coli and the Klebsiella-Enterobacter group.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2613" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Neomycin is not active against anaerobic bowel flora.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2614" LabelDrug="Neomycin Sulfate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Susceptibility Testing For specific information regarding susceptibility test interpretive criteria and associated test methods and quality control standards recognized by FDA for this drug, please see: https://www.fda.gov/STIC.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="anesthetics" precipitantCode="N0000029138 | N0000175681" effect="397785000: Neuromuscular block problem (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="anesthetics" precipitantCode="N0000029138 | N0000175681" effect="95430002: Respiratory tract paralysis (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="decamethonium" precipitantCode="C1CG1S3T2W" effect="397785000: Neuromuscular block problem (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="decamethonium" precipitantCode="C1CG1S3T2W" effect="95430002: Respiratory tract paralysis (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="massive transfusions of citrate anticoagulated blood" precipitantCode="N0000193821" effect="397785000: Neuromuscular block problem (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="massive transfusions of citrate anticoagulated blood" precipitantCode="N0000193821" effect="95430002: Respiratory tract paralysis (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="neuromuscular blocking agents" precipitantCode="N0000175731" effect="397785000: Neuromuscular block problem (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="neuromuscular blocking agents" precipitantCode="N0000175731" effect="95430002: Respiratory tract paralysis (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="succinylcholine" precipitantCode="N0000006153 | J2R869A8YF" effect="397785000: Neuromuscular block problem (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="succinylcholine" precipitantCode="N0000006153 | J2R869A8YF" effect="95430002: Respiratory tract paralysis (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="tubocurarine" precipitantCode="N0000006051 | W9YXS298BM" effect="397785000: Neuromuscular block problem (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="tubocurarine" precipitantCode="N0000006051 | W9YXS298BM" effect="95430002: Respiratory tract paralysis (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="aminoglycosides" precipitantCode="N0000175929" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="amphotericin b" precipitantCode="7XU7A7DROE" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="bacitracin" precipitantCode="58H6RWO52I" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cisplatin" precipitantCode="N0000007062 | Q20Q21Q62J" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="colistin" precipitantCode="Z67X93HJG1" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="paromomycin" precipitantCode="61JJC8N5ZK" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="polymyxin b" precipitantCode="J2VZ07J96K" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="potentially | neurotoxic drugs" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="potentially nephrotoxic | drugs" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="vancomycin" precipitantCode="6Q205EH1VU" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="viomycin" precipitantCode="YVU35998K5" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ethacrynic acid" precipitantCode="M5DP350VZV | N0000007304" effect="9062008: Ototoxicity (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="furosemide" precipitantCode="7LXU5N7ZO5 | N0000007175" effect="9062008: Ototoxicity (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="potent diuretics" precipitantCode="N0000175359" effect="9062008: Ototoxicity (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="intravenous | diuretics" precipitantCode="N0000175359" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="protein" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nephrotoxic drugs" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="236514003: Toxic nephropathy (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="neurotoxic | drugs" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="9062008: Ototoxicity (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="amino-glycosides" precipitantCode="N0000175929" effect="236514003: Toxic nephropathy (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="amino-glycosides" precipitantCode="N0000175929" effect="397785000: Neuromuscular block problem (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="amino-glycosides" precipitantCode="N0000175929" effect="9062008: Ototoxicity (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="polymyxins" precipitantCode="N0000175499" effect="236514003: Toxic nephropathy (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="polymyxins" precipitantCode="N0000175499" effect="397785000: Neuromuscular block problem (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="polymyxins" precipitantCode="N0000175499" effect="9062008: Ototoxicity (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="5-fluorouracil" precipitantCode="U3P01618RT" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="methotrexate" precipitantCode="N0000007370 | YL5FZ2Y5U1" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="oral vitamin b-12" precipitantCode="P6YC3EG204" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="penicillin v" precipitantCode="Z61I075U2W" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="digoxin" precipitantCode="73K4184T59 | N0000005903" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="digoxin" precipitantCode="73K4184T59 | N0000005903"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="anticoagulants" precipitantCode="N0000029110 | N0000175980" effect="10191004: Anticoagulant effect (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="coumarin" precipitantCode="A4VZ22K1WT" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="vitamin k" precipitantCode="A034SE7857" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="calcium" precipitantCode="SY7Q814VUP" effect="32230006: Malabsorption syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="carotene" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="32230006: Malabsorption syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cholesterol" precipitantCode="97C5T2UQ7J" effect="32230006: Malabsorption syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cyanocobalamin" precipitantCode="P6YC3EG204" effect="32230006: Malabsorption syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="fat" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="32230006: Malabsorption syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="glucose" precipitantCode="5SL0G7R0OK" effect="32230006: Malabsorption syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="iron" precipitantCode="E1UOL152H7" effect="32230006: Malabsorption syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="lactose" precipitantCode="J2B2A4N98G" effect="32230006: Malabsorption syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nitrogen" precipitantCode="N762921K75" effect="32230006: Malabsorption syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sodium" precipitantCode="9NEZ333N27" effect="32230006: Malabsorption syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="xylose" precipitantCode="A1TA934AKO" effect="32230006: Malabsorption syndrome (disorder)"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>