<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Entereg" setid="77a67dc6-35d3-48ff-9d18-292d4d442f70">
<Text><Section name="BOXED WARNING SECTION" id="34066-1">
There was a greater incidence of myocardial infarction in alvimopan-treated patients compared to placebo-treated patients in a 12-month clinical trial, although a causal relationship has not been established. In short-term trials with ENTEREG ® , no increased risk of myocardial infarction was observed [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1) ]. Because of the potential risk of myocardial infarction with long-term use, ENTEREG is available only through a restricted program for short-term use (15 doses) under a Risk Evaluation and Mitigation Strategy (REMS) called the ENTEREG Access Support and Education (E.A.S.E. ® ) Program [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1) and (5.2) ]. WARNING: POTENTIAL RISK OF MYOCARDIAL INFARCTION WITH LONG-TERM USE: FOR SHORT-TERM HOSPITAL USE ONLY See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning. Increased incidence of myocardial infarction was seen in a clinical trial of patients taking alvimopan for long-term use. ( 5.1 ) ENTEREG is available only through a restricted program for short-term use (15 doses) called the ENTEREG Access Support and Education (E.A.S.E. ® ) Program. ( 5.1 , 5.2 )</Section>
<Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
ENTEREG is contraindicated in patients who have taken therapeutic doses of opioids for more than 7 consecutive days immediately prior to taking ENTEREG [see Warnings and Precautions (5.3) ]. Patients who have taken therapeutic doses of opioids for more than 7 consecutive days prior to taking ENTEREG ( 4 )</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
For hospital use only. The recommended adult dosage of ENTEREG is 12 mg administered 30 minutes to 5 hours prior to surgery followed by 12 mg twice daily beginning the day after surgery until discharge for a maximum of 7 days. Patients should not receive more than 15 doses of ENTEREG. 12 mg administered 30 minutes to 5 hours prior to surgery followed by 12 mg twice daily beginning the day after surgery for up to 7 days for a maximum of 15 in-hospital doses. ( 2 )</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
An in vitro study indicates that alvimopan is not a substrate of CYP enzymes. Therefore, concomitant administration of ENTEREG with inducers or inhibitors of CYP enzymes is unlikely to alter the metabolism of alvimopan. Based on in vitro data, ENTEREG is unlikely to alter the pharmacokinetics of coadministered drugs through inhibition of CYP isoforms such as 1A2, 2C9, 2C19, 3A4, 2D6, and 2E1 or induction of CYP isoforms such as 1A2, 2B6, 2C9, 2C19, and 3A4. In vitro, ENTEREG did not inhibit p-glycoprotein. Coadministration of alvimopan does not appear to alter the pharmacokinetics of morphine and its metabolite, morphine-6-glucuronide, to a clinically significant degree when morphine is administered intravenously. Dosage adjustment for intravenously administered morphine is not necessary when it is coadministered with alvimopan. A population pharmacokinetic analysis suggests that the pharmacokinetics of alvimopan were not affected by concomitant administration of acid blockers or antibiotics. No dosage adjustments are necessary in patients taking acid blockers or antibiotics.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
A higher number of myocardial infarctions was reported in patients treated with alvimopan 0.5 mg twice daily compared with placebo in a 12-month study in patients treated with opioids for chronic non-cancer pain, although a causal relationship with long-term use has not been established. ( 5.1 ) Patients recently exposed to opioids are expected to be more sensitive to the effects of ENTEREG and therefore may experience abdominal pain, nausea and vomiting, and diarrhea. ( 5.3 ) Not recommended in patients with severe hepatic impairment. ( 5.4 ) Not recommended in patients with end-stage renal disease. ( 5.5 ) Not recommended in patients with complete gastrointestinal obstruction or in patients who have surgery for correction of complete bowel obstruction. ( 5.6 ) Not recommended in pancreatic or gastric anastomosis. ( 5.7 ) There were more reports of myocardial infarctions in patients treated with alvimopan 0.5 mg twice daily compared with placebo-treated patients in a 12-month study of patients treated with opioids for chronic non-cancer pain (alvimopan 0.5 mg, n = 538; placebo, n = 267). In this study, the majority of myocardial infarctions occurred between 1 and 4 months after initiation of treatment. This imbalance has not been observed in other studies of ENTEREG in patients treated with opioids for chronic pain, nor in patients treated within the surgical setting, including patients undergoing surgeries that included bowel resection who received ENTEREG 12 mg twice daily for up to 7 days (the indicated dose and patient population; ENTEREG 12 mg, n = 1,142; placebo, n = 1,120). A causal relationship with alvimopan with long-term use has not been established. ENTEREG is available only through a program under a REMS that restricts use to enrolled hospitals [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2) ]. ENTEREG is available only through a program called the ENTEREG Access Support and Education (E.A.S.E.) ENTEREG REMS Program that restricts use to enrolled hospitals because of the potential risk of myocardial infarction with long-term use of ENTEREG [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1) ]. Notable requirements of the E.A.S.E. Program include the following: ENTEREG is available only for short-term (15 doses) use in hospitalized patients. Only hospitals that have enrolled in and met all of the requirements for the E.A.S.E. program may use ENTEREG. To enroll in the E.A.S.E. Program, an authorized hospital representative must acknowledge that: hospital staff who prescribe, dispense, or administer ENTEREG have been provided the educational materials on the need to limit use of ENTEREG to short-term, inpatient use; patients will not receive more than 15 doses of ENTEREG; and ENTEREG will not be dispensed to patients after they have been discharged from the hospital. Further information is available at www.ENTEREGREMS.com or 1-800-278-0340. Patients recently exposed to opioids are expected to be more sensitive to the effects of μ-opioid receptor antagonists, such as ENTEREG. Since ENTEREG acts peripherally, clinical signs and symptoms of increased sensitivity would be related to the gastrointestinal tract (e.g., abdominal pain, nausea and vomiting, diarrhea). Patients receiving more than 3 doses of an opioid within the week prior to surgery were not studied in the postoperative ileus clinical trials. Therefore, if ENTEREG is administered to these patients, they should be monitored for gastrointestinal adverse reactions. ENTEREG is contraindicated in patients who have taken therapeutic doses of opioids for more than 7 consecutive days immediately prior to taking ENTEREG. Patients with severe hepatic impairment may be at higher risk of serious adverse reactions (including dose-related serious adverse reactions) because up to 10-fold higher plasma levels of drug have been observed in such patients compared with patients with normal hepatic function. Therefore, the use of ENTEREG is not recommended in this population. No studies have been conducted in patients with end-stage renal disease. ENTEREG is not recommended for use in these patients. No studies have been conducted in patients with complete gastrointestinal obstruction or in patients who have surgery for correction of complete bowel obstruction. ENTEREG is not recommended for use in these patients. ENTEREG has not been studied in patients having pancreatic or gastric anastomosis. Therefore, ENTEREG is not recommended for use in these patients.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Alvimopan is a selective antagonist of the cloned human μ-opioid receptor with a Ki of 0.4 nM (0.2 ng/mL) and no measurable opioid-agonist effects in standard pharmacologic assays. The dissociation of [ 3 H]-alvimopan from the human μ-opioid receptor is slower than that of other opioid ligands, consistent with its higher affinity for the receptor. At concentrations of 1 to 10 µM, alvimopan demonstrated no activity at any of over 70 non-opioid receptors, enzymes, and ion channels. Postoperative ileus is the impairment of gastrointestinal motility after intra-abdominal surgery or other, non-abdominal surgeries. Postoperative ileus affects all segments of the gastrointestinal tract and may last from 5 to 6 days, or even longer. This may potentially delay gastrointestinal recovery and hospital discharge until its resolution. It is characterized by abdominal distention and bloating, nausea, vomiting, pain, accumulation of gas and fluids in the bowel, and delayed passage of flatus and defecation. Postoperative ileus is the result of a multifactorial process that includes inhibitory sympathetic input and release of hormones, neurotransmitters, and other mediators (e.g., endogenous opioids). A component of postoperative ileus also results from an inflammatory reaction and the effects of opioid analgesics. Morphine and other μ-opioid receptor agonists are universally used for the treatment of acute postsurgical pain; however, they are known to have an inhibitory effect on gastrointestinal motility and may prolong the duration of postoperative ileus. Following oral administration, alvimopan antagonizes the peripheral effects of opioids on gastrointestinal motility and secretion by competitively binding to gastrointestinal tract μ-opioid receptors. The antagonism produced by alvimopan at opioid receptors is evident in isolated guinea pig ileum preparations in which alvimopan competitively antagonizes the effects of morphine on contractility. Alvimopan achieves this selective gastrointestinal opioid antagonism without reversing the central analgesic effects of μ-opioid agonists. In an exploratory study in healthy volunteers, alvimopan 12 mg administered twice a day reduced the delay in small and large bowel transit induced by codeine 30 mg administered 4 times a day, as measured by gastrointestinal scintigraphy. In the same study, concomitant alvimopan did not reduce the delay in gastric emptying induced by codeine. In a study designed to evaluate potential effects on cardiac conduction, alvimopan did not cause clinically significant QTc prolongation at doses up to 24 mg twice daily (twice the approved dosage regimen) for 7 days. The potential for QTc effects at higher doses has not been studied. Following oral administration of alvimopan, an amide hydrolysis compound is present in the systemic circulation, which is considered a product exclusively of intestinal flora metabolism. This compound is referred to as the 'metabolite'. It is also a μ-opioid receptor antagonist with a Ki of 0.8 nM (0.3 ng/mL). Absorption: Following oral administration of ENTEREG capsules in healthy volunteers, plasma alvimopan concentration peaked at approximately 2 hours postdose. No significant accumulation in alvimopan concentration was observed following twice daily (BID) dosing. The mean peak plasma concentration was 10.98 (±6.43) ng/mL and mean AUC 0–12h was 40.2 (±22.5) ng∙h/mL after dosing of alvimopan at 12 mg BID for 5 days. The absolute bioavailability was estimated to be 6% (range, 1% to 19%). There was a delay in the appearance of the 'metabolite', which had a median T max of 36 hours following administration of a single dose of alvimopan. Concentrations of the 'metabolite' were highly variable between subjects and within a subject. The 'metabolite' accumulated after multiple doses of ENTEREG. The mean C max for the 'metabolite' after alvimopan 12 mg twice daily for 5 days was 35.73 ± 35.29 ng/mL. Concentrations of alvimopan and its 'metabolite' are higher (~1.9-fold and ~1.4-fold, respectively) in postoperative ileus patients than in healthy volunteers. Food Effects: A high-fat meal decreased the extent and rate of alvimopan absorption. The C max and AUC were decreased by approximately 38% and 21%, respectively, and the T max was prolonged by approximately 1 hour. The clinical significance of this decreased bioavailability is unknown. In postoperative ileus clinical trials, the preoperative dose of ENTEREG was administered in a fasting state. Subsequent doses were given without regard to meals. Distribution: The steady-state volume of distribution of alvimopan was estimated to be 30±10 L. Plasma protein binding of alvimopan and its 'metabolite' was independent of concentration over ranges observed clinically and averaged 80% and 94%, respectively. Both alvimopan and the 'metabolite' were bound to albumin and not to alpha-1 acid glycoprotein. Metabolism and Elimination: In vitro data suggest that alvimopan is not a substrate of CYP enzymes. The average plasma clearance for alvimopan was 402 (±89) mL/min. Renal excretion accounted for approximately 35% of total clearance. There was no evidence that hepatic metabolism was a significant route for alvimopan elimination. Biliary secretion was considered the primary pathway for alvimopan elimination. Unabsorbed drug and unchanged alvimopan resulting from biliary excretion were then hydrolyzed to its 'metabolite' by gut microflora. The 'metabolite' was eliminated in the feces and in the urine as unchanged 'metabolite', the glucuronide conjugate of the 'metabolite', and other minor metabolites. The mean terminal phase half-life of alvimopan after multiple oral doses of ENTEREG ranged from 10 to 17 hours. The terminal half-life of the 'metabolite' ranged from 10 to 18 hours. Specific Populations: Age: The pharmacokinetics of alvimopan, but not its 'metabolite', were related to age, but this effect was not clinically significant and does not warrant dosage adjustment based on increased age. Race: The pharmacokinetic characteristics of alvimopan were not affected by Hispanic or Black race. Plasma 'metabolite' concentrations were lower in Black and Hispanic patients (by 43% and 82%, respectively) than in Caucasian patients following alvimopan administration. These changes are not considered to be clinically significant in surgical patients. Japanese healthy male volunteers had an approximately 2-fold increase in plasma alvimopan concentrations, but no change in 'metabolite' pharmacokinetics. The pharmacokinetics of alvimopan have not been studied in subjects of other East Asian ancestry. Dosage adjustment in Japanese patients is not required [see Use in Specific Populations (8.8) ]. Gender: There was no effect of gender on the pharmacokinetics of alvimopan or the 'metabolite'. Hepatic Impairment: Exposure to alvimopan following a single 12 mg dose tended to be higher (1.5- to 2-fold, on average) in patients with mild or moderate hepatic impairment (as defined by Child-Pugh Class A and B, n = 8 each) compared with healthy controls (n = 4). There were no consistent effects on the C max or half-life of alvimopan in patients with hepatic impairment. However, 2 of 16 patients with mild-to-moderate hepatic impairment had longer than expected half-lives of alvimopan, indicating that some accumulation may occur upon multiple dosing. The C max of the 'metabolite' tended to be more variable in patients with mild or moderate hepatic impairment than in matched normal subjects. A study of 3 patients with severe hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh Class C), indicated similar alvimopan exposure in 2 patients and an approximately 10-fold increase in C max and exposure in 1 patient with severe hepatic impairment when compared with healthy control volunteers [see Warnings and Precautions (5.4) and Use in Specific Populations (8.6) ]. Renal Impairment: There was no relationship between renal function (i.e., creatinine clearance [CrCl]) and plasma alvimopan pharmacokinetics (C max , AUC, or half-life) in patients with mild (CrCl 51–80 mL/min), moderate (CrCl 31–50 mL/min), or severe (CrCl &amp;lt;30 mL/min) renal impairment (n = 6 each). Renal clearance of alvimopan was related to renal function; however, because renal clearance was only a small fraction (35%) of the total clearance, renal impairment had a small effect on the apparent oral clearance of alvimopan. The half-lives of alvimopan were comparable in the mild, moderate, and control renal impairment groups but longer in the severe renal impairment group. Exposure to the 'metabolite' tended to be 2- to 5-fold higher in patients with moderate or severe renal impairment compared with patients with mild renal impairment or control subjects. Thus, there may be accumulation of alvimopan and 'metabolite' in patients with severe renal impairment receiving multiple doses of ENTEREG. Patients with end-stage renal disease were not studied [see Warnings and Precautions (5.5) and Use in Specific Populations (8.7) ]. Crohn's Disease: There was no relationship between disease activity in patients with Crohn's disease (measured as Crohn's Disease Activity Index or bowel movement frequency) and alvimopan pharmacokinetics (AUC or C max ). Patients with active or quiescent Crohn's disease had increased variability in alvimopan pharmacokinetics, and exposure tended to be 2-fold higher in patients with quiescent disease than in those with active disease or in normal subjects. Concentrations of the 'metabolite' were lower in patients with Crohn's disease. Drug Interactions: Potential for Drugs to Affect Alvimopan Pharmacokinetics: Concomitant administration of ENTEREG with inducers or inhibitors of CYP enzymes is unlikely to alter the metabolism of alvimopan because ENTEREG is metabolized mainly by non-CYP enzyme pathway. No clinical studies have been performed to assess the effect of concomitant administration of inducers or inhibitors of cytochrome P450 enzymes on alvimopan pharmacokinetics. In vitro studies suggest that alvimopan and its 'metabolite' are substrates for p-glycoprotein. A population pharmacokinetic analysis did not reveal any evidence that alvimopan or 'metabolite' pharmacokinetics were influenced by concomitant medications that are mild-to-moderate p-glycoprotein inhibitors. No clinical studies of concomitant administration of alvimopan and strong inhibitors of p-glycoprotein (e.g., verapamil, cyclosporine, amiodarone, itraconazole, quinine, spironolactone, quinidine, diltiazem, bepridil) have been conducted. A population pharmacokinetic analysis suggests that the pharmacokinetics of alvimopan were not affected by concomitant administration of acid blockers or antibiotics. However, plasma concentrations of the 'metabolite' were lower in patients receiving acid blockers or preoperative oral antibiotics (49% and 81%, respectively). No dosage adjustments are necessary in these patients. Potential for Alvimopan to Affect the Pharmacokinetics of Other Drugs: Alvimopan and its 'metabolite' are not inhibitors of CYP 1A2, 2C9, 2C19, 3A4, 2D6, and 2E1 in vitro at concentrations far in excess of those observed clinically. Alvimopan and its 'metabolite' are not inducers of CYP 1A2, 2B6, 2C9, 2C19, and 3A4. In vitro studies also suggest that alvimopan and its 'metabolite' are not inhibitors of p-glycoprotein. These in vitro findings suggest that ENTEREG is unlikely to alter the pharmacokinetics of coadministered drugs through inhibition or induction of CYP enzymes or inhibition of p-glycoprotein.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="8920" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>There was a greater incidence of myocardial infarction in alvimopan-treated patients compared to placebo-treated patients in a 12-month clinical trial, although a causal relationship has not been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8921" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>In short-term trials with ENTEREG®, no increased risk of myocardial infarction was observed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8922" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Because of the potential risk of myocardial infarction with long-term use, ENTEREG is available only through a restricted program for short-term use (15 doses) under a Risk Evaluation and Mitigation Strategy (REMS) called the ENTEREG Access Support and Education (E.A.S.E.®) Program.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8923" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>WARNING: POTENTIAL RISK OF MYOCARDIAL INFARCTION WITH LONG-TERM USE: FOR SHORT-TERM HOSPITAL USE ONLY See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8924" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Increased incidence of myocardial infarction was seen in a clinical trial of patients taking alvimopan for long-term use.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8925" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>ENTEREG is available only through a restricted program for short-term use (15 doses) called the ENTEREG Access Support and Education (E.A.S.E.®) Program.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8926" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>ENTEREG is contraindicated in patients who have taken therapeutic doses of opioids for more than 7 consecutive days immediately prior to taking ENTEREG.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M1" type="Trigger" span="11 15" str="contraindicated"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="75 7" str="opioids" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M1" precipitant="M2"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8927" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Patients who have taken therapeutic doses of opioids for more than 7 consecutive days prior to taking ENTEREG (4)</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8928" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommended adult dosage of ENTEREG is 12 mg administered 30 minutes to 5 hours prior to surgery followed by 12 mg twice daily beginning the day after surgery until discharge for a maximum of 7 days.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8929" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Patients should not receive more than 15 doses of ENTEREG.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8930" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>12 mg administered 30 minutes to 5 hours prior to surgery followed by 12 mg twice daily beginning the day after surgery for up to 7 days for a maximum of 15 in-hospital doses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8931" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>An in vitro study indicates that alvimopan is not a substrate of CYP enzymes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8932" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Therefore, concomitant administration of ENTEREG with inducers or inhibitors of CYP enzymes is unlikely to alter the metabolism of alvimopan.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8933" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Based on in vitro data, ENTEREG is unlikely to alter the pharmacokinetics of coadministered drugs through inhibition of CYP isoforms such as 1A2, 2C9, 2C19, 3A4, 2D6, and 2E1 or induction of CYP isoforms such as 1A2, 2B6, 2C9, 2C19, and 3A4.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8934" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>In vitro, ENTEREG did not inhibit p-glycoprotein.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8935" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Coadministration of alvimopan does not appear to alter the pharmacokinetics of morphine and its metabolite, morphine-6-glucuronide, to a clinically significant degree when morphine is administered intravenously.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8936" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Dosage adjustment for intravenously administered morphine is not necessary when it is coadministered with alvimopan.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8937" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>A population pharmacokinetic analysis suggests that the pharmacokinetics of alvimopan were not affected by concomitant administration of acid blockers or antibiotics.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8938" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>No dosage adjustments are necessary in patients taking acid blockers or antibiotics.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8939" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>A higher number of myocardial infarctions was reported in patients treated with alvimopan 0.5 mg twice daily compared with placebo in a 12-month study in patients treated with opioids for chronic non-cancer pain, although a causal relationship with long-term use has not been established.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M3" type="Trigger" span="2 13" str="higher number"/>
<Mention id="M4" type="Precipitant" span="176 7" str="opioids" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M5" type="SpecificInteraction" span="19 22" str="myocardial infarctions" code="22298006: Myocardial infarction (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M3" precipitant="M4" effect="M5" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8940" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients recently exposed to opioids are expected to be more sensitive to the effects of ENTEREG and therefore may experience abdominal pain, nausea and vomiting, and diarrhea.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M18" type="Trigger" span="0 8;115 10" str="Patients | experience"/>
<Mention id="M19" type="Precipitant" span="29 7" str="opioids" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M8" type="SpecificInteraction" span="126 14" str="abdominal pain" code="21522001: Abdominal pain (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M11" type="SpecificInteraction" span="167 8" str="diarrhea" code="62315008: Diarrhea (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M12" type="Trigger" span="56 29" str="more sensitive to the effects"/>
<Mention id="M14" type="SpecificInteraction" span="56 40" str="more sensitive to the effects of ENTEREG" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M17" type="SpecificInteraction" span="142 6" str="nausea" code="422587007: Nausea (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M20" type="SpecificInteraction" span="153 8" str="vomiting" code="422400008: Vomiting (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M18" precipitant="M19" effect="M8" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M18" precipitant="M19" effect="M11" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M12" precipitant="M19" effect="M14" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M18" precipitant="M19" effect="M17" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M18" precipitant="M19" effect="M20" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8941" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Not recommended in patients with severe hepatic impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8942" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Not recommended in patients with end-stage renal disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8943" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Not recommended in patients with complete gastrointestinal obstruction or in patients who have surgery for correction of complete bowel obstruction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8944" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Not recommended in pancreatic or gastric anastomosis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8945" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There were more reports of myocardial infarctions in patients treated with alvimopan 0.5 mg twice daily compared with placebo-treated patients in a 12-month study of patients treated with opioids for chronic non-cancer pain (alvimopan 0.5 mg, n = 538; placebo, n = 267).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M21" type="Trigger" span="11 4" str="more"/>
<Mention id="M22" type="Precipitant" span="188 7" str="opioids" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M23" type="SpecificInteraction" span="27 22" str="myocardial infarctions" code="22298006: Myocardial infarction (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M21" precipitant="M22" effect="M23" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8946" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In this study, the majority of myocardial infarctions occurred between 1 and 4 months after initiation of treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8947" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>This imbalance has not been observed in other studies of ENTEREG in patients treated with opioids for chronic pain, nor in patients treated within the surgical setting, including patients undergoing surgeries that included bowel resection who received ENTEREG 12 mg twice daily for up to 7 days (the indicated dose and patient population; ENTEREG 12 mg, n = 1,142; placebo, n = 1,120).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8948" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>A causal relationship with alvimopan with long-term use has not been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8949" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>ENTEREG is available only through a program under a REMS that restricts use to enrolled hospitals.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8950" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>ENTEREG is available only through a program called the ENTEREG Access Support and Education (E.A.S.E.)</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8951" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>ENTEREG REMS Program that restricts use to enrolled hospitals because of the potential risk of myocardial infarction with long-term use of ENTEREG.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8952" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Program include the following: ENTEREG is available only for short-term (15 doses) use in hospitalized patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8953" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Only hospitals that have enrolled in and met all of the requirements for the E.A.S.E. program may use ENTEREG.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8954" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Program, an authorized hospital representative must acknowledge that: hospital staff who prescribe, dispense, or administer ENTEREG have been provided the educational materials on the need to limit use of ENTEREG to short-term, inpatient use; patients will not receive more than 15 doses of ENTEREG; and ENTEREG will not be dispensed to patients after they have been discharged from the hospital.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8955" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Further information is available at www.ENTEREGREMS.com or 1-800-278-0340.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8956" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients recently exposed to opioids are expected to be more sensitive to the effects of μ-opioid receptor antagonists, such as ENTEREG.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M24" type="Trigger" span="56 29" str="more sensitive to the effects"/>
<Mention id="M25" type="Precipitant" span="29 7" str="opioids" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M26" type="SpecificInteraction" span="56 62" str="more sensitive to the effects of μ-opioid receptor antagonists" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M24" precipitant="M25" effect="M26" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8957" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Since ENTEREG acts peripherally, clinical signs and symptoms of increased sensitivity would be related to the gastrointestinal tract (e.g., abdominal pain, nausea and vomiting, diarrhea).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8958" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients receiving more than 3 doses of an opioid within the week prior to surgery were not studied in the postoperative ileus clinical trials.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8959" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Therefore, if ENTEREG is administered to these patients, they should be monitored for gastrointestinal adverse reactions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8960" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients with severe hepatic impairment may be at higher risk of serious adverse reactions (including dose-related serious adverse reactions) because up to 10-fold higher plasma levels of drug have been observed in such patients compared with patients with normal hepatic function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8961" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Therefore, the use of ENTEREG is not recommended in this population.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8962" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>No studies have been conducted in patients with end-stage renal disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8963" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>ENTEREG is not recommended for use in these patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8964" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>No studies have been conducted in patients with complete gastrointestinal obstruction or in patients who have surgery for correction of complete bowel obstruction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8965" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>ENTEREG has not been studied in patients having pancreatic or gastric anastomosis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8966" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Therefore, ENTEREG is not recommended for use in these patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8967" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Alvimopan is a selective antagonist of the cloned human μ-opioid receptor with a Ki of 0.4 nM (0.2 ng/mL) and no measurable opioid-agonist effects in standard pharmacologic assays.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8968" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The dissociation of [3H]-alvimopan from the human μ-opioid receptor is slower than that of other opioid ligands, consistent with its higher affinity for the receptor.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8969" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>At concentrations of 1 to 10 µM, alvimopan demonstrated no activity at any of over 70 non-opioid receptors, enzymes, and ion channels.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8970" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Postoperative ileus is the impairment of gastrointestinal motility after intra-abdominal surgery or other, non-abdominal surgeries.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8971" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Postoperative ileus affects all segments of the gastrointestinal tract and may last from 5 to 6 days, or even longer.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8972" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This may potentially delay gastrointestinal recovery and hospital discharge until its resolution.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8973" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>It is characterized by abdominal distention and bloating, nausea, vomiting, pain, accumulation of gas and fluids in the bowel, and delayed passage of flatus and defecation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8974" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Postoperative ileus is the result of a multifactorial process that includes inhibitory sympathetic input and release of hormones, neurotransmitters, and other mediators (e.g., endogenous opioids).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8975" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A component of postoperative ileus also results from an inflammatory reaction and the effects of opioid analgesics.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8976" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Morphine and other μ-opioid receptor agonists are universally used for the treatment of acute postsurgical pain; however, they are known to have an inhibitory effect on gastrointestinal motility and may prolong the duration of postoperative ileus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8977" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following oral administration, alvimopan antagonizes the peripheral effects of opioids on gastrointestinal motility and secretion by competitively binding to gastrointestinal tract μ-opioid receptors.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8978" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The antagonism produced by alvimopan at opioid receptors is evident in isolated guinea pig ileum preparations in which alvimopan competitively antagonizes the effects of morphine on contractility.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8979" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Alvimopan achieves this selective gastrointestinal opioid antagonism without reversing the central analgesic effects of μ-opioid agonists.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8980" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In an exploratory study in healthy volunteers, alvimopan 12 mg administered twice a day reduced the delay in small and large bowel transit induced by codeine 30 mg administered 4 times a day, as measured by gastrointestinal scintigraphy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8981" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In the same study, concomitant alvimopan did not reduce the delay in gastric emptying induced by codeine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8982" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In a study designed to evaluate potential effects on cardiac conduction, alvimopan did not cause clinically significant QTc prolongation at doses up to 24 mg twice daily (twice the approved dosage regimen) for 7 days.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8983" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The potential for QTc effects at higher doses has not been studied.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8984" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following oral administration of alvimopan, an amide hydrolysis compound is present in the systemic circulation, which is considered a product exclusively of intestinal flora metabolism.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8985" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This compound is referred to as the 'metabolite'.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8986" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>It is also a μ-opioid receptor antagonist with a Ki of 0.8 nM (0.3 ng/mL).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8987" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Absorption: Following oral administration of ENTEREG capsules in healthy volunteers, plasma alvimopan concentration peaked at approximately 2 hours postdose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8988" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No significant accumulation in alvimopan concentration was observed following twice daily (BID) dosing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8989" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mean peak plasma concentration was 10.98 (±6.43) ng/mL and mean AUC0–12h was 40.2 (±22.5) ng∙h/mL after dosing of alvimopan at 12 mg BID for 5 days.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8990" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The absolute bioavailability was estimated to be 6% (range, 1% to 19%).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8991" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There was a delay in the appearance of the 'metabolite', which had a median Tmax of 36 hours following administration of a single dose of alvimopan.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8992" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Concentrations of the 'metabolite' were highly variable between subjects and within a subject.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8993" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The 'metabolite' accumulated after multiple doses of ENTEREG.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8994" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mean Cmax for the 'metabolite' after alvimopan 12 mg twice daily for 5 days was 35.73 ± 35.29 ng/mL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8995" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Concentrations of alvimopan and its 'metabolite' are higher (~1.9-fold and ~1.4-fold, respectively) in postoperative ileus patients than in healthy volunteers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8996" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Food Effects: A high-fat meal decreased the extent and rate of alvimopan absorption.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M29" type="Trigger" span="30 9;73 10" str="decreased | absorption"/>
<Mention id="M28" type="Precipitant" span="0 4" str="Food" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M30" type="Precipitant" span="16 13" str="high-fat meal" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M29" precipitant="M28" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M29" precipitant="M30" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8997" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The Cmax and AUC were decreased by approximately 38% and 21%, respectively, and the Tmax was prolonged by approximately 1 hour.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8998" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The clinical significance of this decreased bioavailability is unknown.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8999" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In postoperative ileus clinical trials, the preoperative dose of ENTEREG was administered in a fasting state.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9000" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Subsequent doses were given without regard to meals.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9001" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Distribution: The steady-state volume of distribution of alvimopan was estimated to be 30±10 L. Plasma protein binding of alvimopan and its 'metabolite' was independent of concentration over ranges observed clinically and averaged 80% and 94%, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9002" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Both alvimopan and the 'metabolite' were bound to albumin and not to alpha-1 acid glycoprotein.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9003" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Metabolism and Elimination: In vitro data suggest that alvimopan is not a substrate of CYP enzymes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9004" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The average plasma clearance for alvimopan was 402 (±89) mL/min.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9005" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Renal excretion accounted for approximately 35% of total clearance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9006" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There was no evidence that hepatic metabolism was a significant route for alvimopan elimination.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9007" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Biliary secretion was considered the primary pathway for alvimopan elimination.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9008" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Unabsorbed drug and unchanged alvimopan resulting from biliary excretion were then hydrolyzed to its 'metabolite' by gut microflora.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9009" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The 'metabolite' was eliminated in the feces and in the urine as unchanged 'metabolite', the glucuronide conjugate of the 'metabolite', and other minor metabolites.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9010" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mean terminal phase half-life of alvimopan after multiple oral doses of ENTEREG ranged from 10 to 17 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9011" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The terminal half-life of the 'metabolite' ranged from 10 to 18 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9012" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Specific Populations: Age: The pharmacokinetics of alvimopan, but not its 'metabolite', were related to age, but this effect was not clinically significant and does not warrant dosage adjustment based on increased age.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9013" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Race: The pharmacokinetic characteristics of alvimopan were not affected by Hispanic or Black race.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9014" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Plasma 'metabolite' concentrations were lower in Black and Hispanic patients (by 43% and 82%, respectively) than in Caucasian patients following alvimopan administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9015" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>These changes are not considered to be clinically significant in surgical patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9016" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Japanese healthy male volunteers had an approximately 2-fold increase in plasma alvimopan concentrations, but no change in 'metabolite' pharmacokinetics.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9017" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacokinetics of alvimopan have not been studied in subjects of other East Asian ancestry.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9018" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Dosage adjustment in Japanese patients is not required.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9019" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Gender: There was no effect of gender on the pharmacokinetics of alvimopan or the 'metabolite'.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9020" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Hepatic Impairment: Exposure to alvimopan following a single 12 mg dose tended to be higher (1.5- to 2-fold, on average) in patients with mild or moderate hepatic impairment (as defined by Child-Pugh Class A and B, n = 8 each) compared with healthy controls (n = 4).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9021" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There were no consistent effects on the Cmax or half-life of alvimopan in patients with hepatic impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9022" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>However, 2 of 16 patients with mild-to-moderate hepatic impairment had longer than expected half-lives of alvimopan, indicating that some accumulation may occur upon multiple dosing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9023" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The Cmax of the 'metabolite' tended to be more variable in patients with mild or moderate hepatic impairment than in matched normal subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9024" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A study of 3 patients with severe hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh Class C), indicated similar alvimopan exposure in 2 patients and an approximately 10-fold increase in Cmax and exposure in 1 patient with severe hepatic impairment when compared with healthy control volunteers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9025" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Renal Impairment: There was no relationship between renal function (i.e., creatinine clearance [CrCl]) and plasma alvimopan pharmacokinetics (Cmax, AUC, or half-life) in patients with mild (CrCl 51–80 mL/min), moderate (CrCl 31–50 mL/min), or severe (CrCl &lt;30 mL/min) renal impairment (n = 6 each).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9026" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Renal clearance of alvimopan was related to renal function; however, because renal clearance was only a small fraction (35%) of the total clearance, renal impairment had a small effect on the apparent oral clearance of alvimopan.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9027" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The half-lives of alvimopan were comparable in the mild, moderate, and control renal impairment groups but longer in the severe renal impairment group.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9028" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Exposure to the 'metabolite' tended to be 2- to 5-fold higher in patients with moderate or severe renal impairment compared with patients with mild renal impairment or control subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9029" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Thus, there may be accumulation of alvimopan and 'metabolite' in patients with severe renal impairment receiving multiple doses of ENTEREG.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9030" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Patients with end-stage renal disease were not studied.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9031" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Crohn's Disease: There was no relationship between disease activity in patients with Crohn's disease (measured as Crohn's Disease Activity Index or bowel movement frequency) and alvimopan pharmacokinetics (AUC or Cmax).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9032" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Patients with active or quiescent Crohn's disease had increased variability in alvimopan pharmacokinetics, and exposure tended to be 2-fold higher in patients with quiescent disease than in those with active disease or in normal subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9033" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Concentrations of the 'metabolite' were lower in patients with Crohn's disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9034" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Drug Interactions: Potential for Drugs to Affect Alvimopan Pharmacokinetics: Concomitant administration of ENTEREG with inducers or inhibitors of CYP enzymes is unlikely to alter the metabolism of alvimopan because ENTEREG is metabolized mainly by non-CYP enzyme pathway.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9035" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No clinical studies have been performed to assess the effect of concomitant administration of inducers or inhibitors of cytochrome P450 enzymes on alvimopan pharmacokinetics.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9036" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In vitro studies suggest that alvimopan and its 'metabolite' are substrates for p-glycoprotein.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9037" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A population pharmacokinetic analysis did not reveal any evidence that alvimopan or 'metabolite' pharmacokinetics were influenced by concomitant medications that are mild-to-moderate p-glycoprotein inhibitors.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9038" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No clinical studies of concomitant administration of alvimopan and strong inhibitors of p-glycoprotein (e.g., verapamil, cyclosporine, amiodarone, itraconazole, quinine, spironolactone, quinidine, diltiazem, bepridil) have been conducted.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9039" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>However, plasma concentrations of the 'metabolite' were lower in patients receiving acid blockers or preoperative oral antibiotics (49% and 81%, respectively).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9040" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No dosage adjustments are necessary in these patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9041" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Potential for Alvimopan to Affect the Pharmacokinetics of Other Drugs: Alvimopan and its 'metabolite' are not inhibitors of CYP 1A2, 2C9, 2C19, 3A4, 2D6, and 2E1 in vitro at concentrations far in excess of those observed clinically.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9042" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Alvimopan and its 'metabolite' are not inducers of CYP 1A2, 2B6, 2C9, 2C19, and 3A4.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9043" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In vitro studies also suggest that alvimopan and its 'metabolite' are not inhibitors of p-glycoprotein.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9044" LabelDrug="Entereg" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>These in vitro findings suggest that ENTEREG is unlikely to alter the pharmacokinetics of coadministered drugs through inhibition or induction of CYP enzymes or inhibition of p-glycoprotein.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="opioids" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="21522001: Abdominal pain (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="opioids" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="22298006: Myocardial infarction (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="opioids" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="422400008: Vomiting (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="opioids" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="422587007: Nausea (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="opioids" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="62315008: Diarrhea (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="opioids" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="opioids" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="food" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="high-fat meal" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54356"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>