<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Boniva" setid="841bf769-0148-42a8-a4d0-ff062b4734e8">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
BONIVA is contraindicated in patients with the following conditions: Abnormalities of the esophagus which delay esophageal emptying such as stricture or achalasia (see Warnings and Precautions [5.1] ) Inability to stand or sit upright for at least 60 minutes (see Dosage and Administration [2.2] , and Warnings and Precautions [5.1] ) Hypocalcemia (see Warnings and Precautions [5.2] ) Known hypersensitivity to BONIVA or to any of its excipients. Cases of anaphylaxis have been reported. (see Adverse Reactions [6.2] ). Abnormalities of the esophagus which delay esophageal emptying such as stricture or achalasia ( 4 , 5.1 ) Inability to stand or sit upright for at least 60 minutes ( 4 , 5.1 ) Hypocalcemia ( 4 ) Hypersensitivity to BONIVA ( 4 )</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
Take one 150 mg tablet once monthly on the same day each month ( 2.1 ) Instruct patient to: ( 2.2 ) Swallow whole tablet with 6-8 oz of plain water only, at least 60 minutes before the first food, beverage, or medication of day. Avoid lying down for at least 60 minutes after taking BONIVA. Do not eat, drink (except for water), or take other medication for 60 minutes after taking BONIVA. Take supplemental calcium and vitamin D if dietary intake inadequate ( 2.3 ) The dose of BONIVA is one 150 mg tablet taken once monthly on the same date each month. Instruct Patients to do the following: Take BONIVA at least 60 minutes before the first food or drink (other than water) of the day or before taking any oral medication or supplementation, including calcium, antacids, or vitamins to maximize absorption and clinical benefit, (see DRUG INTERACTIONS [7.1] ) . Avoid the use of water with supplements including mineral water because they may have a higher concentration of calcium. Swallow BONIVA tablets whole with a full glass of plain water (6 to 8 oz) while standing or sitting in an upright position to reduce the potential for esophageal irritation. Avoid lying down for 60 minutes after taking BONIVA (see WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS [5.1] ) . Do not chew or suck the tablet because of a potential for oropharyngeal ulceration. Do not eat, drink anything except plain water, or take other medications for at least 60 minutes after taking BONIVA. Instruct patients to take supplemental calcium and vitamin D if their dietary intake is inadequate. Avoid the use of calcium supplements within 60 minutes of BONIVA administration because co-administration of BONIVA and calcium may interfere with the absorption of ibandronate sodium (see DRUG INTERACTIONS [7.1] ) . If the once-monthly dose is missed, instruct patients to do the following: If the next scheduled BONIVA day is more than 7 days away, take one BONIVA 150 mg tablet in the morning following the date that it is remembered. If the next scheduled BONIVA day is only 1 to 7 days away, wait until the subsequent month's scheduled BONIVA day to take their tablet. For subsequent monthly doses for both of the above scenarios, instruct patients to return to their original schedule by taking one BONIVA 150 mg tablet every month on their previous chosen day.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
Calcium supplements, antacids and some oral medications may interfere with absorption of ibandronate. Do not take within 60 minutes of dosing ( 7.1 ) Use caution when co-prescribing aspirin/nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs that may worsen gastrointestinal irritation. ( 7.2 ) Products containing calcium and other multivalent cations (such as aluminum, magnesium, iron) are likely to interfere with absorption of BONIVA. Therefore, instruct patients to take BONIVA at least 60 minutes before any oral medications, including medications containing multivalent cations (such as antacids, supplements or vitamins). Also, patients should wait at least 60 minutes after dosing before taking any other oral medications (see Dosage and Administration [2.3] ). Because aspirin, NSAIDs, and bisphosphonates are all associated with gastrointestinal irritation, caution should be exercised in the concomitant use of aspirin or NSAIDs with BONIVA. In healthy volunteers, co-administration with ranitidine resulted in a 20% increased bioavailability of ibandronate, which was not considered to be clinically relevant (see CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY [12.3] ) . Bisphosphonates are known to interfere with the use of bone-imaging agents. Specific studies with ibandronate have not been performed.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
Upper gastrointestinal Adverse Reactions can occur. Instruct patients to follow dosing instructions and discontinue use if new or worsening symptoms occur. ( 5.1 ) Hypocalcemia may worsen during treatment. Correct hypocalcemia before use. ( 5.2 ) Severe Bone, Joint, and Muscle Pain may occur. Consider discontinuing use if symptoms develop. ( 5.3 ) Osteonecrosis of the Jaw has been reported. ( 5.4 ) Atypical Femur Fractures have been reported. Patients with new thigh or groin pain should be evaluated to rule out a femoral fracture. ( 5.5 ) BONIVA, like other bisphosphonates administered orally, may cause local irritation of the upper gastrointestinal mucosa. Because of these possible irritant effects and a potential for worsening of the underlying disease, caution should be used when BONIVA is given to patients with active upper gastrointestinal problems (such as known Barrett's esophagus, dysphagia, other esophageal diseases, gastritis, duodenitis or ulcers). Esophageal adverse experiences, such as esophagitis, esophageal ulcers and esophageal erosions, occasionally with bleeding and rarely followed by esophageal stricture or perforation, have been reported in patients receiving treatment with oral bisphosphonates. In some cases, these have been severe and required hospitalization. Physicians should therefore be alert to any signs or symptoms signaling a possible esophageal reaction and patients should be instructed to discontinue BONIVA and seek medical attention if they develop dysphagia, odynophagia, retrosternal pain or new or worsening heartburn. The risk of severe esophageal adverse experiences appears to be greater in patients who lie down after taking oral bisphosphonates and/or who fail to swallow it with the recommended full glass (6-8 oz) of water, and/or who continue to take oral bisphosphonates after developing symptoms suggestive of esophageal irritation. Therefore, it is very important that the full dosing instructions are provided to, and understood by, the patient (see DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION [2.2] ) . In patients who cannot comply with dosing instructions due to mental disability, therapy with BONIVA should be used under appropriate supervision. There have been post-marketing reports of gastric and duodenal ulcers with oral bisphosphonate use, some severe and with complications, although no increased risk was observed in controlled clinical trials. Hypocalcemia has been reported in patients taking BONIVA. Treat hypocalcemia and other disturbances of bone and mineral metabolism before starting BONIVA therapy. Instruct patients to take supplemental calcium and vitamin D if their dietary intake is inadequate. (see DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION [2.3] ) . Severe and occasionally incapacitating bone, joint, and/or muscle pain has been reported in patients taking BONIVA and other bisphosphonates (see ADVERSE REACTIONS [6] ) . The time to onset of symptoms varied from one day to several months after starting the drug. Most patients had relief of symptoms after stopping. A subset had recurrence of symptoms when rechallenged with the same drug or another bisphosphonate. Consider discontinuing use if severe symptoms develop. Osteonecrosis of the jaw (ONJ), which can occur spontaneously, is generally associated with tooth extraction and/or local infection with delayed healing, and has been reported in patients taking bisphosphonates, including BONIVA. Known risk factors for osteonecrosis of the jaw include invasive dental procedures (e.g., tooth extraction, dental implants, boney surgery), diagnosis of cancer, concomitant therapies (e.g., chemotherapy, corticosteroids, angiogenesis inhibitors), poor oral hygiene, and co-morbid disorders (e.g., periodontal and/or other pre-existing dental disease, anemia, coagulopathy, infection, ill-fitting dentures). The risk of ONJ may increase with duration of exposure to bisphosphonates. For patients requiring invasive dental procedures, discontinuation of bisphosphonate treatment may reduce the risk for ONJ. Clinical judgment of the treating physician and/or oral surgeon should guide the management plan of each patient based on individual benefit/risk assessment. Patients who develop osteonecrosis of the jaw while on bisphosphonate therapy should receive care by an oral surgeon. In these patients, extensive dental surgery to treat ONJ may exacerbate the condition. Discontinuation of bisphosphonate therapy should be considered based on individual benefit/risk assessment. Atypical, low-energy, or low-trauma fractures of the femoral shaft have been reported in bisphosphonate-treated patients. These fractures can occur anywhere in the femoral shaft from just below the lesser trochanter to above the supracondylar flare and are transverse or short oblique in orientation without evidence of comminution. Causality has not been established as these fractures also occur in osteoporotic patients who have not been treated with bisphosphonates. Atypical femur fractures most commonly occur with minimal or no trauma to the affected area. They may be bilateral and many patients report prodromal pain in the affected area, usually presenting as dull, aching thigh pain, weeks to months before a complete fracture occurs. A number of reports note that patients were also receiving treatment with glucocorticoids (e.g., prednisone) at the time of fracture. Any patient with a history of bisphosphonate exposure who presents with thigh or groin pain should be suspected of having an atypical fracture and should be evaluated to rule out an incomplete femur fracture. Patients presenting with an atypical fracture should also be assessed for symptoms and signs of fracture in the contralateral limb. Interruption of bisphosphonate therapy should be considered, pending a risk/benefit assessment, on an individual basis. BONIVA is not recommended for use in patients with severe renal impairment (creatinine clearance of less than 30 mL/min).</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
The action of ibandronate on bone tissue is based on its affinity for hydroxyapatite, which is part of the mineral matrix of bone. Ibandronate inhibits osteoclast activity and reduces bone resorption and turnover. In postmenopausal women, it reduces the elevated rate of bone turnover, leading to, on average, a net gain in bone mass. Osteoporosis is characterized by decreased bone mass and increased fracture risk, most commonly at the spine, hip, and wrist. The diagnosis can be confirmed by a finding of low bone mass, evidence of fracture on x-ray, a history of osteoporotic fracture, or height loss or kyphosis indicative of vertebral fracture. While osteoporosis occurs in both men and women, it is most common among women following menopause. In healthy humans, bone formation and resorption are closely linked; old bone is resorbed and replaced by newly formed bone. In postmenopausal osteoporosis, bone resorption exceeds bone formation, leading to bone loss and increased risk of fracture. After menopause, the risk of fractures of the spine and hip increases; approximately 40% of 50-year-old women will experience an osteoporosis-related fracture during their remaining lifetimes. BONIVA produced biochemical changes indicative of dose-dependent inhibition of bone resorption, including decreases of biochemical markers of bone collagen degradation (such as deoxypyridinoline, and cross-linked C-telopeptide of Type I collagen) in the daily dose range of 0.25 mg to 5 mg and once-monthly doses from 100 mg to 150 mg in postmenopausal women. Treatment with 2.5 mg daily BONIVA resulted in decreases in biochemical markers of bone turnover, including urinary C-terminal telopeptide of Type I collagen (uCTX) and serum osteocalcin, to levels similar to those in premenopausal women. Changes in markers of bone formation were observed later than changes in resorption markers, as expected, due to the coupled nature of bone resorption and formation. Treatment with 2.5 mg daily BONIVA decreased levels of uCTX within 1 month of starting treatment and decreased levels of osteocalcin within 3 months. Bone turnover markers reached a nadir of approximately 64% below baseline values by 6 months of treatment and remained stable with continued treatment for up to 3 years. Following treatment discontinuation, there is a return to pretreatment baseline rates of elevated bone resorption associated with postmenopausal osteoporosis. In a 1-year, study comparing once-monthly vs. once-daily oral dosing regimens, the median decrease from baseline in serum CTX values was -76% for patients treated with the 150 mg once-monthly regimen and -67% for patients treated with the 2.5 mg daily regimen. In a 1-year, prevention study comparing BONIVA 150 mg once-monthly to placebo, the median placebo-subtracted decrease in sCTX was -49.8%. Absorption The absorption of oral ibandronate occurs in the upper gastrointestinal tract. Plasma concentrations increase in a dose-linear manner up to 50 mg oral intake and increases nonlinearly above this dose. Following oral dosing, the time to maximum observed plasma ibandronate concentrations ranged from 0.5 to 2 hours (median 1 hour) in fasted healthy postmenopausal women. The mean oral bioavailability of 2.5 mg ibandronate was about 0.6% compared to intravenous dosing. The extent of absorption is impaired by food or beverages (other than plain water). The oral bioavailability of ibandronate is reduced by about 90% when BONIVA is administered concomitantly with a standard breakfast in comparison with bioavailability observed in fasted subjects. There is no meaningful reduction in bioavailability when ibandronate is taken at least 60 minutes before a meal. However, both bioavailability and the effect on bone mineral density (BMD) are reduced when food or beverages are taken less than 60 minutes following an ibandronate dose. Distribution After absorption, ibandronate either rapidly binds to bone or is excreted into urine. In humans, the apparent terminal volume of distribution is at least 90 L, and the amount of dose removed from the circulation via the bone is estimated to be 40% to 50% of the circulating dose. In vitro protein binding in human serum was 99.5% to 90.9% over an ibandronate concentration range of 2 to 10 ng/mL in one study and approximately 85.7% over a concentration range of 0.5 to 10 ng/mL in another study. Metabolism Ibandronate does not undergo hepatic metabolism and does not inhibit the hepatic cytochrome P450 system. Ibandronate is eliminated by renal excretion. Based on a rat study, the ibandronate secretory pathway does not appear to include known acidic or basic transport systems involved in the excretion of other drugs. There is no evidence that ibandronate is metabolized in humans. Elimination The portion of ibandronate that is not removed from the circulation via bone absorption is eliminated unchanged by the kidney (approximately 50% to 60% of the absorbed dose). Unabsorbed ibandronate is eliminated unchanged in the feces. The plasma elimination of ibandronate is multiphasic. Its renal clearance and distribution into bone accounts for a rapid and early decline in plasma concentrations, reaching 10% of the C max within 3 or 8 hours after intravenous or oral administration, respectively. This is followed by a slower clearance phase as ibandronate redistributes back into the blood from bone. The observed apparent terminal half-life for ibandronate is generally dependent on the dose studied and on assay sensitivity. The observed apparent terminal half-life for the 150 mg ibandronate tablet upon oral administration to healthy postmenopausal women ranges from 37 to 157 hours. Total clearance of ibandronate is low, with average values in the range 84 to 160 mL/min. Renal clearance (about 60 mL/min in healthy postmenopausal females) accounts for 50% to 60% of total clearance and is related to creatinine clearance. The difference between the apparent total and renal clearances likely reflects bone uptake of the drug. Specific Populations Pediatrics The pharmacokinetics of ibandronate has not been studied in patients less than 18 years of age. Geriatric Because ibandronate is not known to be metabolized, the only difference in ibandronate elimination for geriatric patients versus younger patients is expected to relate to progressive age-related changes in renal function. Gender The bioavailability and pharmacokinetics of ibandronate are similar in both men and women. Race Pharmacokinetic differences due to race have not been studied. Renal Impairment Renal clearance of ibandronate in patients with various degrees of renal impairment is linearly related to creatinine clearance (CLcr). Following a single dose of 0.5 mg ibandronate by intravenous administration, patients with CLcr 40 to 70 mL/min had 55% higher exposure (AUC ∞ ) than the exposure observed in subjects with CLcr greater than 90 mL/min. Patients with CLcr less than 30 mL/min had more than a two-fold increase in exposure compared to the exposure for healthy subjects (see DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION [2.4] ) . Hepatic Impairment No studies have been performed to assess the pharmacokinetics of ibandronate in patients with hepatic impairment because ibandronate is not metabolized in the human liver. Drug Interaction Studies Products containing calcium and other multivalent cations (such as aluminum, magnesium, iron), including milk, food, and antacids are likely to interfere with absorption of ibandronate, which is consistent with findings in animal studies. H2 Blockers A pharmacokinetic interaction study in healthy volunteers demonstrated that 75 mg ranitidine (25 mg injected intravenously 90 and 15 minutes before and 30 minutes after ibandronate administration) increased the oral bioavailability of 10 mg ibandronate by about 20%. This degree of increase is not considered to be clinically relevant.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="9206" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>BONIVA is contraindicated in patients with the following conditions: Abnormalities of the esophagus which delay esophageal emptying such as stricture or achalasia Inability to stand or sit upright for at least 60 minutes Hypocalcemia Known hypersensitivity to BONIVA or to any of its excipients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9207" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Abnormalities of the esophagus which delay esophageal emptying such as stricture or achalasia (4, 5.1) Inability to stand or sit upright for at least 60 minutes (4, 5.1) Hypocalcemia (4) Hypersensitivity to BONIVA (4)</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9208" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Take one 150 mg tablet once monthly on the same day each month (2.1) Instruct patient to: (2.2) Swallow whole tablet with 6-8 oz of plain water only, at least 60 minutes before the first food, beverage, or medication of day.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M1" type="Trigger" span="0 4;170 6" str="Take | before"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="187 4" str="food" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M1" precipitant="M2"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9209" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Avoid lying down for at least 60 minutes after taking BONIVA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9210" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not eat, drink (except for water), or take other medication for 60 minutes after taking BONIVA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9211" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Take supplemental calcium and vitamin D if dietary intake inadequate (2.3) The dose of BONIVA is one 150 mg tablet taken once monthly on the same date each month.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9212" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Instruct Patients to do the following: Take BONIVA at least 60 minutes before the first food or drink (other than water) of the day or before taking any oral medication or supplementation, including calcium, antacids, or vitamins to maximize absorption and clinical benefit,.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M9" type="Trigger" span="39 4;71 6" str="Take | before"/>
<Mention id="M4" type="Precipitant" span="208 8" str="antacids" code="N0000029169 | N0000008295"/>
<Mention id="M6" type="Precipitant" span="199 7" str="calcium" code="SY7Q814VUP"/>
<Mention id="M8" type="Precipitant" span="88 4" str="food" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M10" type="Precipitant" span="221 8" str="vitamins" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M9" precipitant="M4"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M9" precipitant="M6"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M9" precipitant="M8"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M9" precipitant="M10"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9213" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Avoid the use of water with supplements including mineral water because they may have a higher concentration of calcium.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M15" type="Trigger" span="0 5" str="Avoid"/>
<Mention id="M12" type="Precipitant" span="112 7" str="calcium" code="SY7Q814VUP"/>
<Mention id="M14" type="Precipitant" span="50 13" str="mineral water" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M16" type="Precipitant" span="17 22" str="water with supplements" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M15" precipitant="M12"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M15" precipitant="M14"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M15" precipitant="M16"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9214" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Swallow BONIVA tablets whole with a full glass of plain water (6 to 8 oz) while standing or sitting in an upright position to reduce the potential for esophageal irritation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9215" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Avoid lying down for 60 minutes after taking BONIVA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9216" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not chew or suck the tablet because of a potential for oropharyngeal ulceration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9217" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not eat, drink anything except plain water, or take other medications for at least 60 minutes after taking BONIVA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9218" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Instruct patients to take supplemental calcium and vitamin D if their dietary intake is inadequate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9219" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Avoid the use of calcium supplements within 60 minutes of BONIVA administration because co-administration of BONIVA and calcium may interfere with the absorption of ibandronate sodium.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M17" type="Trigger" span="132 29" str="interfere with the absorption"/>
<Mention id="M18" type="Precipitant" span="17 7" str="calcium" code="SY7Q814VUP"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M17" precipitant="M18" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9220" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If the once-monthly dose is missed, instruct patients to do the following: If the next scheduled BONIVA day is more than 7 days away, take one BONIVA 150 mg tablet in the morning following the date that it is remembered.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9221" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If the next scheduled BONIVA day is only 1 to 7 days away, wait until the subsequent month's scheduled BONIVA day to take their tablet.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9222" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For subsequent monthly doses for both of the above scenarios, instruct patients to return to their original schedule by taking one BONIVA 150 mg tablet every month on their previous chosen day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9223" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Calcium supplements, antacids and some oral medications may interfere with absorption of ibandronate.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M21" type="Trigger" span="60 25" str="interfere with absorption"/>
<Mention id="M20" type="Precipitant" span="21 8" str="antacids" code="N0000029169 | N0000008295"/>
<Mention id="M22" type="Precipitant" span="0 19" str="Calcium supplements" code="N0000175901"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M21" precipitant="M20" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M21" precipitant="M22" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9224" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Do not take within 60 minutes of dosing (7.1) Use caution when co-prescribing aspirin/nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs that may worsen gastrointestinal irritation.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M26" type="Trigger" span="132 6" str="worsen"/>
<Mention id="M24" type="Precipitant" span="78 7" str="aspirin" code="N0000006582 | R16CO5Y76E"/>
<Mention id="M28" type="SpecificInteraction" span="139 27" str="gastrointestinal irritation" code="95516005: Gastrointestinal irritation (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M27" type="Precipitant" span="86 36" str="nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs" code="N0000175722"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M26" precipitant="M24" effect="M28" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M26" precipitant="M27" effect="M28" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9225" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Products containing calcium and other multivalent cations (such as aluminum, magnesium, iron) are likely to interfere with absorption of BONIVA.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M47" type="Trigger" span="108 25" str="interfere with absorption"/>
<Mention id="M30" type="Precipitant" span="67 8" str="aluminum" code="CPD4NFA903"/>
<Mention id="M32" type="Precipitant" span="20 7" str="calcium" code="SY7Q814VUP"/>
<Mention id="M34" type="Precipitant" span="88 4" str="iron" code="E1UOL152H7"/>
<Mention id="M36" type="Precipitant" span="77 9" str="magnesium" code="I38ZP9992A"/>
<Mention id="M38" type="Precipitant" span="38 19" str="multivalent cations" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M40" type="Precipitant" span="0 19;67 8" str="Products containing | aluminum" code="CPD4NFA903"/>
<Mention id="M42" type="Precipitant" span="0 19;88 4" str="Products containing | iron" code="E1UOL152H7"/>
<Mention id="M44" type="Precipitant" span="0 19;77 9" str="Products containing | magnesium" code="I38ZP9992A"/>
<Mention id="M46" type="Precipitant" span="0 19;38 19" str="Products containing | multivalent cations" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M48" type="Precipitant" span="0 27" str="Products containing calcium" code="SY7Q814VUP"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M47" precipitant="M30" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M47" precipitant="M32" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M47" precipitant="M34" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M47" precipitant="M36" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M47" precipitant="M38" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M47" precipitant="M40" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M47" precipitant="M42" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M47" precipitant="M44" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M47" precipitant="M46" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M47" precipitant="M48" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9226" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Therefore, instruct patients to take BONIVA at least 60 minutes before any oral medications, including medications containing multivalent cations (such as antacids, supplements or vitamins).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M49" type="Trigger" span="32 4;64 6" str="take | before"/>
<Mention id="M50" type="Precipitant" span="75 16;115 30" str="oral medications | containing multivalent cations" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M49" precipitant="M50"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9227" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Also, patients should wait at least 60 minutes after dosing before taking any other oral medications.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9228" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Because aspirin, NSAIDs, and bisphosphonates are all associated with gastrointestinal irritation, caution should be exercised in the concomitant use of aspirin or NSAIDs with BONIVA.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M57" type="Trigger" span="53 15" str="associated with"/>
<Mention id="M52" type="Precipitant" span="8 7" str="aspirin" code="N0000006582 | R16CO5Y76E"/>
<Mention id="M59" type="SpecificInteraction" span="69 27" str="gastrointestinal irritation" code="95516005: Gastrointestinal irritation (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M55" type="Precipitant" span="29 15" str="bisphosphonates" code="N0000175579"/>
<Mention id="M58" type="Precipitant" span="17 6" str="NSAIDs" code="N0000175722"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M57" precipitant="M52" effect="M59" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M57" precipitant="M55" effect="M59" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M57" precipitant="M58" effect="M59" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9229" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>In healthy volunteers, co-administration with ranitidine resulted in a 20% increased bioavailability of ibandronate, which was not considered to be clinically relevant.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M60" type="Trigger" span="75 25" str="increased bioavailability"/>
<Mention id="M61" type="Precipitant" span="46 10" str="ranitidine" code="884KT10YB7"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M60" precipitant="M61" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9230" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Bisphosphonates are known to interfere with the use of bone-imaging agents.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M62" type="Trigger" span="29 14" str="interfere with"/>
<Mention id="M63" type="Precipitant" span="55 19" str="bone-imaging agents" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I29" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M62" precipitant="M63"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9231" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Specific studies with ibandronate have not been performed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9232" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Upper gastrointestinal Adverse Reactions can occur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9233" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Instruct patients to follow dosing instructions and discontinue use if new or worsening symptoms occur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9234" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hypocalcemia may worsen during treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9235" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Severe Bone, Joint, and Muscle Pain may occur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9236" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Consider discontinuing use if symptoms develop.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9237" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Osteonecrosis of the Jaw has been reported.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9238" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Atypical Femur Fractures have been reported.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9239" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients with new thigh or groin pain should be evaluated to rule out a femoral fracture.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9240" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>BONIVA, like other bisphosphonates administered orally, may cause local irritation of the upper gastrointestinal mucosa.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9241" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Because of these possible irritant effects and a potential for worsening of the underlying disease, caution should be used when BONIVA is given to patients with active upper gastrointestinal problems (such as known Barrett's esophagus, dysphagia, other esophageal diseases, gastritis, duodenitis or ulcers).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9242" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Esophageal adverse experiences, such as esophagitis, esophageal ulcers and esophageal erosions, occasionally with bleeding and rarely followed by esophageal stricture or perforation, have been reported in patients receiving treatment with oral bisphosphonates.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9243" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In some cases, these have been severe and required hospitalization.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9244" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Physicians should therefore be alert to any signs or symptoms signaling a possible esophageal reaction and patients should be instructed to discontinue BONIVA and seek medical attention if they develop dysphagia, odynophagia, retrosternal pain or new or worsening heartburn.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9245" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The risk of severe esophageal adverse experiences appears to be greater in patients who lie down after taking oral bisphosphonates and/or who fail to swallow it with the recommended full glass (6-8 oz) of water, and/or who continue to take oral bisphosphonates after developing symptoms suggestive of esophageal irritation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9246" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Therefore, it is very important that the full dosing instructions are provided to, and understood by, the patient.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9247" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In patients who cannot comply with dosing instructions due to mental disability, therapy with BONIVA should be used under appropriate supervision.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9248" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There have been post-marketing reports of gastric and duodenal ulcers with oral bisphosphonate use, some severe and with complications, although no increased risk was observed in controlled clinical trials.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9249" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hypocalcemia has been reported in patients taking BONIVA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9250" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Treat hypocalcemia and other disturbances of bone and mineral metabolism before starting BONIVA therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9251" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Severe and occasionally incapacitating bone, joint, and/or muscle pain has been reported in patients taking BONIVA and other bisphosphonates.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9252" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The time to onset of symptoms varied from one day to several months after starting the drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9253" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Most patients had relief of symptoms after stopping.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9254" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>A subset had recurrence of symptoms when rechallenged with the same drug or another bisphosphonate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9255" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Consider discontinuing use if severe symptoms develop.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9256" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Osteonecrosis of the jaw (ONJ), which can occur spontaneously, is generally associated with tooth extraction and/or local infection with delayed healing, and has been reported in patients taking bisphosphonates, including BONIVA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9257" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Known risk factors for osteonecrosis of the jaw include invasive dental procedures (e.g., tooth extraction, dental implants, boney surgery), diagnosis of cancer, concomitant therapies (e.g., chemotherapy, corticosteroids, angiogenesis inhibitors), poor oral hygiene, and co-morbid disorders (e.g., periodontal and/or other pre-existing dental disease, anemia, coagulopathy, infection, ill-fitting dentures).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M70" type="Trigger" span="6 12" str="risk factors"/>
<Mention id="M65" type="Precipitant" span="222 23" str="angiogenesis inhibitors" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M72" type="SpecificInteraction" span="23 24" str="osteonecrosis of the jaw" code="441809006: Aseptic necrosis of bone of jaw (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M68" type="Precipitant" span="191 12" str="chemotherapy" code="N0000178307"/>
<Mention id="M71" type="Precipitant" span="205 15" str="corticosteroids" code="N0000011309 | N0000175576"/>
<Interaction id="I30" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M70" precipitant="M65" effect="M72" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I31" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M70" precipitant="M68" effect="M72" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I32" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M70" precipitant="M71" effect="M72" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9258" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The risk of ONJ may increase with duration of exposure to bisphosphonates.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9259" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>For patients requiring invasive dental procedures, discontinuation of bisphosphonate treatment may reduce the risk for ONJ.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9260" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Clinical judgment of the treating physician and/or oral surgeon should guide the management plan of each patient based on individual benefit/risk assessment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9261" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients who develop osteonecrosis of the jaw while on bisphosphonate therapy should receive care by an oral surgeon.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9262" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In these patients, extensive dental surgery to treat ONJ may exacerbate the condition.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9263" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Discontinuation of bisphosphonate therapy should be considered based on individual benefit/risk assessment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9264" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Atypical, low-energy, or low-trauma fractures of the femoral shaft have been reported in bisphosphonate-treated patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9265" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>These fractures can occur anywhere in the femoral shaft from just below the lesser trochanter to above the supracondylar flare and are transverse or short oblique in orientation without evidence of comminution.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9266" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Causality has not been established as these fractures also occur in osteoporotic patients who have not been treated with bisphosphonates.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9267" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Atypical femur fractures most commonly occur with minimal or no trauma to the affected area.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9268" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>They may be bilateral and many patients report prodromal pain in the affected area, usually presenting as dull, aching thigh pain, weeks to months before a complete fracture occurs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9269" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>A number of reports note that patients were also receiving treatment with glucocorticoids (e.g., prednisone) at the time of fracture.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M78" type="SpecificInteraction" span="124 8" str="fracture" code="125605004: Fracture of bone (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M74" type="Precipitant" span="74 15" str="glucocorticoids" code="N0000029312 | N0000175576"/>
<Mention id="M77" type="Precipitant" span="97 10" str="prednisone" code="VB0R961HZT"/>
<Interaction id="I33" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M78" precipitant="M74" effect="M78" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I34" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M78" precipitant="M77" effect="M78" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9270" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Any patient with a history of bisphosphonate exposure who presents with thigh or groin pain should be suspected of having an atypical fracture and should be evaluated to rule out an incomplete femur fracture.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9271" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients presenting with an atypical fracture should also be assessed for symptoms and signs of fracture in the contralateral limb.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9272" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Interruption of bisphosphonate therapy should be considered, pending a risk/benefit assessment, on an individual basis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9273" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>BONIVA is not recommended for use in patients with severe renal impairment (creatinine clearance of less than 30 mL/min).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9274" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The action of ibandronate on bone tissue is based on its affinity for hydroxyapatite, which is part of the mineral matrix of bone.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9275" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Ibandronate inhibits osteoclast activity and reduces bone resorption and turnover.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9276" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In postmenopausal women, it reduces the elevated rate of bone turnover, leading to, on average, a net gain in bone mass.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9277" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Osteoporosis is characterized by decreased bone mass and increased fracture risk, most commonly at the spine, hip, and wrist.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9278" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The diagnosis can be confirmed by a finding of low bone mass, evidence of fracture on x-ray, a history of osteoporotic fracture, or height loss or kyphosis indicative of vertebral fracture.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9279" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>While osteoporosis occurs in both men and women, it is most common among women following menopause.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9280" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In healthy humans, bone formation and resorption are closely linked; old bone is resorbed and replaced by newly formed bone.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9281" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In postmenopausal osteoporosis, bone resorption exceeds bone formation, leading to bone loss and increased risk of fracture.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9282" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>After menopause, the risk of fractures of the spine and hip increases; approximately 40% of 50-year-old women will experience an osteoporosis-related fracture during their remaining lifetimes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9283" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>BONIVA produced biochemical changes indicative of dose-dependent inhibition of bone resorption, including decreases of biochemical markers of bone collagen degradation (such as deoxypyridinoline, and cross-linked C-telopeptide of Type I collagen) in the daily dose range of 0.25 mg to 5 mg and once-monthly doses from 100 mg to 150 mg in postmenopausal women.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9284" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Treatment with 2.5 mg daily BONIVA resulted in decreases in biochemical markers of bone turnover, including urinary C-terminal telopeptide of Type I collagen (uCTX) and serum osteocalcin, to levels similar to those in premenopausal women.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9285" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Changes in markers of bone formation were observed later than changes in resorption markers, as expected, due to the coupled nature of bone resorption and formation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9286" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Treatment with 2.5 mg daily BONIVA decreased levels of uCTX within 1 month of starting treatment and decreased levels of osteocalcin within 3 months.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9287" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Bone turnover markers reached a nadir of approximately 64% below baseline values by 6 months of treatment and remained stable with continued treatment for up to 3 years.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9288" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following treatment discontinuation, there is a return to pretreatment baseline rates of elevated bone resorption associated with postmenopausal osteoporosis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9289" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In a 1-year, study comparing once-monthly vs. once-daily oral dosing regimens, the median decrease from baseline in serum CTX values was -76% for patients treated with the 150 mg once-monthly regimen and -67% for patients treated with the 2.5 mg daily regimen.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9290" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In a 1-year, prevention study comparing BONIVA 150 mg once-monthly to placebo, the median placebo-subtracted decrease in sCTX was -49.8%.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9291" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Absorption The absorption of oral ibandronate occurs in the upper gastrointestinal tract.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9292" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Plasma concentrations increase in a dose-linear manner up to 50 mg oral intake and increases nonlinearly above this dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9293" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following oral dosing, the time to maximum observed plasma ibandronate concentrations ranged from 0.5 to 2 hours (median 1 hour) in fasted healthy postmenopausal women.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9294" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mean oral bioavailability of 2.5 mg ibandronate was about 0.6% compared to intravenous dosing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9295" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The extent of absorption is impaired by food or beverages (other than plain water).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M79" type="Trigger" span="14 22" str="absorption is impaired"/>
<Mention id="M80" type="Precipitant" span="40 4" str="food" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I35" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M79" precipitant="M80" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9296" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The oral bioavailability of ibandronate is reduced by about 90% when BONIVA is administered concomitantly with a standard breakfast in comparison with bioavailability observed in fasted subjects.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M81" type="Trigger" span="9 15;43 7" str="bioavailability | reduced"/>
<Mention id="M82" type="Precipitant" span="113 18" str="standard breakfast" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I36" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M81" precipitant="M82" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9297" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There is no meaningful reduction in bioavailability when ibandronate is taken at least 60 minutes before a meal.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9298" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>However, both bioavailability and the effect on bone mineral density (BMD) are reduced when food or beverages are taken less than 60 minutes following an ibandronate dose.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M83" type="Trigger" span="38 6;79 7" str="effect | reduced"/>
<Mention id="M87" type="Precipitant" span="92 4" str="food" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M85" type="SpecificInteraction" span="38 30;79 7" str="effect on bone mineral density | reduced" code="449781000: Bone density below reference range (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M86" type="Trigger" span="14 15;79 7" str="bioavailability | reduced"/>
<Interaction id="I37" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M83" precipitant="M87" effect="M85" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I38" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M86" precipitant="M87" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9299" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Distribution After absorption, ibandronate either rapidly binds to bone or is excreted into urine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9300" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In humans, the apparent terminal volume of distribution is at least 90 L, and the amount of dose removed from the circulation via the bone is estimated to be 40% to 50% of the circulating dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9301" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In vitro protein binding in human serum was 99.5% to 90.9% over an ibandronate concentration range of 2 to 10 ng/mL in one study and approximately 85.7% over a concentration range of 0.5 to 10 ng/mL in another study.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9302" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Metabolism Ibandronate does not undergo hepatic metabolism and does not inhibit the hepatic cytochrome P450 system.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9303" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Ibandronate is eliminated by renal excretion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9304" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Based on a rat study, the ibandronate secretory pathway does not appear to include known acidic or basic transport systems involved in the excretion of other drugs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9305" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There is no evidence that ibandronate is metabolized in humans.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9306" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Elimination The portion of ibandronate that is not removed from the circulation via bone absorption is eliminated unchanged by the kidney (approximately 50% to 60% of the absorbed dose).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9307" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Unabsorbed ibandronate is eliminated unchanged in the feces.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9308" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The plasma elimination of ibandronate is multiphasic.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9309" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Its renal clearance and distribution into bone accounts for a rapid and early decline in plasma concentrations, reaching 10% of the Cmax within 3 or 8 hours after intravenous or oral administration, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9310" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This is followed by a slower clearance phase as ibandronate redistributes back into the blood from bone.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9311" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The observed apparent terminal half-life for ibandronate is generally dependent on the dose studied and on assay sensitivity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9312" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The observed apparent terminal half-life for the 150 mg ibandronate tablet upon oral administration to healthy postmenopausal women ranges from 37 to 157 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9313" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Total clearance of ibandronate is low, with average values in the range 84 to 160 mL/min.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9314" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Renal clearance (about 60 mL/min in healthy postmenopausal females) accounts for 50% to 60% of total clearance and is related to creatinine clearance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9315" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The difference between the apparent total and renal clearances likely reflects bone uptake of the drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9316" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Specific Populations Pediatrics The pharmacokinetics of ibandronate has not been studied in patients less than 18 years of age.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9317" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Geriatric Because ibandronate is not known to be metabolized, the only difference in ibandronate elimination for geriatric patients versus younger patients is expected to relate to progressive age-related changes in renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9318" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Gender The bioavailability and pharmacokinetics of ibandronate are similar in both men and women.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9319" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Race Pharmacokinetic differences due to race have not been studied.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9320" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Renal Impairment Renal clearance of ibandronate in patients with various degrees of renal impairment is linearly related to creatinine clearance (CLcr).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9321" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following a single dose of 0.5 mg ibandronate by intravenous administration, patients with CLcr 40 to 70 mL/min had 55% higher exposure (AUC∞) than the exposure observed in subjects with CLcr greater than 90 mL/min.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9322" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Patients with CLcr less than 30 mL/min had more than a two-fold increase in exposure compared to the exposure for healthy subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9323" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Hepatic Impairment No studies have been performed to assess the pharmacokinetics of ibandronate in patients with hepatic impairment because ibandronate is not metabolized in the human liver.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9324" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Drug Interaction Studies Products containing calcium and other multivalent cations (such as aluminum, magnesium, iron), including milk, food, and antacids are likely to interfere with absorption of ibandronate, which is consistent with findings in animal studies.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M112" type="Trigger" span="169 25" str="interfere with absorption"/>
<Mention id="M89" type="Precipitant" span="92 8" str="aluminum" code="CPD4NFA903"/>
<Mention id="M91" type="Precipitant" span="146 8" str="antacids" code="N0000029169 | N0000008295"/>
<Mention id="M93" type="Precipitant" span="45 7" str="calcium" code="SY7Q814VUP"/>
<Mention id="M95" type="Precipitant" span="136 4" str="food" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M97" type="Precipitant" span="113 4" str="iron" code="E1UOL152H7"/>
<Mention id="M99" type="Precipitant" span="102 9" str="magnesium" code="I38ZP9992A"/>
<Mention id="M101" type="Precipitant" span="130 4" str="milk" code="917J3173FT"/>
<Mention id="M103" type="Precipitant" span="63 19" str="multivalent cations" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M105" type="Precipitant" span="25 19;92 8" str="Products containing | aluminum" code="CPD4NFA903"/>
<Mention id="M107" type="Precipitant" span="25 19;113 4" str="Products containing | iron" code="E1UOL152H7"/>
<Mention id="M109" type="Precipitant" span="25 19;102 9" str="Products containing | magnesium" code="I38ZP9992A"/>
<Mention id="M111" type="Precipitant" span="25 19;63 19" str="Products containing | multivalent cations" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M113" type="Precipitant" span="25 27" str="Products containing calcium" code="SY7Q814VUP"/>
<Interaction id="I39" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M112" precipitant="M89" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I40" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M112" precipitant="M91" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I41" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M112" precipitant="M93" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I42" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M112" precipitant="M95" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I43" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M112" precipitant="M97" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I44" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M112" precipitant="M99" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I45" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M112" precipitant="M101" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I46" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M112" precipitant="M103" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I47" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M112" precipitant="M105" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I48" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M112" precipitant="M107" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I49" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M112" precipitant="M109" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I50" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M112" precipitant="M111" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I51" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M112" precipitant="M113" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9325" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>H2 Blockers A pharmacokinetic interaction study in healthy volunteers demonstrated that 75 mg ranitidine (25 mg injected intravenously 90 and 15 minutes before and 30 minutes after ibandronate administration) increased the oral bioavailability of 10 mg ibandronate by about 20%.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M116" type="Trigger" span="209 34" str="increased the oral bioavailability"/>
<Mention id="M115" type="Precipitant" span="0 11" str="H2 Blockers" code="N0000000151"/>
<Mention id="M117" type="Precipitant" span="94 10" str="ranitidine" code="884KT10YB7"/>
<Interaction id="I52" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M116" precipitant="M115" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I53" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M116" precipitant="M117" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9326" LabelDrug="Boniva" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This degree of increase is not considered to be clinically relevant.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="food" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="449781000: Bone density below reference range (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="food" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="food" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="antacids" precipitantCode="N0000029169 | N0000008295" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="antacids" precipitantCode="N0000029169 | N0000008295"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="calcium" precipitantCode="SY7Q814VUP" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="calcium" precipitantCode="SY7Q814VUP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="vitamins" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="mineral water" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="water with supplements" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="calcium supplements" precipitantCode="N0000175901" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="aspirin" precipitantCode="N0000006582 | R16CO5Y76E" effect="95516005: Gastrointestinal irritation (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="95516005: Gastrointestinal irritation (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="aluminum" precipitantCode="CPD4NFA903" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="iron" precipitantCode="E1UOL152H7" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="magnesium" precipitantCode="I38ZP9992A" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="multivalent cations" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="products containing | aluminum" precipitantCode="CPD4NFA903" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="products containing | iron" precipitantCode="E1UOL152H7" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="products containing | magnesium" precipitantCode="I38ZP9992A" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="products containing | multivalent cations" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="products containing calcium" precipitantCode="SY7Q814VUP" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="oral medications | containing multivalent cations" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="bisphosphonates" precipitantCode="N0000175579" effect="95516005: Gastrointestinal irritation (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nsaids" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="95516005: Gastrointestinal irritation (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="ranitidine" precipitantCode="884KT10YB7" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="bone-imaging agents" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="angiogenesis inhibitors" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="441809006: Aseptic necrosis of bone of jaw (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="chemotherapy" precipitantCode="N0000178307" effect="441809006: Aseptic necrosis of bone of jaw (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="corticosteroids" precipitantCode="N0000011309 | N0000175576" effect="441809006: Aseptic necrosis of bone of jaw (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="glucocorticoids" precipitantCode="N0000029312 | N0000175576" effect="125605004: Fracture of bone (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="prednisone" precipitantCode="VB0R961HZT" effect="125605004: Fracture of bone (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="standard breakfast" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="milk" precipitantCode="917J3173FT" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="h2 blockers" precipitantCode="N0000000151" effect="C54355"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>