<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Ogestrel" setid="90b9421c-5865-43c5-a984-49351e1f20a1">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
Combination oral contraceptives should not be used in women with any of the following conditions: Thrombophlebitis or thromboembolic disorders A past history of deep-vein thrombophlebitis or thromboembolic disorders Cerebral-vascular or coronary-artery disease (current or history) Valvular heart disease with thrombogenic complications Thrombogenic rhythm disorders Major surgery with prolonged immobilization Diabetes with vascular involvement Headaches with focal neurological symptoms Uncontrolled hypertension Known or suspected carcinoma of the breast or personal history of breast cancer Carcinoma of the endometrium or other known or suspected estrogen-dependent neoplasia Undiagnosed abnormal genital bleeding Cholestatic jaundice of pregnancy or jaundice with prior pill use Hepatic adenomas or carcinomas, or active liver disease, as long as liver function has not returned to normal Known or suspected pregnancy Hypersensitivity to any of the components of Ogestrel ® Are receiving Hepatitis C drug combinations containing ombitasvir/paritaprevir/ritonavir, with or without dasabuvir, due to the potential for ALT elevations (see WARNINGS, Risk of Liver Enzyme Elevations with Concomitant Hepatitis C Treatment ).</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
To achieve maximum contraceptive effectiveness, Ogestrel must be taken exactly as directed and at intervals not exceeding 24 hours. The possibility of ovulation and conception prior to initiation of medication should be considered. The dosage of Ogestrel is one white tablet daily for 21 consecutive days, followed by one peach inert tablet daily for 7 consecutive days, according to prescribed schedule. It is recommended that Ogestrel tablets be taken at the same time each day. During the first cycle of medication, the patient is instructed to begin taking Ogestrel on the first Sunday after the onset of menstruation. If menstruation begins on a Sunday, the first tablet (white) is taken that day. One white tablet should be taken daily for 21 consecutive days followed by one peach inert tablet daily for 7 consecutive days. Withdrawal bleeding should usually occur within three days following discontinuation of white tablets and may not have finished before the next pack is started. During the first cycle, contraceptive reliance should not be placed on Ogestrel until a white tablet has been taken daily for 7 consecutive days and a non-hormonal back-up method of birth control should be used during those 7 days. The possibility of ovulation and conception prior to initiation of medication should be considered. The patient begins her next and all subsequent 28-day courses of tablets on the same day of the week (Sunday) on which she began her first course, following the same schedule: 21 days on white tablets—7 days on peach inert tablets. If in any cycle the patient starts tablets later than the proper day, she should protect herself against pregnancy by using a non-hormonal back-up method of birth control until she has taken a white tablet daily for 7 consecutive days. When the patient is switching from a 21-day regimen of tablets, she should wait 7 days after her last tablet before she starts Ogestrel. She will probably experience withdrawal bleeding during that week. She should be sure that no more than 7 days pass after her previous 21-day regimen. When the patient is switching from a 28-day regimen of tablets, she should start her first pack of Ogestrel on the day after her last tablet. She should not wait any days between packs. The patient may switch any day from a progestin-only pill and should begin Ogestrel the next day. If switching from an implant or injection, the patient should start Ogestrel on the day of implant removal or, if using an injection, the day the next injection would be due. In switching from a progestin-only pill, injection, or implant, the patient should be advised to use a non-hormonal back-up method of birth control for the first 7 days of tablet-taking. If spotting or breakthrough bleeding occurs, the patient is instructed to continue on the same regimen. This type of bleeding is usually transient and without significance; however, if the bleeding is persistent or prolonged, the patient is advised to consult her health care professional. Although pregnancy is unlikely if Ogestrel is taken according to directions, if withdrawal bleeding does not occur, the possibility of pregnancy must be considered. If the patient has not adhered to the prescribed schedule (missed one or more tablets or started taking them on a day later than she should have), the probability of pregnancy should be considered at the time of the first missed period and appropriate diagnostic measures taken. If the patient has adhered to the prescribed regimen and misses two consecutive periods, pregnancy should be ruled out. Hormonal contraceptives should be discontinued if pregnancy is confirmed. For additional patient instructions regarding missed tablets, see the “ WHAT TO DO IF YOU MISS PILLS ” section in the DETAILED PATIENT LABELING below. Any time the patient misses two or more white tablets, she should also use another method of contraception until she has taken a white tablet daily for seven consecutive days. If the patient misses one or more peach tablets, she is still protected against pregnancy provided she begins taking white tablets again on the proper day. If breakthrough bleeding occurs following missed white tablets, it will usually be transient and of no consequence. The possibility of ovulation increases with each successive day that scheduled white tablets are missed. Ogestrel may be initiated no earlier than day 28 postpartum in the non-lactating mother due to the increased risk for thromboembolism (see CONTRAINDICATIONS , WARNINGS , and PRECAUTIONS concerning thromboembolic disease). The patient should be advised to use a non-hormonal back-up method for the first 7 days of tablet-taking. However, if intercourse has already occurred, the possibility of ovulation and conception prior to initiation of medication should be considered. In the case of first-trimester abortion, if the patient starts Ogestrel immediately, additional contraceptive measures are not needed.</Section>
<Section name="PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="42232-9">
1. General Patients should be counseled that oral contraceptives do not protect against transmission of HIV (AIDS) and other sexually transmitted diseases (STDs) such as chlamydia, genital herpes, genital warts, gonorrhea, hepatitis B, and syphilis. 2. Physical Examination and Follow-Up A periodic personal and family medical history and complete physical examination are appropriate for all women, including women using oral contraceptives. The physical examination, however, may be deferred until after initiation of oral contraceptives if requested by the woman and judged appropriate by the clinician. The physical examination should include special reference to blood pressure, breasts, abdomen and pelvic organs, including cervical cytology, and relevant laboratory tests. In case of undiagnosed, persistent or recurrent abnormal vaginal bleeding, appropriate diagnostic measures should be conducted to rule out malignancy. Women with a strong family history of breast cancer or who have breast nodules should be monitored with particular care. 3. Lipid Disorders Women who are being treated for hyperlipidemias should be followed closely if they elect to use oral contraceptives. Some progestogens may elevate LDL levels and may render the control of hyperlipidemias more difficult. (See WARNINGS 1d.) In patients with familial defects of lipoprotein metabolism receiving estrogen containing preparations, there have been case reports of significant elevations of plasma triglycerides leading to pancreatitis. 4. Liver Function If jaundice develops in any woman receiving such hormonal contraceptives, the medication should be discontinued. Steroid hormones may be poorly metabolized in patients with impaired liver function. 5. Fluid Retention Oral contraceptives may cause some degree of fluid retention. They should be prescribed with caution, and only with careful monitoring, in patients with conditions which might be aggravated by fluid retention. 6. Emotional Disorders Patients becoming significantly depressed while taking oral contraceptives should stop the medication and use an alternate method of contraception in an attempt to determine whether the symptom is drug related. Women with a history of depression should be carefully observed and the drug discontinued if significant depression occurs. 7. Contact Lenses Contact-lens wearers who develop visual changes or changes in lens tolerance should be assessed by an ophthalmologist. 8. Gastrointestinal Motility Diarrhea and/or vomiting may reduce hormone absorption. 9. Drug Interactions Changes in contraceptive effectiveness associated with coadministration of other products: Contraceptive effectiveness may be reduced when hormonal contraceptives are coadministered with antibiotics, anticonvulsants, and other drugs that increase the metabolism of contraceptive steroids. This could result in unintended pregnancy or breakthrough bleeding. Examples include rifampin, barbiturates, phenylbutazone, phenytoin, carbamazepine, felbamate, oxcarbazepine, topiramate, and griseofulvin. It may take several weeks until enzyme induction has completely subsided, depending on dosage, duration of use, and rate of elimination of the inducing substance. Several cases of contraceptive failure and breakthrough bleeding have been reported in the literature with concomitant administration of antibiotics such as ampicillin and tetracyclines. However, clinical pharmacology studies investigating drug interactions between combined oral contraceptives and these antibiotics have reported inconsistent results. Several of the anti-HIV protease inhibitors have been studied with coadministration of oral combination hormonal contraceptives; significant changes (increase and decrease) in the plasma levels of the estrogen and progestin have been noted in some cases. The safety and efficacy of oral contraceptive products may be affected with coadministration of anti-HIV protease inhibitors. Health care professionals should refer to the label of the individual anti-HIV protease inhibitors for further drug-drug interaction information. Herbal products containing St. John’s Wort (Hypericum perforatum) may induce hepatic enzymes (cytochrome P 450) and p-glycoprotein transporter and may reduce the effectiveness of contraceptive steroids. This may also result in breakthrough bleeding. Increase in plasma levels associated with coadministered drugs: Coadministration of atorvastatin and certain oral contraceptives containing ethinyl estradiol increase AUC values for ethinyl estradiol by approximately 20%. Ascorbic acid and acetaminophen may increase plasma ethinyl estradiol levels, possibly by inhibition of conjugation. CYP 3A4 inhibitors such as itraconazole or ketoconazole may increase plasma hormone levels. Changes in plasma levels of coadministered drugs: Combination hormonal contraceptives containing some synthetic estrogens (e.g., ethinyl estradiol) may inhibit the metabolism of other compounds. Increased plasma concentrations of cyclosporin, prednisolone and theophylline have been reported with concomitant administration of oral contraceptives. Decreased plasma concentrations of acetaminophen and increased clearance of temazepam, salicylic acid, morphine, and clofibric acid, due to induction of conjugation, have been noted when these drugs were administered with oral contraceptives. Troleandomycin may increase the risk of intrahepatic cholestasis during coadministration with combination oral contraceptives. The prescribing information of concomitant medications should be consulted to identify potential interactions. Concomitant Use with HCV Combination Therapy – Liver Enzyme Elevation Do not co-administer Ogestrel with HCV drug combinations containing ombitasvir/paritaprevir/ritonavir, with or without dasabuvir, due to potential for ALT elevations (see WARNINGS, Risk of Liver Enzyme Elevations with Concomitant Hepatitis C Treatment ). 10. Interactions with Laboratory Tests Certain endocrine- and liver-function tests and blood components may be affected by oral contraceptives: Increased prothrombin and factors VII, VIII, IX, and X; decreased antithrombin 3; increased norepinephrine-induced platelet aggregability. Increased thyroid-binding globulin (TBG) leading to increased circulating total thyroid hormone, as measured by protein-bound iodine (PBI), T 4 by column or by radioimmunoassay. Free T 3 resin uptake is decreased, reflecting the elevated TBG; free T 4 concentration is unaltered. Other binding proteins may be elevated in serum. Sex-hormone-binding globulins are increased and result in elevated levels of total circulating sex steroids and corticoids; however, free or biologically active levels remain unchanged. Triglycerides may be increased and levels of various other lipids and lipoproteins may be affected. Glucose tolerance may be decreased. Serum folate levels may be depressed by oral contraceptive therapy. This may be of clinical significance if a woman becomes pregnant shortly after discontinuing oral contraceptives. 11. Carcinogenesis See WARNINGS section. 12. Pregnancy Pregnancy Category X. See CONTRAINDICATIONS and WARNINGS sections. 13. Nursing Mothers Small amounts of oral contraceptive steroids and/or metabolites have been identified in the milk of nursing mothers, and a few adverse effects on the child have been reported, including jaundice and breast enlargement. In addition, combination oral contraceptives given in the postpartum period may interfere with lactation by decreasing the quantity and quality of breast milk. If possible, the nursing mother should be advised not to use combination oral contraceptives but to use other forms of contraception until she has completely weaned her child. 14. Pediatric Use Safety and efficacy of Ogestrel tablets have been established in women of reproductive age. Safety and efficacy are expected to be the same for postpubertal adolescents under the age of 16 and for users 16 years and older. Use of this product before menarche is not indicated. 15. Geriatric Use This product has not been studied in women over 65 years of age and is not indicated in this population.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS SECTION" id="34071-1">
Cigarette smoking increases the risk of serious cardiovascular side effects from oral contraceptive use. This risk increases with age and with the extent of smoking (in epidemiologic studies, 15 or more cigarettes per day was associated with a significantly increased risk) and is quite marked in women over 35 years of age. Women who use oral contraceptives should be strongly advised not to smoke. The use of oral contraceptives is associated with increased risks of several serious conditions including venous and arterial thrombotic and thromboembolic events (such as myocardial infarction, thromboembolism, and stroke), hepatic neoplasia, gallbladder disease, and hypertension, although the risk of serious morbidity or mortality is very small in healthy women without underlying risk factors. The risk of morbidity and mortality increases significantly in the presence of other underlying risk factors such as certain inherited or acquired thrombophilias, hypertension, hyperlipidemias, obesity and diabetes. Practitioners prescribing oral contraceptives should be familiar with the following information relating to these risks. The information contained in this package insert is based principally on studies carried out in patients who used oral contraceptives with higher formulations of estrogens and progestogens than those in common use today. The effect of long-term use of the oral contraceptives with lower formulations of both estrogens and progestogens remains to be determined. Throughout this labeling, epidemiological studies reported are of two types: retrospective or case control studies and prospective or cohort studies. Case control studies provide a measure of the relative risk of disease, namely, a ratio of the incidence of a disease among oral contraceptive users to that among non-users. The relative risk does not provide information on the actual clinical occurrence of a disease. Cohort studies provide a measure of attributable risk, which is the difference in the incidence of disease between oral contraceptive users and non-users. The attributable risk does provide information about the actual occurrence of a disease in the population. For further information, the reader is referred to a text on epidemiological methods. 1. Thromboembolic Disorders and Other Vascular Problems a. Myocardial infarction An increased risk of myocardial infarction has been attributed to oral contraceptive use. This risk is primarily in smokers or women with other underlying risk factors for coronary-artery disease such as hypertension, hypercholesterolemia, morbid obesity, and diabetes. The relative risk of heart attack for current oral contraceptive users has been estimated to be 2 to 6. The risk is very low under the age of 30. Smoking in combination with oral contraceptive use has been shown to contribute substantially to the incidence of myocardial infarction in women in their mid-thirties or older with smoking accounting for the majority of excess cases. Mortality rates associated with circulatory disease have been shown to increase substantially in smokers over the age of 35 and non-smokers over the age of 40 (Table II) among women who use oral contraceptives. CIRCULATORY DISEASE MORTALITY RATES PER 100,000 WOMAN YEARS BY AGE, SMOKING STATUS AND ORAL CONTRACEPTIVE USE TABLE II: (Adapted From P.M. Layde And V. Beral, Lancet, 1 :541-546, 1981.) Oral contraceptives may compound the effects of well-known risk factors, such as hypertension, diabetes, hyperlipidemias, age, and obesity. In particular, some progestogens are known to decrease HDL cholesterol and cause glucose intolerance, while estrogens may create a state of hyperinsulinism. Oral contraceptives have been shown to increase blood pressure among users (see section 9 in WARNINGS ). Similar effects on risk factors have been associated with an increased risk of heart disease. Oral contraceptives must be used with caution in women with cardiovascular disease risk factors. b. Thromboembolism An increased risk of venous thromboembolic and thrombotic disease associated with the use of oral contraceptives is well established. Case control studies have found the relative risk of users compared to non-users to be 3 for the first episode of superficial venous thrombosis, 4 to 11 for deep-vein thrombosis or pulmonary embolism, and 1.5 to 6 for women with predisposing conditions for venous thromboembolic disease. Cohort studies have shown the relative risk to be somewhat lower, about 3 for new cases and about 4.5 for new cases requiring hospitalization. The approximate incidence of deep vein thrombosis and pulmonary embolism in users of low dose (&amp;lt;50 mcg ethinyl estradiol) combination oral contraceptives is up to 4 per 10,000 woman-years compared to 0.5-3 per 10,000 woman-years for non-users. However, the incidence is less than that associated with pregnancy (6 per 10,000 woman-years). The risk of thromboembolic disease due to oral contraceptives is not related to length of use and disappears after pill use is stopped. A 2- to 4-fold increase in relative risk of postoperative thromboembolic complications has been reported with the use of oral contraceptives. The relative risk of venous thrombosis in women who have predisposing conditions is twice that of women without such medical conditions. If feasible, oral contraceptives should be discontinued at least 4 weeks prior to and for 2 weeks after elective surgery of a type associated with an increase in risk of thromboembolism and during and following prolonged immobilization. Since the immediate postpartum period is also associated with an increased risk of thromboembolism, oral contraceptives should be started no earlier than 4 weeks after delivery in women who elect not to breastfeed. c. Cerebrovascular diseases Oral contraceptives have been shown to increase both the relative and attributable risks of cerebrovascular events (thrombotic and hemorrhagic strokes), although, in general, the risk is greatest among older (&amp;gt;35 years), hypertensive women who also smoke. Hypertension was found to be a risk factor for both users and non-users for both types of strokes, while smoking interacted to increase the risk for hemorrhagic strokes. In a large study, the relative risk of thrombotic strokes has been shown to range from 3 for normotensive users to 14 for users with severe hypertension. The relative risk of hemorrhagic stroke is reported to be 1.2 for non-smokers who used oral contraceptives, 2.6 for smokers who did not use oral contraceptives, 7.6 for smokers who used oral contraceptives, 1.8 for normotensive users, and 25.7 for users with severe hypertension. The attributable risk is also greater in older women. Oral contraceptives also increase the risk for stroke in women with other underlying risk factors such as certain inherited or acquired thrombophilias, hyperlipidemias, and obesity. Women with migraine (particularly migraine with aura) who take combination oral contraceptives may be at an increased risk of stroke. d. Dose-related risk of vascular disease from oral contraceptives A positive association has been observed between the amount of estrogen and progestogen in oral contraceptives and the risk of vascular disease. A decline in serum high-density lipoproteins (HDL) has been reported with many progestational agents. A decline in serum high-density lipoproteins has been associated with an increased incidence of ischemic heart disease. Because estrogens increase HDL cholesterol, the net effect of an oral contraceptive depends on a balance achieved between doses of estrogen and progestogen and the nature and absolute amount of progestogen used in the contraceptive. The amount of both hormones should be considered in the choice of an oral contraceptive. Minimizing exposure to estrogen and progestogen is in keeping with good principles of therapeutics. For any particular estrogen/progestogen combination, the dosage regimen prescribed should be one which contains the least amount of estrogen and progestogen that is compatible with a low failure rate and the needs of the individual patient. New acceptors of oral contraceptive agents should be started on preparations containing the lowest estrogen content which is judged appropriate for the individual patient. e. Persistence of risk of vascular disease There are two studies which have shown persistence of risk of vascular disease for ever-users of oral contraceptives. In a study in the United States, the risk of developing myocardial infarction after discontinuing oral contraceptives persists for at least 9 years for women 40–49 years who had used oral contraceptives for 5 or more years, but this increased risk was not demonstrated in other age groups. In another study in Great Britain, the risk of developing cerebrovascular disease persisted for at least 6 years after discontinuation of oral contraceptives, although excess risk was very small. However, both studies were performed with oral contraceptive formulations containing 50 mcg or higher of estrogen. 2. Estimates of Mortality from Contraceptive Use One study gathered data from a variety of sources which have estimated the mortality rate associated with different methods of contraception at different ages (Table III). These estimates include the combined risk of death associated with contraceptive methods plus the risk attributable to pregnancy in the event of method failure. Each method of contraception has its specific benefits and risks. The study concluded that with the exception of oral contraceptive users 35 and older who smoke and 40 and older who do not smoke, mortality associated with all methods of birth control is less than that associated with childbirth. The observation of a possible increase in risk of mortality with age for oral contraceptive users is based on data gathered in the 1970’s—but not reported until 1983. However, current clinical practice involves the use of lower estrogen dose formulations combined with careful restriction of oral contraceptive use to women who do not have the various risk factors listed in this labeling. Because of these changes in practice and, also, because of some limited new data which suggest that the risk of cardiovascular disease with the use of oral contraceptives may now be less than previously observed, the Fertility and Maternal Health Drugs Advisory Committee was asked to review the topic in 1989. The Committee concluded that although cardiovascular-disease risks may be increased with oral contraceptive use after age 40 in healthy non-smoking women (even with the newer low-dose formulations), there are greater potential health risks associated with pregnancy in older women and with the alternative surgical and medical procedures which may be necessary if such women do not have access to effective and acceptable means of contraception. Therefore, the Committee recommended that the benefits of oral contraceptive use by healthy non-smoking women over 40 may outweigh the possible risks. Of course, older women, as all women who take oral contraceptives, should take the lowest possible dose formulation that is effective. TABLE III: ANNUAL NUMBER OF BIRTH-RELATED OR METHOD-RELATED DEATHS ASSOCIATED WITH CONTROL OF FERTILITY PER 100,000 NONSTERILE WOMEN, BY FERTILITY-CONTROL METHOD AND ACCORDING TO AGE Adapted from H.W. Ory, Family Planning Perspectives, 15:57-63, 1983. Method of control and outcome 15–19 20–24 25–29 30–34 35–39 40–44 No fertility- control methods* 7.0 7.4 9.1 14.8 25.7 28.2 Oral contraceptives non-smoker** 0.3 0.5 0.9 1.9 13.8 31.6 Oral contraceptives smoker ** 2.2 3.4 6.6 13.5 51.1 117.2 IUD** 0.8 0.8 1.0 1.0 1.4 1.4 Condom* 1.1 1.6 0.7 0.2 0.3 0.4 Diaphragm/spermicide* 1.9 1.2 1.2 1.3 2.2 2.8 Periodic abstinence* 2.5 1.6 1.6 1.7 2.9 3.6 *Deaths are birth-related **Deaths are method-related 3. Carcinoma of the Reproductive Organs and Breasts Numerous epidemiological studies have been performed on the incidence of breast, endometrial, ovarian and cervical cancer in women using oral contraceptives. Although the risk of having breast cancer diagnosed may be slightly increased among current and recent users of combined oral contraceptives (RR=1.24), this excess risk decreases over time after combination oral contraceptive discontinuation and by 10 years after cessation the increased risk disappears. The risk does not increase with duration of use and no consistent relationships have been found with dose or type of steroid. The patterns of risk are also similar regardless of a woman’s reproductive history or her family breast cancer history. The subgroup for whom risk has been found to be significantly elevated is women who first used oral contraceptives before age 20, but because breast cancer is so rare at these young ages, the number of cases attributable to this early oral contraceptive use is extremely small. Breast cancers diagnosed in current or previous oral contraceptive users tend to be less clinically advanced than in never-users. Women who currently have or have had breast cancer should not use oral contraceptives because breast cancer is a hormone sensitive tumor. Some studies suggest that oral contraceptive use has been associated with an increase in the risk of cervical intraepithelial neoplasia or invasive cervical cancer in some populations of women. However, there continues to be controversy about the extent to which such findings may be due to differences in sexual behavior and other factors. In spite of many studies of the relationship between oral contraceptive use and breast and cervical cancers, a cause-and-effect relationship has not been established. 4. Hepatic Neoplasia Benign hepatic adenomas are associated with oral contraceptive use, although the incidence of benign tumors is rare in the United States. Indirect calculations have estimated the attributable risk to be in the range of 3.3 cases/100,000 for users, a risk that increases after 4 or more years of use. Rupture of rare, benign, hepatic adenomas may cause death through intra-abdominal hemorrhage. Studies from Britain have shown an increased risk of developing hepatocellular carcinoma in long-term (&amp;gt;8 years) oral contraceptive users. However, these cancers are extremely rare in the U.S., and the attributable risk (the excess incidence) of liver cancers in oral contraceptive users approaches less than one per million users. 5. Risk of Liver Enzyme Elevations with Concomitant Hepatitis C Treatment During clinical trials with the Hepatitis C combination drug regimen that contains ombitasvir/paritaprevir/ritonavir, with or without dasabuvir, ALT elevations greater than 5 times the upper limit of normal (ULN), including some cases greater than 20 times the ULN, were significantly more frequent in women using ethinyl estradiol-containing medications such as COCs. Discontinue Ogestrel prior to starting therapy with the combination drug regimen ombitasvir/paritaprevir/ritonavir, with or without dasabuvir (see CONTRAINDICATIONS ). Ogestrel can be restarted approximately 2 weeks following completion of treatment with the combination drug regimen. 6. Ocular Lesions There have been clinical case reports of retinal thrombosis associated with the use of oral contraceptives that may lead to partial or complete loss of vision. Oral contraceptives should be discontinued if there is unexplained partial or complete loss of vision; onset of proptosis or diplopia; papilledema; or retinal vascular lesions. Appropriate diagnostic and therapeutic measures should be undertaken immediately. 7. Oral Contraceptive Use Before or During Early Pregnancy Extensive epidemiological studies have revealed no increased risk of birth defects in infants born to women who have used oral contraceptives prior to pregnancy. Studies also do not suggest a teratogenic effect, particularly insofar as cardiac anomalies and limb-reduction defects are concerned, when taken inadvertently during early pregnancy (see CONTRAINDICATIONS section). The administration of oral contraceptives to induce withdrawal bleeding should not be used as a test for pregnancy. Oral contraceptives should not be used during pregnancy to treat threatened or habitual abortion. It is recommended that for any patient who has missed 2 consecutive periods, pregnancy should be ruled out. If the patient has not adhered to the prescribed schedule, the possibility of pregnancy should be considered at the time of the first missed period. Oral contraceptive use should be discontinued if pregnancy is confirmed. 8. Gallbladder Disease Earlier studies have reported an increased lifetime relative risk of gallbladder surgery in users of oral contraceptives and estrogens. More recent studies, however, have shown that the relative risk of developing gallbladder disease among oral contraceptive users may be minimal. The recent findings of minimal risk may be related to the use of oral contraceptive formulations containing lower hormonal doses of estrogens and progestogens. 9. Carbohydrate and Lipid Metabolic Effects Oral contraceptives have been shown to cause glucose intolerance in a significant percentage of users. Oral contraceptives containing greater than 75 mcg of estrogens cause hyperinsulinism, while lower doses of estrogen cause less glucose intolerance. Progestogens increase insulin secretion and create insulin resistance, this effect varying with different progestational agents. However, in the non-diabetic woman, oral contraceptives appear to have no effect on fasting blood glucose. Because of these demonstrated effects, prediabetic and diabetic women should be carefully observed while taking oral contraceptives. A small proportion of women will have persistent hypertriglyceridemia while on the pill. As discussed earlier (see WARNINGS 1a and 1d), changes in serum triglycerides and lipoprotein levels have been reported in oral contraceptive users. 10. Elevated Blood Pressure Women with significant hypertension should not be started on hormonal contraception. An increase in blood pressure has been reported in women taking oral contraceptives, and this increase is more likely in older oral contraceptive users and with continued use. Data from the Royal College of General Practitioners and subsequent randomized trials have shown that the incidence of hypertension increases with increasing quantities of progestogens. Women with a history of hypertension or hypertension-related diseases, or renal disease, should be encouraged to use another method of contraception. If women with hypertension elect to use oral contraceptives, they should be monitored closely, and if significant elevation of blood pressure occurs, oral contraceptives should be discontinued (see CONTRAINDICATIONS section). For most women, elevated blood pressure will return to normal after stopping oral contraceptives, and there is no difference in the occurrence of hypertension among ever- and never-users. 11. Headache The onset or exacerbation of migraine or development of headache with a new pattern that is recurrent, persistent, or severe requires discontinuation of oral contraceptives and evaluation of the cause. (See WARNINGS 1c.) 12. Bleeding Irregularities Breakthrough bleeding and spotting are sometimes encountered in patients on oral contraceptives, especially during the first 3 months of use. The type and dose of progestogen may be important. If bleeding persists or recurs, non-hormonal causes should be considered and adequate diagnostic measures taken to rule out malignancy or pregnancy in the event of breakthrough bleeding, as in the case of any abnormal vaginal bleeding. If pathology has been excluded, time or a change to another formulation may solve the problem. In the event of amenorrhea, pregnancy should be ruled out. Some women may encounter post-pill amenorrhea or oligomenorrhea (possibly with anovulation), especially when such a condition was pre-existent. 13. Ectopic Pregnancy Ectopic as well as intrauterine pregnancy may occur in contraceptive failures. Table II</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Mode of Action Combination oral contraceptives act by suppression of gonadotropins. Although the primary mechanism of this action is inhibition of ovulation, other alterations include changes in the cervical mucus (which increase the difficulty of sperm entry into the uterus) and the endometrium (which reduce the likelihood of implantation).</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="9531" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Combination oral contraceptives should not be used in women with any of the following conditions: Thrombophlebitis or thromboembolic disorders A past history of deep-vein thrombophlebitis or thromboembolic disorders Cerebral-vascular or coronary-artery disease (current or history) Valvular heart disease with thrombogenic complications Thrombogenic rhythm disorders Major surgery with prolonged immobilization Diabetes with vascular involvement Headaches with focal neurological symptoms Uncontrolled hypertension Known or suspected carcinoma of the breast or personal history of breast cancer Carcinoma of the endometrium or other known or suspected estrogen-dependent neoplasia Undiagnosed abnormal genital bleeding Cholestatic jaundice of pregnancy or jaundice with prior pill use Hepatic adenomas or carcinomas, or active liver disease, as long as liver function has not returned to normal Known or suspected pregnancy Hypersensitivity to any of the components of Ogestrel® Are receiving Hepatitis C drug combinations containing ombitasvir/paritaprevir/ritonavir, with or without dasabuvir, due to the potential for ALT elevations.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M4" type="Trigger" span="1107 13" str="potential for"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="993 74" str="Hepatitis C drug combinations containing ombitasvir/paritaprevir/ritonavir" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M6" type="SpecificInteraction" span="1121 14" str="ALT elevations" code="409673008:  Alanine aminotransferase (serum glutamic-pyruvic transaminase) level raised (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M5" type="Precipitant" span="1034 33" str="ombitasvir/paritaprevir/ritonavir" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M4" precipitant="M2" effect="M6" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M4" precipitant="M5" effect="M6" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9532" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>To achieve maximum contraceptive effectiveness, Ogestrel must be taken exactly as directed and at intervals not exceeding 24 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9533" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The possibility of ovulation and conception prior to initiation of medication should be considered.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9534" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The dosage of Ogestrel is one white tablet daily for 21 consecutive days, followed by one peach inert tablet daily for 7 consecutive days, according to prescribed schedule.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9535" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>It is recommended that Ogestrel tablets be taken at the same time each day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9536" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>During the first cycle of medication, the patient is instructed to begin taking Ogestrel on the first Sunday after the onset of menstruation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9537" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If menstruation begins on a Sunday, the first tablet (white) is taken that day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9538" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>One white tablet should be taken daily for 21 consecutive days followed by one peach inert tablet daily for 7 consecutive days.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9539" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Withdrawal bleeding should usually occur within three days following discontinuation of white tablets and may not have finished before the next pack is started.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9540" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>During the first cycle, contraceptive reliance should not be placed on Ogestrel until a white tablet has been taken daily for 7 consecutive days and a non-hormonal back-up method of birth control should be used during those 7 days.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9541" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The patient begins her next and all subsequent 28-day courses of tablets on the same day of the week (Sunday) on which she began her first course, following the same schedule: 21 days on white tablets—7 days on peach inert tablets.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9542" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If in any cycle the patient starts tablets later than the proper day, she should protect herself against pregnancy by using a non-hormonal back-up method of birth control until she has taken a white tablet daily for 7 consecutive days.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9543" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>When the patient is switching from a 21-day regimen of tablets, she should wait 7 days after her last tablet before she starts Ogestrel.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9544" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>She will probably experience withdrawal bleeding during that week.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9545" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>She should be sure that no more than 7 days pass after her previous 21-day regimen.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9546" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>When the patient is switching from a 28-day regimen of tablets, she should start her first pack of Ogestrel on the day after her last tablet.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9547" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>She should not wait any days between packs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9548" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The patient may switch any day from a progestin-only pill and should begin Ogestrel the next day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9549" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If switching from an implant or injection, the patient should start Ogestrel on the day of implant removal or, if using an injection, the day the next injection would be due.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9550" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In switching from a progestin-only pill, injection, or implant, the patient should be advised to use a non-hormonal back-up method of birth control for the first 7 days of tablet-taking.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9551" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If spotting or breakthrough bleeding occurs, the patient is instructed to continue on the same regimen.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9552" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>This type of bleeding is usually transient and without significance; however, if the bleeding is persistent or prolonged, the patient is advised to consult her health care professional.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9553" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Although pregnancy is unlikely if Ogestrel is taken according to directions, if withdrawal bleeding does not occur, the possibility of pregnancy must be considered.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9554" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If the patient has not adhered to the prescribed schedule (missed one or more tablets or started taking them on a day later than she should have), the probability of pregnancy should be considered at the time of the first missed period and appropriate diagnostic measures taken.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9555" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If the patient has adhered to the prescribed regimen and misses two consecutive periods, pregnancy should be ruled out.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9556" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Hormonal contraceptives should be discontinued if pregnancy is confirmed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9557" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For additional patient instructions regarding missed tablets, see the “WHAT TO DO IF YOU MISS PILLS” section in the DETAILED PATIENT LABELING below.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9558" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Any time the patient misses two or more white tablets, she should also use another method of contraception until she has taken a white tablet daily for seven consecutive days.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9559" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If the patient misses one or more peach tablets, she is still protected against pregnancy provided she begins taking white tablets again on the proper day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9560" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If breakthrough bleeding occurs following missed white tablets, it will usually be transient and of no consequence.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9561" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The possibility of ovulation increases with each successive day that scheduled white tablets are missed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9562" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Ogestrel may be initiated no earlier than day 28 postpartum in the non-lactating mother due to the increased risk for thromboembolism.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9563" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The patient should be advised to use a non-hormonal back-up method for the first 7 days of tablet-taking.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9564" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>However, if intercourse has already occurred, the possibility of ovulation and conception prior to initiation of medication should be considered.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9565" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In the case of first-trimester abortion, if the patient starts Ogestrel immediately, additional contraceptive measures are not needed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9566" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>General Patients should be counseled that oral contraceptives do not protect against transmission of HIV (AIDS) and other sexually transmitted diseases (STDs) such as chlamydia, genital herpes, genital warts, gonorrhea, hepatitis B, and syphilis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9567" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Physical Examination and Follow-Up A periodic personal and family medical history and complete physical examination are appropriate for all women, including women using oral contraceptives.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9568" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The physical examination, however, may be deferred until after initiation of oral contraceptives if requested by the woman and judged appropriate by the clinician.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9569" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The physical examination should include special reference to blood pressure, breasts, abdomen and pelvic organs, including cervical cytology, and relevant laboratory tests.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9570" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In case of undiagnosed, persistent or recurrent abnormal vaginal bleeding, appropriate diagnostic measures should be conducted to rule out malignancy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9571" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Women with a strong family history of breast cancer or who have breast nodules should be monitored with particular care.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9572" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Lipid Disorders Women who are being treated for hyperlipidemias should be followed closely if they elect to use oral contraceptives.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9573" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Some progestogens may elevate LDL levels and may render the control of hyperlipidemias more difficult.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9574" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In patients with familial defects of lipoprotein metabolism receiving estrogen containing preparations, there have been case reports of significant elevations of plasma triglycerides leading to pancreatitis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9575" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Liver Function If jaundice develops in any woman receiving such hormonal contraceptives, the medication should be discontinued.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9576" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Steroid hormones may be poorly metabolized in patients with impaired liver function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9577" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Fluid Retention Oral contraceptives may cause some degree of fluid retention.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9578" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>They should be prescribed with caution, and only with careful monitoring, in patients with conditions which might be aggravated by fluid retention.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9579" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Emotional Disorders Patients becoming significantly depressed while taking oral contraceptives should stop the medication and use an alternate method of contraception in an attempt to determine whether the symptom is drug related.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9580" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Women with a history of depression should be carefully observed and the drug discontinued if significant depression occurs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9581" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Contact Lenses Contact-lens wearers who develop visual changes or changes in lens tolerance should be assessed by an ophthalmologist.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9582" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Gastrointestinal Motility Diarrhea and/or vomiting may reduce hormone absorption.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9583" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Drug Interactions Changes in contraceptive effectiveness associated with coadministration of other products: Contraceptive effectiveness may be reduced when hormonal contraceptives are coadministered with antibiotics, anticonvulsants, and other drugs that increase the metabolism of contraceptive steroids.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M13" type="Trigger" span="123 28" str="effectiveness may be reduced"/>
<Mention id="M17" type="Precipitant" span="205 11" str="antibiotics" code="N0000178296 | n0000029074 | N0000178300"/>
<Mention id="M15" type="SpecificInteraction" span="109 42" str="Contraceptive effectiveness may be reduced" code="102955006: Contraception failure (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M19" type="Precipitant" span="218 15" str="anticonvulsants" code="N0000029145 | N0000175753"/>
<Mention id="M21" type="Precipitant" span="245 60" str="drugs that increase the metabolism of contraceptive steroids" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M20" type="Trigger" span="256 23" str="increase the metabolism"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M13" precipitant="M17" effect="M15" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M13" precipitant="M19" effect="M15" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M13" precipitant="M21" effect="M15" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M20" precipitant="M17" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M20" precipitant="M19" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M20" precipitant="M21" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9584" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>This could result in unintended pregnancy or breakthrough bleeding.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9585" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Examples include rifampin, barbiturates, phenylbutazone, phenytoin, carbamazepine, felbamate, oxcarbazepine, topiramate, and griseofulvin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9586" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>It may take several weeks until enzyme induction has completely subsided, depending on dosage, duration of use, and rate of elimination of the inducing substance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9587" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Several cases of contraceptive failure and breakthrough bleeding have been reported in the literature with concomitant administration of antibiotics such as ampicillin and tetracyclines.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M34" type="Trigger" span="43 12" str="breakthrough"/>
<Mention id="M26" type="Precipitant" span="157 10" str="ampicillin" code="7C782967RD"/>
<Mention id="M36" type="SpecificInteraction" span="43 21" str="breakthrough bleeding" code="56169002: Break-through bleeding (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M37" type="Trigger" span="31 7" str="failure"/>
<Mention id="M39" type="SpecificInteraction" span="17 21" str="contraceptive failure" code="102955006: Contraception failure (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M32" type="Precipitant" span="137 11" str="antibiotics" code="N0000178296 | n0000029074 | N0000178300"/>
<Mention id="M38" type="Precipitant" span="172 13" str="tetracyclines" code="N0000175882"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M34" precipitant="M26" effect="M36" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M37" precipitant="M26" effect="M39" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M34" precipitant="M32" effect="M36" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M37" precipitant="M32" effect="M39" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M34" precipitant="M38" effect="M36" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M37" precipitant="M38" effect="M39" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9588" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>However, clinical pharmacology studies investigating drug interactions between combined oral contraceptives and these antibiotics have reported inconsistent results.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9589" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Several of the anti-HIV protease inhibitors have been studied with coadministration of oral combination hormonal contraceptives; significant changes (increase and decrease) in the plasma levels of the estrogen and progestin have been noted in some cases.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M42" type="Trigger" span="141 7;180 13" str="changes | plasma levels"/>
<Mention id="M41" type="Precipitant" span="15 28" str="anti-HIV protease inhibitors" code="N0000000246"/>
<Mention id="M43" type="Precipitant" span="20 23" str="HIV protease inhibitors" code="N0000175520 | N0000000246"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M42" precipitant="M41"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M42" precipitant="M43"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9590" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The safety and efficacy of oral contraceptive products may be affected with coadministration of anti-HIV protease inhibitors.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M47" type="Trigger" span="4 6;62 8" str="safety | affected "/>
<Mention id="M48" type="Trigger" span="15 8;62 8" str=" efficacy | affected"/>
<Mention id="M46" type="Precipitant" span="96 28" str="anti-HIV protease inhibitors" code="N0000000246"/>
<Mention id="M49" type="Precipitant" span="101 23" str="HIV protease inhibitors" code="N0000175520 | N0000000246"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M47;M48" precipitant="M46"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M47;M48" precipitant="M49"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9591" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Health care professionals should refer to the label of the individual anti-HIV protease inhibitors for further drug-drug interaction information.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M52" type="Trigger" span="116 16" str="drug interaction"/>
<Mention id="M51" type="Precipitant" span="70 28" str="anti-HIV protease inhibitors" code="N0000000246"/>
<Mention id="M53" type="Precipitant" span="75 23" str="HIV protease inhibitors" code="N0000175520 | N0000000246"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M52" precipitant="M51"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M52" precipitant="M53"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9592" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Herbal products containing St. John’s Wort (Hypericum perforatum) may induce hepatic enzymes (cytochrome P 450) and p-glycoprotein transporter and may reduce the effectiveness of contraceptive steroids.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M57" type="Trigger" span="151 24" str="reduce the effectiveness"/>
<Mention id="M55" type="Precipitant" span="44 20" str="Hypericum perforatum" code="XK4IUX8MNB"/>
<Mention id="M59" type="SpecificInteraction" span="151 50" str="reduce the effectiveness of contraceptive steroids" code="102955006: Contraception failure (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M58" type="Precipitant" span="27 15" str="St. John’s Wort" code="N0000022261 | UFH8805FKA"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M57" precipitant="M55" effect="M59" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M57" precipitant="M58" effect="M59" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9593" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>This may also result in breakthrough bleeding.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9594" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Increase in plasma levels associated with coadministered drugs: Coadministration of atorvastatin and certain oral contraceptives containing ethinyl estradiol increase AUC values for ethinyl estradiol by approximately 20%.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M60" type="Trigger" span="158 12" str="increase AUC"/>
<Mention id="M61" type="Precipitant" span="84 12" str="atorvastatin" code="A0JWA85V8F | N0000022046"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M60" precipitant="M61" effect="C54605"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9595" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Ascorbic acid and acetaminophen may increase plasma ethinyl estradiol levels, possibly by inhibition of conjugation.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M64" type="Trigger" span="36 15;70 6" str="increase plasma | levels"/>
<Mention id="M63" type="Precipitant" span="18 13" str="acetaminophen" code="362O9ITL9D"/>
<Mention id="M65" type="Precipitant" span="0 13" str="Ascorbic acid" code="PQ6CK8PD0R"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M64" precipitant="M63" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M64" precipitant="M65" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9596" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>CYP 3A4 inhibitors such as itraconazole or ketoconazole may increase plasma hormone levels.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M70" type="Trigger" span="60 15;84 6" str="increase plasma | levels"/>
<Mention id="M67" type="Precipitant" span="0 18" str="CYP 3A4 inhibitors" code="N0000182141"/>
<Mention id="M69" type="Precipitant" span="27 12" str="itraconazole" code="304NUG5GF4 | N0000006753"/>
<Mention id="M71" type="Precipitant" span="43 12" str="ketoconazole" code="N0000007319 | R9400W927I"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M70" precipitant="M67" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M70" precipitant="M69" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M70" precipitant="M71" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9597" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Changes in plasma levels of coadministered drugs: Combination hormonal contraceptives containing some synthetic estrogens (e.g., ethinyl estradiol) may inhibit the metabolism of other compounds.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9598" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Increased plasma concentrations of cyclosporin, prednisolone and theophylline have been reported with concomitant administration of oral contraceptives.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M76" type="Trigger" span="0 31" str="Increased plasma concentrations"/>
<Mention id="M73" type="Precipitant" span="35 11" str="cyclosporin" code="83HN0GTJ6D"/>
<Mention id="M75" type="Precipitant" span="48 12" str="prednisolone" code="9PHQ9Y1OLM"/>
<Mention id="M77" type="Precipitant" span="65 12" str="theophylline" code="N0000007076 | C137DTR5RG"/>
<Interaction id="I29" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M76" precipitant="M73" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I30" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M76" precipitant="M75" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I31" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M76" precipitant="M77" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9599" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Decreased plasma concentrations of acetaminophen and increased clearance of temazepam, salicylic acid, morphine, and clofibric acid, due to induction of conjugation, have been noted when these drugs were administered with oral contraceptives.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M78" type="Trigger" span="0 31" str="Decreased plasma concentrations"/>
<Mention id="M79" type="Precipitant" span="35 13" str="acetaminophen" code="362O9ITL9D"/>
<Mention id="M86" type="Trigger" span="53 19" str="increased clearance"/>
<Mention id="M81" type="Precipitant" span="117 14" str="clofibric acid" code="53PF01Q249"/>
<Mention id="M83" type="Precipitant" span="103 8" str="morphine" code="76I7G6D29C"/>
<Mention id="M85" type="Precipitant" span="87 14" str="salicylic acid" code="O414PZ4LPZ"/>
<Mention id="M87" type="Precipitant" span="76 9" str="temazepam" code="CHB1QD2QSS"/>
<Interaction id="I32" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M78" precipitant="M79" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I33" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M86" precipitant="M81" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I34" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M86" precipitant="M83" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I35" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M86" precipitant="M85" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I36" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M86" precipitant="M87" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9600" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Troleandomycin may increase the risk of intrahepatic cholestasis during coadministration with combination oral contraceptives.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M88" type="Trigger" span="19 17" str="increase the risk"/>
<Mention id="M89" type="Precipitant" span="0 14" str="Troleandomycin" code="C4DZ64560D"/>
<Mention id="M90" type="SpecificInteraction" span="40 24" str="intrahepatic cholestasis" code="4637005: Intrahepatic cholestasis (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I37" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M88" precipitant="M89" effect="M90" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9601" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The prescribing information of concomitant medications should be consulted to identify potential interactions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9602" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Concomitant Use with HCV Combination Therapy – Liver Enzyme Elevation Do not co-administer Ogestrel with HCV drug combinations containing ombitasvir/paritaprevir/ritonavir, with or without dasabuvir, due to potential for ALT elevations.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M91" type="Trigger" span="60 9" str="Elevation"/>
<Mention id="M92" type="Precipitant" span="21 23" str="HCV Combination Therapy" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M93" type="SpecificInteraction" span="47 22" str="Liver Enzyme Elevation" code="707724006: Elevated liver enzymes level (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M97" type="Trigger" span="207 13" str="potential for"/>
<Mention id="M95" type="Precipitant" span="105 66" str="HCV drug combinations containing ombitasvir/paritaprevir/ritonavir" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M99" type="SpecificInteraction" span="221 14" str="ALT elevations" code="409673008:  Alanine aminotransferase (serum glutamic-pyruvic transaminase) level raised (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M98" type="Precipitant" span="138 33" str="ombitasvir/paritaprevir/ritonavir" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I38" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M91" precipitant="M92" effect="M93" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I39" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M97" precipitant="M95" effect="M99" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I40" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M97" precipitant="M98" effect="M99" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9603" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Interactions with Laboratory Tests Certain endocrine- and liver-function tests and blood components may be affected by oral contraceptives: Increased prothrombin and factors VII, VIII, IX, and X; decreased antithrombin 3; increased norepinephrine-induced platelet aggregability.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9604" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Increased thyroid-binding globulin (TBG) leading to increased circulating total thyroid hormone, as measured by protein-bound iodine (PBI), T4 by column or by radioimmunoassay.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9605" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Free T3 resin uptake is decreased, reflecting the elevated TBG; free T4 concentration is unaltered.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M100" type="Trigger" span="14 19" str="uptake is decreased"/>
<Mention id="M101" type="Precipitant" span="0 13" str="Free T3 resin" code="06LU7C9H1V"/>
<Interaction id="I41" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M100" precipitant="M101" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9606" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Other binding proteins may be elevated in serum.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9607" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Sex-hormone-binding globulins are increased and result in elevated levels of total circulating sex steroids and corticoids; however, free or biologically active levels remain unchanged.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9608" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Triglycerides may be increased and levels of various other lipids and lipoproteins may be affected.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9609" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Serum folate levels may be depressed by oral contraceptive therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9610" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>This may be of clinical significance if a woman becomes pregnant shortly after discontinuing oral contraceptives.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9611" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>See CONTRAINDICATIONS and WARNINGS sections.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9612" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Nursing Mothers Small amounts of oral contraceptive steroids and/or metabolites have been identified in the milk of nursing mothers, and a few adverse effects on the child have been reported, including jaundice and breast enlargement.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9613" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In addition, combination oral contraceptives given in the postpartum period may interfere with lactation by decreasing the quantity and quality of breast milk.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9614" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>If possible, the nursing mother should be advised not to use combination oral contraceptives but to use other forms of contraception until she has completely weaned her child.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9615" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Pediatric Use Safety and efficacy of Ogestrel tablets have been established in women of reproductive age.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9616" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Safety and efficacy are expected to be the same for postpubertal adolescents under the age of 16 and for users 16 years and older.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9617" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Use of this product before menarche is not indicated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9618" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Geriatric Use This product has not been studied in women over 65 years of age and is not indicated in this population.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9619" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Cigarette smoking increases the risk of serious cardiovascular side effects from oral contraceptive use.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M102" type="Trigger" span="18 18" str="increases the risk "/>
<Mention id="M103" type="Trigger" span="63 12" str=" side effects"/>
<Mention id="M104" type="Precipitant" span="0 17" str="Cigarette smoking" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M105" type="SpecificInteraction" span="40 35" str="serious cardiovascular side effects" code="267037003: Cardiovascular symptoms (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I42" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M102;M103" precipitant="M104" effect="M105" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9620" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>This risk increases with age and with the extent of smoking (in epidemiologic studies, 15 or more cigarettes per day was associated with a significantly increased risk) and is quite marked in women over 35 years of age.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M109" type="Trigger" span="5 14" str="risk increases "/>
<Mention id="M110" type="Trigger" span="153 14" str=" increased risk"/>
<Mention id="M108" type="Precipitant" span="98 10" str="cigarettes" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M111" type="Precipitant" span="52 7" str="smoking" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I43" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M109;M110" precipitant="M108"/>
<Interaction id="I44" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M109;M110" precipitant="M111"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9621" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Women who use oral contraceptives should be strongly advised not to smoke.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M112" type="Trigger" span="34 33" str="should be strongly advised not to"/>
<Mention id="M113" type="Precipitant" span="68 5" str="smoke" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I45" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M112" precipitant="M113"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9622" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The use of oral contraceptives is associated with increased risks of several serious conditions including venous and arterial thrombotic and thromboembolic events (such as myocardial infarction, thromboembolism, and stroke), hepatic neoplasia, gallbladder disease, and hypertension, although the risk of serious morbidity or mortality is very small in healthy women without underlying risk factors.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9623" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The risk of morbidity and mortality increases significantly in the presence of other underlying risk factors such as certain inherited or acquired thrombophilias, hypertension, hyperlipidemias, obesity and diabetes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9624" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Practitioners prescribing oral contraceptives should be familiar with the following information relating to these risks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9625" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The information contained in this package insert is based principally on studies carried out in patients who used oral contraceptives with higher formulations of estrogens and progestogens than those in common use today.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9626" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The effect of long-term use of the oral contraceptives with lower formulations of both estrogens and progestogens remains to be determined.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9627" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Throughout this labeling, epidemiological studies reported are of two types: retrospective or case control studies and prospective or cohort studies.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9628" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Case control studies provide a measure of the relative risk of disease, namely, a ratio of the incidence of a disease among oral contraceptive users to that among non-users.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9629" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The relative risk does not provide information on the actual clinical occurrence of a disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9630" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Cohort studies provide a measure of attributable risk, which is the difference in the incidence of disease between oral contraceptive users and non-users.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9631" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The attributable risk does provide information about the actual occurrence of a disease in the population.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9632" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>For further information, the reader is referred to a text on epidemiological methods.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9633" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Thromboembolic Disorders and Other Vascular Problems a. Myocardial infarction An increased risk of myocardial infarction has been attributed to oral contraceptive use.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9634" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>This risk is primarily in smokers or women with other underlying risk factors for coronary-artery disease such as hypertension, hypercholesterolemia, morbid obesity, and diabetes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9635" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The relative risk of heart attack for current oral contraceptive users has been estimated to be 2 to 6.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9636" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The risk is very low under the age of 30.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9637" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Smoking in combination with oral contraceptive use has been shown to contribute substantially to the incidence of myocardial infarction in women in their mid-thirties or older with smoking accounting for the majority of excess cases.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M114" type="Trigger" span="69 41" str="contribute substantially to the incidence "/>
<Mention id="M115" type="Trigger" span="189 43" str=" accounting for the majority of excess cases"/>
<Mention id="M116" type="Precipitant" span="0 7" str="Smoking" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M117" type="SpecificInteraction" span="114 21" str="myocardial infarction" code="22298006: Myocardial infarction (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I46" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M114;M115" precipitant="M116" effect="M117" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9638" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Mortality rates associated with circulatory disease have been shown to increase substantially in smokers over the age of 35 and non-smokers over the age of 40 (Table II) among women who use oral contraceptives.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9639" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>CIRCULATORY DISEASE MORTALITY RATES PER 100,000 WOMAN YEARS BY AGE, SMOKING STATUS AND ORAL CONTRACEPTIVE USE TABLE II: (Adapted From P.M. Layde And V. Beral, Lancet, 1:541-546, 1981.)</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9640" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Oral contraceptives may compound the effects of well-known risk factors, such as hypertension, diabetes, hyperlipidemias, age, and obesity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9641" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>In particular, some progestogens are known to decrease HDL cholesterol and cause glucose intolerance, while estrogens may create a state of hyperinsulinism.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9642" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Oral contraceptives have been shown to increase blood pressure among users.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9643" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Similar effects on risk factors have been associated with an increased risk of heart disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9644" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Oral contraceptives must be used with caution in women with cardiovascular disease risk factors. b. Thromboembolism An increased risk of venous thromboembolic and thrombotic disease associated with the use of oral contraceptives is well established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9645" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Case control studies have found the relative risk of users compared to non-users to be 3 for the first episode of superficial venous thrombosis, 4 to 11 for deep-vein thrombosis or pulmonary embolism, and 1.5 to 6 for women with predisposing conditions for venous thromboembolic disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9646" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Cohort studies have shown the relative risk to be somewhat lower, about 3 for new cases and about 4.5 for new cases requiring hospitalization.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9647" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The approximate incidence of deep vein thrombosis and pulmonary embolism in users of low dose (&lt;50 mcg ethinyl estradiol) combination oral contraceptives is up to 4 per 10,000 woman-years compared to 0.5-3 per 10,000 woman-years for non-users.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9648" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>However, the incidence is less than that associated with pregnancy (6 per 10,000 woman-years).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9649" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The risk of thromboembolic disease due to oral contraceptives is not related to length of use and disappears after pill use is stopped.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9650" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>A 2- to 4-fold increase in relative risk of postoperative thromboembolic complications has been reported with the use of oral contraceptives.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9651" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The relative risk of venous thrombosis in women who have predisposing conditions is twice that of women without such medical conditions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9652" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>If feasible, oral contraceptives should be discontinued at least 4 weeks prior to and for 2 weeks after elective surgery of a type associated with an increase in risk of thromboembolism and during and following prolonged immobilization.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9653" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Since the immediate postpartum period is also associated with an increased risk of thromboembolism, oral contraceptives should be started no earlier than 4 weeks after delivery in women who elect not to breastfeed. c. Cerebrovascular diseases Oral contraceptives have been shown to increase both the relative and attributable risks of cerebrovascular events (thrombotic and hemorrhagic strokes), although, in general, the risk is greatest among older (&gt;35 years), hypertensive women who also smoke.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M130" type="Trigger" span="422 16" str="risk is greatest"/>
<Mention id="M131" type="Precipitant" span="492 5" str="smoke" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M120" type="SpecificInteraction" span="218 24" str="Cerebrovascular diseases" code="62914000: Cerebrovascular disease (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M123" type="SpecificInteraction" span="335 22" str="cerebrovascular events" code="230690007: Cerebrovascular accident (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M126" type="SpecificInteraction" span="374 19" str="hemorrhagic strokes" code="5571000124103: Cerebrovascular accident with intracranial hemorrhage (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M129" type="SpecificInteraction" span="386 7" str="strokes" code="230690007: Cerebrovascular accident (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M132" type="SpecificInteraction" span="359 10;386 7" str="thrombotic | strokes" code="371040005: Thrombotic stroke (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I47" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M130" precipitant="M131" effect="M120" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I48" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M130" precipitant="M131" effect="M123" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I49" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M130" precipitant="M131" effect="M126" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I50" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M130" precipitant="M131" effect="M129" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I51" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M130" precipitant="M131" effect="M132" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9654" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Hypertension was found to be a risk factor for both users and non-users for both types of strokes, while smoking interacted to increase the risk for hemorrhagic strokes.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M133" type="Trigger" span="127 17" str="increase the risk"/>
<Mention id="M134" type="Precipitant" span="105 7" str="smoking" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M135" type="SpecificInteraction" span="149 19" str="hemorrhagic strokes" code="5571000124103: Cerebrovascular accident with intracranial hemorrhage (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I52" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M133" precipitant="M134" effect="M135" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9655" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>In a large study, the relative risk of thrombotic strokes has been shown to range from 3 for normotensive users to 14 for users with severe hypertension.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9656" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The relative risk of hemorrhagic stroke is reported to be 1.2 for non-smokers who used oral contraceptives, 2.6 for smokers who did not use oral contraceptives, 7.6 for smokers who used oral contraceptives, 1.8 for normotensive users, and 25.7 for users with severe hypertension.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9657" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The attributable risk is also greater in older women.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9658" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Oral contraceptives also increase the risk for stroke in women with other underlying risk factors such as certain inherited or acquired thrombophilias, hyperlipidemias, and obesity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9659" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Women with migraine (particularly migraine with aura) who take combination oral contraceptives may be at an increased risk of stroke. d. Dose-related risk of vascular disease from oral contraceptives A positive association has been observed between the amount of estrogen and progestogen in oral contraceptives and the risk of vascular disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9660" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>A decline in serum high-density lipoproteins (HDL) has been reported with many progestational agents.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9661" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>A decline in serum high-density lipoproteins has been associated with an increased incidence of ischemic heart disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9662" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Because estrogens increase HDL cholesterol, the net effect of an oral contraceptive depends on a balance achieved between doses of estrogen and progestogen and the nature and absolute amount of progestogen used in the contraceptive.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9663" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The amount of both hormones should be considered in the choice of an oral contraceptive.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9664" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Minimizing exposure to estrogen and progestogen is in keeping with good principles of therapeutics.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9665" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>For any particular estrogen/progestogen combination, the dosage regimen prescribed should be one which contains the least amount of estrogen and progestogen that is compatible with a low failure rate and the needs of the individual patient.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9666" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>New acceptors of oral contraceptive agents should be started on preparations containing the lowest estrogen content which is judged appropriate for the individual patient. e. Persistence of risk of vascular disease There are two studies which have shown persistence of risk of vascular disease for ever-users of oral contraceptives.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9667" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>In a study in the United States, the risk of developing myocardial infarction after discontinuing oral contraceptives persists for at least 9 years for women 40–49 years who had used oral contraceptives for 5 or more years, but this increased risk was not demonstrated in other age groups.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9668" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>In another study in Great Britain, the risk of developing cerebrovascular disease persisted for at least 6 years after discontinuation of oral contraceptives, although excess risk was very small.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9669" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>However, both studies were performed with oral contraceptive formulations containing 50 mcg or higher of estrogen.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9670" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Estimates of Mortality from Contraceptive Use One study gathered data from a variety of sources which have estimated the mortality rate associated with different methods of contraception at different ages (Table III).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9671" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>These estimates include the combined risk of death associated with contraceptive methods plus the risk attributable to pregnancy in the event of method failure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9672" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Each method of contraception has its specific benefits and risks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9673" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The study concluded that with the exception of oral contraceptive users 35 and older who smoke and 40 and older who do not smoke, mortality associated with all methods of birth control is less than that associated with childbirth.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9674" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The observation of a possible increase in risk of mortality with age for oral contraceptive users is based on data gathered in the 1970’s—but not reported until 1983.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9675" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>However, current clinical practice involves the use of lower estrogen dose formulations combined with careful restriction of oral contraceptive use to women who do not have the various risk factors listed in this labeling.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9676" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Because of these changes in practice and, also, because of some limited new data which suggest that the risk of cardiovascular disease with the use of oral contraceptives may now be less than previously observed, the Fertility and Maternal Health Drugs Advisory Committee was asked to review the topic in 1989.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9677" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The Committee concluded that although cardiovascular-disease risks may be increased with oral contraceptive use after age 40 in healthy non-smoking women (even with the newer low-dose formulations), there are greater potential health risks associated with pregnancy in older women and with the alternative surgical and medical procedures which may be necessary if such women do not have access to effective and acceptable means of contraception.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9678" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Therefore, the Committee recommended that the benefits of oral contraceptive use by healthy non-smoking women over 40 may outweigh the possible risks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9679" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Of course, older women, as all women who take oral contraceptives, should take the lowest possible dose formulation that is effective.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9680" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>TABLE III: ANNUAL NUMBER OF BIRTH-RELATED OR METHOD-RELATED DEATHS ASSOCIATED WITH CONTROL OF FERTILITY PER 100,000 NONSTERILE WOMEN, BY FERTILITY-CONTROL METHOD AND ACCORDING TO AGE Adapted from H.W.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9681" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Ory, Family Planning Perspectives, 15:57-63, 1983.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9682" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Method of control and outcome 15–19 20–24 25–29 30–34 35–39 40–44 No fertility- control methods* 7.0 7.4 9.1 14.8 25.7 28.2 Oral contraceptives non-smoker** 0.3 0.5 0.9 1.9 13.8 31.6 Oral contraceptives smoker ** 2.2 3.4 6.6 13.5 51.1 117.2 IUD** 0.8 0.8 1.0 1.0 1.4 1.4 Condom* 1.1 1.6 0.7 0.2 0.3 0.4 Diaphragm/spermicide* 1.9 1.2 1.2 1.3 2.2 2.8 Periodic abstinence* 2.5 1.6 1.6 1.7 2.9 3.6 *Deaths are birth-related **Deaths are method-related 3.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9683" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Carcinoma of the Reproductive Organs and Breasts Numerous epidemiological studies have been performed on the incidence of breast, endometrial, ovarian and cervical cancer in women using oral contraceptives.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9684" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Although the risk of having breast cancer diagnosed may be slightly increased among current and recent users of combined oral contraceptives (RR=1.24), this excess risk decreases over time after combination oral contraceptive discontinuation and by 10 years after cessation the increased risk disappears.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9685" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The risk does not increase with duration of use and no consistent relationships have been found with dose or type of steroid.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9686" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The patterns of risk are also similar regardless of a woman’s reproductive history or her family breast cancer history.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9687" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The subgroup for whom risk has been found to be significantly elevated is women who first used oral contraceptives before age 20, but because breast cancer is so rare at these young ages, the number of cases attributable to this early oral contraceptive use is extremely small.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9688" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Breast cancers diagnosed in current or previous oral contraceptive users tend to be less clinically advanced than in never-users.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9689" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Women who currently have or have had breast cancer should not use oral contraceptives because breast cancer is a hormone sensitive tumor.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9690" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Some studies suggest that oral contraceptive use has been associated with an increase in the risk of cervical intraepithelial neoplasia or invasive cervical cancer in some populations of women.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9691" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>However, there continues to be controversy about the extent to which such findings may be due to differences in sexual behavior and other factors.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9692" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>In spite of many studies of the relationship between oral contraceptive use and breast and cervical cancers, a cause-and-effect relationship has not been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9693" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Hepatic Neoplasia Benign hepatic adenomas are associated with oral contraceptive use, although the incidence of benign tumors is rare in the United States.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9694" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Indirect calculations have estimated the attributable risk to be in the range of 3.3 cases/100,000 for users, a risk that increases after 4 or more years of use.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9695" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Rupture of rare, benign, hepatic adenomas may cause death through intra-abdominal hemorrhage.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9696" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Studies from Britain have shown an increased risk of developing hepatocellular carcinoma in long-term (&gt;8 years) oral contraceptive users.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9697" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>However, these cancers are extremely rare in the U.S., and the attributable risk (the excess incidence) of liver cancers in oral contraceptive users approaches less than one per million users.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9698" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Risk of Liver Enzyme Elevations with Concomitant Hepatitis C Treatment During clinical trials with the Hepatitis C combination drug regimen that contains ombitasvir/paritaprevir/ritonavir, with or without dasabuvir, ALT elevations greater than 5 times the upper limit of normal (ULN), including some cases greater than 20 times the ULN, were significantly more frequent in women using ethinyl estradiol-containing medications such as COCs.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M142" type="Trigger" span="356 13" str="more frequent"/>
<Mention id="M137" type="Precipitant" span="103 84" str="Hepatitis C combination drug regimen that contains ombitasvir/paritaprevir/ritonavir" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M144" type="SpecificInteraction" span="216 22" str="ALT elevations greater" code="409673008:  Alanine aminotransferase (serum glutamic-pyruvic transaminase) level raised (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M139" type="Trigger" span="0 7" str="Risk of"/>
<Mention id="M140" type="Precipitant" span="49 21;154 33" str="Hepatitis C Treatment | ombitasvir/paritaprevir/ritonavir" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M141" type="SpecificInteraction" span="8 23" str="Liver Enzyme Elevations" code="707724006: Elevated liver enzymes level (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M143" type="Precipitant" span="154 33" str="ombitasvir/paritaprevir/ritonavir" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I53" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M142" precipitant="M137" effect="M144" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I54" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M139" precipitant="M140" effect="M141" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I55" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M142" precipitant="M143" effect="M144" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9699" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Discontinue Ogestrel prior to starting therapy with the combination drug regimen ombitasvir/paritaprevir/ritonavir, with or without dasabuvir.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M145" type="Trigger" span="0 11" str="Discontinue"/>
<Mention id="M146" type="Precipitant" span="81 33" str="ombitasvir/paritaprevir/ritonavir" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I56" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M145" precipitant="M146"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9700" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Ogestrel can be restarted approximately 2 weeks following completion of treatment with the combination drug regimen.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9701" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Ocular Lesions There have been clinical case reports of retinal thrombosis associated with the use of oral contraceptives that may lead to partial or complete loss of vision.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9702" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Oral contraceptives should be discontinued if there is unexplained partial or complete loss of vision; onset of proptosis or diplopia; papilledema; or retinal vascular lesions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9703" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Appropriate diagnostic and therapeutic measures should be undertaken immediately.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9704" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Oral Contraceptive Use Before or During Early Pregnancy Extensive epidemiological studies have revealed no increased risk of birth defects in infants born to women who have used oral contraceptives prior to pregnancy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9705" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Studies also do not suggest a teratogenic effect, particularly insofar as cardiac anomalies and limb-reduction defects are concerned, when taken inadvertently during early pregnancy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9706" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The administration of oral contraceptives to induce withdrawal bleeding should not be used as a test for pregnancy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9707" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Oral contraceptives should not be used during pregnancy to treat threatened or habitual abortion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9708" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>It is recommended that for any patient who has missed 2 consecutive periods, pregnancy should be ruled out.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9709" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>If the patient has not adhered to the prescribed schedule, the possibility of pregnancy should be considered at the time of the first missed period.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9710" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Oral contraceptive use should be discontinued if pregnancy is confirmed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9711" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Gallbladder Disease Earlier studies have reported an increased lifetime relative risk of gallbladder surgery in users of oral contraceptives and estrogens.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9712" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>More recent studies, however, have shown that the relative risk of developing gallbladder disease among oral contraceptive users may be minimal.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9713" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The recent findings of minimal risk may be related to the use of oral contraceptive formulations containing lower hormonal doses of estrogens and progestogens.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9714" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Carbohydrate and Lipid Metabolic Effects Oral contraceptives have been shown to cause glucose intolerance in a significant percentage of users.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9715" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Oral contraceptives containing greater than 75 mcg of estrogens cause hyperinsulinism, while lower doses of estrogen cause less glucose intolerance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9716" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Progestogens increase insulin secretion and create insulin resistance, this effect varying with different progestational agents.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9717" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>However, in the non-diabetic woman, oral contraceptives appear to have no effect on fasting blood glucose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9718" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Because of these demonstrated effects, prediabetic and diabetic women should be carefully observed while taking oral contraceptives.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9719" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>A small proportion of women will have persistent hypertriglyceridemia while on the pill.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9720" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>As discussed earlier, changes in serum triglycerides and lipoprotein levels have been reported in oral contraceptive users.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9721" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Elevated Blood Pressure Women with significant hypertension should not be started on hormonal contraception.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9722" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>An increase in blood pressure has been reported in women taking oral contraceptives, and this increase is more likely in older oral contraceptive users and with continued use.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9723" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Data from the Royal College of General Practitioners and subsequent randomized trials have shown that the incidence of hypertension increases with increasing quantities of progestogens.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9724" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Women with a history of hypertension or hypertension-related diseases, or renal disease, should be encouraged to use another method of contraception.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9725" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>If women with hypertension elect to use oral contraceptives, they should be monitored closely, and if significant elevation of blood pressure occurs, oral contraceptives should be discontinued.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9726" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>For most women, elevated blood pressure will return to normal after stopping oral contraceptives, and there is no difference in the occurrence of hypertension among ever- and never-users.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9727" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Headache The onset or exacerbation of migraine or development of headache with a new pattern that is recurrent, persistent, or severe requires discontinuation of oral contraceptives and evaluation of the cause.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9728" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Bleeding Irregularities Breakthrough bleeding and spotting are sometimes encountered in patients on oral contraceptives, especially during the first 3 months of use.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9729" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The type and dose of progestogen may be important.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9730" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>If bleeding persists or recurs, non-hormonal causes should be considered and adequate diagnostic measures taken to rule out malignancy or pregnancy in the event of breakthrough bleeding, as in the case of any abnormal vaginal bleeding.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9731" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>If pathology has been excluded, time or a change to another formulation may solve the problem.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9732" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>In the event of amenorrhea, pregnancy should be ruled out.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9733" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Some women may encounter post-pill amenorrhea or oligomenorrhea (possibly with anovulation), especially when such a condition was pre-existent.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9734" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Ectopic Pregnancy Ectopic as well as intrauterine pregnancy may occur in contraceptive failures.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9735" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Mode of Action Combination oral contraceptives act by suppression of gonadotropins.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9736" LabelDrug="Ogestrel" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Although the primary mechanism of this action is inhibition of ovulation, other alterations include changes in the cervical mucus (which increase the difficulty of sperm entry into the uterus) and the endometrium (which reduce the likelihood of implantation).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="hepatitis c drug combinations containing ombitasvir/paritaprevir/ritonavir" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="409673008:  Alanine aminotransferase (serum glutamic-pyruvic transaminase) level raised (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ombitasvir/paritaprevir/ritonavir" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="409673008:  Alanine aminotransferase (serum glutamic-pyruvic transaminase) level raised (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="ombitasvir/paritaprevir/ritonavir" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="antibiotics" precipitantCode="N0000178296 | n0000029074 | N0000178300" effect="102955006: Contraception failure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="antibiotics" precipitantCode="N0000178296 | n0000029074 | N0000178300" effect="56169002: Break-through bleeding (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="antibiotics" precipitantCode="N0000178296 | n0000029074 | N0000178300" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="anticonvulsants" precipitantCode="N0000029145 | N0000175753" effect="102955006: Contraception failure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="anticonvulsants" precipitantCode="N0000029145 | N0000175753" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="drugs that increase the metabolism of contraceptive steroids" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="102955006: Contraception failure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="drugs that increase the metabolism of contraceptive steroids" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ampicillin" precipitantCode="7C782967RD" effect="102955006: Contraception failure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ampicillin" precipitantCode="7C782967RD" effect="56169002: Break-through bleeding (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="tetracyclines" precipitantCode="N0000175882" effect="102955006: Contraception failure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="tetracyclines" precipitantCode="N0000175882" effect="56169002: Break-through bleeding (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="anti-hiv protease inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000000246"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="hiv protease inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175520 | N0000000246"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="hypericum perforatum" precipitantCode="XK4IUX8MNB" effect="102955006: Contraception failure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="st. john’s wort" precipitantCode="N0000022261 | UFH8805FKA" effect="102955006: Contraception failure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="atorvastatin" precipitantCode="A0JWA85V8F | N0000022046" effect="C54605"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="acetaminophen" precipitantCode="362O9ITL9D" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="acetaminophen" precipitantCode="362O9ITL9D" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="ascorbic acid" precipitantCode="PQ6CK8PD0R" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cyp 3a4 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000182141" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="itraconazole" precipitantCode="304NUG5GF4 | N0000006753" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="ketoconazole" precipitantCode="N0000007319 | R9400W927I" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cyclosporin" precipitantCode="83HN0GTJ6D" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="prednisolone" precipitantCode="9PHQ9Y1OLM" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="theophylline" precipitantCode="N0000007076 | C137DTR5RG" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="clofibric acid" precipitantCode="53PF01Q249" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="morphine" precipitantCode="76I7G6D29C" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="salicylic acid" precipitantCode="O414PZ4LPZ" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="temazepam" precipitantCode="CHB1QD2QSS" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="troleandomycin" precipitantCode="C4DZ64560D" effect="4637005: Intrahepatic cholestasis (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="hcv combination therapy" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="707724006: Elevated liver enzymes level (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="hcv drug combinations containing ombitasvir/paritaprevir/ritonavir" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="409673008:  Alanine aminotransferase (serum glutamic-pyruvic transaminase) level raised (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="free t3 resin" precipitantCode="06LU7C9H1V" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cigarette smoking" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="267037003: Cardiovascular symptoms (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="cigarettes" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="smoking" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="22298006: Myocardial infarction (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="smoking" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="5571000124103: Cerebrovascular accident with intracranial hemorrhage (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="smoking" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="smoke" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="230690007: Cerebrovascular accident (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="smoke" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="371040005: Thrombotic stroke (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="smoke" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="5571000124103: Cerebrovascular accident with intracranial hemorrhage (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="smoke" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="62914000: Cerebrovascular disease (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="smoke" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="hepatitis c combination drug regimen that contains ombitasvir/paritaprevir/ritonavir" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="409673008:  Alanine aminotransferase (serum glutamic-pyruvic transaminase) level raised (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="hepatitis c treatment | ombitasvir/paritaprevir/ritonavir" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="707724006: Elevated liver enzymes level (finding)"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>