<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Dexilant" setid="9819f033-3bbe-442e-8e92-45fec77b237d">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
DEXILANT is contraindicated in patients with known hypersensitivity to any component of the formulation [see Description (11) ] . Hypersensitivity reactions, including anaphylaxis have been reported [see Adverse Reactions (6.1 , 6.2) ]. Acute interstitial nephritis (AIN) has been reported with other proton pump inhibitors (PPIs), including lansoprazole of which dexlansoprazole is the R-enantiomer . PPIs, including DEXILANT, are contraindicated with rilpivirine-containing products [see Drug Interactions (7) ]. Patients with known hypersensitivity to any component of the formulation. ( 4 ) Patients receiving rilpivirine-containing products. ( 4 , 7 )</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
Recommended dosage in patients 12 years of age and older : See full prescribing information for complete dosing information for DEXILANT by indication and age group and dosage adjustment in patients with hepatic impairment. ( 2.1 , 2.2 ) Administration Instructions ( 2.3 ) : Take without regard to food. Swallow whole; do not chew. See full prescribing information for alternative administration options. Table 1. Recommended DEXILANT Capsules Dosage Regimen by Indication in Patients 12 Years of Age and Older Indication Dosage of DEXILANT Capsules Duration Healing of EE One 60 mg capsule once daily. Up to 8 weeks. Maintenance of Healed EE and Relief of Heartburn One 30 mg capsule once daily. Controlled studies did not extend beyond 6 months in adults and 16 weeks in patients 12 to 17 years of age. Symptomatic Non-Erosive GERD One 30 mg capsule once daily. 4 weeks. For patients with moderate hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh Class B), the recommended dosage is 30 mg DEXILANT once daily for up to eight weeks. DEXILANT is not recommended in patients with severe hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh Class C) [see Use in Specific Populations (8.6) ]. Take without regard to food. Missed doses: If a dose is missed, administer as soon as possible. However, if the next scheduled dose is due, do not take the missed dose, and take the next dose on time. Do not take two doses at one time to make up for a missed dose. Swallow whole; do not chew. For patients who have trouble swallowing capsules, DEXILANT capsules can be opened and administered with applesauce as follows: Place one tablespoonful of applesauce into a clean container. Open capsule. Sprinkle intact granules on applesauce. Swallow applesauce and granules immediately. Do not chew granules. Do not save the applesauce and granules for later use. Alternatively, the capsule can be administered with water via oral syringe or nasogastric (NG) tube. Administration with Water in an Oral Syringe Open the capsule and empty the granules into a clean container with 20 mL of water. Withdraw the entire mixture into a syringe. Gently swirl the syringe in order to keep granules from settling. Administer the mixture immediately into the mouth. Do not save the water and granule mixture for later use. Refill the syringe with 10 mL of water, swirl gently, and administer. Refill the syringe again with 10 mL of water, swirl gently, and administer. Administration with Water via a NG Tube (≥16 French) Open the capsule and empty the granules into a clean container with 20 mL of water. Withdraw the entire mixture into a catheter-tip syringe. Swirl the catheter-tip syringe gently in order to keep the granules from settling, and immediately inject the mixture through the NG tube into the stomach. Do not save the water and granule mixture for later use. Refill the catheter-tip syringe with 10 mL of water, swirl gently, and flush the tube. Refill the catheter-tip syringe again with 10 mL of water, swirl gently, and administer.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
Tables 3 and 4 include drugs with clinically important drug interactions and interaction with diagnostics when administered concomitantly with DEXILANT and instructions for preventing or managing them. Consult the labeling of concomitantly used drugs to obtain further information about interactions with PPIs. Table 3. Clinically Relevant Interactions Affecting Drugs Co-Administered with DEXILANT and Interactions with Diagnostics Antiretrovirals Clinical Impact: The effect of PPIs on antiretroviral drugs is variable. The clinical importance and the mechanisms behind these interactions are not always known. Decreased exposure of some antiretroviral drugs (e.g., rilpivirine, atazanavir, and nelfinavir) when used concomitantly with dexlansoprazole may reduce antiviral effect and promote the development of drug resistance . Increased exposure of other antiretroviral drugs (e.g., saquinavir) when used concomitantly with dexlansoprazole may increase toxicity of the antiretroviral drugs. There are other antiretroviral drugs which do not result in clinically relevant interactions with dexlansoprazole. Intervention: Rilpivirine-containing products : Concomitant use with DEXILANT is contraindicated [see Contraindications (4) ] . See prescribing information. Atazanavir : See prescribing information for atazanavir for dosing information. Nelfinavir : Avoid concomitant use with DEXILANT. See prescribing information for nelfinavir. Saquinavir : See the prescribing information for saquinavir and monitor for potential saquinavir toxicities. Other antiretrovirals : See prescribing information. Warfarin Clinical Impact: Increased INR and prothrombin time in patients receiving PPIs and warfarin concomitantly. Increases in INR and prothrombin time may lead to abnormal bleeding and even death. Intervention: Monitor INR and prothrombin time. Dose adjustment of warfarin may be needed to maintain target INR range. See prescribing information for warfarin. Methotrexate Clinical Impact: Concomitant use of PPIs with methotrexate (primarily at high dose) may elevate and prolong serum concentrations of methotrexate and/or its metabolite hydroxymethotrexate, possibly leading to methotrexate toxicities. No formal drug interaction studies of high-dose methotrexate with PPIs have been conducted [see Warnings and Precautions (5.9) ]. Intervention: A temporary withdrawal of DEXILANT may be considered in some patients receiving high-dose methotrexate. Digoxin Clinical Impact: Potential for increased exposure of digoxin. Intervention: Monitor digoxin concentrations. Dose adjustment of digoxin may be needed to maintain therapeutic drug concentrations. See prescribing information for digoxin. Drugs Dependent on Gastric pH for Absorption (e.g., iron salts, erlotinib, dasatinib, nilotinib, mycophenolate mofetil, ketoconazole/itraconazole) Clinical Impact: Dexlansoprazole can reduce the absorption of other drugs due to its effect on reducing intragastric acidity. Intervention: Mycophenolate mofetil (MMF): Co-administration of PPIs in healthy subjects and in transplant patients receiving MMF has been reported to reduce the exposure to the active metabolite, mycophenolic acid (MPA), possibly due to a decrease in MMF solubility at an increased gastric pH. The clinical relevance of reduced MPA exposure on organ rejection has not been established in transplant patients receiving DEXILANT and MMF. Use DEXILANT with caution in transplant patients receiving MMF. See the prescribing information for other drugs dependent on gastric pH for absorption. Tacrolimus Clinical Impact: Potentially increased exposure of tacrolimus, especially in transplant patients who are intermediate or poor metabolizers of CYP2C19 . Intervention: Monitor tacrolimus whole blood trough concentrations. Dose adjustment of tacrolimus may be needed to maintain therapeutic drug concentrations. See prescribing information for tacrolimus. Interactions with Investigations of Neuroendocrine Tumors Clinical Impact: CgA levels increase secondary to PPI-induced decreases in gastric acidity. The increased CgA level may cause false positive results in diagnostic investigations for neuroendocrine tumors [see Warnings and Precautions (5.8) , Clinical Pharmacology (12.2) ]. Intervention: Temporarily stop DEXILANT treatment at least 14 days before assessing CgA levels and consider repeating the test if initial CgA levels are high. If serial tests are performed (e.g., for monitoring), the same commercial laboratory should be used for testing, as reference ranges between tests may vary. Interaction with Secretin Stimulation Test Clinical Impact: Hyper-response in gastrin secretion in response to secretin stimulation test, falsely suggesting gastrinoma. Intervention: Temporarily stop DEXILANT treatment at least 30 days before assessing to allow gastrin levels to return to baseline [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.2) ]. False Positive Urine Tests for THC Clinical Impact: There have been reports of false positive urine screening tests for tetrahydrocannabinol (THC) in patients receiving PPIs. Intervention: An alternative confirmatory method should be considered to verify positive results. Table 4. Clinically Relevant Interactions Affecting DEXILANT When Co-Administered with Other Drugs and Substances CYP2C19 or CYP3A4 Inducers Clinical Impact: Decreased exposure of dexlansoprazole when used concomitantly with strong inducers [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3) ]. Intervention: St. John's Wort, rifampin : Avoid concomitant use with DEXILANT. Ritonavir-containing products : See prescribing information. CYP2C19 or CYP3A4 Inhibitors Clinical Impact: Increased exposure of dexlansoprazole is expected when used concomitantly with strong inhibitors [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3) ]. Intervention: Voriconazole : See prescribing information. See full prescribing information for a list of clinically important drug interactions. ( 7 )</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
Gastric Malignancy : In adults, symptomatic response with DEXILANT does not preclude the presence of gastric malignancy. Consider additional follow-up and diagnostic testing. ( 5.1 ) Acute Interstitial Nephritis : Observed in patients taking PPIs. ( 5.2 ) Clostridium difficile -Associated Diarrhea : PPI therapy may be associated with increased risk. ( 5.3 ) Bone Fracture : Long-term and multiple daily dose PPI therapy may be associated with an increased risk for osteoporosis-related fractures of the hip, wrist or spine. ( 5.4 ) Cutaneous and Systemic Lupus Erythematosus : Mostly cutaneous; new onset or exacerbation of existing disease; discontinue DEXILANT and refer to specialist for evaluation. ( 5.5 ) Cyanocobalamin (Vitamin B12) Deficiency : Daily long-term use (e.g., longer than 3 years) may lead to malabsorption or a deficiency of cyanocobalamin. ( 5.6 ) Hypomagnesemia : Reported rarely with prolonged treatment with PPIs. ( 5.7 ) Interactions with Investigations for Neuroendocrine Tumors : Increases in intragastric pH may result in hypergastrinemia and enterochromaffin-like cell hyperplasia and increased chromogranin A levels which may interfere with diagnostic investigations for neuroendocrine tumors. ( 5.8 , 7 ) Interaction with Methotrexate : Concomitant use with PPIs may elevate and/or prolong serum concentrations of methotrexate and/or its metabolite, possibly leading to toxicity. With high-dose methotrexate administration, consider a temporary withdrawal of DEXILANT. ( 5.9 , 7 ) Fundic Gland Polyps : Risk increases with long-term use, especially beyond 1 year. Use the shortest duration of therapy. ( 5.10 ) In adults, symptomatic response to therapy with DEXILANT does not preclude the presence of gastric malignancy. Consider additional follow-up and diagnostic testing in adult patients who have a suboptimal response or an early symptomatic relapse after completing treatment with a PPI. In older patients, also consider an endoscopy. Acute interstitial nephritis has been observed in patients taking PPIs including lansoprazole . Acute interstitial nephritis may occur at any point during PPI therapy and is generally attributed to an idiopathic hypersensitivity reaction. Discontinue DEXILANT if acute interstitial nephritis develops [see Contraindications (4) ] . Published observational studies suggest that PPI therapy like DEXILANT may be associated with an increased risk of Clostridium difficile -associated diarrhea, especially in hospitalized patients. This diagnosis should be considered for diarrhea that does not improve [see Adverse Reactions (6.2) ]. Patients should use the lowest dose and shortest duration of PPI therapy appropriate to the condition being treated. Several published observational studies suggest that PPI therapy may be associated with an increased risk for osteoporosis-related fractures of the hip, wrist or spine. The risk of fracture was increased in patients who received high-dose, defined as multiple daily doses, and long-term PPI therapy (a year or longer). Patients should use the lowest dose and shortest duration of PPI therapy appropriate to the conditions being treated. Patients at risk for osteoporosis-related fractures should be managed according to established treatment guidelines [see Dosage and Administration (2) , Adverse Reactions (6.2) ]. Cutaneous lupus erythematosus (CLE) and systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE) have been reported in patients taking PPIs. These events have occurred as both new onset and an exacerbation of existing autoimmune disease. The majority of PPI-induced lupus erythematosus cases were CLE. The most common form of CLE reported in patients treated with PPIs was subacute CLE (SCLE) and occurred within weeks to years after continuous drug therapy in patients ranging from infants to the elderly. Generally, histological findings were observed without organ involvement. Systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE) is less commonly reported than CLE in patients receiving PPIs. PPI-associated SLE is usually milder than non-drug induced SLE. Onset of SLE typically occurred within days to years after initiating treatment primarily in patients ranging from young adults to the elderly. The majority of patients presented with rash; however, arthralgia and cytopenia were also reported. Avoid administration of PPIs for longer than medically indicated. If signs or symptoms consistent with CLE or SLE are noted in patients receiving DEXILANT, discontinue the drug and refer the patient to the appropriate specialist for evaluation. Most patients improve with discontinuation of the PPI alone in four to 12 weeks. Serological testing (e.g., ANA) may be positive and elevated serological test results may take longer to resolve than clinical manifestations. Daily treatment with any acid-suppressing medications over a long period of time (e.g., longer than three years) may lead to malabsorption of cyanocobalamin (Vitamin B12) caused by hypo- or achlorhydria. Rare reports of cyanocobalamin deficiency occurring with acid-suppressing therapy have been reported in the literature. This diagnosis should be considered if clinical symptoms consistent with cyanocobalamin deficiency are observed in patients treated with DEXILANT. Hypomagnesemia, symptomatic and asymptomatic, has been reported rarely in patients treated with PPIs for at least three months, in most cases after a year of therapy. Serious adverse events include tetany, arrhythmias, and seizures. In most patients, treatment of hypomagnesemia required magnesium replacement and discontinuation of the PPI. For patients expected to be on prolonged treatment or who take PPIs with medications such as digoxin or drugs that may cause hypomagnesemia (e.g., diuretics), healthcare professionals may consider monitoring magnesium levels prior to initiation of PPI treatment and periodically [see Adverse Reactions (6.2) ]. Serum chromogranin A (CgA) levels increase secondary to drug-induced decreases in gastric acidity. The increased CgA level may cause false positive results in diagnostic investigations for neuroendocrine tumors. Healthcare providers should temporarily stop dexlansoprazole treatment at least 14 days before assessing CgA levels and consider repeating the test if initial CgA levels are high. If serial tests are performed (e.g., for monitoring), the same commercial laboratory should be used for testing, as reference ranges between tests may vary [see Drug Interactions (7) , Clinical Pharmacology (12.2) ]. Literature suggests that concomitant use of PPIs with methotrexate (primarily at high dose) may elevate and prolong serum levels of methotrexate and/or its metabolite, possibly leading to methotrexate toxicities. In high-dose methotrexate administration, a temporary withdrawal of the PPI may be considered in some patients [see Drug Interactions (7) ]. PPI use is associated with an increased risk of fundic gland polyps that increases with long-term use, especially beyond one year. Most PPI users who developed fundic gland polyps were asymptomatic and fundic gland polyps were identified incidentally on endoscopy. Use the shortest duration of PPI therapy appropriate to the condition being treated.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Dexlansoprazole belongs to a class of antisecretory compounds, the substituted benzimidazoles, that suppress gastric acid secretion by specific inhibition of the (H + , K + )-ATPase at the secretory surface of the gastric parietal cell. Because this enzyme is regarded as the acid (proton) pump within the parietal cell, dexlansoprazole has been characterized as a gastric proton-pump inhibitor, in that it blocks the final step of acid production. Antisecretory Activity The effects of DEXILANT 60 mg (n=20) or lansoprazole 30 mg (n=23) once daily for five days on 24 hour intragastric pH were assessed in healthy subjects in a multiple-dose crossover study. The results are summarized in Table 5. Table 5. Effect on 24 Hour Intragastric pH on Day 5 After Administration of DEXILANT or Lansoprazole DEXILANT 60 mg Lansoprazole 30 mg Mean Intragastric pH 4.55 4.13 % Time Intragastric pH &amp;gt;4 (hours) 71 (17 hours) 60 (14 hours) Serum Gastrin Effects The effect of dexlansoprazole on serum gastrin concentrations was evaluated in approximately 3460 patients in clinical trials up to eight weeks and in 1023 patients for up to six to 12 months. The mean fasting gastrin concentrations increased from baseline during treatment with 30 and 60 mg DEXILANT. In patients treated for more than six months, mean serum gastrin levels increased during approximately the first three months of treatment and were stable for the remainder of treatment. Mean serum gastrin levels returned to pre-treatment levels within one month of discontinuation of treatment. Increased gastrin causes enterochromaffin-like cell hyperplasia and increased serum CgA levels. The increased CgA levels may cause false positive results in diagnostic investigations for neuroendocrine tumors [see Warnings and Precautions (5.8) ] . Enterochromaffin-Like Cell (ECL) Effects There were no reports of ECL cell hyperplasia in gastric biopsy specimens obtained from 653 patients treated with DEXILANT 30, 60, or 90 mg for up to 12 months. During lifetime exposure of rats dosed daily with up to 150 mg/kg/day of lansoprazole, marked hypergastrinemia was observed followed by ECL cell proliferation and formation of carcinoid tumors, especially in female rats [see Nonclinical Toxicology (13.1) ] . Cardiac Electrophysiology At a dose five times the maximum recommended dose, dexlansoprazole does not prolong the QT interval to any clinically relevant extent. The dual delayed-release formulation of DEXILANT results in a dexlansoprazole plasma concentration-time profile with two distinct peaks; the first peak occurs one to two hours after administration, followed by a second peak within four to five hours ( see Figure 1 ). Dexlansoprazole is eliminated with a half-life of approximately one to two hours in healthy subjects and in patients with symptomatic GERD. No accumulation of dexlansoprazole occurs after multiple, once daily doses of DEXILANT 30 or 60 mg although mean AUC t and C max values of dexlansoprazole were slightly higher (less than 10%) on Day 5 than on Day 1. Figure 1: Mean Plasma Dexlansoprazole Concentration – Time Profile Following Oral Administration of 30 or 60 mg DEXILANT Once Daily for 5 Days in Healthy Adult Subjects The pharmacokinetics of dexlansoprazole are highly variable, with percent coefficient of variation (%CV) values for C max , AUC, and CL/F of greater than 30% (see Table 6 ) . Table 6. Mean (%CV) Pharmacokinetic Parameters for Adult Subjects on Day 5 After Administration of DEXILANT Dose (mg) C max (ng/mL) AUC 24 (ng∙h/mL) CL/F (L/h) 30 658 (40%) (N=44) 3275 (47%) (N=43) 11.4 (48%) (N=43) 60 1397 (51%) (N=79) 6529 (60%) (N=73) 11.6 (46%) (N=41) Absorption After oral administration of DEXILANT 30 or 60 mg to healthy subjects and symptomatic GERD patients, mean C max and AUC values of dexlansoprazole increased approximately dose proportionally ( see Figure 1 ). When granules of DEXILANT 60 mg are mixed with water and dosed via NG tube or orally via syringe, the bioavailability (C max and AUC) of dexlansoprazole was similar to that when DEXILANT 60 mg was administered as an intact capsule [see Dosage and Administration (2.3) ]. Effect on Food In food-effect studies in healthy subjects receiving DEXILANT under various fed conditions compared to fasting, increases in C max ranged from 12 to 55%, increases in AUC ranged from 9 to 37%, and T max varied (ranging from a decrease of 0.7 hours to an increase of three hours) [see Dosage and Administration (2.3) ]. Distribution Plasma protein binding of dexlansoprazole ranged from 96 to 99% in healthy subjects and was independent of concentration from 0.01 to 20 mcg/mL. The apparent volume of distribution (V z /F) after multiple doses in symptomatic GERD patients was 40 L. Elimination Metabolism Dexlansoprazole is extensively metabolized in the liver by oxidation, reduction, and subsequent formation of sulfate, glucuronide and glutathione conjugates to inactive metabolites. Oxidative metabolites are formed by the cytochrome P450 (CYP) enzyme system including hydroxylation mainly by CYP2C19, and oxidation to the sulfone by CYP3A4. CYP2C19 is a polymorphic liver enzyme which exhibits three phenotypes in the metabolism of CYP2C19 substrates: extensive metabolizers (*1/*1), intermediate metabolizers (*1/mutant) and poor metabolizers (mutant/mutant). Dexlansoprazole is the major circulating component in plasma regardless of CYP2C19 metabolizer status. In CYP2C19 intermediate and extensive metabolizers, the major plasma metabolites are 5-hydroxy dexlansoprazole and its glucuronide conjugate, while in CYP2C19 poor metabolizers dexlansoprazole sulfone is the major plasma metabolite. Excretion Following the administration of DEXILANT, no unchanged dexlansoprazole is excreted in urine. Following the administration of [ 14 C] dexlansoprazole to six healthy male subjects, approximately 50.7% (standard deviation (SD): 9.0%) of the administered radioactivity was excreted in urine and 47.6% (SD: 7.3%) in the feces. Apparent clearance (CL/F) in healthy subjects was 11.4 to 11.6 L/hour, respectively, after five days of 30 or 60 mg once daily administration. Specific Populations Age: Pediatric Population The pharmacokinetics of dexlansoprazole in patients under the age of 12 years have not been studied. Patients 12 to 17 Years of Age The pharmacokinetics of dexlansoprazole were studied in 36 patients 12 to 17 years of age with symptomatic GERD in a multi-center trial. Patients were randomized to receive DEXILANT 30 or 60 mg once daily for seven days. The dexlansoprazole mean C max and AUC in patients 12 to 17 years of age were 105 and 88%, respectively, compared to those observed in adults at the 30 mg dose, and were 81 and 78%, respectively, at the 60 mg dose (see Tables 6 and 7 ) . Table 7. Mean (%CV) Pharmacokinetic Parameters in Patients 12 to 17 Years of Age with Symptomatic GERD on Day 7 After Administration of DEXILANT Once Daily for 7 Days Dose C max (ng/mL) AUC tau (ng∙h/mL) CL/F (L/h) 30 mg (N=17) 691 (53) 2886 (47) 12.8 (48) 60 mg (N=18) 1136 (51) 5120 (58) 15.3 (49) Age: Geriatric Population The terminal elimination half-life of dexlansoprazole is significantly increased in geriatric subjects compared to younger subjects (2.2 and 1.5 hours, respectively). Dexlansoprazole exhibited higher systemic exposure (AUC) in geriatric subjects (34% higher) than younger subjects [see Use in Specific Populations (8.5) ]. Sex In a study of 12 male and 12 female healthy subjects who received a single dose of DEXILANT 60 mg, females had higher systemic exposure (AUC) (43% higher) than males. This difference in exposure between males and female does not represent a significant safety concern. Renal Impairment Dexlansoprazole is extensively metabolized in the liver to inactive metabolites, and no parent drug is recovered in the urine following an oral dose of dexlansoprazole. Therefore, the pharmacokinetics of dexlansoprazole are not expected to be altered in patients with renal impairment, and no studies were conducted in patients with renal impairment. In addition, the pharmacokinetics of lansoprazole were not clinically different in patients with mild, moderate or severe renal impairment compared to healthy subjects with normal renal function. Hepatic Impairment In a study of 12 patients with moderate hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh Class B) who received a single dose of 60 mg DEXILANT, the systemic exposure (AUC) of bound and unbound dexlansoprazole was approximately two times greater compared to subjects with normal hepatic function. This difference in exposure was not due to a difference in protein binding. No studies have been conducted in patients with severe hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh Class C) [see Dosage and Administration (2.2) , Use in Specific Populations (8.6) ]. Drug-Drug Interactions Effect of Dexlansoprazole on Other Drugs Cytochrome P 450 Interactions Dexlansoprazole is metabolized, in part, by CYP2C19 and CYP3A4 [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3) ] . In vitro studies have shown that dexlansoprazole is not likely to inhibit CYP isoforms 1A1, 1A2, 2A6, 2B6, 2C8, 2C9, 2D6, 2E1 or 3A4. As such, no clinically relevant interactions with drugs metabolized by these CYP enzymes would be expected. Furthermore, in vivo studies showed that DEXILANT did not have an impact on the pharmacokinetics of co-administered phenytoin (CYP2C9 substrate) or theophylline (CYP1A2 substrate). The subjects' CYP1A2 genotypes in the drug-drug interaction study with theophylline were not determined. Although in vitro studies indicated that DEXILANT has the potential to inhibit CYP2C19 in vivo , an in vivo drug-drug interaction study in mainly CYP2C19 extensive and intermediate metabolizers has shown that DEXILANT does not affect the pharmacokinetics of diazepam (CYP2C19 substrate). Clopidogrel Clopidogrel is metabolized to its active metabolite in part by CYP2C19. A study of healthy subjects who were CYP2C19 extensive metabolizers, receiving once daily administration of clopidogrel 75 mg alone or concomitantly with DEXILANT 60 mg (n=40), for nine days was conducted. The mean AUC of the active metabolite of clopidogrel was reduced by approximately 9% (mean AUC ratio was 91%, with 90% CI of 86 to 97%) when DEXILANT was co-administered compared to administration of clopidogrel alone. Pharmacodynamic parameters were also measured and demonstrated that the change in inhibition of platelet aggregation (induced by 5 mcM ADP) was related to the change in the exposure to clopidogrel active metabolite. The effect on exposure to the active metabolite of clopidogrel and on clopidogrel-induced platelet inhibition is not considered clinically important. Effect of Other Drugs on Dexlansoprazole Because dexlansoprazole is metabolized by CYP2C19 and CYP3A4, inducers and inhibitors of these enzymes may potentially alter exposure of dexlansoprazole. Figure 1 Effect of CYP2C19 Polymorphism on Systemic Exposure of Dexlansoprazole Systemic exposure of dexlansoprazole is generally higher in intermediate and poor metabolizers. In male Japanese subjects who received a single dose of DEXILANT 30 or 60 mg (N=2 to 6 subjects/group), mean dexlansoprazole C max and AUC values were up to two times higher in intermediate compared to extensive metabolizers; in poor metabolizers, mean C max was up to four times higher and mean AUC was up to 12 times higher compared to extensive metabolizers. Though such study was not conducted in Caucasians and African Americans, it is expected dexlansoprazole exposure in these races will be affected by CYP2C19 phenotypes as well.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="2856" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>DEXILANT is contraindicated in patients with known hypersensitivity to any component of the formulation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2857" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Hypersensitivity reactions, including anaphylaxis have been reported.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2858" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Acute interstitial nephritis (AIN) has been reported with other proton pump inhibitors (PPIs), including lansoprazole of which dexlansoprazole is the R-enantiomer.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2859" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>PPIs, including DEXILANT, are contraindicated with rilpivirine-containing products.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M3" type="Trigger" span="30 15" str="contraindicated"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="51 11" str="rilpivirine" code="FI96A8X663"/>
<Mention id="M4" type="Precipitant" span="51 31" str="rilpivirine-containing products" code="FI96A8X663"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M3" precipitant="M2"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M3" precipitant="M4"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2860" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Patients with known hypersensitivity to any component of the formulation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2861" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Patients receiving rilpivirine-containing products.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2862" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Recommended dosage in patients 12 years of age and older: See full prescribing information for complete dosing information for DEXILANT by indication and age group and dosage adjustment in patients with hepatic impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2863" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Administration Instructions (2.3): Take without regard to food.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2864" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>See full prescribing information for alternative administration options.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2865" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Recommended DEXILANT Capsules Dosage Regimen by Indication in Patients 12 Years of Age and Older Indication Dosage of DEXILANT Capsules Duration Healing of EE One 60 mg capsule once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2866" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Maintenance of Healed EE and Relief of Heartburn One 30 mg capsule once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2867" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Controlled studies did not extend beyond 6 months in adults and 16 weeks in patients 12 to 17 years of age.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2868" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Symptomatic Non-Erosive GERD One 30 mg capsule once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2869" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For patients with moderate hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh Class B), the recommended dosage is 30 mg DEXILANT once daily for up to eight weeks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2870" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>DEXILANT is not recommended in patients with severe hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh Class C).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2871" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Missed doses: If a dose is missed, administer as soon as possible.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2872" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>However, if the next scheduled dose is due, do not take the missed dose, and take the next dose on time.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2873" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not take two doses at one time to make up for a missed dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2874" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For patients who have trouble swallowing capsules, DEXILANT capsules can be opened and administered with applesauce as follows: Place one tablespoonful of applesauce into a clean container.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2875" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Swallow applesauce and granules immediately.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2876" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not save the applesauce and granules for later use.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2877" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Alternatively, the capsule can be administered with water via oral syringe or nasogastric (NG) tube.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2878" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Administration with Water in an Oral Syringe Open the capsule and empty the granules into a clean container with 20 mL of water.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2879" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Withdraw the entire mixture into a syringe.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2880" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Gently swirl the syringe in order to keep granules from settling.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2881" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Administer the mixture immediately into the mouth.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2882" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not save the water and granule mixture for later use.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2883" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Refill the syringe with 10 mL of water, swirl gently, and administer.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2884" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Refill the syringe again with 10 mL of water, swirl gently, and administer.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2885" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Administration with Water via a NG Tube (≥16 French) Open the capsule and empty the granules into a clean container with 20 mL of water.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2886" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Withdraw the entire mixture into a catheter-tip syringe.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2887" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Swirl the catheter-tip syringe gently in order to keep the granules from settling, and immediately inject the mixture through the NG tube into the stomach.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2888" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Refill the catheter-tip syringe with 10 mL of water, swirl gently, and flush the tube.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2889" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Refill the catheter-tip syringe again with 10 mL of water, swirl gently, and administer.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2890" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Tables 3 and 4 include drugs with clinically important drug interactions and interaction with diagnostics when administered concomitantly with DEXILANT and instructions for preventing or managing them.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2891" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Consult the labeling of concomitantly used drugs to obtain further information about interactions with PPIs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2892" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Clinically Relevant Interactions Affecting Drugs Co-Administered with DEXILANT and Interactions with Diagnostics Antiretrovirals Clinical Impact: The effect of PPIs on antiretroviral drugs is variable.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M5" type="Trigger" span="150 6;192 8" str="effect | variable"/>
<Mention id="M6" type="Precipitant" span="168 20" str="antiretroviral drugs" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M5" precipitant="M6"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2893" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The clinical importance and the mechanisms behind these interactions are not always known.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2894" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Decreased exposure of some antiretroviral drugs (e.g., rilpivirine, atazanavir, and nelfinavir) when used concomitantly with dexlansoprazole may reduce antiviral effect and promote the development of drug resistance.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M25" type="Trigger" span="173 7" str="promote"/>
<Mention id="M32" type="Precipitant" span="27 20" str="antiretroviral drugs" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M27" type="SpecificInteraction" span="173 7;200 15" str="promote | drug resistance" code="31438003: Drug resistance (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M28" type="Trigger" span="145 6;162 6" str="reduce | effect"/>
<Mention id="M30" type="SpecificInteraction" span="145 23" str="reduce antiviral effect" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M34" type="Precipitant" span="68 10" str="atazanavir" code="N0000022320 | QZU4H47A3S"/>
<Mention id="M36" type="Precipitant" span="84 10" str="nelfinavir" code="HO3OGH5D7I | N0000006047"/>
<Mention id="M38" type="Precipitant" span="55 11" str="rilpivirine" code="FI96A8X663"/>
<Mention id="M37" type="Trigger" span="0 18" str="Decreased exposure"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M25" precipitant="M32" effect="M27" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M28" precipitant="M32" effect="M30" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M25" precipitant="M34" effect="M27" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M28" precipitant="M34" effect="M30" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M25" precipitant="M36" effect="M27" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M28" precipitant="M36" effect="M30" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M25" precipitant="M38" effect="M27" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M28" precipitant="M38" effect="M30" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M37" precipitant="M32" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M37" precipitant="M34" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M37" precipitant="M36" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M37" precipitant="M38" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2895" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Increased exposure of other antiretroviral drugs (e.g., saquinavir) when used concomitantly with dexlansoprazole may increase toxicity of the antiretroviral drugs.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M42" type="Trigger" span="0 18" str="Increased exposure "/>
<Mention id="M43" type="Trigger" span="117 17" str=" increase toxicity"/>
<Mention id="M41" type="Precipitant" span="28 20" str="antiretroviral drugs" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M44" type="Precipitant" span="56 10" str="saquinavir" code="N0000007376 | L3JE09KZ2F"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M42;M43" precipitant="M41" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M42;M43" precipitant="M44" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2896" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>There are other antiretroviral drugs which do not result in clinically relevant interactions with dexlansoprazole.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2897" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Intervention: Rilpivirine-containing products: Concomitant use with DEXILANT is contraindicated.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M47" type="Trigger" span="80 15" str="contraindicated"/>
<Mention id="M46" type="Precipitant" span="14 11" str="Rilpivirine" code="FI96A8X663"/>
<Mention id="M48" type="Precipitant" span="14 31" str="Rilpivirine-containing products" code="FI96A8X663"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M47" precipitant="M46"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M47" precipitant="M48"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2898" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Atazanavir: See prescribing information for atazanavir for dosing information.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M49" type="Trigger" span="12 27" str="See prescribing information"/>
<Mention id="M50" type="Precipitant" span="0 10" str="Atazanavir" code="N0000022320 | QZU4H47A3S"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M49" precipitant="M50"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2899" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Nelfinavir: Avoid concomitant use with DEXILANT.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M51" type="Trigger" span="12 5" str="Avoid"/>
<Mention id="M52" type="Precipitant" span="0 10" str="Nelfinavir" code="HO3OGH5D7I | N0000006047"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M51" precipitant="M52"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2900" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>See prescribing information for nelfinavir.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M53" type="Trigger" span="0 27" str="See prescribing information"/>
<Mention id="M54" type="Precipitant" span="32 10" str="nelfinavir" code="HO3OGH5D7I | N0000006047"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M53" precipitant="M54"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2901" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Saquinavir: See the prescribing information for saquinavir and monitor for potential saquinavir toxicities.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M55" type="Trigger" span="12 31" str="See the prescribing information "/>
<Mention id="M56" type="Trigger" span="63 7" str=" monitor"/>
<Mention id="M57" type="Precipitant" span="0 10" str="saquinavir" code="N0000007376 | L3JE09KZ2F"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M55;M56" precipitant="M57"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2902" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Other antiretrovirals: See prescribing information.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M58" type="Trigger" span="23 27" str="See prescribing information"/>
<Mention id="M59" type="Precipitant" span="6 15" str="antiretrovirals" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M58" precipitant="M59"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2903" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Warfarin Clinical Impact: Increased INR and prothrombin time in patients receiving PPIs and warfarin concomitantly.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M63" type="Trigger" span="26 9" str="Increased"/>
<Mention id="M64" type="Precipitant" span="0 8" str="warfarin" code="5Q7ZVV76EI | N0000006403"/>
<Mention id="M62" type="SpecificInteraction" span="26 9;44 16" str="Increased | prothrombin time" code="409674002: Prothrombin time increased (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M65" type="SpecificInteraction" span="26 13" str="Increased INR" code="313341008: International Normalized Ratio raised (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M63" precipitant="M64" effect="M62" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M63" precipitant="M64" effect="M65" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2904" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Increases in INR and prothrombin time may lead to abnormal bleeding and even death.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2905" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Intervention: Monitor INR and prothrombin time.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2906" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Dose adjustment of warfarin may be needed to maintain target INR range.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M66" type="Trigger" span="0 15;42 11" str="Dose adjustment | to maintain"/>
<Mention id="M67" type="Precipitant" span="19 8" str="warfarin" code="5Q7ZVV76EI | N0000006403"/>
<Mention id="M68" type="SpecificInteraction" span="54 16" str="target INR range" code="165583001: International normalized ratio abnormal (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M66" precipitant="M67" effect="M68" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2907" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>See prescribing information for warfarin.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M69" type="Trigger" span="0 27" str="See prescribing information"/>
<Mention id="M70" type="Precipitant" span="32 8" str="warfarin" code="5Q7ZVV76EI | N0000006403"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M69" precipitant="M70"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2908" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Methotrexate Clinical Impact: Concomitant use of PPIs with methotrexate (primarily at high dose) may elevate and prolong serum concentrations of methotrexate and/or its metabolite hydroxymethotrexate, possibly leading to methotrexate toxicities.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M71" type="Trigger" span="101 7;121 20" str="elevate | serum concentrations "/>
<Mention id="M72" type="Trigger" span="234 10" str=" toxicities"/>
<Mention id="M75" type="Precipitant" span="0 12" str="methotrexate" code="N0000007370 | YL5FZ2Y5U1"/>
<Mention id="M74" type="Trigger" span="113 28" str="prolong serum concentrations"/>
<Interaction id="I29" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M71;M72" precipitant="M75" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I30" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M74" precipitant="M75" effect="C54611"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2909" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>No formal drug interaction studies of high-dose methotrexate with PPIs have been conducted.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2910" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Intervention: A temporary withdrawal of DEXILANT may be considered in some patients receiving high-dose methotrexate.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M76" type="Trigger" span="26 10" str="withdrawal"/>
<Mention id="M77" type="Precipitant" span="94 22" str="high-dose methotrexate" code="YL5FZ2Y5U1"/>
<Interaction id="I31" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M76" precipitant="M77"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2911" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Digoxin Clinical Impact: Potential for increased exposure of digoxin.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M78" type="Trigger" span="39 18" str="increased exposure"/>
<Mention id="M79" type="Precipitant" span="0 7" str="digoxin" code="73K4184T59 | N0000005903"/>
<Interaction id="I32" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M78" precipitant="M79" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2912" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Intervention: Monitor digoxin concentrations.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M80" type="Trigger" span="14 7" str="Monitor"/>
<Mention id="M81" type="Precipitant" span="22 7" str="digoxin" code="73K4184T59 | N0000005903"/>
<Interaction id="I33" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M80" precipitant="M81"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2913" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Dose adjustment of digoxin may be needed to maintain therapeutic drug concentrations.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M82" type="Trigger" span="0 15" str="Dose adjustment"/>
<Mention id="M83" type="Precipitant" span="19 7" str="digoxin" code="73K4184T59 | N0000005903"/>
<Interaction id="I34" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M82" precipitant="M83"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2914" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Drugs Dependent on Gastric pH for Absorption (e.g., iron salts, erlotinib, dasatinib, nilotinib, mycophenolate mofetil, ketoconazole/itraconazole) Clinical Impact: Dexlansoprazole can reduce the absorption of other drugs due to its effect on reducing intragastric acidity.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M100" type="Trigger" span="184 21" str="reduce the absorption"/>
<Mention id="M85" type="Precipitant" span="75 9" str="dasatinib" code="RBZ1571X5H"/>
<Mention id="M87" type="Precipitant" span="0 44" str="Drugs Dependent on Gastric pH for Absorption" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M89" type="Precipitant" span="64 9" str="erlotinib" code="J4T82NDH7E"/>
<Mention id="M91" type="Precipitant" span="52 10" str="iron salts" code="E1UOL152H7"/>
<Mention id="M93" type="Precipitant" span="133 12" str="itraconazole" code="304NUG5GF4 | N0000006753"/>
<Mention id="M95" type="Precipitant" span="120 12" str="ketoconazole" code="N0000007319 | R9400W927I"/>
<Mention id="M97" type="Precipitant" span="120 25" str="ketoconazole/itraconazole" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M99" type="Precipitant" span="97 21" str="mycophenolate mofetil" code="9242ECW6R0"/>
<Mention id="M101" type="Precipitant" span="86 9" str="nilotinib" code="F41401512X"/>
<Interaction id="I35" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M100" precipitant="M85" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I36" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M100" precipitant="M87" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I37" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M100" precipitant="M89" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I38" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M100" precipitant="M91" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I39" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M100" precipitant="M93" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I40" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M100" precipitant="M95" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I41" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M100" precipitant="M97" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I42" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M100" precipitant="M99" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I43" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M100" precipitant="M101" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2915" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Intervention: Mycophenolate mofetil (MMF): Co-administration of PPIs in healthy subjects and in transplant patients receiving MMF has been reported to reduce the exposure to the active metabolite, mycophenolic acid (MPA), possibly due to a decrease in MMF solubility at an increased gastric pH.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M108" type="Trigger" span="151 19" str="reduce the exposure"/>
<Mention id="M103" type="Precipitant" span="37 3" str="MMF" code="45IUB1PX8R"/>
<Mention id="M105" type="Precipitant" span="216 3" str="MPA" code="HU9DX48N0T"/>
<Mention id="M107" type="Precipitant" span="14 21" str="Mycophenolate mofetil" code="9242ECW6R0"/>
<Mention id="M109" type="Precipitant" span="197 17" str="mycophenolic acid" code="HU9DX48N0T"/>
<Interaction id="I44" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M108" precipitant="M103" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I45" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M108" precipitant="M105" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I46" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M108" precipitant="M107" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I47" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M108" precipitant="M109" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2916" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The clinical relevance of reduced MPA exposure on organ rejection has not been established in transplant patients receiving DEXILANT and MMF.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M110" type="Trigger" span="26 7;38 8" str="reduced | exposure"/>
<Mention id="M111" type="Precipitant" span="34 3" str="MPA" code="HU9DX48N0T"/>
<Interaction id="I48" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M110" precipitant="M111" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2917" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Use DEXILANT with caution in transplant patients receiving MMF.See the prescribing information for other drugs dependent on gastric pH for absorption.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M115" type="Trigger" span="18 7" str="caution "/>
<Mention id="M116" type="Trigger" span="63 31" str=" See the prescribing information"/>
<Mention id="M114" type="Precipitant" span="105 44" str="drugs dependent on gastric pH for absorption" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M117" type="Precipitant" span="59 3" str="MMF" code="45IUB1PX8R"/>
<Interaction id="I49" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M115;M116" precipitant="M114"/>
<Interaction id="I50" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M115;M116" precipitant="M117"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2918" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Tacrolimus Clinical Impact: Potentially increased exposure of tacrolimus, especially in transplant patients who are intermediate or poor metabolizers of CYP2C19.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M118" type="Trigger" span="40 18" str="increased exposure"/>
<Mention id="M119" type="Precipitant" span="0 10" str="tacrolimus" code="WM0HAQ4WNM"/>
<Interaction id="I51" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M118" precipitant="M119" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2919" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Intervention: Monitor tacrolimus whole blood trough concentrations.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M120" type="Trigger" span="14 7" str="Monitor"/>
<Mention id="M121" type="Precipitant" span="22 10" str="tacrolimus" code="WM0HAQ4WNM"/>
<Interaction id="I52" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M120" precipitant="M121"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2920" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Dose adjustment of tacrolimus may be needed to maintain therapeutic drug concentrations.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M122" type="Trigger" span="0 15" str="Dose adjustment"/>
<Mention id="M123" type="Precipitant" span="19 10" str="tacrolimus" code="WM0HAQ4WNM"/>
<Interaction id="I53" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M122" precipitant="M123"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2921" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>See prescribing information for tacrolimus.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M124" type="Trigger" span="0 27" str="See prescribing information"/>
<Mention id="M125" type="Precipitant" span="32 10" str="tacrolimus" code="WM0HAQ4WNM"/>
<Interaction id="I54" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M124" precipitant="M125"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2922" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Interactions with Investigations of Neuroendocrine Tumors Clinical Impact: CgA levels increase secondary to PPI-induced decreases in gastric acidity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2923" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The increased CgA level may cause false positive results in diagnostic investigations for neuroendocrine tumors.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2924" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Intervention: Temporarily stop DEXILANT treatment at least 14 days before assessing CgA levels and consider repeating the test if initial CgA levels are high.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2925" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>If serial tests are performed (e.g., for monitoring), the same commercial laboratory should be used for testing, as reference ranges between tests may vary.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2926" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Interaction with Secretin Stimulation Test Clinical Impact: Hyper-response in gastrin secretion in response to secretin stimulation test, falsely suggesting gastrinoma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2927" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Intervention: Temporarily stop DEXILANT treatment at least 30 days before assessing to allow gastrin levels to return to baseline.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2928" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>False Positive Urine Tests for THC Clinical Impact: There have been reports of false positive urine screening tests for tetrahydrocannabinol (THC) in patients receiving PPIs.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M126" type="Trigger" span="0 5;21 5" str="false | tests"/>
<Mention id="M127" type="Precipitant" span="120 20" str="tetrahydrocannabinol" code="7J8897W37S"/>
<Mention id="M128" type="SpecificInteraction" span="79 61" str="false positive urine screening tests for tetrahydrocannabinol" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M132" type="Trigger" span="0 5;21 5" str="False | tests"/>
<Mention id="M133" type="Precipitant" span="31 3" str="THC" code="7J8897W37S"/>
<Mention id="M131" type="SpecificInteraction" span="79 40;31 3" str="false positive urine screening tests for | THC" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M134" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 34" str="False Positive Urine Tests for THC" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I55" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M126" precipitant="M127" effect="M128" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I56" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M132" precipitant="M133" effect="M131" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I57" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M132" precipitant="M133" effect="M134" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2929" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Intervention: An alternative confirmatory method should be considered to verify positive results.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2930" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Clinically Relevant Interactions Affecting DEXILANT When Co-Administered with Other Drugs and Substances CYP2C19 or CYP3A4 Inducers Clinical Impact: Decreased exposure of dexlansoprazole when used concomitantly with strong inducers.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M137" type="Trigger" span="149 18" str="Decreased exposure"/>
<Mention id="M136" type="Precipitant" span="105 7;123 8" str="CYP2C19 | Inducers" code="N0000185607"/>
<Mention id="M138" type="Precipitant" span="116 15" str="CYP3A4 Inducers" code="N0000185506"/>
<Interaction id="I58" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M137" precipitant="M136" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I59" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M137" precipitant="M138" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2931" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Intervention: St. John's Wort, rifampin: Avoid concomitant use with DEXILANT.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M141" type="Trigger" span="41 5" str="Avoid"/>
<Mention id="M140" type="Precipitant" span="31 8" str="rifampin" code="VJT6J7R4TR | N0000006026"/>
<Mention id="M142" type="Precipitant" span="14 15" str="St. John's Wort" code="N0000022261 | UFH8805FKA"/>
<Interaction id="I60" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M141" precipitant="M140"/>
<Interaction id="I61" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M141" precipitant="M142"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2932" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Ritonavir-containing products: See prescribing information.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M145" type="Trigger" span="31 27" str="See prescribing information"/>
<Mention id="M144" type="Precipitant" span="0 9" str="Ritonavir" code="O3J8G9O825 | N0000007423"/>
<Mention id="M146" type="Precipitant" span="0 29" str="Ritonavir-containing products" code="O3J8G9O825"/>
<Interaction id="I62" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M145" precipitant="M144"/>
<Interaction id="I63" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M145" precipitant="M146"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2933" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>CYP2C19 or CYP3A4 Inhibitors Clinical Impact: Increased exposure of dexlansoprazole is expected when used concomitantly with strong inhibitors.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M149" type="Trigger" span="46 18" str="Increased exposure"/>
<Mention id="M148" type="Precipitant" span="0 7;18 10" str="CYP2C19 | Inhibitors" code="N0000182140"/>
<Mention id="M150" type="Precipitant" span="11 17" str="CYP3A4 Inhibitors" code="N0000182141"/>
<Interaction id="I64" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M149" precipitant="M148" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I65" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M149" precipitant="M150" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2934" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Intervention: Voriconazole: See prescribing information.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M151" type="Trigger" span="28 27" str="See prescribing information"/>
<Mention id="M152" type="Precipitant" span="14 12" str="Voriconazole" code="N0000010191 | JFU09I87TR"/>
<Interaction id="I66" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M151" precipitant="M152"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2935" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>See full prescribing information for a list of clinically important drug interactions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2936" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Gastric Malignancy: In adults, symptomatic response with DEXILANT does not preclude the presence of gastric malignancy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2937" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Consider additional follow-up and diagnostic testing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2938" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Acute Interstitial Nephritis: Observed in patients taking PPIs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2939" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Clostridium difficile-Associated Diarrhea: PPI therapy may be associated with increased risk.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2940" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Bone Fracture: Long-term and multiple daily dose PPI therapy may be associated with an increased risk for osteoporosis-related fractures of the hip, wrist or spine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2941" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Cutaneous and Systemic Lupus Erythematosus: Mostly cutaneous; new onset or exacerbation of existing disease; discontinue DEXILANT and refer to specialist for evaluation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2942" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Cyanocobalamin (Vitamin B12) Deficiency: Daily long-term use (e.g., longer than 3 years) may lead to malabsorption or a deficiency of cyanocobalamin.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M157" type="Trigger" span="93 37" str="lead to malabsorption or a deficiency "/>
<Mention id="M158" type="Trigger" span="93 21" str=" lead to malabsorption "/>
<Mention id="M159" type="Trigger" span="93 7;29 10" str=" lead to | deficiency"/>
<Mention id="M156" type="Precipitant" span="0 14" str="cyanocobalamin" code="P6YC3EG204"/>
<Mention id="M160" type="Precipitant" span="16 11" str="Vitamin B12" code="P6YC3EG204"/>
<Interaction id="I67" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M157;M158;M159" precipitant="M156" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I68" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M157;M158;M159" precipitant="M160" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2943" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hypomagnesemia: Reported rarely with prolonged treatment with PPIs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2944" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Interactions with Investigations for Neuroendocrine Tumors: Increases in intragastric pH may result in hypergastrinemia and enterochromaffin-like cell hyperplasia and increased chromogranin A levels which may interfere with diagnostic investigations for neuroendocrine tumors.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2945" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Interaction with Methotrexate: Concomitant use with PPIs may elevate and/or prolong serum concentrations of methotrexate and/or its metabolite, possibly leading to toxicity.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M161" type="Trigger" span="61 7;84 20" str="elevate | serum concentrations "/>
<Mention id="M162" type="Trigger" span="164 8" str=" toxicity"/>
<Mention id="M165" type="Precipitant" span="17 12" str="methotrexate" code="N0000007370 | YL5FZ2Y5U1"/>
<Mention id="M164" type="Trigger" span="76 28" str="prolong serum concentrations"/>
<Interaction id="I69" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M161;M162" precipitant="M165" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I70" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M164" precipitant="M165" effect="C54611"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2946" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>With high-dose methotrexate administration, consider a temporary withdrawal of DEXILANT.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M166" type="Trigger" span="65 10" str="withdrawal"/>
<Mention id="M167" type="Precipitant" span="5 22" str="high-dose methotrexate" code="YL5FZ2Y5U1"/>
<Interaction id="I71" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M166" precipitant="M167"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2947" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Fundic Gland Polyps: Risk increases with long-term use, especially beyond 1 year.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2948" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In adults, symptomatic response to therapy with DEXILANT does not preclude the presence of gastric malignancy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2949" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Consider additional follow-up and diagnostic testing in adult patients who have a suboptimal response or an early symptomatic relapse after completing treatment with a PPI.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2950" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In older patients, also consider an endoscopy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2951" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Acute interstitial nephritis has been observed in patients taking PPIs including lansoprazole.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2952" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Acute interstitial nephritis may occur at any point during PPI therapy and is generally attributed to an idiopathic hypersensitivity reaction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2953" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Discontinue DEXILANT if acute interstitial nephritis develops.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2954" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Published observational studies suggest that PPI therapy like DEXILANT may be associated with an increased risk of Clostridium difficile-associated diarrhea, especially in hospitalized patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2955" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>This diagnosis should be considered for diarrhea that does not improve.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2956" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients should use the lowest dose and shortest duration of PPI therapy appropriate to the condition being treated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2957" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Several published observational studies suggest that PPI therapy may be associated with an increased risk for osteoporosis-related fractures of the hip, wrist or spine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2958" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The risk of fracture was increased in patients who received high-dose, defined as multiple daily doses, and long-term PPI therapy (a year or longer).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2959" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients should use the lowest dose and shortest duration of PPI therapy appropriate to the conditions being treated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2960" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients at risk for osteoporosis-related fractures should be managed according to established treatment guidelines.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2961" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Cutaneous lupus erythematosus (CLE) and systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE) have been reported in patients taking PPIs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2962" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>These events have occurred as both new onset and an exacerbation of existing autoimmune disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2963" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The majority of PPI-induced lupus erythematosus cases were CLE.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2964" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The most common form of CLE reported in patients treated with PPIs was subacute CLE (SCLE) and occurred within weeks to years after continuous drug therapy in patients ranging from infants to the elderly.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2965" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Generally, histological findings were observed without organ involvement.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2966" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE) is less commonly reported than CLE in patients receiving PPIs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2967" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>PPI-associated SLE is usually milder than non-drug induced SLE.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2968" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Onset of SLE typically occurred within days to years after initiating treatment primarily in patients ranging from young adults to the elderly.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2969" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The majority of patients presented with rash; however, arthralgia and cytopenia were also reported.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2970" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Avoid administration of PPIs for longer than medically indicated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2971" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If signs or symptoms consistent with CLE or SLE are noted in patients receiving DEXILANT, discontinue the drug and refer the patient to the appropriate specialist for evaluation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2972" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Most patients improve with discontinuation of the PPI alone in four to 12 weeks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2973" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Serological testing (e.g., ANA) may be positive and elevated serological test results may take longer to resolve than clinical manifestations.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2974" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Daily treatment with any acid-suppressing medications over a long period of time (e.g., longer than three years) may lead to malabsorption of cyanocobalamin (Vitamin B12) caused by hypo- or achlorhydria.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M170" type="Trigger" span="117 21" str="lead to malabsorption"/>
<Mention id="M169" type="Precipitant" span="142 14" str="cyanocobalamin" code="P6YC3EG204"/>
<Mention id="M171" type="Precipitant" span="158 11" str="Vitamin B12" code="P6YC3EG204"/>
<Interaction id="I72" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M170" precipitant="M169" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I73" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M170" precipitant="M171" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2975" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Rare reports of cyanocobalamin deficiency occurring with acid-suppressing therapy have been reported in the literature.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M172" type="Trigger" span="31 10" str="deficiency"/>
<Mention id="M173" type="Precipitant" span="16 14" str="cyanocobalamin" code="P6YC3EG204"/>
<Interaction id="I74" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M172" precipitant="M173" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2976" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>This diagnosis should be considered if clinical symptoms consistent with cyanocobalamin deficiency are observed in patients treated with DEXILANT.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M174" type="Trigger" span="88 10" str="deficiency"/>
<Mention id="M175" type="Precipitant" span="73 14" str="cyanocobalamin" code="P6YC3EG204"/>
<Interaction id="I75" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M174" precipitant="M175" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2977" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hypomagnesemia, symptomatic and asymptomatic, has been reported rarely in patients treated with PPIs for at least three months, in most cases after a year of therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2978" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Serious adverse events include tetany, arrhythmias, and seizures.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2979" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In most patients, treatment of hypomagnesemia required magnesium replacement and discontinuation of the PPI.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M176" type="Trigger" span="46 8;65 11" str="required | replacement"/>
<Mention id="M177" type="Precipitant" span="55 9" str="magnesium" code="I38ZP9992A"/>
<Interaction id="I76" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M176" precipitant="M177" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2980" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>For patients expected to be on prolonged treatment or who take PPIs with medications such as digoxin or drugs that may cause hypomagnesemia (e.g., diuretics), healthcare professionals may consider monitoring magnesium levels prior to initiation of PPI treatment and periodically.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M184" type="Trigger" span="119 5" str="cause"/>
<Mention id="M179" type="Precipitant" span="93 7" str="digoxin" code="73K4184T59 | N0000005903"/>
<Mention id="M186" type="SpecificInteraction" span="125 14" str="hypomagnesemia" code="190855004: Hypomagnesemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M182" type="Precipitant" span="147 9" str="diuretics" code="N0000029125 | N0000175359"/>
<Mention id="M185" type="Precipitant" span="104 35" str="drugs that may cause hypomagnesemia" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M187" type="Trigger" span="197 10" str="monitoring"/>
<Mention id="M188" type="Precipitant" span="208 9" str="magnesium" code="I38ZP9992A"/>
<Interaction id="I77" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M184" precipitant="M179" effect="M186" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I78" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M184" precipitant="M182" effect="M186" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I79" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M184" precipitant="M185" effect="M186" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I80" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M187" precipitant="M188"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2981" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Serum chromogranin A (CgA) levels increase secondary to drug-induced decreases in gastric acidity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2982" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Healthcare providers should temporarily stop dexlansoprazole treatment at least 14 days before assessing CgA levels and consider repeating the test if initial CgA levels are high.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2983" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Literature suggests that concomitant use of PPIs with methotrexate (primarily at high dose) may elevate and prolong serum levels of methotrexate and/or its metabolite, possibly leading to methotrexate toxicities.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M189" type="Trigger" span="96 7;116 12" str="elevate | serum levels "/>
<Mention id="M190" type="Trigger" span="201 10" str=" toxicities"/>
<Mention id="M193" type="Precipitant" span="54 12" str="methotrexate" code="N0000007370 | YL5FZ2Y5U1"/>
<Mention id="M192" type="Trigger" span="108 20" str="prolong serum levels"/>
<Interaction id="I81" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M189;M190" precipitant="M193" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I82" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M192" precipitant="M193" effect="C54611"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2984" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In high-dose methotrexate administration, a temporary withdrawal of the PPI may be considered in some patients.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M194" type="Trigger" span="54 10" str="withdrawal"/>
<Mention id="M195" type="Precipitant" span="3 22" str="high-dose methotrexate" code="YL5FZ2Y5U1"/>
<Interaction id="I83" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M194" precipitant="M195"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2985" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>PPI use is associated with an increased risk of fundic gland polyps that increases with long-term use, especially beyond one year.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2986" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Most PPI users who developed fundic gland polyps were asymptomatic and fundic gland polyps were identified incidentally on endoscopy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2987" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Use the shortest duration of PPI therapy appropriate to the condition being treated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2988" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Dexlansoprazole belongs to a class of antisecretory compounds, the substituted benzimidazoles, that suppress gastric acid secretion by specific inhibition of the (H+, K+)-ATPase at the secretory surface of the gastric parietal cell.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2989" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Because this enzyme is regarded as the acid (proton) pump within the parietal cell, dexlansoprazole has been characterized as a gastric proton-pump inhibitor, in that it blocks the final step of acid production.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2990" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Antisecretory Activity The effects of DEXILANT 60 mg (n=20) or lansoprazole 30 mg (n=23) once daily for five days on 24 hour intragastric pH were assessed in healthy subjects in a multiple-dose crossover study.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2991" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Effect on 24 Hour Intragastric pH on Day 5 After Administration of DEXILANT or Lansoprazole DEXILANT60 mg Lansoprazole30 mg Mean Intragastric pH 4.55 4.13 % Time Intragastric pH &gt;4 (hours) 71(17 hours) 60(14 hours) Serum Gastrin Effects The effect of dexlansoprazole on serum gastrin concentrations was evaluated in approximately 3460 patients in clinical trials up to eight weeks and in 1023 patients for up to six to 12 months.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2992" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mean fasting gastrin concentrations increased from baseline during treatment with 30 and 60 mg DEXILANT.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2993" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In patients treated for more than six months, mean serum gastrin levels increased during approximately the first three months of treatment and were stable for the remainder of treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2994" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Mean serum gastrin levels returned to pre-treatment levels within one month of discontinuation of treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2995" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Increased gastrin causes enterochromaffin-like cell hyperplasia and increased serum CgA levels.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2996" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The increased CgA levels may cause false positive results in diagnostic investigations for neuroendocrine tumors.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2997" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Enterochromaffin-Like Cell (ECL) Effects There were no reports of ECL cell hyperplasia in gastric biopsy specimens obtained from 653 patients treated with DEXILANT 30, 60, or 90 mg for up to 12 months.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2998" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>During lifetime exposure of rats dosed daily with up to 150 mg/kg/day of lansoprazole, marked hypergastrinemia was observed followed by ECL cell proliferation and formation of carcinoid tumors, especially in female rats.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2999" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Cardiac Electrophysiology At a dose five times the maximum recommended dose, dexlansoprazole does not prolong the QT interval to any clinically relevant extent.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3000" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The dual delayed-release formulation of DEXILANT results in a dexlansoprazole plasma concentration-time profile with two distinct peaks; the first peak occurs one to two hours after administration, followed by a second peak within four to five hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3001" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Dexlansoprazole is eliminated with a half-life of approximately one to two hours in healthy subjects and in patients with symptomatic GERD.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3002" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No accumulation of dexlansoprazole occurs after multiple, once daily doses of DEXILANT 30 or 60 mg although mean AUCt and Cmax values of dexlansoprazole were slightly higher (less than 10%) on Day 5 than on Day 1.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3003" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Figure 1: Mean Plasma Dexlansoprazole Concentration – Time Profile Following Oral Administration of 30 or 60 mg DEXILANT Once Daily for 5 Days in Healthy Adult Subjects The pharmacokinetics of dexlansoprazole are highly variable, with percent coefficient of variation (%CV) values for Cmax, AUC, and CL/F of greater than 30%.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3004" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Mean (%CV) Pharmacokinetic Parameters for Adult Subjects on Day 5 After Administration of DEXILANT Dose(mg) Cmax (ng/mL) AUC24 (ng∙h/mL) CL/F(L/h) 30 658 (40%)(N=44) 3275 (47%)(N=43) 11.4 (48%)(N=43) 60 1397 (51%)(N=79) 6529 (60%)(N=73) 11.6 (46%)(N=41) Absorption After oral administration of DEXILANT 30 or 60 mg to healthy subjects and symptomatic GERD patients, mean Cmax and AUC values of dexlansoprazole increased approximately dose proportionally.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3005" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>When granules of DEXILANT 60 mg are mixed with water and dosed via NG tube or orally via syringe, the bioavailability (Cmax and AUC) of dexlansoprazole was similar to that when DEXILANT 60 mg was administered as an intact capsule.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3006" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Effect on Food In food-effect studies in healthy subjects receiving DEXILANT under various fed conditions compared to fasting, increases in Cmax ranged from 12 to 55%, increases in AUC ranged from 9 to 37%, and Tmax varied (ranging from a decrease of 0.7 hours to an increase of three hours).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M196" type="Trigger" span="168 16" str="increases in AUC"/>
<Mention id="M201" type="Precipitant" span="10 4" str="Food" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M198" type="Trigger" span="127 17" str="increases in Cmax"/>
<Mention id="M200" type="Trigger" span="211 11" str="Tmax varied"/>
<Interaction id="I84" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M196" precipitant="M201" effect="C54605"/>
<Interaction id="I85" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M198" precipitant="M201" effect="C54602"/>
<Interaction id="I86" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M200" precipitant="M201"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3007" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Distribution Plasma protein binding of dexlansoprazole ranged from 96 to 99% in healthy subjects and was independent of concentration from 0.01 to 20 mcg/mL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3008" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The apparent volume of distribution (Vz/F) after multiple doses in symptomatic GERD patients was 40 L. Elimination Metabolism Dexlansoprazole is extensively metabolized in the liver by oxidation, reduction, and subsequent formation of sulfate, glucuronide and glutathione conjugates to inactive metabolites.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3009" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Oxidative metabolites are formed by the cytochrome P450 (CYP) enzyme system including hydroxylation mainly by CYP2C19, and oxidation to the sulfone by CYP3A4.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3010" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>CYP2C19 is a polymorphic liver enzyme which exhibits three phenotypes in the metabolism of CYP2C19 substrates: extensive metabolizers (*1/*1), intermediate metabolizers (*1/mutant) and poor metabolizers (mutant/mutant).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3011" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Dexlansoprazole is the major circulating component in plasma regardless of CYP2C19 metabolizer status.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3012" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In CYP2C19 intermediate and extensive metabolizers, the major plasma metabolites are 5-hydroxy dexlansoprazole and its glucuronide conjugate, while in CYP2C19 poor metabolizers dexlansoprazole sulfone is the major plasma metabolite.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3013" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Excretion Following the administration of DEXILANT, no unchanged dexlansoprazole is excreted in urine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3014" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following the administration of [14C] dexlansoprazole to six healthy male subjects, approximately 50.7% (standard deviation (SD): 9.0%) of the administered radioactivity was excreted in urine and 47.6% (SD: 7.3%) in the feces.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3015" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Apparent clearance (CL/F) in healthy subjects was 11.4 to 11.6 L/hour, respectively, after five days of 30 or 60 mg once daily administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3016" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Specific Populations Age: Pediatric Population The pharmacokinetics of dexlansoprazole in patients under the age of 12 years have not been studied.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3017" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Patients 12 to 17 Years of Age The pharmacokinetics of dexlansoprazole were studied in 36 patients 12 to 17 years of age with symptomatic GERD in a multi-center trial.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3018" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Patients were randomized to receive DEXILANT 30 or 60 mg once daily for seven days.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3019" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The dexlansoprazole mean Cmax and AUC in patients 12 to 17 years of age were 105 and 88%, respectively, compared to those observed in adults at the 30 mg dose, and were 81 and 78%, respectively, at the 60 mg dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3020" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Mean (%CV) Pharmacokinetic Parameters in Patients 12 to 17 Years of Age with Symptomatic GERD on Day 7 After Administration of DEXILANT Once Daily for 7 Days Dose Cmax (ng/mL) AUCtau (ng∙h/mL) CL/F(L/h) 30 mg(N=17) 691(53) 2886(47) 12.8(48) 60 mg(N=18) 1136(51) 5120(58) 15.3(49) Age: Geriatric Population The terminal elimination half-life of dexlansoprazole is significantly increased in geriatric subjects compared to younger subjects (2.2 and 1.5 hours, respectively).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3021" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Dexlansoprazole exhibited higher systemic exposure (AUC) in geriatric subjects (34% higher) than younger subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3022" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Sex In a study of 12 male and 12 female healthy subjects who received a single dose of DEXILANT 60 mg, females had higher systemic exposure (AUC) (43% higher) than males.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3023" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This difference in exposure between males and female does not represent a significant safety concern.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3024" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Renal Impairment Dexlansoprazole is extensively metabolized in the liver to inactive metabolites, and no parent drug is recovered in the urine following an oral dose of dexlansoprazole.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3025" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Therefore, the pharmacokinetics of dexlansoprazole are not expected to be altered in patients with renal impairment, and no studies were conducted in patients with renal impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3026" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In addition, the pharmacokinetics of lansoprazole were not clinically different in patients with mild, moderate or severe renal impairment compared to healthy subjects with normal renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3027" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Hepatic Impairment In a study of 12 patients with moderate hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh Class B) who received a single dose of 60 mg DEXILANT, the systemic exposure (AUC) of bound and unbound dexlansoprazole was approximately two times greater compared to subjects with normal hepatic function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3028" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This difference in exposure was not due to a difference in protein binding.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3029" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No studies have been conducted in patients with severe hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh Class C).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3030" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Drug-Drug Interactions Effect of Dexlansoprazole on Other Drugs Cytochrome P 450 Interactions Dexlansoprazole is metabolized, in part, by CYP2C19 and CYP3A4.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3031" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In vitro studies have shown that dexlansoprazole is not likely to inhibit CYP isoforms 1A1, 1A2, 2A6, 2B6, 2C8, 2C9, 2D6, 2E1 or 3A4.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3032" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>As such, no clinically relevant interactions with drugs metabolized by these CYP enzymes would be expected.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3033" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Furthermore, in vivo studies showed that DEXILANT did not have an impact on the pharmacokinetics of co-administered phenytoin (CYP2C9 substrate) or theophylline (CYP1A2 substrate).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3034" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The subjects' CYP1A2 genotypes in the drug-drug interaction study with theophylline were not determined.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3035" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Although in vitro studies indicated that DEXILANT has the potential to inhibit CYP2C19 in vivo, an in vivo drug-drug interaction study in mainly CYP2C19 extensive and intermediate metabolizers has shown that DEXILANT does not affect the pharmacokinetics of diazepam (CYP2C19 substrate).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3036" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Clopidogrel Clopidogrel is metabolized to its active metabolite in part by CYP2C19.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3037" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A study of healthy subjects who were CYP2C19 extensive metabolizers, receiving once daily administration of clopidogrel 75 mg alone or concomitantly with DEXILANT 60 mg (n=40), for nine days was conducted.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3038" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mean AUC of the active metabolite of clopidogrel was reduced by approximately 9% (mean AUC ratio was 91%, with 90% CI of 86 to 97%) when DEXILANT was co-administered compared to administration of clopidogrel alone.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M202" type="Trigger" span="9 3;57 7" str="AUC | reduced"/>
<Mention id="M203" type="Precipitant" span="41 11" str="clopidogrel" code="A74586SNO7 | N0000007277"/>
<Interaction id="I87" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M202" precipitant="M203" effect="C54614"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3039" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Pharmacodynamic parameters were also measured and demonstrated that the change in inhibition of platelet aggregation (induced by 5 mcM ADP) was related to the change in the exposure to clopidogrel active metabolite.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M204" type="Trigger" span="72 6" str="change "/>
<Mention id="M205" type="Trigger" span="82 10" str=" inhibition"/>
<Mention id="M206" type="Precipitant" span="185 11" str="clopidogrel" code="A74586SNO7 | N0000007277"/>
<Mention id="M207" type="SpecificInteraction" span="82 34" str="inhibition of platelet aggregation" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I88" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M204;M205" precipitant="M206" effect="M207" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3040" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The effect on exposure to the active metabolite of clopidogrel and on clopidogrel-induced platelet inhibition is not considered clinically important.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3041" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Effect of Other Drugs on Dexlansoprazole Because dexlansoprazole is metabolized by CYP2C19 and CYP3A4, inducers and inhibitors of these enzymes may potentially alter exposure of dexlansoprazole.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M214" type="Trigger" span="160 14" str="alter exposure"/>
<Mention id="M209" type="Precipitant" span="83 7;103 8" str="CYP2C19 | inducers" code="N0000185607"/>
<Mention id="M211" type="Precipitant" span="83 7;116 10" str="CYP2C19 | inhibitors" code="N0000182140"/>
<Mention id="M213" type="Precipitant" span="95 6;103 8" str="CYP3A4 | inducers" code="N0000185506"/>
<Mention id="M215" type="Precipitant" span="95 6;116 10" str="CYP3A4 | inhibitors" code="N0000182141"/>
<Interaction id="I89" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M214" precipitant="M209"/>
<Interaction id="I90" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M214" precipitant="M211"/>
<Interaction id="I91" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M214" precipitant="M213"/>
<Interaction id="I92" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M214" precipitant="M215"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3042" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Figure 1 Effect of CYP2C19 Polymorphism on Systemic Exposure of Dexlansoprazole Systemic exposure of dexlansoprazole is generally higher in intermediate and poor metabolizers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3043" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In male Japanese subjects who received a single dose of DEXILANT 30 or 60 mg (N=2 to 6 subjects/group), mean dexlansoprazole Cmax and AUC values were up to two times higher in intermediate compared to extensive metabolizers; in poor metabolizers, mean Cmax was up to four times higher and mean AUC was up to 12 times higher compared to extensive metabolizers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3044" LabelDrug="Dexilant" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Though such study was not conducted in Caucasians and African Americans, it is expected dexlansoprazole exposure in these races will be affected by CYP2C19 phenotypes as well.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="rilpivirine" precipitantCode="FI96A8X663" effect="31438003: Drug resistance (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="rilpivirine" precipitantCode="FI96A8X663" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="rilpivirine" precipitantCode="FI96A8X663" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="rilpivirine" precipitantCode="FI96A8X663"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="rilpivirine-containing products" precipitantCode="FI96A8X663"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="antiretroviral drugs" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="31438003: Drug resistance (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="antiretroviral drugs" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="antiretroviral drugs" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="antiretroviral drugs" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="antiretroviral drugs" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="atazanavir" precipitantCode="N0000022320 | QZU4H47A3S" effect="31438003: Drug resistance (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="atazanavir" precipitantCode="N0000022320 | QZU4H47A3S" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="atazanavir" precipitantCode="N0000022320 | QZU4H47A3S" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="atazanavir" precipitantCode="N0000022320 | QZU4H47A3S"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nelfinavir" precipitantCode="HO3OGH5D7I | N0000006047" effect="31438003: Drug resistance (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nelfinavir" precipitantCode="HO3OGH5D7I | N0000006047" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="nelfinavir" precipitantCode="HO3OGH5D7I | N0000006047" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="nelfinavir" precipitantCode="HO3OGH5D7I | N0000006047"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="saquinavir" precipitantCode="N0000007376 | L3JE09KZ2F" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="saquinavir" precipitantCode="N0000007376 | L3JE09KZ2F"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="antiretrovirals" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="warfarin" precipitantCode="5Q7ZVV76EI | N0000006403" effect="165583001: International normalized ratio abnormal (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="warfarin" precipitantCode="5Q7ZVV76EI | N0000006403" effect="313341008: International Normalized Ratio raised (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="warfarin" precipitantCode="5Q7ZVV76EI | N0000006403" effect="409674002: Prothrombin time increased (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="warfarin" precipitantCode="5Q7ZVV76EI | N0000006403"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="methotrexate" precipitantCode="N0000007370 | YL5FZ2Y5U1" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="methotrexate" precipitantCode="N0000007370 | YL5FZ2Y5U1" effect="C54611"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="high-dose methotrexate" precipitantCode="YL5FZ2Y5U1"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="digoxin" precipitantCode="73K4184T59 | N0000005903" effect="190855004: Hypomagnesemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="digoxin" precipitantCode="73K4184T59 | N0000005903" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="digoxin" precipitantCode="73K4184T59 | N0000005903"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="dasatinib" precipitantCode="RBZ1571X5H" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="drugs dependent on gastric ph for absorption" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="drugs dependent on gastric ph for absorption" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="erlotinib" precipitantCode="J4T82NDH7E" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="iron salts" precipitantCode="E1UOL152H7" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="itraconazole" precipitantCode="304NUG5GF4 | N0000006753" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="ketoconazole" precipitantCode="N0000007319 | R9400W927I" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="ketoconazole/itraconazole" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="mycophenolate mofetil" precipitantCode="9242ECW6R0" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="nilotinib" precipitantCode="F41401512X" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="mmf" precipitantCode="45IUB1PX8R" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="mmf" precipitantCode="45IUB1PX8R"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="mpa" precipitantCode="HU9DX48N0T" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="mycophenolic acid" precipitantCode="HU9DX48N0T" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="tacrolimus" precipitantCode="WM0HAQ4WNM" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="tacrolimus" precipitantCode="WM0HAQ4WNM"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="tetrahydrocannabinol" precipitantCode="7J8897W37S" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="thc" precipitantCode="7J8897W37S" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cyp2c19 | inducers" precipitantCode="N0000185607" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="cyp2c19 | inducers" precipitantCode="N0000185607"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cyp3a4 inducers" precipitantCode="N0000185506" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="rifampin" precipitantCode="VJT6J7R4TR | N0000006026"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="st. john's wort" precipitantCode="N0000022261 | UFH8805FKA"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="ritonavir" precipitantCode="O3J8G9O825 | N0000007423"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="ritonavir-containing products" precipitantCode="O3J8G9O825"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cyp2c19 | inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000182140" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="cyp2c19 | inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000182140"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cyp3a4 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000182141" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="voriconazole" precipitantCode="N0000010191 | JFU09I87TR"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cyanocobalamin" precipitantCode="P6YC3EG204" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="vitamin b12" precipitantCode="P6YC3EG204" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="magnesium" precipitantCode="I38ZP9992A" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="magnesium" precipitantCode="I38ZP9992A"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="diuretics" precipitantCode="N0000029125 | N0000175359" effect="190855004: Hypomagnesemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="drugs that may cause hypomagnesemia" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="190855004: Hypomagnesemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="food" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54602"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="food" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54605"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="food" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="clopidogrel" precipitantCode="A74586SNO7 | N0000007277" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="clopidogrel" precipitantCode="A74586SNO7 | N0000007277" effect="C54614"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="cyp3a4 | inducers" precipitantCode="N0000185506"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="cyp3a4 | inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000182141"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>