<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="FIRMAGON" setid="ab11dd8a-0fd9-4013-89ab-e114557c7e4b">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
FIRMAGON is contraindicated in patients with known hypersensitivity to degarelix or to any of the product components. [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2) ] . Degarelix is contraindicated in women who are or may become pregnant. Degarelix can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. Degarelix given to rabbits during organogenesis at doses that were 0.02% of the clinical loading dose (240 mg) on a mg/m 2 basis caused embryo/fetal lethality and abortion. When degarelix was given to female rats during organogenesis, at doses that were just 0.036% of the clinical loading dose on an mg/m 2 basis, there was an increase post implantation loss and a decrease in the number of live fetuses. If this drug is used during pregnancy, or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking this drug, the patient should be apprised of the potential hazard to the fetus. FIRMAGON is contraindicated in: Patients with previous hypersensitivity reactions to degarelix ( 4 ) Pregnancy Category X. Fetal harm can occur when administered to pregnant women ( 4 )</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
FIRMAGON is for subcutaneous administration only Treatment is started with a dose of 240 mg given as two injections of 120 mg each ( 2.1 ) The starting dose is followed by maintenance doses of 80 mg administered as a single injection every 28 days ( 2.1 ) FIRMAGON is administered as a subcutaneous injection in the abdominal region only. Starting dose Maintenance dose – Administration every 28 days 240 mg given as two subcutaneous injections of 120 mg at a concentration of 40 mg/mL 80 mg given as one subcutaneous injection at a concentration of 20 mg/mL The first maintenance dose should be given 28 days after the starting dose. FIRMAGON ® is to be administered by a healthcare professional only . Before administering FIRMAGON read the Instructions for reconstitution and administration carefully. As with other drugs administered by subcutaneous injection, the injection site should vary periodically. Injections should be given in areas of the abdomen that will not be exposed to pressure, e.g., not close to waistband or belt nor close to the ribs. FIRMAGON is supplied as a powder to be reconstituted with Sterile Water for Injection, USP (WFI). The instruction for reconstitution needs to be carefully followed. Administration of other concentrations is not recommended. Read the complete instructions before performing the injection. NOTE : FIRMAGON is for subcutaneous administration to the abdominal region only. Reconstituted drug must be administered within one hour after addition of Sterile Water for Injection, USP. Do not shake the vials. Follow aseptic technique. FIRMAGON 240 mg Starting Dose Kit contains: 2 vials containing the 120 mg FIRMAGON ® powder (a) 2 syringes containing Sterile Water for Injection, USP (b) 2 vial adapters (c) 2 injection needles (d) 2 plunger rods (e) FIRMAGON 80 mg Maintenance Dose Kit contains: 1 vial containing the 80 mg FIRMAGON ® powder (f) 1 syringe containing Sterile Water for Injection, USP (g) 1 vial adapter (h) 1 injection needle (i) 1 plunger rod (j) In addition the healthcare professional will need: gloves (k) alcohol pads (l) a clean, flat surface (m) to work on, like a table a sharps disposal container (n) for throwing away your used needles and syringes. See " Disposing used needles and syringes " at the end of these instructions. The drug product must be prepared using the following instructions: NOTE: The mixing process must be repeated for the two injections of the Starting Dose prior to injecting the product into the patient's abdomen. Step 1: Attaching the vial adaptor to the vial Thoroughly wash your hands using soap and water and put on a pair of clean gloves. Place all the supplies required on a clean surface. Check that there is powder in the FIRMAGON ® vial and that the Sterile Water, USP is clear and free from particles. IMPORTANT: DO NOT USE if there is no powder in the vial or the Sterile Water, USP is discolored. Uncap the vial containing the FIRMAGON ® powder (o). Wipe the vial rubber stopper with an alcohol pad. IMPORTANT: Do not touch the top of the vial after wiping. Peel off the seal from the vial adaptor cover. IMPORTANT: Do not touch the vial adapter. Firmly press the vial adaptor (p) onto the vial containing the FIRMAGON ® powder until the adaptor snaps into place. Pull the vial adaptor cover off the vial. Step 2: Assembling the syringe Insert the plunger rod (q) into the prefilled syringe containing Sterile Water, USP (r) and screw the plunger rod clockwise to tighten. IMPORTANT: Do not pull the back stopper (flange) (s) off the syringe. NOTE: You will only feel light resistance screwing the plunger rod in position. Step 3: Transferring sterile water, USP from the syringe to the vial Unscrew the gray syringe plug (t) attached to the Luer lock adaptor on the syringe. IMPORTANT: Do not pull off the Luer lock adaptor (u). Carefully twist the prefilled syringe containing sterile water, USP onto the vial adapter on the FIRMAGON ® powder vial, until it is tight. IMPORTANT: Be careful not to over twist the syringe. Press the plunger slowly to transfer all the sterile water, USP from the syringe to the FIRMAGON ® powder vial. Step 4: Preparing the reconstituted injection With the syringe still attached to the vial adaptor, swirl gently until the liquid is clear with no powder or visible particles . IMPORTANT: Do not shake the vial as this will cause bubbles. Reconstitute just prior to administration. NOTE : If the powder adheres to the side of the vial, tilt the vial slightly. A ring of small air bubbles on the surface of the liquid is acceptable. Reconstitution time can take up to 15 min but usually takes a few minutes. Step 5: Transferring the liquid to the syringe Turn the vial completely upside down and pull down the plunger to withdraw all of the reconstituted liquid from the vial to the syringe. Tap the syringe gently with your fingers to raise air bubbles in the syringe tip. Press the plunger to the line marked on the syringe to expel all air bubbles. Step 6: Preparing the syringe for injection Holding the vial adaptor detach the syringe from the vial by unscrewing the syringe from the vial adaptor. NOTE : Reconstitute just prior to administration . While holding the syringe with the tip pointing up, screw the injection needle (v) clockwise (right) onto the syringe. Step 7: Preparing the patient Select one of the four available injection sites on the abdomen. IMPORTANT: Do not inject in areas where the patient will be exposed to pressure, such as area around the belt of the waistband or close to the ribs. Vary the injection site periodically during treatment to minimize discomfort to the patient. Clean the injection site with an alcohol pad. Step 8: Performing the injection Move the needle shield (w) away from the needle and carefully remove the needle cover (x). Pinch and elevate the skin of the abdomen. Insert the needle into the skin at a 45 degree angle all the way to the hub . Do not inject into a vein or muscle. Gently pull back the plunger to check if blood is aspirated. IMPORTANT: If blood appears in the syringe, the product should not be injected. Discontinue the injection and discard the syringe and the needle (reconstitute a new dose for the patient). Perform a slow , deep subcutaneous injection over 30 seconds. Remove the needle and then release the skin. IMPORTANT: Do not rub the injection site after retracting the needle. Step 9: Locking the needle into the shield Position the needle shield approximately 45 degrees to a flat surface. Press down with a firm, quick motion until a distinct, audible "click" is heard. Visually confirm that the needle is fully engaged under the lock (y). IMPORTANT: Syringe is for single use only. Do not reuse the syringe and needle . Step 10: Advising the patient Instruct the patient not to rub or scratch the injection site. Inform that some patients may feel a lump at the injection site and experience redness, soreness and discomfort for a few days after the injection. Figure Figure Figure Figure Figure Figure Figure Figure Figure Figure Figure Figure Figure Figure Figure Figure Figure Figure Figure Figure Figure Figure Disposing used needles and syringes Put used alcohol swabs, needles and syringes in an FDA-cleared sharps disposal container right away after use. Do not throw away loose needles and syringes in the trash. For more information about safe sharps disposal, go to the FDA's website at: http://www.fda.gov/safesharpsdisposal .</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
No drug-drug interaction studies were conducted. Degarelix is not a substrate for the human CYP450 system. Degarelix is not an inducer or inhibitor of the CYP450 system in vitro . Therefore, clinically significant CYP450 pharmacokinetic drug-drug interactions are unlikely. Clinically significant CYP450 pharmacokinetic drug-drug interactions are unlikely ( 7 )</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
Hypersensitivity: Anaphylaxis, urticaria and angioedema have been reported. Discontinue Firmagon if a serious hypersensitivity reaction occurs, and manage as clinically indicated ( 5.2 ) Effect on QT/QTc Interval: Androgen deprivation therapy may prolong the QT interval. Consider risks and benefits ( 5.3 ) Pregnancy Category X Women who are or may become pregnant should not take FIRMAGON [see Contraindications (4) and Use in Specific Populations (8.1) ]. Hypersensitivity reactions, including anaphylaxis, urticaria and angioedema, have been reported post-marketing with Firmagon. In case of a serious hypersensitivity reaction, discontinue Firmagon immediately if the injection has not been completed, and manage as clinically indicated. Patients with a known history of serious hypersensitivity reactions to Firmagon should not be re-challenged with Firmagon. Androgen deprivation therapy may prolong the QT interval. Providers should consider whether the benefits of androgen deprivation therapy outweigh the potential risks in patients with congenital long QT syndrome, congestive heart failure, frequent electrolyte abnormalities, and in patients taking drugs known to prolong the QT interval. Electrolyte abnormalities should be corrected. Consider periodic monitoring of electrocardiograms and electrolytes. In the randomized, active-controlled trial comparing FIRMAGON to leuprolide, periodic electro-cardiograms were performed. Seven patients, three (&amp;lt;1%) in the pooled degarelix group and four (2%) patients in the leuprolide 7.5 mg group, had a QTcF ≥ 500 msec. From baseline to end of study, the median change for FIRMAGON was 12.3 msec and for leuprolide was 16.7 msec.In the randomized, active-controlled trial comparing FIRMAGON to leuprolide, periodic electro-cardiograms were performed. Seven patients, three (&amp;lt;1%) in the pooled degarelix group and four (2%) patients in the leuprolide 7.5 mg group, had a QTcF ≥ 500 msec. From baseline to end of study, the median change for FIRMAGON was 12.3 msec and for leuprolide was 16.7 msec. Therapy with FIRMAGON results in suppression of the pituitary gonadal system. Results of diagnostic tests of the pituitary gonadotropic and gonadal functions conducted during and after FIRMAGON may be affected. The therapeutic effect of FIRMAGON should be monitored by measuring serum concentrations of prostate-specific antigen (PSA) periodically. If PSA increases, serum concentrations of testosterone should be measured.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Degarelix is a GnRH receptor antagonist. It binds reversibly to the pituitary GnRH receptors, thereby reducing the release of gonadotropins and consequently testosterone. A single dose of 240 mg FIRMAGON causes a decrease in the plasma concentrations of luteinizing hormone (LH) and follicle stimulating hormone (FSH), and subsequently testosterone. FIRMAGON is effective in achieving and maintaining testosterone suppression below the castration level of 50 ng/dL. Figure 1: Plasma Testosterone Levels from Day 0 to 364 for Degarelix 240 mg/80 mg (Median with Interquartile Ranges) Figure 1 Absorption FIRMAGON forms a depot upon subcutaneous administration, from which degarelix is released to the circulation. Following administration of FIRMAGON 240 mg at a product concentration of 40 mg/mL, the mean Cmax was 26.2 ng/mL (coefficient of variation, CV 83%) and the mean AUC was 1054 ng∙day/mL (CV 35%). Typically Cmax occurred within 2 days after subcutaneous administration. In prostate cancer patients at a product concentration of 40 mg/mL, the pharmacokinetics of degarelix were linear over a dose range of 120 to 240 mg. The pharmacokinetic behavior of the drug is strongly influenced by its concentration in the injection solution. Distribution The distribution volume of degarelix after intravenous (&amp;gt; 1 L/kg) or subcutaneous administration (&amp;gt; 1000L) indicates that degarelix is distributed throughout total body water. In vitro plasma protein binding of degarelix is estimated to be approximately 90%. Metabolism Degarelix is subject to peptide hydrolysis during the passage of the hepato-biliary system and is mainly excreted as peptide fragments in the feces. No quantitatively significant metabolites were detected in plasma samples after subcutaneous administration. In vitro studies have shown that degarelix is not a substrate, inducer or inhibitor of the CYP450 or p-glycoprotein transporter systems. Excretion Following subcutaneous administration of 240 mg FIRMAGON at a concentration of 40 mg/mL to prostate cancer patients, degarelix is eliminated in a biphasic fashion, with a median terminal half-life of approximately 53 days. The long half-life after subcutaneous administration is a consequence of a very slow release of degarelix from the FIRMAGON depot formed at the injection site(s). Approximately 20-30% of a given dose of degarelix was renally excreted, suggesting that approximately 70-80% is excreted via the hepato-biliary system in humans. Following subcutaneous administration of degarelix to prostate cancer patients the clearance is approximately 9 L/hr. Effect of Age, Weight and Race There was no effect of age, weight or race on the degarelix pharmacokinetic parameters or testosterone concentration.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="5091" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>FIRMAGON is contraindicated in patients with known hypersensitivity to degarelix or to any of the product components.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5092" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Degarelix is contraindicated in women who are or may become pregnant.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5093" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Degarelix can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5094" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Degarelix given to rabbits during organogenesis at doses that were 0.02% of the clinical loading dose (240 mg) on a mg/m2 basis caused embryo/fetal lethality and abortion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5095" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>When degarelix was given to female rats during organogenesis, at doses that were just 0.036% of the clinical loading dose on an mg/m2 basis, there was an increase post implantation loss and a decrease in the number of live fetuses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5096" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>If this drug is used during pregnancy, or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking this drug, the patient should be apprised of the potential hazard to the fetus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5097" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>FIRMAGON is contraindicated in: Patients with previous hypersensitivity reactions to degarelix (4) Pregnancy Category X. Fetal harm can occur when administered to pregnant women (4)</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5098" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>FIRMAGON is for subcutaneous administration only Treatment is started with a dose of 240 mg given as two injections of 120 mg each (2.1) The starting dose is followed by maintenance doses of 80 mg administered as a single injection every 28 days (2.1) FIRMAGON is administered as a subcutaneous injection in the abdominal region only.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5099" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Starting dose Maintenance dose – Administration every 28 days 240 mg given as two subcutaneous injections of 120 mg at a concentration of 40 mg/mL 80 mg given as one subcutaneous injection at a concentration of 20 mg/mL The first maintenance dose should be given 28 days after the starting dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5100" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>FIRMAGON® is to be administered by a healthcare professional only.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5101" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Before administering FIRMAGON read the Instructions for reconstitution and administration carefully.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5102" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>As with other drugs administered by subcutaneous injection, the injection site should vary periodically.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5103" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Injections should be given in areas of the abdomen that will not be exposed to pressure, e.g., not close to waistband or belt nor close to the ribs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5104" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>FIRMAGON is supplied as a powder to be reconstituted with Sterile Water for Injection, USP (WFI).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5105" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The instruction for reconstitution needs to be carefully followed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5106" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Administration of other concentrations is not recommended.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5107" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Read the complete instructions before performing the injection.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5108" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>NOTE: FIRMAGON is for subcutaneous administration to the abdominal region only.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5109" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Reconstituted drug must be administered within one hour after addition of Sterile Water for Injection, USP.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5110" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>FIRMAGON 240 mg Starting Dose Kit contains: 2 vials containing the 120 mg FIRMAGON® powder (a) 2 syringes containing Sterile Water for Injection, USP (b) 2 vial adapters (c) 2 injection needles (d) 2 plunger rods (e) FIRMAGON 80 mg Maintenance Dose Kit contains: 1 vial containing the 80 mg FIRMAGON® powder (f) 1 syringe containing Sterile Water for Injection, USP (g) 1 vial adapter (h) 1 injection needle (i) 1 plunger rod (j) In addition the healthcare professional will need: gloves (k) alcohol pads (l) a clean, flat surface (m) to work on, like a table a sharps disposal container (n) for throwing away your used needles and syringes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5111" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>See Disposing used needles and syringes at the end of these instructions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5112" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The drug product must be prepared using the following instructions: NOTE: The mixing process must be repeated for the two injections of the Starting Dose prior to injecting the product into the patient's abdomen.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5113" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Step 1: Attaching the vial adaptor to the vial Thoroughly wash your hands using soap and water and put on a pair of clean gloves.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5114" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Place all the supplies required on a clean surface.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5115" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Check that there is powder in the FIRMAGON® vial and that the Sterile Water, USP is clear and free from particles.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5116" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>IMPORTANT: DO NOT USE if there is no powder in the vial or the Sterile Water, USP is discolored.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5117" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Uncap the vial containing the FIRMAGON® powder (o).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5118" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Wipe the vial rubber stopper with an alcohol pad.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5119" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>IMPORTANT: Do not touch the top of the vial after wiping.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5120" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Peel off the seal from the vial adaptor cover.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5121" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>IMPORTANT: Do not touch the vial adapter.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5122" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Firmly press the vial adaptor (p) onto the vial containing the FIRMAGON® powder until the adaptor snaps into place.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5123" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Pull the vial adaptor cover off the vial.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5124" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Step 2: Assembling the syringe Insert the plunger rod (q) into the prefilled syringe containing Sterile Water, USP (r) and screw the plunger rod clockwise to tighten.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5125" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>IMPORTANT: Do not pull the back stopper (flange) (s) off the syringe.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5126" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>NOTE: You will only feel light resistance screwing the plunger rod in position.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5127" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Step 3: Transferring sterile water, USP from the syringe to the vial Unscrew the gray syringe plug (t) attached to the Luer lock adaptor on the syringe.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5128" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>IMPORTANT: Do not pull off the Luer lock adaptor (u).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5129" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Carefully twist the prefilled syringe containing sterile water, USP onto the vial adapter on the FIRMAGON® powder vial, until it is tight.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5130" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>IMPORTANT: Be careful not to over twist the syringe.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5131" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Press the plunger slowly to transfer all the sterile water, USP from the syringe to the FIRMAGON® powder vial.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5132" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Step 4: Preparing the reconstituted injection With the syringe still attached to the vial adaptor, swirl gently until the liquid is clear with no powder or visible particles.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5133" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>IMPORTANT: Do not shake the vial as this will cause bubbles.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5134" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Reconstitute just prior to administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5135" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>NOTE: If the powder adheres to the side of the vial, tilt the vial slightly.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5136" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>A ring of small air bubbles on the surface of the liquid is acceptable.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5137" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Reconstitution time can take up to 15 min but usually takes a few minutes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5138" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Step 5: Transferring the liquid to the syringe Turn the vial completely upside down and pull down the plunger to withdraw all of the reconstituted liquid from the vial to the syringe.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5139" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Tap the syringe gently with your fingers to raise air bubbles in the syringe tip.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5140" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Press the plunger to the line marked on the syringe to expel all air bubbles.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5141" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Step 6: Preparing the syringe for injection Holding the vial adaptor detach the syringe from the vial by unscrewing the syringe from the vial adaptor.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5142" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>NOTE: Reconstitute just prior to administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5143" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>While holding the syringe with the tip pointing up, screw the injection needle (v) clockwise (right) onto the syringe.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5144" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Step 7: Preparing the patient Select one of the four available injection sites on the abdomen.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5145" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>IMPORTANT: Do not inject in areas where the patient will be exposed to pressure, such as area around the belt of the waistband or close to the ribs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5146" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Vary the injection site periodically during treatment to minimize discomfort to the patient.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5147" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Clean the injection site with an alcohol pad.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5148" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Step 8: Performing the injection Move the needle shield (w) away from the needle and carefully remove the needle cover (x).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5149" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Pinch and elevate the skin of the abdomen.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5150" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Insert the needle into the skin at a 45 degree angle all the way to the hub.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5151" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Gently pull back the plunger to check if blood is aspirated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5152" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>IMPORTANT: If blood appears in the syringe, the product should not be injected.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5153" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Discontinue the injection and discard the syringe and the needle (reconstitute a new dose for the patient).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5154" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Perform a slow, deep subcutaneous injection over 30 seconds.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5155" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Remove the needle and then release the skin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5156" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>IMPORTANT: Do not rub the injection site after retracting the needle.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5157" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Step 9: Locking the needle into the shield Position the needle shield approximately 45 degrees to a flat surface.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5158" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Press down with a firm, quick motion until a distinct, audible click is heard.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5159" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Visually confirm that the needle is fully engaged under the lock (y).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5160" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>IMPORTANT: Syringe is for single use only.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5161" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Step 10: Advising the patient Instruct the patient not to rub or scratch the injection site.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5162" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Inform that some patients may feel a lump at the injection site and experience redness, soreness and discomfort for a few days after the injection.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5163" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Figure Figure Figure Figure Figure Figure Figure Figure Figure Figure Figure Figure Figure Figure Figure Figure Figure Figure Figure Figure Figure Figure Disposing used needles and syringes Put used alcohol swabs, needles and syringes in an FDA-cleared sharps disposal container right away after use.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5164" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not throw away loose needles and syringes in the trash.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5165" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For more information about safe sharps disposal, go to the FDA's website at: http://www.fda.gov/safesharpsdisposal.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5166" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>No drug-drug interaction studies were conducted.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5167" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Degarelix is not a substrate for the human CYP450 system.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5168" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Degarelix is not an inducer or inhibitor of the CYP450 system in vitro.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5169" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Therefore, clinically significant CYP450 pharmacokinetic drug-drug interactions are unlikely.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5170" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Clinically significant CYP450 pharmacokinetic drug-drug interactions are unlikely (7)</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5171" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hypersensitivity: Anaphylaxis, urticaria and angioedema have been reported.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5172" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Discontinue Firmagon if a serious hypersensitivity reaction occurs, and manage as clinically indicated (5.2) Effect on QT/QTc Interval: Androgen deprivation therapy may prolong the QT interval.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5173" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Consider risks and benefits (5.3) Pregnancy Category X Women who are or may become pregnant should not take FIRMAGON.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5174" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hypersensitivity reactions, including anaphylaxis, urticaria and angioedema, have been reported post-marketing with Firmagon.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5175" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In case of a serious hypersensitivity reaction, discontinue Firmagon immediately if the injection has not been completed, and manage as clinically indicated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5176" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients with a known history of serious hypersensitivity reactions to Firmagon should not be re-challenged with Firmagon.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5177" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Androgen deprivation therapy may prolong the QT interval.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5178" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Providers should consider whether the benefits of androgen deprivation therapy outweigh the potential risks in patients with congenital long QT syndrome, congestive heart failure, frequent electrolyte abnormalities, and in patients taking drugs known to prolong the QT interval.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M1" type="Trigger" span="102 5" str="risks"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="239 38" str="drugs known to prolong the QT interval" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M1" precipitant="M2"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5179" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Electrolyte abnormalities should be corrected.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5180" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Consider periodic monitoring of electrocardiograms and electrolytes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5181" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In the randomized, active-controlled trial comparing FIRMAGON to leuprolide, periodic electro-cardiograms were performed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5182" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Seven patients, three (&lt;1%) in the pooled degarelix group and four (2%) patients in the leuprolide 7.5 mg group, had a QTcF ≥ 500 msec.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5183" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>From baseline to end of study, the median change for FIRMAGON was 12.3 msec and for leuprolide was 16.7 msec.In the randomized, active-controlled trial comparing FIRMAGON to leuprolide, periodic electro-cardiograms were performed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5184" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>From baseline to end of study, the median change for FIRMAGON was 12.3 msec and for leuprolide was 16.7 msec.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5185" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Therapy with FIRMAGON results in suppression of the pituitary gonadal system.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5186" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Results of diagnostic tests of the pituitary gonadotropic and gonadal functions conducted during and after FIRMAGON may be affected.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5187" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The therapeutic effect of FIRMAGON should be monitored by measuring serum concentrations of prostate-specific antigen (PSA) periodically.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5188" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If PSA increases, serum concentrations of testosterone should be measured.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5189" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>It binds reversibly to the pituitary GnRH receptors, thereby reducing the release of gonadotropins and consequently testosterone.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5190" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A single dose of 240 mg FIRMAGON causes a decrease in the plasma concentrations of luteinizing hormone (LH) and follicle stimulating hormone (FSH), and subsequently testosterone.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5191" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>FIRMAGON is effective in achieving and maintaining testosterone suppression below the castration level of 50 ng/dL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5192" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Figure 1: Plasma Testosterone Levels from Day 0 to 364 for Degarelix 240 mg/80 mg (Median with Interquartile Ranges) Figure 1 Absorption FIRMAGON forms a depot upon subcutaneous administration, from which degarelix is released to the circulation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5193" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following administration of FIRMAGON 240 mg at a product concentration of 40 mg/mL, the mean Cmax was 26.2 ng/mL (coefficient of variation, CV 83%) and the mean AUC was 1054 ng∙day/mL (CV 35%).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5194" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Typically Cmax occurred within 2 days after subcutaneous administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5195" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In prostate cancer patients at a product concentration of 40 mg/mL, the pharmacokinetics of degarelix were linear over a dose range of 120 to 240 mg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5196" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacokinetic behavior of the drug is strongly influenced by its concentration in the injection solution.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5197" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Distribution The distribution volume of degarelix after intravenous (&gt; 1 L/kg) or subcutaneous administration (&gt; 1000L) indicates that degarelix is distributed throughout total body water.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5198" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In vitro plasma protein binding of degarelix is estimated to be approximately 90%.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5199" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Metabolism Degarelix is subject to peptide hydrolysis during the passage of the hepato-biliary system and is mainly excreted as peptide fragments in the feces.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5200" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No quantitatively significant metabolites were detected in plasma samples after subcutaneous administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5201" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In vitro studies have shown that degarelix is not a substrate, inducer or inhibitor of the CYP450 or p-glycoprotein transporter systems.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5202" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Excretion Following subcutaneous administration of 240 mg FIRMAGON at a concentration of 40 mg/mL to prostate cancer patients, degarelix is eliminated in a biphasic fashion, with a median terminal half-life of approximately 53 days.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5203" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The long half-life after subcutaneous administration is a consequence of a very slow release of degarelix from the FIRMAGON depot formed at the injection site(s).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5204" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Approximately 20-30% of a given dose of degarelix was renally excreted, suggesting that approximately 70-80% is excreted via the hepato-biliary system in humans.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5205" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following subcutaneous administration of degarelix to prostate cancer patients the clearance is approximately 9 L/hr.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5206" LabelDrug="FIRMAGON" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Effect of Age, Weight and Race There was no effect of age, weight or race on the degarelix pharmacokinetic parameters or testosterone concentration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="drugs known to prolong the qt interval" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>