<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" setid="aed29594-211d-49ef-813f-131975a8d0e3">
<Text><Section name="BOXED WARNING SECTION" id="34066-1">
Serious and fatal blood dyscrasias (aplastic anemia, hypoplastic anemia, thrombocytopenia and granulocytopenia) are known to occur after the administration of chloramphenicol.  In addition, there have been reports of aplastic anemia attributed to chloramphenicol which later terminated in leukemia.  Blood dyscrasias have occurred after both short-term and prolonged therapy with this drug.  Chloramphenicol must not be used when less potentially dangerous agents will be effective, as described in the  INDICATIONS AND USAGE section.  It must not be used in the treatment of trivial infections or where it is not indicated, as in colds, influenza, infections of the throat; or as a prophylactic agent to prevent bacterial infections. Precautions: It is essential that adequate blood studies be made during treatment with the drug.  While blood studies may detect early peripheral blood changes, such as leukopenia, reticulocytopenia, or granulocytopenia, before they become irreversible, such studies cannot be relied on to detect bone marrow depression prior to development of aplastic anemia.  To facilitate appropriate studies and observation during therapy, it is desirable that patients be hospitalized.</Section>
<Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
Chloramphenicol is contraindicated in individuals with a history of previous hypersensitivity and/or toxic reaction to it.   It must not be used in the treatment of trivial infections or where it is not indicated, as in colds, influenza, infections of the throat; or as a prophylactic agent to prevent bacterial infections.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
Concurrent therapy with other drugs that may cause bone marrow depression should be avoided.</Section>
<Section name="PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="42232-9">
Repeated courses of chloramphenicol treatment should be avoided if at all possible.  Treatment should not be continued longer than required to produce a cure with little or no risk or relapse of the disease. Excessive blood levels may result from administration of the recommended dose to patients with impaired liver or kidney function.  The dosage should be adjusted accordingly, or preferably, the blood concentration should be determined at appropriate intervals. The use of this antibiotic, as with other antibiotics, may result in an overgrowth of nonsusceptible organisms, including fungi.  If infections caused by nonsusceptible organisms appear during therapy, appropriate measures should be taken. Baseline blood studies should be followed by periodic blood studies approximately every two days during therapy.  The drug should be discontinued upon appearance of reticulocytopenia, leukopenia, thrombocytopenia, anemia or any other blood study findings attributable to chloramphenicol.  However, it should be noted that such studies do not exclude the possible later appearance of the irreversible type of bone marrow depression. Concurrent therapy with other drugs that may cause bone marrow depression should be avoided. No studies have been conducted in animals or humans to evaluate the possibility of these effects with chloramphenicol. Pregnancy Category C – Animal reproduction studies have not been conducted with chloramphenicol.  There are no adequate and well-controlled studies to establish safety of this drug in pregnancy.  It is not known whether chloramphenicol can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman.  Orally administered chloramphenicol has been shown to cross the placental barrier.  Because of potential toxic effects on the fetus (see  ADVERSE REACTIONS, “Gray Syndrome” ), chloramphenicol should be given to a pregnant woman only if the potential benefit justifies the potential risk to the fetus. Chloramphenicol is excreted in human milk following oral administration of the drug.  Because of the potential for serious adverse reactions in nursing infants from chloramphenicol, a decision should be made whether to discontinue nursing or to discontinue the drug, taking into account the importance of the drug to the mother (see  ADVERSE REACTIONS, “Gray Syndrome” ). Precaution should be used in therapy of premature and full-term neonates and infants to avoid “gray syndrome” toxicity.  Due to immature metabolic processes in the neonate and infant, excessive blood levels may result from administration of the recommended dose.  The dosage should be adjusted accordingly or, preferable, the blood concentration should be determined at appropriate intervals (see ADVERSE REACTIONS ,  "Gray Syndrome" ). See  DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION for dosing information in the pediatric population. Clinical studies of chloramphenicol sodium succinate did not include sufficient numbers of subjects aged 65 and over to determine whether they respond differently from younger subjects.  Other reported clinical experience has not identified differences in responses between the elderly and younger patients.  In general, dose selection for an elderly patient should be cautious, usually starting at the low end of the dosing range, reflecting the greater frequency of decreased hepatic, renal, or cardiac function, and of concomitant disease or other drug therapy.  This drug is known to be substantially excreted by the kidney, and the risk of toxic reactions to this drug may be greater in patients with impaired renal function.  Because elderly patients are more likely to have decreased renal function, care should be taken in dose selection, and it may be useful to monitor renal function. Each gram (10 mL of a 10% solution) of chloramphenicol sodium succinate contains approximately 52 mg (2.25 mEq) of sodium.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Chloramphenicol administered orally is absorbed rapidly from the intestinal tract.  In controlled studies in adult volunteers using the recommended dosage of 50 mg/kg/day, a dosage of 1 g every 6 hours for 8 doses was given.  Using the microbiological assay method, the average peak serum level was 11.2 mcg/mL one hour after the first dose.  A cumulative effect gave a peak rise to 18.4 mcg/mL after the fifth dose of 1 g.  Mean serum levels ranged from 8 to 14 mcg/mL over the 48-hour period.  Total urinary excretion of chloramphenicol in these studies ranged from a low of 68% to a high of 99% over a three-day period.  From 8% to 12% of the antibiotic excreted is in the form of free chloramphenicol; the remainder consists of microbiologically inactive metabolites, principally the conjugate with glucuronic acid.  Since the glucuronide is excreted rapidly, most chloramphenicol detected in the blood is in the microbiologically active free form.  Despite the small proportion of unchanged drug excreted in the urine, the concentration of free chloramphenicol is relatively high, amounting to several hundred mcg/mL in patients receiving divided doses of 50 mg/kg/day.  Small amounts of active drug are found in bile and feces.  Chloramphenicol diffuses rapidly, but its distribution is not uniform.  Highest concentrations are found in liver and kidney, and lowest concentrations are found in brain and cerebrospinal fluid.  Chloramphenicol enters cerebrospinal fluid even in the absence of meningeal inflammation, appearing in concentrations about half of those found in the blood.  Measurable levels are also detected in pleural and in ascitic fluids, saliva, milk, and in the aqueous and vitreous humors.  Transport across the placental barrier occurs with somewhat lower concentration in cord blood of neonates than in maternal blood. Mechanism of Action Chloramphenicol is a broad-spectrum antibiotic originally isolated from Streptomyces venezuelae .  It inhibits bacterial protein synthesis by interfering with the transfer of activated amino acids from soluble RNA to ribosomes.  In vitro, chloramphenicol exerts mainly a bacteriostatic effect on a wide range of gram-negative and gram-positive bacteria. Antimicrobial Activity Chloramphenicol has been shown to be active against most strains of the following microorganisms, both in vitro and in clinical infections as described in the  INDICATIONS AND USAGE section. Aerobic gram-negative microorganisms Haemophilus influenzae Salmonella species, including Salmonella typhi Other microorganisms Lymphogranuloma-psittacosis group Rickettsia When available, the clinical microbiology laboratory should provide cumulative reports of in vitro susceptibility test results for antimicrobial drugs used in local hospitals and practice areas to the physician as periodic reports that describe the susceptibility profile of nosocomial and community-acquired pathogens.  These reports should aid the physician in selecting an antibacterial drug for treatment. Dilution Techniques Quantitative methods are used to determine antimicrobial minimum inhibitory concentrations (MICs).  These MICs provide estimates of the susceptibility of bacteria to antimicrobial compounds.  The MICs should be determined using a standardized (broth and/or agar). 1,3 The MIC values should be interpreted according to the criteria provided in Table 1. Diffusion Techniques Quantitative methods that require measurement of zone diameters can also provide reproducible estimates of the susceptibility of bacteria to antimicrobial compounds.  The zone size should be determined using a standardized test method. 2,3 This procedure uses paper disks impregnated with 30 mcg chloramphenicol to test the susceptibility of bacteria to chloramphenicol.  The disc diffusion breakpoints should be interpreted according to the criteria provided in Table 1.  Table 1.  Susceptibility Test Interpretive Criteria for Chloramphenicol Pathogen Minimum Inhibitory Concentrations (mcg/mL) Zone Diameters (mm) S I R S I R Salmonella spp. &amp;lt; 8 16 &amp;gt; 32 &amp;gt; 18 13 to 17 &amp;lt; 12 Haemophilus influenzae &amp;lt; 2 4 &amp;gt; 8 ≥ 29 26 to 28 &amp;lt; 25 A report of Susceptible (S) indicates that the antimicrobial drug is likely to inhibit growth of the pathogen if the antimicrobial drug reaches the concentration usually achievable at the site of infection.  A report of Intermediate (I) indicates that the result should be considered equivocal, and, if the microorganism is not fully susceptible to alternative, clinically feasible drugs, the test should be repeated.  This category implies possible clinical applicability in body sites where the drug is physiologically concentrated or in situations where a high dosage of the drug can be used.  This category also provides a buffer zone that prevents small uncontrolled technical factors from causing major discrepancies in interpretation.  A report of Resistant (R) indicates that the antimicrobial drug is not likely to inhibit growth of the pathogen if the antimicrobial drug reaches the concentration usually achievable at the infection site; other therapy should be selected. Quality Control Standardized susceptibility test procedures require the use of laboratory controls to monitor and ensure the accuracy and precision of supplies and reagents used in the assay, and the techniques of the individuals performing the test. 1,2,3 Standard chloramphenicol powder should provide the following range of MIC values noted in Table 2.  For the disc diffusion technique using the 30 mcg disk, the criteria in Table 2 should be achieved.   Table 2.  Quality Control Parameters for Chloramphenicol QC Strain Minimum Inhibitory Concentrations (mcg/mL) Zone Diameters (mm) Escherichia coli ATCC 25922 2 to 8 21 to 27 Haemophilus influenzae ATCC 49247 0.25 to 1 31 to 40 When available, the clinical microbiology laboratory should provide cumulative reports of in vitro susceptibility test results for antimicrobial drugs used in local hospitals and practice areas to the physician as periodic reports that describe the susceptibility profile of nosocomial and community-acquired pathogens.  These reports should aid the physician in selecting an antibacterial drug for treatment. Dilution Techniques Quantitative methods are used to determine antimicrobial minimum inhibitory concentrations (MICs).  These MICs provide estimates of the susceptibility of bacteria to antimicrobial compounds.  The MICs should be determined using a standardized (broth and/or agar). 1,3 The MIC values should be interpreted according to the criteria provided in Table 1. Diffusion Techniques Quantitative methods that require measurement of zone diameters can also provide reproducible estimates of the susceptibility of bacteria to antimicrobial compounds.  The zone size should be determined using a standardized test method. 2,3 This procedure uses paper disks impregnated with 30 mcg chloramphenicol to test the susceptibility of bacteria to chloramphenicol.  The disc diffusion breakpoints should be interpreted according to the criteria provided in Table 1.  Table 1.  Susceptibility Test Interpretive Criteria for Chloramphenicol Pathogen Minimum Inhibitory Concentrations (mcg/mL) Zone Diameters (mm) S I R S I R Salmonella spp. &amp;lt; 8 16 &amp;gt; 32 &amp;gt; 18 13 to 17 &amp;lt; 12 Haemophilus influenzae &amp;lt; 2 4 &amp;gt; 8 ≥ 29 26 to 28 &amp;lt; 25 A report of Susceptible (S) indicates that the antimicrobial drug is likely to inhibit growth of the pathogen if the antimicrobial drug reaches the concentration usually achievable at the site of infection.  A report of Intermediate (I) indicates that the result should be considered equivocal, and, if the microorganism is not fully susceptible to alternative, clinically feasible drugs, the test should be repeated.  This category implies possible clinical applicability in body sites where the drug is physiologically concentrated or in situations where a high dosage of the drug can be used.  This category also provides a buffer zone that prevents small uncontrolled technical factors from causing major discrepancies in interpretation.  A report of Resistant (R) indicates that the antimicrobial drug is not likely to inhibit growth of the pathogen if the antimicrobial drug reaches the concentration usually achievable at the infection site; other therapy should be selected. Quality Control Standardized susceptibility test procedures require the use of laboratory controls to monitor and ensure the accuracy and precision of supplies and reagents used in the assay, and the techniques of the individuals performing the test. 1,2,3 Standard chloramphenicol powder should provide the following range of MIC values noted in Table 2.  For the disc diffusion technique using the 30 mcg disk, the criteria in Table 2 should be achieved.   Table 2.  Quality Control Parameters for Chloramphenicol QC Strain Minimum Inhibitory Concentrations (mcg/mL) Zone Diameters (mm) Escherichia coli ATCC 25922 2 to 8 21 to 27 Haemophilus influenzae ATCC 49247 0.25 to 1 31 to 40</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="2292" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Serious and fatal blood dyscrasias (aplastic anemia, hypoplastic anemia, thrombocytopenia and granulocytopenia) are known to occur after the administration of chloramphenicol.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2293" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>In addition, there have been reports of aplastic anemia attributed to chloramphenicol which later terminated in leukemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2294" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Blood dyscrasias have occurred after both short-term and prolonged therapy with this drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2295" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Chloramphenicol must not be used when less potentially dangerous agents will be effective, as described in the INDICATIONS AND USAGE section.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2296" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>It must not be used in the treatment of trivial infections or where it is not indicated, as in colds, influenza, infections of the throat; or as a prophylactic agent to prevent bacterial infections.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2297" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Precautions: It is essential that adequate blood studies be made during treatment with the drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2298" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>While blood studies may detect early peripheral blood changes, such as leukopenia, reticulocytopenia, or granulocytopenia, before they become irreversible, such studies cannot be relied on to detect bone marrow depression prior to development of aplastic anemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2299" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>To facilitate appropriate studies and observation during therapy, it is desirable that patients be hospitalized.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2300" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Chloramphenicol is contraindicated in individuals with a history of previous hypersensitivity and/or toxic reaction to it.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2301" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Concurrent therapy with other drugs that may cause bone marrow depression should be avoided.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M1" type="Trigger" span="45 5" str="cause "/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Trigger" span="74 17" str=" should be avoided"/>
<Mention id="M3" type="Precipitant" span="30 43" str="drugs that may cause bone marrow depression" code="N0000008759"/>
<Mention id="M4" type="SpecificInteraction" span="51 22" str="bone marrow depression" code="307762000: Bone marrow depression (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M1;M2" precipitant="M3" effect="M4" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2302" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Repeated courses of chloramphenicol treatment should be avoided if at all possible.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2303" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Treatment should not be continued longer than required to produce a cure with little or no risk or relapse of the disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2304" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Excessive blood levels may result from administration of the recommended dose to patients with impaired liver or kidney function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2305" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The dosage should be adjusted accordingly, or preferably, the blood concentration should be determined at appropriate intervals.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2306" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The use of this antibiotic, as with other antibiotics, may result in an overgrowth of nonsusceptible organisms, including fungi.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2307" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>If infections caused by nonsusceptible organisms appear during therapy, appropriate measures should be taken.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2308" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Baseline blood studies should be followed by periodic blood studies approximately every two days during therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2309" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The drug should be discontinued upon appearance of reticulocytopenia, leukopenia, thrombocytopenia, anemia or any other blood study findings attributable to chloramphenicol.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2310" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>However, it should be noted that such studies do not exclude the possible later appearance of the irreversible type of bone marrow depression.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2311" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>No studies have been conducted in animals or humans to evaluate the possibility of these effects with chloramphenicol.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2312" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Pregnancy Category C – Animal reproduction studies have not been conducted with chloramphenicol.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2313" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>There are no adequate and well-controlled studies to establish safety of this drug in pregnancy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2314" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>It is not known whether chloramphenicol can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2315" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Orally administered chloramphenicol has been shown to cross the placental barrier.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2316" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because of potential toxic effects on the fetus, chloramphenicol should be given to a pregnant woman only if the potential benefit justifies the potential risk to the fetus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2317" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Chloramphenicol is excreted in human milk following oral administration of the drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2318" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because of the potential for serious adverse reactions in nursing infants from chloramphenicol, a decision should be made whether to discontinue nursing or to discontinue the drug, taking into account the importance of the drug to the mother.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2319" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Precaution should be used in therapy of premature and full-term neonates and infants to avoid “gray syndrome” toxicity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2320" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Due to immature metabolic processes in the neonate and infant, excessive blood levels may result from administration of the recommended dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2321" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The dosage should be adjusted accordingly or, preferable, the blood concentration should be determined at appropriate intervals.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2322" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>See DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION for dosing information in the pediatric population.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2323" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Clinical studies of chloramphenicol sodium succinate did not include sufficient numbers of subjects aged 65 and over to determine whether they respond differently from younger subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2324" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Other reported clinical experience has not identified differences in responses between the elderly and younger patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2325" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In general, dose selection for an elderly patient should be cautious, usually starting at the low end of the dosing range, reflecting the greater frequency of decreased hepatic, renal, or cardiac function, and of concomitant disease or other drug therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2326" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>This drug is known to be substantially excreted by the kidney, and the risk of toxic reactions to this drug may be greater in patients with impaired renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2327" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because elderly patients are more likely to have decreased renal function, care should be taken in dose selection, and it may be useful to monitor renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2328" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Each gram (10 mL of a 10% solution) of chloramphenicol sodium succinate contains approximately 52 mg (2.25 mEq) of sodium.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2329" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Chloramphenicol administered orally is absorbed rapidly from the intestinal tract.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2330" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In controlled studies in adult volunteers using the recommended dosage of 50 mg/kg/day, a dosage of 1 g every 6 hours for 8 doses was given.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2331" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Using the microbiological assay method, the average peak serum level was 11.2 mcg/mL one hour after the first dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2332" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A cumulative effect gave a peak rise to 18.4 mcg/mL after the fifth dose of 1 g. Mean serum levels ranged from 8 to 14 mcg/mL over the 48-hour period.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2333" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Total urinary excretion of chloramphenicol in these studies ranged from a low of 68% to a high of 99% over a three-day period.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2334" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>From 8% to 12% of the antibiotic excreted is in the form of free chloramphenicol; the remainder consists of microbiologically inactive metabolites, principally the conjugate with glucuronic acid.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2335" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Since the glucuronide is excreted rapidly, most chloramphenicol detected in the blood is in the microbiologically active free form.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2336" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Despite the small proportion of unchanged drug excreted in the urine, the concentration of free chloramphenicol is relatively high, amounting to several hundred mcg/mL in patients receiving divided doses of 50 mg/kg/day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2337" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Small amounts of active drug are found in bile and feces.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2338" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Chloramphenicol diffuses rapidly, but its distribution is not uniform.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2339" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Highest concentrations are found in liver and kidney, and lowest concentrations are found in brain and cerebrospinal fluid.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2340" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Chloramphenicol enters cerebrospinal fluid even in the absence of meningeal inflammation, appearing in concentrations about half of those found in the blood.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2341" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Measurable levels are also detected in pleural and in ascitic fluids, saliva, milk, and in the aqueous and vitreous humors.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2342" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Transport across the placental barrier occurs with somewhat lower concentration in cord blood of neonates than in maternal blood.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2343" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Mechanism of Action Chloramphenicol is a broad-spectrum antibiotic originally isolated from Streptomyces venezuelae.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2344" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>It inhibits bacterial protein synthesis by interfering with the transfer of activated amino acids from soluble RNA to ribosomes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2345" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In vitro, chloramphenicol exerts mainly a bacteriostatic effect on a wide range of gram-negative and gram-positive bacteria.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2346" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Antimicrobial Activity Chloramphenicol has been shown to be active against most strains of the following microorganisms, both in vitro and in clinical infections as described in the INDICATIONS AND USAGE section.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2347" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Aerobic gram-negative microorganisms Haemophilus influenzae Salmonella species, including Salmonella typhi Other microorganisms Lymphogranuloma-psittacosis group Rickettsia When available, the clinical microbiology laboratory should provide cumulative reports of in vitro susceptibility test results for antimicrobial drugs used in local hospitals and practice areas to the physician as periodic reports that describe the susceptibility profile of nosocomial and community-acquired pathogens.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2348" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>These reports should aid the physician in selecting an antibacterial drug for treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2349" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Dilution Techniques Quantitative methods are used to determine antimicrobial minimum inhibitory concentrations (MICs).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2350" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>These MICs provide estimates of the susceptibility of bacteria to antimicrobial compounds.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2351" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The MICs should be determined using a standardized (broth and/or agar).1,3 The MIC values should be interpreted according to the criteria provided in Table 1.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2352" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Diffusion Techniques Quantitative methods that require measurement of zone diameters can also provide reproducible estimates of the susceptibility of bacteria to antimicrobial compounds.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2353" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The zone size should be determined using a standardized test method.2,3 This procedure uses paper disks impregnated with 30 mcg chloramphenicol to test the susceptibility of bacteria to chloramphenicol.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2354" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The disc diffusion breakpoints should be interpreted according to the criteria provided in Table 1.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2355" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Susceptibility Test Interpretive Criteria for Chloramphenicol Pathogen Minimum Inhibitory Concentrations (mcg/mL) Zone Diameters (mm) S I R S I R Salmonella spp.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2356" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>&lt; 8 16 &gt; 32 &gt; 18 13 to 17 &lt; 12 Haemophilus influenzae &lt; 2 4 &gt; 8 ≥ 29 26 to 28 &lt; 25 A report of Susceptible (S) indicates that the antimicrobial drug is likely to inhibit growth of the pathogen if the antimicrobial drug reaches the concentration usually achievable at the site of infection.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2357" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A report of Intermediate (I) indicates that the result should be considered equivocal, and, if the microorganism is not fully susceptible to alternative, clinically feasible drugs, the test should be repeated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2358" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This category implies possible clinical applicability in body sites where the drug is physiologically concentrated or in situations where a high dosage of the drug can be used.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2359" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This category also provides a buffer zone that prevents small uncontrolled technical factors from causing major discrepancies in interpretation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2360" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A report of Resistant (R) indicates that the antimicrobial drug is not likely to inhibit growth of the pathogen if the antimicrobial drug reaches the concentration usually achievable at the infection site; other therapy should be selected.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2361" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Quality Control Standardized susceptibility test procedures require the use of laboratory controls to monitor and ensure the accuracy and precision of supplies and reagents used in the assay, and the techniques of the individuals performing the test.1,2,3 Standard chloramphenicol powder should provide the following range of MIC values noted in Table 2.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2362" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>For the disc diffusion technique using the 30 mcg disk, the criteria in Table 2 should be achieved.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2363" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Quality Control Parameters for Chloramphenicol QC Strain Minimum Inhibitory Concentrations (mcg/mL) Zone Diameters (mm) Escherichia coli ATCC 25922 2 to 8 21 to 27 Haemophilus influenzae ATCC 49247 0.25 to 1 31 to 40</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2364" LabelDrug="Chloramphenicol Sodium Succinate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>When available, the clinical microbiology laboratory should provide cumulative reports of in vitro susceptibility test results for antimicrobial drugs used in local hospitals and practice areas to the physician as periodic reports that describe the susceptibility profile of nosocomial and community-acquired pathogens.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="drugs that may cause bone marrow depression" precipitantCode="N0000008759" effect="307762000: Bone marrow depression (disorder)"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>