<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Glucotrol" setid="b4f55916-91a2-4171-a361-919e7cb329b0">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
GLUCOTROL is contraindicated in patients with: Known hypersensitivity to the drug. Type 1 diabetes mellitus, diabetic ketoacidosis, with or without coma. This condition should be treated with insulin.</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
There is no fixed dosage regimen for the management of diabetes mellitus with GLUCOTROL or any other hypoglycemic agent. In addition to the usual monitoring of urinary glucose, the patient's blood glucose must also be monitored periodically to determine the minimum effective dose for the patient; to detect primary failure, i.e., inadequate lowering of blood glucose at the maximum recommended dose of medication; and to detect secondary failure, i.e., loss of an adequate blood-glucose-lowering response after an initial period of effectiveness. Glycosylated hemoglobin levels may also be of value in monitoring the patient's response to therapy. Short-term administration of GLUCOTROL may be sufficient during periods of transient loss of control in patients usually controlled well on diet. In general, GLUCOTROL should be given approximately 30 minutes before a meal to achieve the greatest reduction in postprandial hyperglycemia. The recommended starting dose is 5 mg, given before breakfast. Geriatric patients or those with liver disease may be started on 2.5 mg. Dosage adjustments should ordinarily be in increments of 2.5–5 mg, as determined by blood glucose response. At least several days should elapse between titration steps. If response to a single dose is not satisfactory, dividing that dose may prove effective. The maximum recommended once daily dose is 15 mg. Doses above 15 mg should ordinarily be divided and given before meals of adequate caloric content. The maximum recommended total daily dose is 40 mg. Some patients may be effectively controlled on a once-a-day regimen, while others show better response with divided dosing. Total daily doses above 15 mg should ordinarily be divided. Total daily doses above 30 mg have been safely given on a b.i.d. basis to long-term patients. In elderly patients, debilitated or malnourished patients, and patients with impaired renal or hepatic function, the initial and maintenance dosing should be conservative to avoid hypoglycemic reactions (see PRECAUTIONS section). As with other sulfonylurea-class hypoglycemics, many stable non-insulin-dependent diabetic patients receiving insulin may be safely placed on GLUCOTROL. When transferring patients from insulin to GLUCOTROL, the following general guidelines should be considered: For patients whose daily insulin requirement is 20 units or less, insulin may be discontinued and GLUCOTROL therapy may begin at usual dosages. Several days should elapse between GLUCOTROL titration steps. For patients whose daily insulin requirement is greater than 20 units, the insulin dose should be reduced by 50% and GLUCOTROL therapy may begin at usual dosages. Subsequent reductions in insulin dosage should depend on individual patient response. Several days should elapse between GLUCOTROL titration steps. During the insulin withdrawal period, the patient should test urine samples for sugar and ketone bodies at least three times daily. Patients should be instructed to contact the prescriber immediately if these tests are abnormal. In some cases, especially when patient has been receiving greater than 40 units of insulin daily, it may be advisable to consider hospitalization during the transition period. As with other sulfonylurea-class hypoglycemics, no transition period is necessary when transferring patients to GLUCOTROL. Patients should be observed carefully (1–2 weeks) for hypoglycemia when being transferred from longer half-life sulfonylureas (e.g., chlorpropamide) to GLUCOTROL due to potential overlapping of drug effect. When colesevelam is coadministered with glipizide ER, maximum plasma concentration and total exposure to glipizide is reduced. Therefore, GLUCOTROL should be administered at least 4 hours prior to colesevelam.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
The hypoglycemic action of sulfonylureas may be potentiated by certain drugs including nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory agents, some azoles, and other drugs that are highly protein bound, salicylates, sulfonamides, chloramphenicol, probenecid, coumarins, monoamine oxidase inhibitors, quinolones and beta adrenergic blocking agents. When such drugs are administered to a patient receiving GLUCOTROL, the patient should be observed closely for hypoglycemia. When such drugs are withdrawn from a patient receiving GLUCOTROL, the patient should be observed closely for loss of control. In vitro binding studies with human serum proteins indicate that GLUCOTROL binds differently than tolbutamide and does not interact with salicylate or dicumarol. However, caution must be exercised in extrapolating these findings to the clinical situation and in the use of GLUCOTROL with these drugs. Certain drugs tend to produce hyperglycemia and may lead to loss of control. These drugs include the thiazides and other diuretics, corticosteroids, phenothiazines, thyroid products, estrogens, oral contraceptives, phenytoin, nicotinic acid, sympathomimetics, calcium channel blocking drugs, and isoniazid. When such drugs are administered to a patient receiving GLUCOTROL, the patient should be closely observed for loss of control. When such drugs are withdrawn from a patient receiving GLUCOTROL, the patient should be observed closely for hypoglycemia. A potential interaction between oral miconazole and oral hypoglycemic agents leading to severe hypoglycemia has been reported. Whether this interaction also occurs with the intravenous, topical, or vaginal preparations of miconazole is not known. The effect of concomitant administration of DIFLUCAN ® (fluconazole) and GLUCOTROL has been demonstrated in a placebo-controlled crossover study in normal volunteers. All subjects received GLUCOTROL alone and following treatment with 100 mg of DIFLUCAN as a single daily oral dose for 7 days. The mean percentage increase in the GLUCOTROL AUC after fluconazole administration was 56.9% (range: 35 to 81). In studies assessing the effect of colesevelam on the pharmacokinetics of glipizide ER in healthy volunteers, reductions in glipizide AUC 0–∞ and C max of 12% and 13%, respectively were observed when colesevelam was coadministered with glipizide ER. When glipizide ER was administered 4 hours prior to colesevelam, there was no significant change in glipizide AUC 0–∞ or C max, -4% and 0%, respectively. Therefore, GLUCOTROL should be administered at least 4 hours prior to colesevelam to ensure that colesevelam does not reduce the absorption of glipizide.</Section>
<Section name="PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="42232-9">
There have been no clinical studies establishing conclusive evidence of macrovascular risk reduction with GLUCOTROL or any other anti-diabetic drug. The metabolism and excretion of GLUCOTROL may be slowed in patients with impaired renal and/or hepatic function. If hypoglycemia should occur in such patients, it may be prolonged and appropriate management should be instituted. All sulfonylurea drugs are capable of producing severe hypoglycemia. Proper patient selection, dosage, and instructions are important to avoid hypoglycemic episodes. Renal or hepatic insufficiency may cause elevated blood levels of GLUCOTROL and the latter may also diminish gluconeogenic capacity, both of which increase the risk of serious hypoglycemic reactions. Elderly, debilitated or malnourished patients, and those with adrenal or pituitary insufficiency, are particularly susceptible to the hypoglycemic action of glucose-lowering drugs. Hypoglycemia may be difficult to recognize in the elderly, and in people who are taking beta-adrenergic blocking drugs. Hypoglycemia is more likely to occur when caloric intake is deficient, after severe or prolonged exercise, when alcohol is ingested, or when more than one glucose-lowering drug is used. When a patient stabilized on any diabetic regimen is exposed to stress such as fever, trauma, infection, or surgery, a loss of control may occur. At such times, it may be necessary to discontinue GLUCOTROL and administer insulin. The effectiveness of any oral hypoglycemic drug, including GLUCOTROL, in lowering blood glucose to a desired level decreases in many patients over a period of time, which may be due to progression of the severity of the diabetes or to diminished responsiveness to the drug. This phenomenon is known as secondary failure, to distinguish it from primary failure in which the drug is ineffective in an individual patient when first given. Treatment of patients with glucose 6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PD) deficiency with sulfonylurea agents can lead to hemolytic anemia. Because GLUCOTROL belongs to the class of sulfonylurea agents, caution should be used in patients with G6PD deficiency and a non-sulfonylurea alternative should be considered. In post-marketing reports, hemolytic anemia has also been reported in patients who did not have known G6PD deficiency. Blood and urine glucose should be monitored periodically. Measurement of glycosylated hemoglobin may be useful. Patients should be informed of the potential risks and advantages of GLUCOTROL and of alternative modes of therapy. They should also be informed about the importance of adhering to dietary instructions, of a regular exercise program, and of regular testing of urine and/or blood glucose. The risks of hypoglycemia, its symptoms and treatment, and conditions that predispose to its development should be explained to patients and responsible family members. Primary and secondary failure should also be explained. In initiating treatment for type 2 diabetes, diet should be emphasized as the primary form of treatment. Caloric restriction and weight loss are essential in the obese diabetic patient. Proper dietary management alone may be effective in controlling the blood glucose and symptoms of hyperglycemia. The importance of regular physical activity should also be stressed, and cardiovascular risk factors should be identified and corrective measures taken where possible. Use of GLUCOTROL or other antidiabetic medications must be viewed by both the physician and patient as a treatment in addition to diet and not as a substitution or as a convenient mechanism for avoiding dietary restraint. Furthermore, loss of blood glucose control on diet alone may be transient, thus requiring only short-term administration of GLUCOTROL or other antidiabetic medications. Maintenance or discontinuation of GLUCOTROL or other antidiabetic medications should be based on clinical judgment using regular clinical and laboratory evaluations. The hypoglycemic action of sulfonylureas may be potentiated by certain drugs including nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory agents, some azoles, and other drugs that are highly protein bound, salicylates, sulfonamides, chloramphenicol, probenecid, coumarins, monoamine oxidase inhibitors, quinolones and beta adrenergic blocking agents. When such drugs are administered to a patient receiving GLUCOTROL, the patient should be observed closely for hypoglycemia. When such drugs are withdrawn from a patient receiving GLUCOTROL, the patient should be observed closely for loss of control. In vitro binding studies with human serum proteins indicate that GLUCOTROL binds differently than tolbutamide and does not interact with salicylate or dicumarol. However, caution must be exercised in extrapolating these findings to the clinical situation and in the use of GLUCOTROL with these drugs. Certain drugs tend to produce hyperglycemia and may lead to loss of control. These drugs include the thiazides and other diuretics, corticosteroids, phenothiazines, thyroid products, estrogens, oral contraceptives, phenytoin, nicotinic acid, sympathomimetics, calcium channel blocking drugs, and isoniazid. When such drugs are administered to a patient receiving GLUCOTROL, the patient should be closely observed for loss of control. When such drugs are withdrawn from a patient receiving GLUCOTROL, the patient should be observed closely for hypoglycemia. A potential interaction between oral miconazole and oral hypoglycemic agents leading to severe hypoglycemia has been reported. Whether this interaction also occurs with the intravenous, topical, or vaginal preparations of miconazole is not known. The effect of concomitant administration of DIFLUCAN ® (fluconazole) and GLUCOTROL has been demonstrated in a placebo-controlled crossover study in normal volunteers. All subjects received GLUCOTROL alone and following treatment with 100 mg of DIFLUCAN as a single daily oral dose for 7 days. The mean percentage increase in the GLUCOTROL AUC after fluconazole administration was 56.9% (range: 35 to 81). In studies assessing the effect of colesevelam on the pharmacokinetics of glipizide ER in healthy volunteers, reductions in glipizide AUC 0–∞ and C max of 12% and 13%, respectively were observed when colesevelam was coadministered with glipizide ER. When glipizide ER was administered 4 hours prior to colesevelam, there was no significant change in glipizide AUC 0–∞ or C max, -4% and 0%, respectively. Therefore, GLUCOTROL should be administered at least 4 hours prior to colesevelam to ensure that colesevelam does not reduce the absorption of glipizide. A twenty month study in rats and an eighteen month study in mice at doses up to 75 times the maximum human dose revealed no evidence of drug-related carcinogenicity. Bacterial and in vivo mutagenicity tests were uniformly negative. Studies in rats of both sexes at doses up to 75 times the human dose showed no effects on fertility. GLUCOTROL (glipizide) was found to be mildly fetotoxic in rat reproductive studies at all dose levels (5–50 mg/kg). This fetotoxicity has been similarly noted with other sulfonylureas, such as tolbutamide and tolazamide. The effect is perinatal and believed to be directly related to the pharmacologic (hypoglycemic) action of GLUCOTROL. In studies in rats and rabbits, no teratogenic effects were found. There are no adequate and well controlled studies in pregnant women. GLUCOTROL should be used during pregnancy only if the potential benefit justifies the potential risk to the fetus. Because recent information suggests that abnormal blood glucose levels during pregnancy are associated with a higher incidence of congenital abnormalities, many experts recommend that insulin be used during pregnancy to maintain blood glucose levels as close to normal as possible. Prolonged severe hypoglycemia (4 to 10 days) has been reported in neonates born to mothers who were receiving a sulfonylurea drug at the time of delivery. This has been reported more frequently with the use of agents with prolonged half-lives. If GLUCOTROL is used during pregnancy, it should be discontinued at least one month before the expected delivery date. Although it is not known whether GLUCOTROL is excreted in human milk, some sulfonylurea drugs are known to be excreted in human milk. Because the potential for hypoglycemia in nursing infants may exist, a decision should be made whether to discontinue nursing or to discontinue the drug, taking into account the importance of the drug to the mother. If the drug is discontinued and if diet alone is inadequate for controlling blood glucose, insulin therapy should be considered. Safety and effectiveness in children have not been established. A determination has not been made whether controlled clinical studies of GLUCOTROL included sufficient numbers of subjects aged 65 and over to define a difference in response from younger subjects. Other reported clinical experience has not identified differences in responses between the elderly and younger patients. In general, dose selection for an elderly patient should be cautious, usually starting at the low end of the dosing range, reflecting the greater frequency of decreased hepatic, renal, or cardiac function, and of concomitant disease or other drug therapy.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS SECTION" id="34071-1">
The administration of oral hypoglycemic drugs has been reported to be associated with increased cardiovascular mortality as compared to treatment with diet alone or diet plus insulin. This warning is based on the study conducted by the University Group Diabetes Program (UGDP), a long-term prospective clinical trial designed to evaluate the effectiveness of glucose-lowering drugs in preventing or delaying vascular complications in patients with non-insulin-dependent diabetes. The study involved 823 patients who were randomly assigned to one of four treatment groups ( Diabetes , 19, supp. 2: 747–830, 1970). UGDP reported that patients treated for 5 to 8 years with diet plus a fixed dose of tolbutamide (1.5 grams per day) had a rate of cardiovascular mortality approximately 2½ times that of patients treated with diet alone. A significant increase in total mortality was not observed, but the use of tolbutamide was discontinued based on the increase in cardiovascular mortality, thus limiting the opportunity for the study to show an increase in overall mortality. Despite controversy regarding the interpretation of these results, the findings of the UGDP study provide an adequate basis for this warning. The patient should be informed of the potential risks and advantages of GLUCOTROL and of alternative modes of therapy. Although only one drug in the sulfonylurea class (tolbutamide) was included in this study, it is prudent from a safety standpoint to consider that this warning may also apply to other oral hypoglycemic drugs in this class, in view of their close similarities in mode of action and chemical structure.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
The primary mode of action of GLUCOTROL in experimental animals appears to be the stimulation of insulin secretion from the beta cells of pancreatic islet tissue and is thus dependent on functioning beta cells in the pancreatic islets. In humans, GLUCOTROL appears to lower the blood glucose acutely by stimulating the release of insulin from the pancreas, an effect dependent upon functioning beta cells in the pancreatic islets. The mechanism by which GLUCOTROL lowers blood glucose during long-term administration has not been clearly established. In man, stimulation of insulin secretion by GLUCOTROL in response to a meal is undoubtedly of major importance. Fasting insulin levels are not elevated even on long-term GLUCOTROL administration, but the postprandial insulin response continues to be enhanced after at least 6 months of treatment. The insulinotropic response to a meal occurs within 30 minutes after an oral dose of GLUCOTROL in diabetic patients, but elevated insulin levels do not persist beyond the time of the meal challenge. Extrapancreatic effects may play a part in the mechanism of action of oral sulfonylurea hypoglycemic drugs. Blood sugar control persists in some patients for up to 24 hours after a single dose of GLUCOTROL, even though plasma levels have declined to a small fraction of peak levels by that time (see Pharmacokinetics below). Some patients fail to respond initially, or gradually lose their responsiveness to sulfonylurea drugs, including GLUCOTROL. Alternatively, GLUCOTROL may be effective in some patients who have not responded or have ceased to respond to other sulfonylureas. It has been shown that GLUCOTROL therapy was effective in controlling blood sugar without deleterious changes in the plasma lipoprotein profiles of patients treated for NIDDM. In a placebo-controlled, crossover study in normal volunteers, GLUCOTROL had no antidiuretic activity and, in fact, led to a slight increase in free water clearance. Gastrointestinal absorption of GLUCOTROL in man is uniform, rapid, and essentially complete. Peak plasma concentrations occur 1–3 hours after a single oral dose. The half-life of elimination ranges from 2–4 hours in normal subjects, whether given intravenously or orally. The metabolic and excretory patterns are similar with the two routes of administration, indicating that first-pass metabolism is not significant. GLUCOTROL does not accumulate in plasma on repeated oral administration. Total absorption and disposition of an oral dose was unaffected by food in normal volunteers, but absorption was delayed by about 40 minutes. Thus, GLUCOTROL was more effective when administered about 30 minutes before, rather than with, a test meal in diabetic patients. Protein binding was studied in serum from volunteers who received either oral or intravenous GLUCOTROL and found to be 98–99% one hour after either route of administration. The apparent volume of distribution of GLUCOTROL after intravenous administration was 11 liters, indicative of localization within the extracellular fluid compartment. In mice, no GLUCOTROL or metabolites were detectable autoradiographically in the brain or spinal cord of males or females, nor in the fetuses of pregnant females. In another study, however, very small amounts of radioactivity were detected in the fetuses of rats given labelled drug. The metabolism of GLUCOTROL is extensive and occurs mainly in the liver. The primary metabolites are inactive hydroxylation products and polar conjugates and are excreted mainly in the urine. Less than 10% unchanged GLUCOTROL is found in the urine.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="9045" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>GLUCOTROL is contraindicated in patients with: Known hypersensitivity to the drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9046" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Type 1 diabetes mellitus, diabetic ketoacidosis, with or without coma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9047" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>This condition should be treated with insulin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9048" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>There is no fixed dosage regimen for the management of diabetes mellitus with GLUCOTROL or any other hypoglycemic agent.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9049" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In addition to the usual monitoring of urinary glucose, the patient's blood glucose must also be monitored periodically to determine the minimum effective dose for the patient; to detect primary failure, i.e., inadequate lowering of blood glucose at the maximum recommended dose of medication; and to detect secondary failure, i.e., loss of an adequate blood-glucose-lowering response after an initial period of effectiveness.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9050" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Glycosylated hemoglobin levels may also be of value in monitoring the patient's response to therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9051" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Short-term administration of GLUCOTROL may be sufficient during periods of transient loss of control in patients usually controlled well on diet.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9052" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In general, GLUCOTROL should be given approximately 30 minutes before a meal to achieve the greatest reduction in postprandial hyperglycemia.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M1" type="Trigger" span="22 15;63 6" str="should be given | before"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="72 4" str="meal" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M3" type="SpecificInteraction" span="101 39" str="reduction in postprandial hyperglycemia" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M1" precipitant="M2" effect="M3" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9053" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommended starting dose is 5 mg, given before breakfast.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9054" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Geriatric patients or those with liver disease may be started on 2.5 mg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9055" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dosage adjustments should ordinarily be in increments of 2.5–5 mg, as determined by blood glucose response.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9056" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>At least several days should elapse between titration steps.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9057" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If response to a single dose is not satisfactory, dividing that dose may prove effective.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9058" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The maximum recommended once daily dose is 15 mg. Doses above 15 mg should ordinarily be divided and given before meals of adequate caloric content.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M4" type="Trigger" span="101 12" str="given before"/>
<Mention id="M5" type="Precipitant" span="114 5" str="meals" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M4" precipitant="M5"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9059" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The maximum recommended total daily dose is 40 mg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9060" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Some patients may be effectively controlled on a once-a-day regimen, while others show better response with divided dosing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9061" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Total daily doses above 15 mg should ordinarily be divided.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9062" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Total daily doses above 30 mg have been safely given on a b.i.d. basis to long-term patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9063" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In elderly patients, debilitated or malnourished patients, and patients with impaired renal or hepatic function, the initial and maintenance dosing should be conservative to avoid hypoglycemic reactions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9064" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>As with other sulfonylurea-class hypoglycemics, many stable non-insulin-dependent diabetic patients receiving insulin may be safely placed on GLUCOTROL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9065" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>When transferring patients from insulin to GLUCOTROL, the following general guidelines should be considered: For patients whose daily insulin requirement is 20 units or less, insulin may be discontinued and GLUCOTROL therapy may begin at usual dosages.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M6" type="Trigger" span="190 12" str="discontinued"/>
<Mention id="M7" type="Precipitant" span="32 7" str="insulin" code="N0000004931 | N0000175944"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M6" precipitant="M7"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9066" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Several days should elapse between GLUCOTROL titration steps.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9067" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For patients whose daily insulin requirement is greater than 20 units, the insulin dose should be reduced by 50% and GLUCOTROL therapy may begin at usual dosages.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M8" type="Trigger" span="83 4;98 7" str="dose | reduced"/>
<Mention id="M9" type="Precipitant" span="25 7" str="insulin" code="N0000004931 | N0000175944"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M8" precipitant="M9"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9068" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Subsequent reductions in insulin dosage should depend on individual patient response.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M10" type="Trigger" span="11 10;33 6" str="reductions | dosage"/>
<Mention id="M11" type="Precipitant" span="25 7" str="insulin" code="N0000004931 | N0000175944"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M10" precipitant="M11"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9069" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>During the insulin withdrawal period, the patient should test urine samples for sugar and ketone bodies at least three times daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9070" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Patients should be instructed to contact the prescriber immediately if these tests are abnormal.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9071" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In some cases, especially when patient has been receiving greater than 40 units of insulin daily, it may be advisable to consider hospitalization during the transition period.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9072" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>As with other sulfonylurea-class hypoglycemics, no transition period is necessary when transferring patients to GLUCOTROL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9073" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Patients should be observed carefully (1–2 weeks) for hypoglycemia when being transferred from longer half-life sulfonylureas (e.g., chlorpropamide) to GLUCOTROL due to potential overlapping of drug effect.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M16" type="Trigger" span="9 18" str="should be observed "/>
<Mention id="M17" type="Trigger" span="179 11;199 6" str=" overlapping | effect"/>
<Mention id="M14" type="Precipitant" span="133 14" str="chlorpropamide" code="WTM2C3IL2X"/>
<Mention id="M19" type="SpecificInteraction" span="54 12" str="hypoglycemia" code="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M18" type="Precipitant" span="95 30" str="longer half-life sulfonylureas" code="N0000175608"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M16;M17" precipitant="M14" effect="M19" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M16;M17" precipitant="M18" effect="M19" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9074" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>When colesevelam is coadministered with glipizide ER, maximum plasma concentration and total exposure to glipizide is reduced.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M20" type="Trigger" span="93 8;118 7" str="exposure | reduced"/>
<Mention id="M23" type="Precipitant" span="5 11" str="colesevelam" code="1XU104G55N"/>
<Mention id="M22" type="Trigger" span="54 28;118 7" str="maximum plasma concentration | reduced"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M20" precipitant="M23" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M22" precipitant="M23" effect="C54606"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9075" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Therefore, GLUCOTROL should be administered at least 4 hours prior to colesevelam.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M24" type="Trigger" span="21 22;61 8" str="should be administered | prior to"/>
<Mention id="M25" type="Precipitant" span="70 11" str="colesevelam" code="1XU104G55N"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M24" precipitant="M25"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9076" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The hypoglycemic action of sulfonylureas may be potentiated by certain drugs including nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory agents, some azoles, and other drugs that are highly protein bound, salicylates, sulfonamides, chloramphenicol, probenecid, coumarins, monoamine oxidase inhibitors, quinolones and beta adrenergic blocking agents.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M56" type="Trigger" span="48 11" str="potentiated"/>
<Mention id="M27" type="Precipitant" span="131 6" str="azoles" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M58" type="SpecificInteraction" span="4 19" str="hypoglycemic action" code="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M30" type="Precipitant" span="298 31" str="beta adrenergic blocking agents" code="N0000000161 | N0000175556"/>
<Mention id="M33" type="Precipitant" span="213 15" str="chloramphenicol" code="66974FR9Q1"/>
<Mention id="M36" type="Precipitant" span="242 9" str="coumarins" code="A4VZ22K1WT"/>
<Mention id="M39" type="Precipitant" span="149 35" str="drugs that are highly protein bound" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M42" type="Precipitant" span="253 28" str="monoamine oxidase inhibitors" code="N0000000184 | N0000175744"/>
<Mention id="M45" type="Precipitant" span="87 37" str="nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory agents" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M48" type="Precipitant" span="230 10" str="probenecid" code="PO572Z7917"/>
<Mention id="M51" type="Precipitant" span="283 10" str="quinolones" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M54" type="Precipitant" span="186 11" str="salicylates" code="N0000006035 | O414PZ4LPZ"/>
<Mention id="M57" type="Precipitant" span="199 12" str="sulfonamides" code="N0000175880"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M56" precipitant="M27" effect="M58" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M56" precipitant="M30" effect="M58" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M56" precipitant="M33" effect="M58" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M56" precipitant="M36" effect="M58" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M56" precipitant="M39" effect="M58" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M56" precipitant="M42" effect="M58" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M56" precipitant="M45" effect="M58" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M56" precipitant="M48" effect="M58" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M56" precipitant="M51" effect="M58" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M56" precipitant="M54" effect="M58" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M56" precipitant="M57" effect="M58" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9077" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>When such drugs are administered to a patient receiving GLUCOTROL, the patient should be observed closely for hypoglycemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9078" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>When such drugs are withdrawn from a patient receiving GLUCOTROL, the patient should be observed closely for loss of control.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9079" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>In vitro binding studies with human serum proteins indicate that GLUCOTROL binds differently than tolbutamide and does not interact with salicylate or dicumarol.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9080" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>However, caution must be exercised in extrapolating these findings to the clinical situation and in the use of GLUCOTROL with these drugs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9081" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Certain drugs tend to produce hyperglycemia and may lead to loss of control.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9082" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>These drugs include the thiazides and other diuretics, corticosteroids, phenothiazines, thyroid products, estrogens, oral contraceptives, phenytoin, nicotinic acid, sympathomimetics, calcium channel blocking drugs, and isoniazid.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9083" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>When such drugs are administered to a patient receiving GLUCOTROL, the patient should be closely observed for loss of control.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9084" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>When such drugs are withdrawn from a patient receiving GLUCOTROL, the patient should be observed closely for hypoglycemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9085" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>A potential interaction between oral miconazole and oral hypoglycemic agents leading to severe hypoglycemia has been reported.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M59" type="Trigger" span="12 11" str="interaction "/>
<Mention id="M60" type="Trigger" span="77 10" str=" leading to"/>
<Mention id="M61" type="Precipitant" span="32 15" str="oral miconazole" code="7NNO0D7S5M"/>
<Mention id="M62" type="SpecificInteraction" span="88 19" str="severe hypoglycemia" code="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M59;M60" precipitant="M61" effect="M62" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9086" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Whether this interaction also occurs with the intravenous, topical, or vaginal preparations of miconazole is not known.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9087" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The effect of concomitant administration of DIFLUCAN® (fluconazole) and GLUCOTROL has been demonstrated in a placebo-controlled crossover study in normal volunteers.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M65" type="Trigger" span="4 6;91 12" str="effect | demonstrated"/>
<Mention id="M64" type="Precipitant" span="44 8" str="DIFLUCAN" code="8VZV102JFY"/>
<Mention id="M66" type="Precipitant" span="55 11" str="fluconazole" code="N0000006331 | 8VZV102JFY"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M65" precipitant="M64"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M65" precipitant="M66"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9088" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>All subjects received GLUCOTROL alone and following treatment with 100 mg of DIFLUCAN as a single daily oral dose for 7 days.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9089" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The mean percentage increase in the GLUCOTROL AUC after fluconazole administration was 56.9% (range: 35 to 81).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M67" type="Trigger" span="20 8;46 3" str="increase | AUC"/>
<Mention id="M68" type="Precipitant" span="56 11" str="fluconazole" code="N0000006331 | 8VZV102JFY"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M67" precipitant="M68" effect="C54605"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9090" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>In studies assessing the effect of colesevelam on the pharmacokinetics of glipizide ER in healthy volunteers, reductions in glipizide AUC0–∞ and Cmax of 12% and 13%, respectively were observed when colesevelam was coadministered with glipizide ER.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M69" type="Trigger" span="110 10;134 3" str="reductions | AUC"/>
<Mention id="M72" type="Precipitant" span="35 11" str="colesevelam" code="1XU104G55N"/>
<Mention id="M71" type="Trigger" span="110 10;145 4" str="reductions | Cmax"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M69" precipitant="M72" effect="C54609"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M71" precipitant="M72" effect="C54606"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9091" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>When glipizide ER was administered 4 hours prior to colesevelam, there was no significant change in glipizide AUC0–∞ or Cmax, -4% and 0%, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9092" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Therefore, GLUCOTROL should be administered at least 4 hours prior to colesevelam to ensure that colesevelam does not reduce the absorption of glipizide.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M73" type="Trigger" span="118 21" str="reduce the absorption"/>
<Mention id="M74" type="Precipitant" span="70 11" str="colesevelam" code="1XU104G55N"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M73" precipitant="M74" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9093" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>There have been no clinical studies establishing conclusive evidence of macrovascular risk reduction with GLUCOTROL or any other anti-diabetic drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9094" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The metabolism and excretion of GLUCOTROL may be slowed in patients with impaired renal and/or hepatic function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9095" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>If hypoglycemia should occur in such patients, it may be prolonged and appropriate management should be instituted.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9096" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>All sulfonylurea drugs are capable of producing severe hypoglycemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9097" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Proper patient selection, dosage, and instructions are important to avoid hypoglycemic episodes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9098" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Renal or hepatic insufficiency may cause elevated blood levels of GLUCOTROL and the latter may also diminish gluconeogenic capacity, both of which increase the risk of serious hypoglycemic reactions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9099" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Elderly, debilitated or malnourished patients, and those with adrenal or pituitary insufficiency, are particularly susceptible to the hypoglycemic action of glucose-lowering drugs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9100" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Hypoglycemia may be difficult to recognize in the elderly, and in people who are taking beta-adrenergic blocking drugs.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M75" type="Trigger" span="63 24" str="in people who are taking"/>
<Mention id="M76" type="Precipitant" span="88 30" str="beta-adrenergic blocking drugs" code="N0000000161"/>
<Mention id="M77" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 12" str="hypoglycemia" code="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I29" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M75" precipitant="M76" effect="M77" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9101" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Hypoglycemia is more likely to occur when caloric intake is deficient, after severe or prolonged exercise, when alcohol is ingested, or when more than one glucose-lowering drug is used.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M81" type="Trigger" span="16 20" str="more likely to occur"/>
<Mention id="M79" type="Precipitant" span="112 7" str="alcohol" code="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M"/>
<Mention id="M83" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 12" str="hypoglycemia" code="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M82" type="Precipitant" span="155 21" str="glucose-lowering drug" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I30" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M81" precipitant="M79" effect="M83" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I31" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M81" precipitant="M82" effect="M83" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9102" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>When a patient stabilized on any diabetic regimen is exposed to stress such as fever, trauma, infection, or surgery, a loss of control may occur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9103" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>At such times, it may be necessary to discontinue GLUCOTROL and administer insulin.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M84" type="Trigger" span="38 11" str="discontinue"/>
<Mention id="M85" type="Precipitant" span="75 7" str="insulin" code="N0000004931 | N0000175944"/>
<Interaction id="I32" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M84" precipitant="M85"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9104" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The effectiveness of any oral hypoglycemic drug, including GLUCOTROL, in lowering blood glucose to a desired level decreases in many patients over a period of time, which may be due to progression of the severity of the diabetes or to diminished responsiveness to the drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9105" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>This phenomenon is known as secondary failure, to distinguish it from primary failure in which the drug is ineffective in an individual patient when first given.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9106" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Treatment of patients with glucose 6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PD) deficiency with sulfonylurea agents can lead to hemolytic anemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9107" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because GLUCOTROL belongs to the class of sulfonylurea agents, caution should be used in patients with G6PD deficiency and a non-sulfonylurea alternative should be considered.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9108" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In post-marketing reports, hemolytic anemia has also been reported in patients who did not have known G6PD deficiency.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9109" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Blood and urine glucose should be monitored periodically.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9110" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Measurement of glycosylated hemoglobin may be useful.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9111" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Patients should be informed of the potential risks and advantages of GLUCOTROL and of alternative modes of therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9112" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>They should also be informed about the importance of adhering to dietary instructions, of a regular exercise program, and of regular testing of urine and/or blood glucose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9113" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The risks of hypoglycemia, its symptoms and treatment, and conditions that predispose to its development should be explained to patients and responsible family members.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9114" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Primary and secondary failure should also be explained.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9115" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In initiating treatment for type 2 diabetes, diet should be emphasized as the primary form of treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9116" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Caloric restriction and weight loss are essential in the obese diabetic patient.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9117" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Proper dietary management alone may be effective in controlling the blood glucose and symptoms of hyperglycemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9118" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The importance of regular physical activity should also be stressed, and cardiovascular risk factors should be identified and corrective measures taken where possible.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9119" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Use of GLUCOTROL or other antidiabetic medications must be viewed by both the physician and patient as a treatment in addition to diet and not as a substitution or as a convenient mechanism for avoiding dietary restraint.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9120" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Furthermore, loss of blood glucose control on diet alone may be transient, thus requiring only short-term administration of GLUCOTROL or other antidiabetic medications.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9121" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Maintenance or discontinuation of GLUCOTROL or other antidiabetic medications should be based on clinical judgment using regular clinical and laboratory evaluations.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M86" type="Trigger" span="15 15" str="discontinuation"/>
<Mention id="M87" type="Precipitant" span="53 24" str="antidiabetic medications" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I33" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M86" precipitant="M87"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9122" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>A twenty month study in rats and an eighteen month study in mice at doses up to 75 times the maximum human dose revealed no evidence of drug-related carcinogenicity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9123" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Bacterial and in vivo mutagenicity tests were uniformly negative.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9124" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Studies in rats of both sexes at doses up to 75 times the human dose showed no effects on fertility.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9125" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>GLUCOTROL (glipizide) was found to be mildly fetotoxic in rat reproductive studies at all dose levels (5–50 mg/kg).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9126" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>This fetotoxicity has been similarly noted with other sulfonylureas, such as tolbutamide and tolazamide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9127" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The effect is perinatal and believed to be directly related to the pharmacologic (hypoglycemic) action of GLUCOTROL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9128" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In studies in rats and rabbits, no teratogenic effects were found.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9129" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>There are no adequate and well controlled studies in pregnant women.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9130" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>GLUCOTROL should be used during pregnancy only if the potential benefit justifies the potential risk to the fetus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9131" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because recent information suggests that abnormal blood glucose levels during pregnancy are associated with a higher incidence of congenital abnormalities, many experts recommend that insulin be used during pregnancy to maintain blood glucose levels as close to normal as possible.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9132" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Prolonged severe hypoglycemia (4 to 10 days) has been reported in neonates born to mothers who were receiving a sulfonylurea drug at the time of delivery.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9133" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>This has been reported more frequently with the use of agents with prolonged half-lives.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9134" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>If GLUCOTROL is used during pregnancy, it should be discontinued at least one month before the expected delivery date.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9135" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Although it is not known whether GLUCOTROL is excreted in human milk, some sulfonylurea drugs are known to be excreted in human milk.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9136" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because the potential for hypoglycemia in nursing infants may exist, a decision should be made whether to discontinue nursing or to discontinue the drug, taking into account the importance of the drug to the mother.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9137" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>If the drug is discontinued and if diet alone is inadequate for controlling blood glucose, insulin therapy should be considered.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9138" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Safety and effectiveness in children have not been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9139" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>A determination has not been made whether controlled clinical studies of GLUCOTROL included sufficient numbers of subjects aged 65 and over to define a difference in response from younger subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9140" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Other reported clinical experience has not identified differences in responses between the elderly and younger patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9141" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In general, dose selection for an elderly patient should be cautious, usually starting at the low end of the dosing range, reflecting the greater frequency of decreased hepatic, renal, or cardiac function, and of concomitant disease or other drug therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9142" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The administration of oral hypoglycemic drugs has been reported to be associated with increased cardiovascular mortality as compared to treatment with diet alone or diet plus insulin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9143" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>This warning is based on the study conducted by the University Group Diabetes Program (UGDP), a long-term prospective clinical trial designed to evaluate the effectiveness of glucose-lowering drugs in preventing or delaying vascular complications in patients with non-insulin-dependent diabetes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9144" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The study involved 823 patients who were randomly assigned to one of four treatment groups (Diabetes, 19, supp.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9145" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>UGDP reported that patients treated for 5 to 8 years with diet plus a fixed dose of tolbutamide (1.5 grams per day) had a rate of cardiovascular mortality approximately 2½ times that of patients treated with diet alone.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9146" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>A significant increase in total mortality was not observed, but the use of tolbutamide was discontinued based on the increase in cardiovascular mortality, thus limiting the opportunity for the study to show an increase in overall mortality.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9147" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Despite controversy regarding the interpretation of these results, the findings of the UGDP study provide an adequate basis for this warning.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9148" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The patient should be informed of the potential risks and advantages of GLUCOTROL and of alternative modes of therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9149" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Although only one drug in the sulfonylurea class (tolbutamide) was included in this study, it is prudent from a safety standpoint to consider that this warning may also apply to other oral hypoglycemic drugs in this class, in view of their close similarities in mode of action and chemical structure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9150" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The primary mode of action of GLUCOTROL in experimental animals appears to be the stimulation of insulin secretion from the beta cells of pancreatic islet tissue and is thus dependent on functioning beta cells in the pancreatic islets.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9151" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In humans, GLUCOTROL appears to lower the blood glucose acutely by stimulating the release of insulin from the pancreas, an effect dependent upon functioning beta cells in the pancreatic islets.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9152" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mechanism by which GLUCOTROL lowers blood glucose during long-term administration has not been clearly established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9153" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In man, stimulation of insulin secretion by GLUCOTROL in response to a meal is undoubtedly of major importance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9154" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Fasting insulin levels are not elevated even on long-term GLUCOTROL administration, but the postprandial insulin response continues to be enhanced after at least 6 months of treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9155" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The insulinotropic response to a meal occurs within 30 minutes after an oral dose of GLUCOTROL in diabetic patients, but elevated insulin levels do not persist beyond the time of the meal challenge.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9156" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Extrapancreatic effects may play a part in the mechanism of action of oral sulfonylurea hypoglycemic drugs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9157" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Blood sugar control persists in some patients for up to 24 hours after a single dose of GLUCOTROL, even though plasma levels have declined to a small fraction of peak levels by that time.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9158" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Some patients fail to respond initially, or gradually lose their responsiveness to sulfonylurea drugs, including GLUCOTROL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9159" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Alternatively, GLUCOTROL may be effective in some patients who have not responded or have ceased to respond to other sulfonylureas.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9160" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>It has been shown that GLUCOTROL therapy was effective in controlling blood sugar without deleterious changes in the plasma lipoprotein profiles of patients treated for NIDDM.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9161" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In a placebo-controlled, crossover study in normal volunteers, GLUCOTROL had no antidiuretic activity and, in fact, led to a slight increase in free water clearance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9162" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Gastrointestinal absorption of GLUCOTROL in man is uniform, rapid, and essentially complete.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9163" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Peak plasma concentrations occur 1–3 hours after a single oral dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9164" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The half-life of elimination ranges from 2–4 hours in normal subjects, whether given intravenously or orally.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9165" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The metabolic and excretory patterns are similar with the two routes of administration, indicating that first-pass metabolism is not significant.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9166" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>GLUCOTROL does not accumulate in plasma on repeated oral administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9167" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Total absorption and disposition of an oral dose was unaffected by food in normal volunteers, but absorption was delayed by about 40 minutes.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M88" type="Trigger" span="98 22" str="absorption was delayed"/>
<Mention id="M89" type="Precipitant" span="67 4" str="food" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I34" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M88" precipitant="M89" effect="C54604"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9168" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Thus, GLUCOTROL was more effective when administered about 30 minutes before, rather than with, a test meal in diabetic patients.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M90" type="Trigger" span="20 14;70 6" str="more effective | before"/>
<Mention id="M91" type="Precipitant" span="103 4" str="meal" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I35" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M90" precipitant="M91"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9169" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Protein binding was studied in serum from volunteers who received either oral or intravenous GLUCOTROL and found to be 98–99% one hour after either route of administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9170" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The apparent volume of distribution of GLUCOTROL after intravenous administration was 11 liters, indicative of localization within the extracellular fluid compartment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9171" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In mice, no GLUCOTROL or metabolites were detectable autoradiographically in the brain or spinal cord of males or females, nor in the fetuses of pregnant females.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9172" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In another study, however, very small amounts of radioactivity were detected in the fetuses of rats given labelled drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9173" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The metabolism of GLUCOTROL is extensive and occurs mainly in the liver.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9174" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The primary metabolites are inactive hydroxylation products and polar conjugates and are excreted mainly in the urine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9175" LabelDrug="Glucotrol" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Less than 10% unchanged GLUCOTROL is found in the urine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="meal" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="meal" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="meals" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="insulin" precipitantCode="N0000004931 | N0000175944"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="chlorpropamide" precipitantCode="WTM2C3IL2X" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="longer half-life sulfonylureas" precipitantCode="N0000175608" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="colesevelam" precipitantCode="1XU104G55N" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="colesevelam" precipitantCode="1XU104G55N" effect="C54606"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="colesevelam" precipitantCode="1XU104G55N" effect="C54609"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="colesevelam" precipitantCode="1XU104G55N"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="azoles" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="beta adrenergic blocking agents" precipitantCode="N0000000161 | N0000175556" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="chloramphenicol" precipitantCode="66974FR9Q1" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="coumarins" precipitantCode="A4VZ22K1WT" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="drugs that are highly protein bound" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="monoamine oxidase inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000000184 | N0000175744" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory agents" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="probenecid" precipitantCode="PO572Z7917" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="quinolones" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="salicylates" precipitantCode="N0000006035 | O414PZ4LPZ" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sulfonamides" precipitantCode="N0000175880" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="oral miconazole" precipitantCode="7NNO0D7S5M" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="diflucan" precipitantCode="8VZV102JFY"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="fluconazole" precipitantCode="N0000006331 | 8VZV102JFY" effect="C54605"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="fluconazole" precipitantCode="N0000006331 | 8VZV102JFY"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="beta-adrenergic blocking drugs" precipitantCode="N0000000161" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="alcohol" precipitantCode="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="glucose-lowering drug" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="antidiabetic medications" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="food" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54604"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>