<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Dimenhydrinate" setid="bc71539e-1a33-4709-8a24-c2894e8dbc1c">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
Neonates and patients with a history of hypersensitivity to dimenhydrinate or its components (diphenhydramine or 8-chlorotheophylline) should not be treated with dimenhydrinate. Note: This product contains Benzyl Alcohol.  Benzyl Alcohol has been associated with a fatal “Gasping Syndrome” in premature infants and infants of low birth weight.</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
Dimenhydrinate in the injectable form is indicated when the oral form is impractical. Nausea or vomiting may be expected to be controlled for approximately 4 hours with 50 mg, and prevented by a similar dose every 4 hours.  Its administration may be attended by some degree of drowsiness in some patients, and 100 mg every 4 hours may be given in conditions in which drowsiness is not objectionable or is even desirable. For intramuscular administration, each milliliter (50 mg) of solution is injected as needed, but for intravenous administration, each milliliter (50 mg) of solution must be diluted in 10 mL of 0.9% Sodium Chloride Injection, USP and injected over a period of 2 minutes. For intramuscular administration, 1.25 mg/kg of body weight or 37.5 mg/m 2 of body surface area is administered four times daily.  The maximum dose should not exceed 300 mg daily (see CONTRAINDICATIONS ). Parenteral drug products should be inspected visually for particulate matter and discoloration prior to administration, whenever solution and container permit. Nausea or vomiting may be expected to be controlled for approximately 4 hours with 50 mg, and prevented by a similar dose every 4 hours.  Its administration may be attended by some degree of drowsiness in some patients, and 100 mg every 4 hours may be given in conditions in which drowsiness is not objectionable or is even desirable. For intramuscular administration, each milliliter (50 mg) of solution is injected as needed, but for intravenous administration, each milliliter (50 mg) of solution must be diluted in 10 mL of 0.9% Sodium Chloride Injection, USP and injected over a period of 2 minutes. For intramuscular administration, 1.25 mg/kg of body weight or 37.5 mg/m 2 of body surface area is administered four times daily.  The maximum dose should not exceed 300 mg daily (see CONTRAINDICATIONS ). Parenteral drug products should be inspected visually for particulate matter and discoloration prior to administration, whenever solution and container permit.</Section>
<Section name="PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="42232-9">
Drowsiness may be experienced by some patients, especially with high dosage.  This effect frequently is not undesirable in conditions for which the drug is used. Because of the potential for drowsiness, patients taking dimenhydrinate should be cautioned against operating automobiles or dangerous machinery (see WARNINGS ). Mutagenicity screening tests performed with dimenhydrinate, diphenhydramine, and 8-chlorotheophylline produced positive results in the bacterial systems and negative results in the mammalian systems.  There are no human data that indicate dimenhydrinate is a carcinogen or mutagen or that it impairs fertility. Pregnancy Category B. Reproduction studies have been performed in rats at doses up to 20 times the human dose, and in rabbits at doses up to 25 times the human dose (on a mg/kg basis), and have revealed no evidence of impaired fertility or harm to the fetus due to dimenhydrinate. There are no adequate and well-controlled studies in pregnant women.  However, clinical studies in pregnant women have not indicated that dimenhydrinate increases the risk of abnormalities when administered in any trimester of pregnancy.  It would appear that the possibility of fetal harm is remote when the drug is used during pregnancy.  Nevertheless, because the studies in humans cannot rule out the possibility of harm, dimenhydrinate should be used during pregnancy only if clearly needed. The safety of dimenhydrinate given during labor and delivery has not been established. Reports have indicated dimenhydrinate may have an oxytocic effect.  Caution is advised when this effect is unwanted or in situations where it may prove detrimental. Small amounts of dimenhydrinate are excreted in breast milk.  Because of the potential for adverse reactions in nursing infants from dimenhydrinate, a decision should be made whether to discontinue nursing or to discontinue the drug, taking into account the importance of the drug to the mother. Drowsiness may be experienced by some patients, especially with high dosage.  This effect frequently is not undesirable in conditions for which the drug is used. Because of the potential for drowsiness, patients taking dimenhydrinate should be cautioned against operating automobiles or dangerous machinery (see WARNINGS ). Mutagenicity screening tests performed with dimenhydrinate, diphenhydramine, and 8-chlorotheophylline produced positive results in the bacterial systems and negative results in the mammalian systems.  There are no human data that indicate dimenhydrinate is a carcinogen or mutagen or that it impairs fertility. The safety of dimenhydrinate given during labor and delivery has not been established. Reports have indicated dimenhydrinate may have an oxytocic effect.  Caution is advised when this effect is unwanted or in situations where it may prove detrimental. Small amounts of dimenhydrinate are excreted in breast milk.  Because of the potential for adverse reactions in nursing infants from dimenhydrinate, a decision should be made whether to discontinue nursing or to discontinue the drug, taking into account the importance of the drug to the mother.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS SECTION" id="34071-1">
Caution should be used when dimenhydrinate is given in conjunction with certain antibiotics that may cause ototoxicity, since dimenhydrinate is capable of masking ototoxic symptoms, and an irreversible state may be reached. This drug may impair the mental and/or physical abilities required for the performance of potentially hazardous tasks, such as driving a vehicle or operating machinery.  The concomitant use of alcohol or other central nervous system depressants may have an additive effect. Therefore, patients should be warned accordingly. Dimenhydrinate should be used with caution in patients having conditions which might be aggravated by anticholinergic therapy (i.e., prostatic hypertrophy, stenosing peptic ulcer, pyloroduodenal obstruction, bladder neck obstruction, narrow-angle glaucoma, bronchial asthma, or cardiac arrhythmias). The preparation should not be injected intra-arterially. For infants and children especially, antihistamines in overdosage may cause hallucinations, convulsions, or death. As in adults, antihistamines may diminish mental alertness in pediatric patients.  In the young child, particularly, they may produce excitation (see CONTRAINDICATIONS ). For infants and children especially, antihistamines in overdosage may cause hallucinations, convulsions, or death. As in adults, antihistamines may diminish mental alertness in pediatric patients.  In the young child, particularly, they may produce excitation (see CONTRAINDICATIONS ).</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
While the precise mode of action of dimenhydrinate is not known, it has a depressant action on hyperstimulated labyrinthine function.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="1539" LabelDrug="Dimenhydrinate" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Neonates and patients with a history of hypersensitivity to dimenhydrinate or its components (diphenhydramine or 8-chlorotheophylline) should not be treated with dimenhydrinate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1540" LabelDrug="Dimenhydrinate" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Note: This product contains Benzyl Alcohol.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1541" LabelDrug="Dimenhydrinate" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Benzyl Alcohol has been associated with a fatal “Gasping Syndrome” in premature infants and infants of low birth weight.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1542" LabelDrug="Dimenhydrinate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dimenhydrinate in the injectable form is indicated when the oral form is impractical.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1543" LabelDrug="Dimenhydrinate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Nausea or vomiting may be expected to be controlled for approximately 4 hours with 50 mg, and prevented by a similar dose every 4 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1544" LabelDrug="Dimenhydrinate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Its administration may be attended by some degree of drowsiness in some patients, and 100 mg every 4 hours may be given in conditions in which drowsiness is not objectionable or is even desirable.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1545" LabelDrug="Dimenhydrinate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For intramuscular administration, each milliliter (50 mg) of solution is injected as needed, but for intravenous administration, each milliliter (50 mg) of solution must be diluted in 10 mL of 0.9% Sodium Chloride Injection, USP and injected over a period of 2 minutes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1546" LabelDrug="Dimenhydrinate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For intramuscular administration, 1.25 mg/kg of body weight or 37.5 mg/m2 of body surface area is administered four times daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1547" LabelDrug="Dimenhydrinate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The maximum dose should not exceed 300 mg daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1548" LabelDrug="Dimenhydrinate" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Parenteral drug products should be inspected visually for particulate matter and discoloration prior to administration, whenever solution and container permit.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1549" LabelDrug="Dimenhydrinate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Drowsiness may be experienced by some patients, especially with high dosage.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1550" LabelDrug="Dimenhydrinate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>This effect frequently is not undesirable in conditions for which the drug is used.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1551" LabelDrug="Dimenhydrinate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because of the potential for drowsiness, patients taking dimenhydrinate should be cautioned against operating automobiles or dangerous machinery.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1552" LabelDrug="Dimenhydrinate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Mutagenicity screening tests performed with dimenhydrinate, diphenhydramine, and 8-chlorotheophylline produced positive results in the bacterial systems and negative results in the mammalian systems.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1553" LabelDrug="Dimenhydrinate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>There are no human data that indicate dimenhydrinate is a carcinogen or mutagen or that it impairs fertility.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1554" LabelDrug="Dimenhydrinate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Pregnancy Category B. Reproduction studies have been performed in rats at doses up to 20 times the human dose, and in rabbits at doses up to 25 times the human dose (on a mg/kg basis), and have revealed no evidence of impaired fertility or harm to the fetus due to dimenhydrinate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1555" LabelDrug="Dimenhydrinate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>There are no adequate and well-controlled studies in pregnant women.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1556" LabelDrug="Dimenhydrinate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>However, clinical studies in pregnant women have not indicated that dimenhydrinate increases the risk of abnormalities when administered in any trimester of pregnancy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1557" LabelDrug="Dimenhydrinate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>It would appear that the possibility of fetal harm is remote when the drug is used during pregnancy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1558" LabelDrug="Dimenhydrinate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Nevertheless, because the studies in humans cannot rule out the possibility of harm, dimenhydrinate should be used during pregnancy only if clearly needed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1559" LabelDrug="Dimenhydrinate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The safety of dimenhydrinate given during labor and delivery has not been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1560" LabelDrug="Dimenhydrinate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Reports have indicated dimenhydrinate may have an oxytocic effect.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1561" LabelDrug="Dimenhydrinate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Caution is advised when this effect is unwanted or in situations where it may prove detrimental.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1562" LabelDrug="Dimenhydrinate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Small amounts of dimenhydrinate are excreted in breast milk.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1563" LabelDrug="Dimenhydrinate" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because of the potential for adverse reactions in nursing infants from dimenhydrinate, a decision should be made whether to discontinue nursing or to discontinue the drug, taking into account the importance of the drug to the mother.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1564" LabelDrug="Dimenhydrinate" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Caution should be used when dimenhydrinate is given in conjunction with certain antibiotics that may cause ototoxicity, since dimenhydrinate is capable of masking ototoxic symptoms, and an irreversible state may be reached.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1565" LabelDrug="Dimenhydrinate" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>This drug may impair the mental and/or physical abilities required for the performance of potentially hazardous tasks, such as driving a vehicle or operating machinery.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1566" LabelDrug="Dimenhydrinate" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The concomitant use of alcohol or other central nervous system depressants may have an additive effect.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M4" type="Trigger" span="87 15" str="additive effect"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="23 7" str="alcohol" code="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M"/>
<Mention id="M3" type="SpecificInteraction" span="23 7;87 15" str="alcohol | additive effect" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M5" type="Precipitant" span="40 34" str="central nervous system depressants" code="N0000175758"/>
<Mention id="M6" type="SpecificInteraction" span="40 34;87 15" str="central nervous system depressants | additive effect" code="418072004: Central nervous system depression (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M4" precipitant="M2" effect="M3" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M4" precipitant="M5" effect="M6" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1567" LabelDrug="Dimenhydrinate" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Therefore, patients should be warned accordingly.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1568" LabelDrug="Dimenhydrinate" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Dimenhydrinate should be used with caution in patients having conditions which might be aggravated by anticholinergic therapy (i.e., prostatic hypertrophy, stenosing peptic ulcer, pyloroduodenal obstruction, bladder neck obstruction, narrow-angle glaucoma, bronchial asthma, or cardiac arrhythmias).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1569" LabelDrug="Dimenhydrinate" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The preparation should not be injected intra-arterially.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1570" LabelDrug="Dimenhydrinate" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>For infants and children especially, antihistamines in overdosage may cause hallucinations, convulsions, or death.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1571" LabelDrug="Dimenhydrinate" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>As in adults, antihistamines may diminish mental alertness in pediatric patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1572" LabelDrug="Dimenhydrinate" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>In the young child, particularly, they may produce excitation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1573" LabelDrug="Dimenhydrinate" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>While the precise mode of action of dimenhydrinate is not known, it has a depressant action on hyperstimulated labyrinthine function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="alcohol" precipitantCode="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="central nervous system depressants" precipitantCode="N0000175758" effect="418072004: Central nervous system depression (disorder)"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>