<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Levoleucovorin" setid="bfc8bd60-d228-45a0-93fa-2166d1324c77">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
Levoleucovorin is contraindicated in patients who have had severe hypersensitivity to leucovorin products, folic acid, or folinic acid  [see Adverse Reactions ( 6.2 )] . Patients who have had severe hypersensitivity reactions to leucovorin products, folic acid, or folinic acid. ( 4 )</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
For intravenous administration only. Do not administer intrathecally. ( 2.1 ) Administer intravenously at a rate of less than 16 mL per minute. ( 2.1 , 5.1 ) Rescue After High-Dose Methotrexate Therapy Rescue recommendations are based on a methotrexate dose of 12 grams/m 2 administered by intravenous infusion over 4 hours. Initiate rescue at 7.5 mg (approximately 5 mg/m 2 ) every 6 hours, 24 hours after beginning methotrexate infusion. ( 2.2 ) Continue until methotrexate level is below 5 x 10 -8 M (0.05 micromolar). Adjust dose if necessary based on methotrexate elimination; refer to Full Prescribing Information. ( 2.2 ) Methotrexate Overdosage or Impaired Methotrexate Elimination Start as soon as possible after methotrexate overdosage, or within 24 hours of delayed methotrexate elimination. ( 2.3 )   Administer Levoleucovorin for injection 7.5 mg (approximately 5 mg/m 2 ) intravenously every 6 hours until methotrexate level is less than 10 -8 M (0.05 micromolar). ( 2.3 ) Levoleucovorin for injection is indicated for intravenous administration only.  Do not administer intrathecally. Administer intravenously at a rate less than 16 mL (160 mg of levoleucovorin) per minute [see Warnings and Precautions ( 5.1 )] . The recommendations for Levoleucovorin for injection rescue are based on a methotrexate dose of 12 grams/m 2 administered by intravenous infusion over 4 hours (refer to methotrexate prescribing information that includes high-dose methotrexate regimens) in adult and pediatric patients. Twenty-four hours after starting the methotrexate infusion, initiate Levoleucovorin for injection rescue at a dose of 7.5 mg (approximately 5 mg/m 2 ) every 6 hours.  Monitor serum creatinine and methotrexate levels at least once daily. Continue Levoleucovorin for injection administration, hydration, and urinary alkalinization (pH 7.0 or greater) until the methotrexate level is below 5 x 10 -8 M (0.05 micromolar). Adjust dosage or extend duration based on the guidelines in Table 1. Table 1 Guidelines for Levoleucovorin for Injection Dosage and Administration Clinical Situation Laboratory Findings Recommendation Normal methotrexate elimination Serum methotrexate level approximately    10 micromolar at 24 hours after administration, 1 micromolar at 48 hours, and less than 0.2 micromolar at 72 hours.  Administer 7.5 mg by intravenous infusion every          6 hours for 60 hours (10 doses starting 24 hours after start of methotrexate infusion). Delayed late methotrexate elimination Serum methotrexate level remaining above 0.2 micromolar at 72 hours, and more than 0.05 micromolar at 96 hours after administration. Continue 7.5 mg by intravenous infusion every 6 hours, until methotrexate level is less than 0.05 micromolar. Delayed early methotrexate elimination and/or evidence of acute renal injury*  Serum methotrexate level of 50 micromolar or more at 24 hours, or 5 micromolar or more at 48 hours after administration, OR 100% or greater increase in serum creatinine level at 24 hours after methotrexate administration (e.g., an increase from 0.5 mg/dL to a level of 1 mg/dL or more).   Administer 75 mg by intravenous infusion every 3 hours until methotrexate level is less than 1 micromolar; then   7.5 mg by intravenous infusion every 3 hours until methotrexate level is less than 0.05 micromolar. * These patients are likely to develop reversible renal failure.  In addition to appropriate levoleucovorin for injection therapy, continue hydration and urinary alkalinization, and monitoring of fluid and electrolyte status, until the serum methotrexate level has fallen to below 0.05 micromolar and the renal failure has resolved. Impaired Methotrexate Elimination or Renal Impairment Decreased methotrexate elimination or renal impairment which are clinically important but less severe than abnormalities described in Table 1 can occur following methotrexate administration.  If toxicity is observed, extend Levoleucovorin for injection rescue for an additional 24 hours (total of 14 doses over 84 hours) in subsequent courses. Third - Space Fluid Collection and Other Causes of Delayed Methotrexate E limination Accumulation in a third-space fluid collection (i.e., ascites, pleural effusion), renal insufficiency, or inadequate hydration can cause delayed methotrexate elimination. Under such circumstances, higher doses of Levoleucovorin for injection or prolonged administration may be indicated. Start Levoleucovorin for injection rescue in adult and pediatric patients as soon as possible after an overdosage of methotrexate or within 24 hours of methotrexate administration when there is impaired methotrexate elimination. As the time interval between methotrexate administration and Levoleucovorin for injection rescue increases, effectiveness of Levoleucovorin for injection in diminishing toxicity may decrease. Administer Levoleucovorin for injection 7.5 mg (approximately 5 mg/m 2 ) intravenously every 6 hours until the serum methotrexate level is less than 10 -8 M (0.05 micromolar).   Monitor serum creatinine and methotrexate levels at least every 24 hours. If 24-hour serum creatinine has increased 50% over baseline or if the 24-hour methotrexate level is greater than 5 x 10 -6 M or 48-hour level is greater than 9 x 10 -7 M, increase the dose of Levoleucovorin for injection to 50 mg/m 2 intravenously every 3 hours until the methotrexate level is less than 10 -8 M. Continue concomitant hydration (3 L per day) and urinary alkalinization with sodium bicarbonate. Adjust the bicarbonate dose to maintain urine pH at 7.0 or greater. Preparation Reconstitute vial contents with 17.7 mL of 0.9% Sodium Chloride Injection, USP, to obtain a clear, colorless to yellowish solution (resultant concentration 10 mg/mL levoleucovorin).  Reconstitution with a sodium chloride solution with preservatives (e.g. benzyl alcohol) has not been studied. Discard vial if particulate matter or discoloration is observed. Dilute reconstituted solution immediately, to concentrations of 0.5 mg/mL to 5 mg/mL in 0.9% Sodium Chloride Injection, USP, or 5% Dextrose Injection, USP. Storage If necessary, store reconstituted solution for not more than 24 hours at room temperature. Do not store reconstituted solution diluted with 0.9% Sodium Chloride Injection, USP, for more than 24 hours at room temperature. Do not store reconstituted solution diluted with 5% Dextrose Injection, USP, for more than 4 hours at room temperature. Administration Inspect reconstituted solution in the vial for particulate matter and discoloration prior to administration.   Do not co-administer with other agents in the same admixture, due to risk of precipitation. Administer intravenously at a rate less than 16 mL (160 mg of levoleucovorin) per minute  [see Warnings and Precautions ( 5.1 )] .</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
Effect of leu co vorin products on fluorouracil : Leucovorin products increase the toxicity of fluorouracil   [see Warnings and Precautions ( 5.2 )] .</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
Hypercalcemia : Limit rate of infusion due to calcium content. ( 2.1 , 2.4 , 5.1 ) Increased gastrointestinal toxicities with fluorouracil ( 5.2 , 7 ) Drug interaction with trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole : Increased rates of treatment failure with concomitant use of d,l -leucovorin with trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole for Pneumocystis jiroveci pneumonia in patients with HIV. ( 5.3 ) Due to the calcium content of the levoleucovorin solution, inject no more than 16 mL (160 mg of levoleucovorin) intravenously per minute  [see Dosage and Administration ( 2.1 and 2.4 )] . Leucovorin products increase the toxicities of fluorouracil  [see Drug Interactions ( 7 )] .  Gastrointestinal toxicities, (particularly stomatitis and diarrhea) occur more commonly, and may be of greater severity and prolonged duration. Deaths from severe enterocolitis, diarrhea, and dehydration have been reported in elderly patients receiving weekly d,l -leucovorin and fluorouracil. Concomitant use of d,l -leucovorin with trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole for the acute treatment of Pneumocystis jiroveci pneumonia in patients with HIV infection was associated with increased rates of treatment failure and morbidity in a placebo-controlled study.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Levoleucovorin is the pharmacologically active isomer of 5-formyl tetrahydrofolic acid (THF). Levoleucovorin does not require reduction by dihydrofolate reductase to participate in reactions utilizing folates as a source of “one-carbon” moieties. Administration of levoleucovorin counteracts the therapeutic and toxic effects of folic acid antagonists such as methotrexate, which act by inhibiting dihydrofolate reductase. In a crossover-design pharmacokinetic comparability study, healthy subjects received a single 2-hour infusion of either levoleucovorin (200 mg/m 2 ) or racemic d,l -leucovorin (400 mg/m 2 ). The 90% confidence intervals for the geometric mean ratios for both AUC 0-inf and C max were within the standard limit of 80-125% for both l -leucovorin and l -5-methyl-THF. The exposure to l -leucovorin and 5-methyl-THF was comparable whether it was administered as levoleucovorin or as d,l -leucovorin as shown in Table 3: Table 3 Geometric Mean Pharmacokinetic Parameters Parameter l -leucovorin d,l -leucovorin 5-methyl-THF- l - leucovorin 5-methyl-THF- d,l -leucovorin AUC 0-inf (ng.h/mL) 30719 31296 52105 50137 C max (ng.h/mL) 10895 11301 4930 4658 Distribution The pharmacokinetics of levoleucovorin after intravenous administration of a 15 mg dose was studied in healthy male volunteers. After rapid intravenous administration, serum total tetrahydrofolate (total-THF) concentrations reached a mean peak of 1722 ng/mL. Serum (6S)-5-methyl-5,6,7,8-tetrahydrofolate concentrations reached a mean peak of 275 ng/mL and the mean time to peak was 0.9 hours. Elimination The mean terminal half-life for total-THF and (6S)-5-methyl-5,6,7,8-tetrahydrofolate was 5.1 and 6.8 hours, respectively.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="5790" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Levoleucovorin is contraindicated in patients who have had severe hypersensitivity to leucovorin products, folic acid, or folinic acid.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5791" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Patients who have had severe hypersensitivity reactions to leucovorin products, folic acid, or folinic acid.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5792" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Administer intravenously at a rate of less than 16 mL per minute.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5793" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Rescue After High-Dose Methotrexate Therapy Rescue recommendations are based on a methotrexate dose of 12 grams/m2 administered by intravenous infusion over 4 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5794" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Initiate rescue at 7.5 mg (approximately 5 mg/m2) every 6 hours, 24 hours after beginning methotrexate infusion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5795" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Continue until methotrexate level is below 5 x 10-8 M (0.05 micromolar).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M1" type="Trigger" span="0 14;28 14" str="Continue until | level is below"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="15 12" str="methotrexate" code="N0000007370 | YL5FZ2Y5U1"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M1" precipitant="M2" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5796" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Adjust dose if necessary based on methotrexate elimination; refer to Full Prescribing Information.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5797" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Methotrexate Overdosage or Impaired Methotrexate Elimination Start as soon as possible after methotrexate overdosage, or within 24 hours of delayed methotrexate elimination.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5798" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Administer Levoleucovorin for injection 7.5 mg (approximately 5 mg/m2) intravenously every 6 hours until methotrexate level is less than 10-8 M (0.05 micromolar).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5799" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Levoleucovorin for injection is indicated for intravenous administration only.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5800" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Administer intravenously at a rate less than 16 mL (160 mg of levoleucovorin) per minute.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5801" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommendations for Levoleucovorin for injection rescue are based on a methotrexate dose of 12 grams/m2 administered by intravenous infusion over 4 hours (refer to methotrexate prescribing information that includes high-dose methotrexate regimens) in adult and pediatric patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5802" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Twenty-four hours after starting the methotrexate infusion, initiate Levoleucovorin for injection rescue at a dose of 7.5 mg (approximately 5 mg/m2) every 6 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5803" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor serum creatinine and methotrexate levels at least once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5804" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Continue Levoleucovorin for injection administration, hydration, and urinary alkalinization (pH 7.0 or greater) until the methotrexate level is below 5 x 10-8 M (0.05 micromolar).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M3" type="Trigger" span="0 8;112 5;135 14" str="Continue | until | level is below"/>
<Mention id="M4" type="Precipitant" span="122 12" str="methotrexate" code="N0000007370 | YL5FZ2Y5U1"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M3" precipitant="M4" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5805" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Adjust dosage or extend duration based on the guidelines in Table 1.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5806" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Table 1 Guidelines for Levoleucovorin for Injection Dosage and Administration Clinical Situation Laboratory Findings Recommendation Normal methotrexate elimination Serum methotrexate level approximately 10 micromolar at 24 hours after administration, 1 micromolar at 48 hours, and less than 0.2 micromolar at 72 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5807" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Administer 7.5 mg by intravenous infusion every 6 hours for 60 hours (10 doses starting 24 hours after start of methotrexate infusion).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5808" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Delayed late methotrexate elimination Serum methotrexate level remaining above 0.2 micromolar at 72 hours, and more than 0.05 micromolar at 96 hours after administration.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M5" type="Trigger" span="0 7;26 11" str="Delayed | elimination"/>
<Mention id="M6" type="Precipitant" span="13 12" str="methotrexate" code="N0000007370 | YL5FZ2Y5U1"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M5" precipitant="M6" effect="C54611"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5809" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Continue 7.5 mg by intravenous infusion every 6 hours, until methotrexate level is less than 0.05 micromolar.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M7" type="Trigger" span="0 8;55 5;74 18" str="Continue | until | level is less than"/>
<Mention id="M8" type="Precipitant" span="61 12" str="methotrexate" code="N0000007370 | YL5FZ2Y5U1"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M7" precipitant="M8" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5810" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Delayed early methotrexate elimination and/or evidence of acute renal injury* Serum methotrexate level of 50 micromolar or more at 24 hours, or 5 micromolar or more at 48 hours after administration, OR 100% or greater increase in serum creatinine level at 24 hours after methotrexate administration (e.g., an increase from 0.5 mg/dL to a level of 1 mg/dL or more).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M9" type="Trigger" span="0 7;27 11" str="Delayed | elimination"/>
<Mention id="M10" type="Precipitant" span="14 12" str="methotrexate" code="N0000007370 | YL5FZ2Y5U1"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M9" precipitant="M10" effect="C54611"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5811" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Administer 75 mg by intravenous infusion every 3 hours until methotrexate level is less than 1 micromolar; then 7.5 mg by intravenous infusion every 3 hours until methotrexate level is less than 0.05 micromolar.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5812" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>* These patients are likely to develop reversible renal failure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5813" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In addition to appropriate levoleucovorin for injection therapy, continue hydration and urinary alkalinization, and monitoring of fluid and electrolyte status, until the serum methotrexate level has fallen to below 0.05 micromolar and the renal failure has resolved.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M11" type="Trigger" span="65 8;160 15;189 25" str="continue | until the serum | level has fallen to below"/>
<Mention id="M12" type="Precipitant" span="176 12" str="methotrexate" code="N0000007370 | YL5FZ2Y5U1"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M11" precipitant="M12" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5814" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Impaired Methotrexate Elimination or Renal Impairment Decreased methotrexate elimination or renal impairment which are clinically important but less severe than abnormalities described in Table 1 can occur following methotrexate administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5815" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If toxicity is observed, extend Levoleucovorin for injection rescue for an additional 24 hours (total of 14 doses over 84 hours) in subsequent courses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5816" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Third - Space Fluid Collection and Other Causes of Delayed Methotrexate E limination Accumulation in a third-space fluid collection (i.e., ascites, pleural effusion), renal insufficiency, or inadequate hydration can cause delayed methotrexate elimination.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5817" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Under such circumstances, higher doses of Levoleucovorin for injection or prolonged administration may be indicated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5818" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Start Levoleucovorin for injection rescue in adult and pediatric patients as soon as possible after an overdosage of methotrexate or within 24 hours of methotrexate administration when there is impaired methotrexate elimination.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5819" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>As the time interval between methotrexate administration and Levoleucovorin for injection rescue increases, effectiveness of Levoleucovorin for injection in diminishing toxicity may decrease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5820" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Administer Levoleucovorin for injection 7.5 mg (approximately 5 mg/m2) intravenously every 6 hours until the serum methotrexate level is less than 10-8 M (0.05 micromolar).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5821" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor serum creatinine and methotrexate levels at least every 24 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5822" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If 24-hour serum creatinine has increased 50% over baseline or if the 24-hour methotrexate level is greater than 5 x 10-6 M or 48-hour level is greater than 9 x 10-7 M, increase the dose of Levoleucovorin for injection to 50 mg/m2 intravenously every 3 hours until the methotrexate level is less than 10-8 M. Continue concomitant hydration (3 L per day) and urinary alkalinization with sodium bicarbonate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5823" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Adjust the bicarbonate dose to maintain urine pH at 7.0 or greater.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5824" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Preparation Reconstitute vial contents with 17.7 mL of 0.9% Sodium Chloride Injection, USP, to obtain a clear, colorless to yellowish solution (resultant concentration 10 mg/mL levoleucovorin).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5825" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Reconstitution with a sodium chloride solution with preservatives (e.g. benzyl alcohol) has not been studied.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5826" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Discard vial if particulate matter or discoloration is observed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5827" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dilute reconstituted solution immediately, to concentrations of 0.5 mg/mL to 5 mg/mL in 0.9% Sodium Chloride Injection, USP, or 5% Dextrose Injection, USP.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5828" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Storage If necessary, store reconstituted solution for not more than 24 hours at room temperature.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5829" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not store reconstituted solution diluted with 0.9% Sodium Chloride Injection, USP, for more than 24 hours at room temperature.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5830" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not store reconstituted solution diluted with 5% Dextrose Injection, USP, for more than 4 hours at room temperature.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5831" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Administration Inspect reconstituted solution in the vial for particulate matter and discoloration prior to administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5832" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not co-administer with other agents in the same admixture, due to risk of precipitation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5833" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Effect of leu co vorin products on fluorouracil : Leucovorin products increase the toxicity of fluorouracil.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M13" type="Trigger" span="70 21" str="increase the toxicity"/>
<Mention id="M14" type="Precipitant" span="35 12" str="fluorouracil" code="U3P01618RT"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M13" precipitant="M14" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5834" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hypercalcemia: Limit rate of infusion due to calcium content.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5835" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Increased gastrointestinal toxicities with fluorouracil (5.2, 7) Drug interaction with trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole: Increased rates of treatment failure with concomitant use of d,l-leucovorin with trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole for Pneumocystis jiroveci pneumonia in patients with HIV.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M15" type="Trigger" span="0 9" str="Increased"/>
<Mention id="M23" type="Precipitant" span="43 12" str="fluorouracil" code="U3P01618RT"/>
<Mention id="M17" type="SpecificInteraction" span="10 27" str="gastrointestinal toxicities" code="196757008: Drug-induced gastrointestinal disturbance (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M18" type="Trigger" span="0 9" str="Increased "/>
<Mention id="M19" type="Trigger" span="147 7" str=" failure"/>
<Mention id="M20" type="Precipitant" span="87 29" str="trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M21" type="SpecificInteraction" span="233 52" str="Pneumocystis jiroveci pneumonia in patients with HIV" code="415125002: Pneumocystosis jirovecii pneumonia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M22" type="Trigger" span="0 9;27 10" str="Increased | toxicities"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M15" precipitant="M23" effect="M17" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M18;M19" precipitant="M20" effect="M21" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M22" precipitant="M23" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5836" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Due to the calcium content of the levoleucovorin solution, inject no more than 16 mL (160 mg of levoleucovorin) intravenously per minute.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5837" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Leucovorin products increase the toxicities of fluorouracil.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M24" type="Trigger" span="20 23" str="increase the toxicities"/>
<Mention id="M25" type="Precipitant" span="47 12" str="fluorouracil" code="U3P01618RT"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M24" precipitant="M25" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5838" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Gastrointestinal toxicities, (particularly stomatitis and diarrhea) occur more commonly, and may be of greater severity and prolonged duration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5839" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Deaths from severe enterocolitis, diarrhea, and dehydration have been reported in elderly patients receiving weekly d,l-leucovorin and fluorouracil.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M28" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 6" str="Deaths" code="419620001: Death (event)"/>
<Mention id="M36" type="Precipitant" span="135 12" str="fluorouracil" code="U3P01618RT"/>
<Mention id="M31" type="SpecificInteraction" span="48 11" str="dehydration" code="34095006: Dehydration (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M34" type="SpecificInteraction" span="34 8" str="diarrhea" code="62315008: Diarrhea (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M37" type="SpecificInteraction" span="12 20" str="severe enterocolitis" code="43752006: Inflammation of small intestine and colon (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M28" precipitant="M36" effect="M28" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M31" precipitant="M36" effect="M31" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M34" precipitant="M36" effect="M34" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M37" precipitant="M36" effect="M37" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5840" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant use of d,l-leucovorin with trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole for the acute treatment of Pneumocystis jiroveci pneumonia in patients with HIV infection was associated with increased rates of treatment failure and morbidity in a placebo-controlled study.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M42" type="Trigger" span="163 15" str="associated with "/>
<Mention id="M43" type="Trigger" span="179 15" str=" increased rates"/>
<Mention id="M44" type="Precipitant" span="39 29" str="trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M41" type="SpecificInteraction" span="220 9" str="morbidity" code="87858002: Drug-related disorder (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M45" type="SpecificInteraction" span="198 17" str="treatment failure" code="102471002: Absence of therapeutic response (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M42;M43" precipitant="M44" effect="M41" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M42;M43" precipitant="M44" effect="M45" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5841" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Levoleucovorin is the pharmacologically active isomer of 5-formyl tetrahydrofolic acid (THF).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5842" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Levoleucovorin does not require reduction by dihydrofolate reductase to participate in reactions utilizing folates as a source of “one-carbon” moieties.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5843" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Administration of levoleucovorin counteracts the therapeutic and toxic effects of folic acid antagonists such as methotrexate, which act by inhibiting dihydrofolate reductase.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M46" type="Trigger" span="33 11" str="counteracts"/>
<Mention id="M47" type="Precipitant" span="82 22" str="folic acid antagonists" code="N0000000111"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M46" precipitant="M47"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5844" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In a crossover-design pharmacokinetic comparability study, healthy subjects received a single 2-hour infusion of either levoleucovorin (200 mg/m2) or racemic d,l-leucovorin (400 mg/m2).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5845" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The 90% confidence intervals for the geometric mean ratios for both AUC0-inf and Cmax were within the standard limit of 80-125% for both l-leucovorin and l-5-methyl-THF.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5846" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The exposure to l-leucovorin and 5-methyl-THF was comparable whether it was administered as levoleucovorin or as d,l-leucovorin as shown in Table 3: Table 3 Geometric Mean Pharmacokinetic Parameters Parameter l -leucovorin d,l -leucovorin 5-methyl-THF- l - leucovorin 5-methyl-THF- d,l -leucovorin AUC0-inf (ng.h/mL) 30719 31296 52105 50137 Cmax (ng.h/mL) 10895 11301 4930 4658 Distribution The pharmacokinetics of levoleucovorin after intravenous administration of a 15 mg dose was studied in healthy male volunteers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5847" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>After rapid intravenous administration, serum total tetrahydrofolate (total-THF) concentrations reached a mean peak of 1722 ng/mL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5848" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Serum (6S)-5-methyl-5,6,7,8-tetrahydrofolate concentrations reached a mean peak of 275 ng/mL and the mean time to peak was 0.9 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5849" LabelDrug="Levoleucovorin" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Elimination The mean terminal half-life for total-THF and (6S)-5-methyl-5,6,7,8-tetrahydrofolate was 5.1 and 6.8 hours, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="methotrexate" precipitantCode="N0000007370 | YL5FZ2Y5U1" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="methotrexate" precipitantCode="N0000007370 | YL5FZ2Y5U1" effect="C54611"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="fluorouracil" precipitantCode="U3P01618RT" effect="196757008: Drug-induced gastrointestinal disturbance (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="fluorouracil" precipitantCode="U3P01618RT" effect="34095006: Dehydration (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="fluorouracil" precipitantCode="U3P01618RT" effect="419620001: Death (event)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="fluorouracil" precipitantCode="U3P01618RT" effect="43752006: Inflammation of small intestine and colon (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="fluorouracil" precipitantCode="U3P01618RT" effect="62315008: Diarrhea (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="fluorouracil" precipitantCode="U3P01618RT" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="102471002: Absence of therapeutic response (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="415125002: Pneumocystosis jirovecii pneumonia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="87858002: Drug-related disorder (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="folic acid antagonists" precipitantCode="N0000000111"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>