<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Methazolamide" setid="c26c8834-961e-4c9c-9ad4-5db2d9419938">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
Methazolamide therapy is contraindicated in situations in which sodium and/or potassium serum levels are depressed, in cases of marked kidney or liver disease or dysfunction, in adrenal gland failure, and in hyperchloremic acidosis. In patients with cirrhosis, use may precipitate the development of hepatic encephalopathy. Long-term administration of methazolamide is contraindicated in patients with angle-closure glaucoma, since organic closure of the angle may occur in spite of lowered intraocular pressure.</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
The effective therapeutic dose administered varies from 50 mg to 100 mg two or three times daily. The drug may be used concomitantly with miotic and osmotic agents.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
Methazolamide should be used with caution in patients on steroid therapy because of the potential for developing hypokalemia. Caution is advised for patients receiving high-dose aspirin and methazolamide concomitantly, as anorexia, tachypnea, lethargy, coma and death have been reported with concomitant use of high-dose aspirin and carbonic anhydrase inhibitors (see WARNINGS ).</Section>
<Section name="PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="42232-9">
Potassium excretion is increased initially upon administration of methazolamide and in patients with cirrhosis or hepatic insufficiency could precipitate a hepatic coma. In patients with pulmonary obstruction or emphysema, where alveolar ventilation may be impaired, methazolamide should be used with caution because it may precipitate or aggravate acidosis. Adverse reactions common to all sulfonamide derivatives may occur: anaphylaxis, fever, rash (including erythema multiforme, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis), crystalluria, renal calculus, bone marrow depression, thrombocytopenic purpura, hemolytic anemia, leukopenia, pancytopenia, and agranulocytosis. Precaution is advised for early detection of such reactions, and the drug should be discontinued and appropriate therapy instituted. Caution is advised for patients receiving high-dose aspirin and methazolamide concomitantly. To monitor for hematologic reactions common to all sulfonamides, it is recommended that a baseline CBC and platelet count be obtained on patients prior to initiating methazolamide therapy and at regular intervals during therapy. If significant changes occur, early discontinuance and institution of appropriate therapy are important. Periodic monitoring of serum electrolytes is also recommended. Methazolamide should be used with caution in patients on steroid therapy because of the potential for developing hypokalemia. Caution is advised for patients receiving high-dose aspirin and methazolamide concomitantly, as anorexia, tachypnea, lethargy, coma and death have been reported with concomitant use of high-dose aspirin and carbonic anhydrase inhibitors (see WARNINGS ). Long-term studies in animals to evaluate the carcinogenic potential of methazolamide and its effect on fertility have not been conducted. Methazolamide was not mutagenic in the Ames bacterial test. Teratogenic effects Pregnancy Category C Methazolamide has been shown to be teratogenic (skeletal anomalies) in rats when given in doses approximately 40 times the human dose. There are no adequate and well controlled studies in pregnant women. Methazolamide should be used during pregnancy only if the potential benefit justifies the potential risk to the fetus. It is not known whether this drug is excreted in human milk. Because many drugs are excreted in human milk and because of the potential for serious adverse reactions in nursing infants from methazolamide, a decision should be made whether to discontinue nursing or to discontinue the drug, taking into account the importance of the drug to the mother. The safety and effectiveness of methazolamide in children have not been established.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS SECTION" id="34071-1">
Fatalities have occurred, although rarely, due to severe reactions to sulfonamides including Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis, fulminant hepatic necrosis, agranulocytosis, aplastic anemia, and other blood dyscrasias. Hypersensitivity reactions may recur when a sulfonamide is readministered, irrespective of the route of administration. If hypersensitivity or other serious reactions occur, the use of this drug should be discontinued. Caution is advised for patients receiving high-dose aspirin and methazolamide concomitantly, as anorexia, tachypnea, lethargy, coma, and death have been reported with concomitant use of high-dose aspirin and carbonic anhydrase inhibitors.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Methazolamide is a potent inhibitor of carbonic anhydrase. Methazolamide is well absorbed from the gastrointestinal tract. Peak plasma concentrations are observed 1 to 2 hours after dosing. In a multiple-dose, pharmacokinetic study, administration of methazolamide 25 mg bid, 50 mg bid, and 100 mg bid demonstrated a linear relationship between plasma methazolamide levels and methazolamide dose. Peak plasma concentrations (C max ) for the 25 mg, 50 mg and 100 mg bid regimens were 2.5 mcg/mL, 5.1 mcg/mL, and 10.7 mcg/mL, respectively. The area under the plasma concentration-time curves (AUC) was 1130 mcg.min/mL, 2571 mcg.min/mL, and 5418 mcg.min/mL for the 25 mg, 50 mg, and 100 mg dosage regimens, respectively. Methazolamide is distributed throughout the body including the plasma, cerebrospinal fluid, aqueous humor of the eye, red blood cells, bile and extra-cellular fluid. The mean apparent volume of distribution (V area /F) ranges from 17 L to 23 L. Approximately 55% is bound to plasma proteins. The steady-state methazolamide red blood cell:plasma ratio varies with dose and was found to be 27:1, 16:1, and 10:1 following the administration of methazolamide 25 mg bid, 50 mg bid, and 100 mg bid, respectively. The mean steady-state plasma elimination half-life for methazolamide is approximately 14 hours. At steady-state, approximately 25% of the dose is recovered unchanged in the urine over the dosing interval. Renal clearance accounts for 20% to 25% of the total clearance of drug. After repeated bid-tid dosing, methazolamide accumulates to steady-state concentrations in 7 days. Methazolamide’s inhibitory action on carbonic anhydrase decreases the secretion of aqueous humor and results in a decrease in intraocular pressure. The onset of the decrease in intraocular pressure generally occurs within 2 to 4 hours, has a peak effect in 6 to 8 hours and a total duration of 10 to 18 hours. Methazolamide is a sulfonamide derivative; however, it does not have any clinically significant antimicrobial properties. Although methazolamide achieves a high concentration in the cerebrospinal fluid, it is not considered an effective anticonvulsant. Methazolamide has a weak and transient diuretic effect; therefore, use results in an increase in urinary volume, with excretion of sodium, potassium, and chloride. The drug should not be used as a diuretic. Inhibition of renal bicarbonate reabsorption produces an alkaline urine. Plasma bicarbonate decreases, and a relative, transient metabolic acidosis may occur due to a disequilibrium in carbon dioxide transport in the red blood cell. Urinary citrate excretion is decreased by approximately 40% after doses of 100 mg every 8 hours. Uric acid output has been shown to decrease 36% in the first 24 hour period.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="1931" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Methazolamide therapy is contraindicated in situations in which sodium and/or potassium serum levels are depressed, in cases of marked kidney or liver disease or dysfunction, in adrenal gland failure, and in hyperchloremic acidosis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1932" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>In patients with cirrhosis, use may precipitate the development of hepatic encephalopathy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1933" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Long-term administration of methazolamide is contraindicated in patients with angle-closure glaucoma, since organic closure of the angle may occur in spite of lowered intraocular pressure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1934" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The effective therapeutic dose administered varies from 50 mg to 100 mg two or three times daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1935" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The drug may be used concomitantly with miotic and osmotic agents.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1936" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Methazolamide should be used with caution in patients on steroid therapy because of the potential for developing hypokalemia.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M1" type="Trigger" span="34 7" str="caution "/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Trigger" span="88 13" str=" potential for"/>
<Mention id="M3" type="Precipitant" span="57 15" str="steroid therapy" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M4" type="SpecificInteraction" span="113 11" str="hypokalemia" code="43339004: Hypokalemia (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M1;M2" precipitant="M3" effect="M4" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1937" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Caution is advised for patients receiving high-dose aspirin and methazolamide concomitantly, as anorexia, tachypnea, lethargy, coma and death have been reported with concomitant use of high-dose aspirin and carbonic anhydrase inhibitors.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M17" type="Trigger" span="0 7" str="Caution"/>
<Mention id="M18" type="Precipitant" span="42 17" str="high-dose aspirin" code="R16CO5Y76E"/>
<Mention id="M7" type="SpecificInteraction" span="96 8" str="anorexia" code="79890006: Loss of appetite (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M10" type="SpecificInteraction" span="127 4" str="coma" code="371632003: Coma (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M13" type="SpecificInteraction" span="136 5" str="death" code="419620001: Death (event)"/>
<Mention id="M16" type="SpecificInteraction" span="117 8" str="lethargy" code="214264003: Lethargy (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M19" type="SpecificInteraction" span="106 9" str="tachypnea" code="271823003: Tachypnea (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M17" precipitant="M18" effect="M7" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M17" precipitant="M18" effect="M10" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M17" precipitant="M18" effect="M13" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M17" precipitant="M18" effect="M16" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M17" precipitant="M18" effect="M19" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1938" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Potassium excretion is increased initially upon administration of methazolamide and in patients with cirrhosis or hepatic insufficiency could precipitate a hepatic coma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1939" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In patients with pulmonary obstruction or emphysema, where alveolar ventilation may be impaired, methazolamide should be used with caution because it may precipitate or aggravate acidosis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1940" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Adverse reactions common to all sulfonamide derivatives may occur: anaphylaxis, fever, rash (including erythema multiforme, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis), crystalluria, renal calculus, bone marrow depression, thrombocytopenic purpura, hemolytic anemia, leukopenia, pancytopenia, and agranulocytosis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1941" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Precaution is advised for early detection of such reactions, and the drug should be discontinued and appropriate therapy instituted.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1942" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Caution is advised for patients receiving high-dose aspirin and methazolamide concomitantly.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M20" type="Trigger" span="0 7" str="Caution"/>
<Mention id="M21" type="Precipitant" span="42 17" str="high-dose aspirin" code="R16CO5Y76E"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M20" precipitant="M21"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1943" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>To monitor for hematologic reactions common to all sulfonamides, it is recommended that a baseline CBC and platelet count be obtained on patients prior to initiating methazolamide therapy and at regular intervals during therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1944" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>If significant changes occur, early discontinuance and institution of appropriate therapy are important.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1945" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Periodic monitoring of serum electrolytes is also recommended.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1946" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Long-term studies in animals to evaluate the carcinogenic potential of methazolamide and its effect on fertility have not been conducted.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1947" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Methazolamide was not mutagenic in the Ames bacterial test.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1948" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Teratogenic effects Pregnancy Category C Methazolamide has been shown to be teratogenic (skeletal anomalies) in rats when given in doses approximately 40 times the human dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1949" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>There are no adequate and well controlled studies in pregnant women.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1950" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Methazolamide should be used during pregnancy only if the potential benefit justifies the potential risk to the fetus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1951" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>It is not known whether this drug is excreted in human milk.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1952" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because many drugs are excreted in human milk and because of the potential for serious adverse reactions in nursing infants from methazolamide, a decision should be made whether to discontinue nursing or to discontinue the drug, taking into account the importance of the drug to the mother.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1953" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The safety and effectiveness of methazolamide in children have not been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1954" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Fatalities have occurred, although rarely, due to severe reactions to sulfonamides including Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis, fulminant hepatic necrosis, agranulocytosis, aplastic anemia, and other blood dyscrasias.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1955" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Hypersensitivity reactions may recur when a sulfonamide is readministered, irrespective of the route of administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1956" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>If hypersensitivity or other serious reactions occur, the use of this drug should be discontinued.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1957" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Caution is advised for patients receiving high-dose aspirin and methazolamide concomitantly, as anorexia, tachypnea, lethargy, coma, and death have been reported with concomitant use of high-dose aspirin and carbonic anhydrase inhibitors.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M34" type="Trigger" span="0 7" str="Caution"/>
<Mention id="M35" type="Precipitant" span="42 17" str="high-dose aspirin" code="R16CO5Y76E"/>
<Mention id="M24" type="SpecificInteraction" span="96 8" str="anorexia" code="79890006: Loss of appetite (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M27" type="SpecificInteraction" span="127 4" str="coma" code="371632003: Coma (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M30" type="SpecificInteraction" span="137 5" str="death" code="419620001: Death (event)"/>
<Mention id="M33" type="SpecificInteraction" span="117 8" str="lethargy" code="214264003: Lethargy (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M36" type="SpecificInteraction" span="106 9" str="tachypnea" code="271823003: Tachypnea (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M34" precipitant="M35" effect="M24" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M34" precipitant="M35" effect="M27" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M34" precipitant="M35" effect="M30" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M34" precipitant="M35" effect="M33" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M34" precipitant="M35" effect="M36" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1958" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Methazolamide is a potent inhibitor of carbonic anhydrase.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1959" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Methazolamide is well absorbed from the gastrointestinal tract.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1960" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Peak plasma concentrations are observed 1 to 2 hours after dosing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1961" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In a multiple-dose, pharmacokinetic study, administration of methazolamide 25 mg bid, 50 mg bid, and 100 mg bid demonstrated a linear relationship between plasma methazolamide levels and methazolamide dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1962" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Peak plasma concentrations (Cmax) for the 25 mg, 50 mg and 100 mg bid regimens were 2.5 mcg/mL, 5.1 mcg/mL, and 10.7 mcg/mL, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1963" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The area under the plasma concentration-time curves (AUC) was 1130 mcg.min/mL, 2571 mcg.min/mL, and 5418 mcg.min/mL for the 25 mg, 50 mg, and 100 mg dosage regimens, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1964" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Methazolamide is distributed throughout the body including the plasma, cerebrospinal fluid, aqueous humor of the eye, red blood cells, bile and extra-cellular fluid.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1965" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mean apparent volume of distribution (Varea/F) ranges from 17 L to 23 L. Approximately 55% is bound to plasma proteins.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1966" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The steady-state methazolamide red blood cell:plasma ratio varies with dose and was found to be 27:1, 16:1, and 10:1 following the administration of methazolamide 25 mg bid, 50 mg bid, and 100 mg bid, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1967" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mean steady-state plasma elimination half-life for methazolamide is approximately 14 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1968" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>At steady-state, approximately 25% of the dose is recovered unchanged in the urine over the dosing interval.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1969" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Renal clearance accounts for 20% to 25% of the total clearance of drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1970" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>After repeated bid-tid dosing, methazolamide accumulates to steady-state concentrations in 7 days.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1971" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Methazolamide’s inhibitory action on carbonic anhydrase decreases the secretion of aqueous humor and results in a decrease in intraocular pressure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1972" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The onset of the decrease in intraocular pressure generally occurs within 2 to 4 hours, has a peak effect in 6 to 8 hours and a total duration of 10 to 18 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1973" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Methazolamide is a sulfonamide derivative; however, it does not have any clinically significant antimicrobial properties.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1974" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Although methazolamide achieves a high concentration in the cerebrospinal fluid, it is not considered an effective anticonvulsant.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1975" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Methazolamide has a weak and transient diuretic effect; therefore, use results in an increase in urinary volume, with excretion of sodium, potassium, and chloride.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1976" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The drug should not be used as a diuretic.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1977" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Inhibition of renal bicarbonate reabsorption produces an alkaline urine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1978" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Plasma bicarbonate decreases, and a relative, transient metabolic acidosis may occur due to a disequilibrium in carbon dioxide transport in the red blood cell.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1979" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Urinary citrate excretion is decreased by approximately 40% after doses of 100 mg every 8 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1980" LabelDrug="Methazolamide" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Uric acid output has been shown to decrease 36% in the first 24 hour period.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="steroid therapy" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="43339004: Hypokalemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="high-dose aspirin" precipitantCode="R16CO5Y76E" effect="214264003: Lethargy (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="high-dose aspirin" precipitantCode="R16CO5Y76E" effect="271823003: Tachypnea (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="high-dose aspirin" precipitantCode="R16CO5Y76E" effect="371632003: Coma (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="high-dose aspirin" precipitantCode="R16CO5Y76E" effect="419620001: Death (event)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="high-dose aspirin" precipitantCode="R16CO5Y76E" effect="79890006: Loss of appetite (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="high-dose aspirin" precipitantCode="R16CO5Y76E"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>