<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Rebif" setid="c6fcb5d2-8fcd-44fa-a838-b84ee5f44f0f">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
REBIF is contraindicated in patients with a history of hypersensitivity to natural or recombinant interferon beta, human albumin, or any other component of the formulation. History of hypersensitivity to natural or recombinant interferon beta, human albumin, or any other component of the formulation ( 4 )</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
For subcutaneous injection only ( 2.1 ) The recommended dose is either 22 mcg or 44 mcg injected subcutaneously three times per week ( 2.1 ) Titration: Generally, the starting dose should be 20% of the prescribed dose three times per week, and increased over a 4 week period to the targeted recommended dose of either 22 mcg or 44 mcg injected subcutaneously three times per week ( 2.1 ) Analgesics and/or antipyretics on treatment days may help ameliorate flu-like symptoms ( 2.3 ) The recommended dose of REBIF is either 22 mcg or 44 mcg injected subcutaneously three times per week. REBIF should be administered, if possible, at the same time (preferably in the late afternoon or evening) on the same three days (e.g., Monday, Wednesday, and Friday) at least 48 hours apart each week. Generally, patients should be started at 20% of the prescribed dose three times per week and increased over a 4-week period to the targeted dose, either 22 mcg three times per week (see Table 1 ) or 44 mcg three times per week (see Table 2 ). Patients prescribed a targeted dose of 22 mcg three times per week should use the prefilled syringes for titration. A Titration Pack containing 6 doses of 8.8 mcg (0.2 mL) and 6 doses of 22 mcg (0.5 mL) is available for use during the titration period in both REBIF prefilled syringes and REBIF Rebidose autoinjectors. Table 1: Titration Schedule for a 22 mcg Prescribed Dose Use only prefilled syringes, not autoinjectors, to titrate to the 22 mcg Prescribed Dose Week of Use Dose Syringe to Use Amount of syringe Week 1 Titration 4.4 mcg 8.8 mcg syringe Use half of syringe Week 2 Titration 4.4 mcg 8.8 mcg syringe Use half of syringe Week 3 Titration 11 mcg 22 mcg syringe Use half of syringe Week 4 Titration 11 mcg 22 mcg syringe Use half of syringe Week 5 and after 22 mcg 22 mcg syringe or autoinjector Use full syringe or autoinjector Table 2: Titration Schedule for a 44 mcg Prescribed Dose Prefilled syringes or autoinjectors can be used to titrate to the 44 mcg Prescribed Dose Week of Use Dose Syringe or Autoinjector to Use Amount of syringe or autoinjector Week 1 Titration 8.8 mcg 8.8 mcg syringe or autoinjector Use full syringe or autoinjector Week 2 Titration 8.8 mcg 8.8 mcg syringe or autoinjector Use full syringe or autoinjector Week 3 Titration 22 mcg 22 mcg syringe or autoinjector Use full syringe or autoinjector Week 4 Titration 22 mcg 22 mcg syringe or autoinjector Use full syringe or autoinjector Week 5 and after 44 mcg 44 mcg syringe or autoinjector Use full syringe or autoinjector Decreased peripheral blood counts or elevated liver function tests may necessitate dose reduction or discontinuation of REBIF administration until toxicity is resolved [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2 , 5.5) and Adverse Reactions (6) ]. REBIF is intended for use under the guidance and supervision of a physician. It is recommended that physicians or qualified medical personnel train patients in the proper technique for self-administering subcutaneous injections using the prefilled syringe or injection device approved for use with REBIF. Injection depth of the REBIF Rebidose autoinjector is fixed at 8 mm; the health care provider should determine the injection technique. The initial injection should be performed under the supervision of an appropriately qualified health care provider. Appropriate instruction for self-injection or injection by another person should be provided to the patient or their caregiver, including careful review of the REBIF Medication Guide and the REBIF Rebidose autoinjector Instructions for Use that accompanies the product. Users should demonstrate competency in all aspects of the injection prior to independent use. If a patient is to self-administer REBIF, the physical and cognitive ability of that patient to self-administer and properly dispose of prefilled syringes or the REBIF Rebidose autoinjectors should be assessed. Patients with severe neurological deficits should not self-administer injections without assistance from a trained caregiver. Advise patients and caregivers to: visually inspect REBIF for particulate matter and discoloration prior to administration use aseptic technique when administering REBIF rotate site of injection with each dose to minimize the likelihood of severe injection site reactions or necrosis [see Warnings and Precautions, (5.4) ] use a puncture-resistant container for safe disposal of used needles, prefilled syringes and REBIF Rebidose autoinjectors do not re-use needles, syringes or REBIF Rebidose autoinjectors Concurrent use of analgesics and/or antipyretics may help ameliorate flu-like symptoms associated with REBIF use on treatment days.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
Depression and Suicide: Advise patients to immediately report any symptoms of depression and/or suicidal ideation; consider discontinuation of REBIF if depression occurs ( 5.1 ) Hepatic injury: Monitor liver function tests; monitor patients for signs and symptoms of hepatic injury; consider discontinuing REBIF if hepatic injury occurs ( 5.2 ) Anaphylaxis and Other Allergic Reactions: Discontinue REBIF if anaphylaxis occurs ( 5.3 ) Injection Site Reactions including Necrosis: Do not administer REBIF into affected area until fully healed; if multiple lesions occur, discontinue REBIF until healing of skin lesions ( 5.4 ) Decreased Peripheral Blood Counts: Monitor complete blood counts ( 5.5 ) Thrombotic Microangiopathy: Cases of thrombotic microangiopathy have been reported. Discontinue REBIF if clinical symptoms and laboratory findings consistent with TMA occur ( 5.6 ). Seizures: Monitor for seizures when administering REBIF to patients, particularly those with pre-existing seizure disorders ( 5.7 ) REBIF (interferon beta-1a) should be used with caution in patients with depression, a condition that is common in people with multiple sclerosis. Depression, suicidal ideation, and suicide attempts have been reported to occur with increased frequency in patients receiving interferon compounds, including REBIF. In addition, there have been postmarketing reports of suicide in patients treated with REBIF. Patients should be advised to report immediately any symptoms of depression and/or suicidal ideation to the prescribing physician. If a patient develops depression, cessation of treatment with REBIF should be considered. Severe liver injury, including some cases of hepatic failure requiring liver transplantation, has been reported rarely in patients taking REBIF. Symptoms of liver dysfunction began from one to six months following the initiation of REBIF. If jaundice or other symptoms of liver dysfunction appear, treatment with REBIF should be discontinued immediately due to the potential for rapid progression to liver failure. Asymptomatic elevation of hepatic transaminases (particularly SGPT) is common with interferon therapy [see Adverse Reactions (6.1) ] . REBIF should be initiated with caution in patients with active liver disease, alcohol abuse, increased serum SGPT (&amp;gt; 2.5 times ULN), or a history of significant liver disease. Also, the potential risk of REBIF used in combination with known hepatotoxic products should be considered prior to REBIF administration, or when adding new agents to the regimen of patients already on REBIF. Reduction of REBIF dose should be considered if SGPT rises above 5 times the upper limit of normal. The dose may be gradually re-escalated when enzyme levels have normalized [see Warnings and Precautions (5.8) ; and Dosage and Administration (2.1) ]. Anaphylaxis has been reported as a rare complication of REBIF use. Other allergic reactions have included skin rash and urticaria, and have ranged from mild to severe without a clear relationship to dose or duration of exposure. Several allergic reactions, some severe, have occurred after prolonged use. Discontinue REBIF if anaphylaxis occurs. In controlled clinical trials, injection site reactions occurred more frequently in REBIF-treated patients (92% in the 44 mcg group and 89% in the 22 mcg group) than in placebo-treated patients (39%) and at a higher frequency in REBIF treated patients (83%) than in AVONEX-treated patients (28%). Injection site necrosis also occurred more frequently in REBIF-treated patients (3% in the 44 mcg group and 1% in the 22 mcg group) than in placebo-treated patients (0) during the two years of therapy. All events resolved with conservative management. Injection site reactions including injection site pain, erythema, edema, cellulitis, abscess, and necrosis have been reported in the postmarketing setting. Some occurred more than 2 years after initiation of REBIF. Necrosis occurred at single and at multiple injection sites. Some cases of injection site necrosis required treatment with intravenous antibiotics and surgical intervention (debridement and skin grafting). Patient understanding and use of aseptic self-injection techniques and procedures should be periodically evaluated, particularly if injection site necrosis has occurred. Patients should be advised of the importance of rotating sites of injection with each dose and not reusing syringes. Patients should be advised against injecting an area which is inflamed, edematous, erythematous, ecchymotic, or has any other signs of infection. These signs should be reported to a healthcare professional immediately. Decreased peripheral blood counts in all cell lines, including pancytopenia, have been reported in REBIF-treated patients. In controlled clinical trials, leukopenia occurred at a higher frequency in REBIF-treated patients (36% in 44 mcg group and 28% in 22 mcg group) than in placebo-treated patients (14%) and at a higher frequency in REBIF-treated patients (6%) compared to the AVONEX-treated patients (&amp;lt;1%). Thrombocytopenia and anemia occurred more frequently in 44 mcg REBIF-treated patients (8% and 5%, respectively) than in placebo-treated patients (2% and 3%, respectively). In a pooled analysis of 7 placebo controlled trials with REBIF doses of 22 mcg or 44 mcg, the rate of pancytopenia (in subjects with normal baseline values who developed laboratory values less than the lower limit of normal for all 3 hematology parameters simultaneously) was higher in the total REBIF group (5.5 per 1000 subject-year) than in the placebo group (1.2 per 1000 subject-year). Patients should be monitored for symptoms or signs of decreased blood counts. Monitoring of complete blood and differential white blood cell counts is also recommended [see Dosage and Administration (2.1) and Warnings and Precautions (5.8) ]. Cases of thrombotic microangiopathy (TMA), including thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura and hemolytic uremic syndrome, some fatal, have been reported with interferon beta products, including REBIF. Cases have been reported several weeks to years after starting interferon beta products. Discontinue REBIF if clinical symptoms and laboratory findings consistent with TMA occur, and manage as clinically indicated. Caution should be exercised when administering REBIF to patients with pre-existing seizure disorders. Seizures have been temporally associated with the use of beta interferons, including REBIF, in clinical trials and in postmarketing reports. In addition to those laboratory tests normally required for monitoring patients with multiple sclerosis, blood cell counts and liver function tests are recommended at regular intervals (1, 3, and 6 months) following introduction of REBIF therapy and then periodically thereafter in the absence of clinical symptoms. Patients with myelosuppression may require more intensive monitoring of complete blood cell counts, with differential and platelet counts [see Dosage and Administration (2.1) and Warnings and Precautions (5.5) ] . New or worsening thyroid abnormalities have developed in some patients treated with REBIF. Thyroid function tests are recommended every 6 months in patients with a history of thyroid dysfunction or as clinically indicated.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
The mechanism(s) by which REBIF (interferon beta-1a) exerts its therapeutic effects in patients with multiple sclerosis is unknown. The relationships between serum interferon beta-1a levels and measurable pharmacodynamic activities to the mechanism(s) by which REBIF exerts its effects in multiple sclerosis are unknown. No gender-related effects on pharmacodynamic parameters have been observed. The pharmacokinetics of REBIF (interferon beta-1a) in people with multiple sclerosis have not been evaluated. In healthy subjects, a single subcutaneous (sc) injection of 60 mcg of REBIF (liquid formulation) resulted in a peak serum concentration (C max ) of 5.1 ± 1.7 IU/mL (mean ± SD), with a median time of peak serum concentration (T max ) of 16 hours. The serum elimination half-life (t 1/2 ) was 69 ± 37 hours, and the area under the serum concentration versus time curve (AUC) from zero to 96 hours was 294 ± 81 IU h/mL. Following every other day sc injections in healthy subjects, an increase in AUC of approximately 240% was observed, suggesting that accumulation of interferon beta-1a occurs after repeat administration. Total clearance is approximately 33-55 L/hour. There have been no observed gender-related effects on pharmacokinetic parameters. Pharmacokinetics of REBIF in pediatric and geriatric patients or patients with renal or hepatic insufficiency have not been established.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="8613" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>REBIF is contraindicated in patients with a history of hypersensitivity to natural or recombinant interferon beta, human albumin, or any other component of the formulation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8614" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>History of hypersensitivity to natural or recombinant interferon beta, human albumin, or any other component of the formulation (4)</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8615" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For subcutaneous injection only (2.1) The recommended dose is either 22 mcg or 44 mcg injected subcutaneously three times per week (2.1) Titration: Generally, the starting dose should be 20% of the prescribed dose three times per week, and increased over a 4 week period to the targeted recommended dose of either 22 mcg or 44 mcg injected subcutaneously three times per week (2.1) Analgesics and/or antipyretics on treatment days may help ameliorate flu-like symptoms (2.3) The recommended dose of REBIF is either 22 mcg or 44 mcg injected subcutaneously three times per week.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8616" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>REBIF should be administered, if possible, at the same time (preferably in the late afternoon or evening) on the same three days (e.g., Monday, Wednesday, and Friday) at least 48 hours apart each week.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8617" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Generally, patients should be started at 20% of the prescribed dose three times per week and increased over a 4-week period to the targeted dose, either 22 mcg three times per week or 44 mcg three times per week.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8618" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Patients prescribed a targeted dose of 22 mcg three times per week should use the prefilled syringes for titration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8619" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>A Titration Pack containing 6 doses of 8.8 mcg (0.2 mL) and 6 doses of 22 mcg (0.5 mL) is available for use during the titration period in both REBIF prefilled syringes and REBIF Rebidose autoinjectors.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8620" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Table 1: Titration Schedule for a 22 mcg Prescribed DoseUse only prefilled syringes, not autoinjectors, to titrate to the 22 mcg Prescribed Dose Week of Use Dose Syringe to Use Amount of syringe Week 1 Titration 4.4 mcg 8.8 mcg syringe Use half of syringe Week 2 Titration 4.4 mcg 8.8 mcg syringe Use half of syringe Week 3 Titration 11 mcg 22 mcg syringe Use half of syringe Week 4 Titration 11 mcg 22 mcg syringe Use half of syringe Week 5 and after 22 mcg 22 mcg syringe or autoinjector Use full syringe or autoinjector Table 2: Titration Schedule for a 44 mcg Prescribed DosePrefilled syringes or autoinjectors can be used to titrate to the 44 mcg Prescribed Dose Week of Use Dose Syringe or Autoinjector to Use Amount of syringe or autoinjector Week 1 Titration 8.8 mcg 8.8 mcg syringe or autoinjector Use full syringe or autoinjector Week 2 Titration 8.8 mcg 8.8 mcg syringe or autoinjector Use full syringe or autoinjector Week 3 Titration 22 mcg 22 mcg syringe or autoinjector Use full syringe or autoinjector Week 4 Titration 22 mcg 22 mcg syringe or autoinjector Use full syringe or autoinjector Week 5 and after 44 mcg 44 mcg syringe or autoinjector Use full syringe or autoinjector Decreased peripheral blood counts or elevated liver function tests may necessitate dose reduction or discontinuation of REBIF administration until toxicity is resolved.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8621" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>REBIF is intended for use under the guidance and supervision of a physician.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8622" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>It is recommended that physicians or qualified medical personnel train patients in the proper technique for self-administering subcutaneous injections using the prefilled syringe or injection device approved for use with REBIF.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8623" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Injection depth of the REBIF Rebidose autoinjector is fixed at 8 mm; the health care provider should determine the injection technique.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8624" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The initial injection should be performed under the supervision of an appropriately qualified health care provider.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8625" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Appropriate instruction for self-injection or injection by another person should be provided to the patient or their caregiver, including careful review of the REBIF Medication Guide and the REBIF Rebidose autoinjector Instructions for Use that accompanies the product.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8626" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Users should demonstrate competency in all aspects of the injection prior to independent use.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8627" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If a patient is to self-administer REBIF, the physical and cognitive ability of that patient to self-administer and properly dispose of prefilled syringes or the REBIF Rebidose autoinjectors should be assessed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8628" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Patients with severe neurological deficits should not self-administer injections without assistance from a trained caregiver.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8629" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Advise patients and caregivers to: visually inspect REBIF for particulate matter and discoloration prior to administration use aseptic technique when administering REBIF rotate site of injection with each dose to minimize the likelihood of severe injection site reactions or necrosis use a puncture-resistant container for safe disposal of used needles, prefilled syringes and REBIF Rebidose autoinjectors do not re-use needles, syringes or REBIF Rebidose autoinjectors Concurrent use of analgesics and/or antipyretics may help ameliorate flu-like symptoms associated with REBIF use on treatment days.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8630" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Depression and Suicide: Advise patients to immediately report any symptoms of depression and/or suicidal ideation; consider discontinuation of REBIF if depression occurs (5.1) Hepatic injury: Monitor liver function tests; monitor patients for signs and symptoms of hepatic injury; consider discontinuing REBIF if hepatic injury occurs (5.2) Anaphylaxis and Other Allergic Reactions: Discontinue REBIF if anaphylaxis occurs (5.3) Injection Site Reactions including Necrosis: Do not administer REBIF into affected area until fully healed; if multiple lesions occur, discontinue REBIF until healing of skin lesions (5.4) Decreased Peripheral Blood Counts: Monitor complete blood counts (5.5) Thrombotic Microangiopathy: Cases of thrombotic microangiopathy have been reported.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8631" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Discontinue REBIF if clinical symptoms and laboratory findings consistent with TMA occur (5.6).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8632" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Seizures: Monitor for seizures when administering REBIF to patients, particularly those with pre-existing seizure disorders (5.7) REBIF (interferon beta-1a) should be used with caution in patients with depression, a condition that is common in people with multiple sclerosis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8633" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Depression, suicidal ideation, and suicide attempts have been reported to occur with increased frequency in patients receiving interferon compounds, including REBIF.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8634" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In addition, there have been postmarketing reports of suicide in patients treated with REBIF.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8635" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients should be advised to report immediately any symptoms of depression and/or suicidal ideation to the prescribing physician.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8636" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If a patient develops depression, cessation of treatment with REBIF should be considered.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8637" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Severe liver injury, including some cases of hepatic failure requiring liver transplantation, has been reported rarely in patients taking REBIF.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8638" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Symptoms of liver dysfunction began from one to six months following the initiation of REBIF.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8639" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If jaundice or other symptoms of liver dysfunction appear, treatment with REBIF should be discontinued immediately due to the potential for rapid progression to liver failure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8640" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Asymptomatic elevation of hepatic transaminases (particularly SGPT) is common with interferon therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8641" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>REBIF should be initiated with caution in patients with active liver disease, alcohol abuse, increased serum SGPT (&gt; 2.5 times ULN), or a history of significant liver disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8642" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Also, the potential risk of REBIF used in combination with known hepatotoxic products should be considered prior to REBIF administration, or when adding new agents to the regimen of patients already on REBIF.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M1" type="Trigger" span="20 4" str="risk"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="65 20" str="hepatotoxic products" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M1" precipitant="M2"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8643" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Reduction of REBIF dose should be considered if SGPT rises above 5 times the upper limit of normal.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8644" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The dose may be gradually re-escalated when enzyme levels have normalized.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8645" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Anaphylaxis has been reported as a rare complication of REBIF use.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8646" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Other allergic reactions have included skin rash and urticaria, and have ranged from mild to severe without a clear relationship to dose or duration of exposure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8647" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Several allergic reactions, some severe, have occurred after prolonged use.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8648" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In controlled clinical trials, injection site reactions occurred more frequently in REBIF-treated patients (92% in the 44 mcg group and 89% in the 22 mcg group) than in placebo-treated patients (39%) and at a higher frequency in REBIF treated patients (83%) than in AVONEX-treated patients (28%).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8649" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Injection site necrosis also occurred more frequently in REBIF-treated patients (3% in the 44 mcg group and 1% in the 22 mcg group) than in placebo-treated patients (0) during the two years of therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8650" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>All events resolved with conservative management.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8651" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Injection site reactions including injection site pain, erythema, edema, cellulitis, abscess, and necrosis have been reported in the postmarketing setting.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8652" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Some occurred more than 2 years after initiation of REBIF.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8653" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Necrosis occurred at single and at multiple injection sites.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8654" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Some cases of injection site necrosis required treatment with intravenous antibiotics and surgical intervention (debridement and skin grafting).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8655" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patient understanding and use of aseptic self-injection techniques and procedures should be periodically evaluated, particularly if injection site necrosis has occurred.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8656" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients should be advised of the importance of rotating sites of injection with each dose and not reusing syringes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8657" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients should be advised against injecting an area which is inflamed, edematous, erythematous, ecchymotic, or has any other signs of infection.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8658" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>These signs should be reported to a healthcare professional immediately.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8659" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Decreased peripheral blood counts in all cell lines, including pancytopenia, have been reported in REBIF-treated patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8660" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In controlled clinical trials, leukopenia occurred at a higher frequency in REBIF-treated patients (36% in 44 mcg group and 28% in 22 mcg group) than in placebo-treated patients (14%) and at a higher frequency in REBIF-treated patients (6%) compared to the AVONEX-treated patients (&lt;1%).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8661" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Thrombocytopenia and anemia occurred more frequently in 44 mcg REBIF-treated patients (8% and 5%, respectively) than in placebo-treated patients (2% and 3%, respectively).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8662" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In a pooled analysis of 7 placebo controlled trials with REBIF doses of 22 mcg or 44 mcg, the rate of pancytopenia (in subjects with normal baseline values who developed laboratory values less than the lower limit of normal for all 3 hematology parameters simultaneously) was higher in the total REBIF group (5.5 per 1000 subject-year) than in the placebo group (1.2 per 1000 subject-year).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8663" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients should be monitored for symptoms or signs of decreased blood counts.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8664" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Monitoring of complete blood and differential white blood cell counts is also recommended.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8665" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Cases of thrombotic microangiopathy (TMA), including thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura and hemolytic uremic syndrome, some fatal, have been reported with interferon beta products, including REBIF.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8666" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Cases have been reported several weeks to years after starting interferon beta products.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8667" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Discontinue REBIF if clinical symptoms and laboratory findings consistent with TMA occur, and manage as clinically indicated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8668" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Caution should be exercised when administering REBIF to patients with pre-existing seizure disorders.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8669" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Seizures have been temporally associated with the use of beta interferons, including REBIF, in clinical trials and in postmarketing reports.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8670" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In addition to those laboratory tests normally required for monitoring patients with multiple sclerosis, blood cell counts and liver function tests are recommended at regular intervals (1, 3, and 6 months) following introduction of REBIF therapy and then periodically thereafter in the absence of clinical symptoms.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8671" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients with myelosuppression may require more intensive monitoring of complete blood cell counts, with differential and platelet counts.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8672" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>New or worsening thyroid abnormalities have developed in some patients treated with REBIF.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8673" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Thyroid function tests are recommended every 6 months in patients with a history of thyroid dysfunction or as clinically indicated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8674" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mechanism(s) by which REBIF (interferon beta-1a) exerts its therapeutic effects in patients with multiple sclerosis is unknown.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8675" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The relationships between serum interferon beta-1a levels and measurable pharmacodynamic activities to the mechanism(s) by which REBIF exerts its effects in multiple sclerosis are unknown.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8676" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No gender-related effects on pharmacodynamic parameters have been observed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8677" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacokinetics of REBIF (interferon beta-1a) in people with multiple sclerosis have not been evaluated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8678" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In healthy subjects, a single subcutaneous (sc) injection of 60 mcg of REBIF (liquid formulation) resulted in a peak serum concentration (Cmax) of 5.1 ± 1.7 IU/mL (mean ± SD), with a median time of peak serum concentration (Tmax) of 16 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8679" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The serum elimination half-life (t1/2) was 69 ± 37 hours, and the area under the serum concentration versus time curve (AUC) from zero to 96 hours was 294 ± 81 IU h/mL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8680" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following every other day sc injections in healthy subjects, an increase in AUC of approximately 240% was observed, suggesting that accumulation of interferon beta-1a occurs after repeat administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8681" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Total clearance is approximately 33-55 L/hour.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8682" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There have been no observed gender-related effects on pharmacokinetic parameters.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="8683" LabelDrug="Rebif" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Pharmacokinetics of REBIF in pediatric and geriatric patients or patients with renal or hepatic insufficiency have not been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="hepatotoxic products" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>