<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="STELARA" setid="c77a9664-e3bb-4023-b400-127aa53bca2b">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
STELARA ® is contraindicated in patients with clinically significant hypersensitivity to ustekinumab or to any of the excipients [see Warnings and Precautions (5.5) ]. Clinically significant hypersensitivity to ustekinumab or to any of the excipients. ( 4 )</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
Psoriasis Adult Subcutaneous Recommended Dosage ( 2.1 ): Weight Range (kilogram) Dosage Regimen less than or equal to 100 kg 45 mg administered subcutaneously initially and 4 weeks later, followed by 45 mg administered subcutaneously every 12 weeks greater than 100 kg 90 mg administered subcutaneously initially and 4 weeks later, followed by 90 mg administered subcutaneously every 12 weeks Psoriasis Adolescent (12 years and older) Subcutaneous Recommended Dosage ( 2.1 ): Weight based dosing is recommended at the initial dose, 4 weeks later, then every 12 weeks thereafter. Weight Range (kilogram) Dosage Regimen less than 60 kg 0.75 mg/kg 60 kg to 100 kg 45 mg greater than 100 kg 90 mg Psoriatic Arthritis Adult Subcutaneous Recommended Dosage ( 2.2 ): The recommended dosage is 45 mg administered subcutaneously initially and 4 weeks later, followed by 45 mg administered subcutaneously every 12 weeks. For patients with co-existent moderate-to-severe plaque psoriasis weighing greater than 100 kg, the recommended dosage is 90 mg administered subcutaneously initially and 4 weeks later, followed by 90 mg administered subcutaneously every 12 weeks. Crohn's Disease Initial Adult Intravenous Recommended Dosage ( 2.3 ): A single intravenous infusion using weight-based dosing: Weight Range (kilogram) Recommended Dosage up to 55 kg 260 mg (2 vials) greater than 55 kg to 85 kg 390 mg (3 vials) greater than 85 kg 520 mg (4 vials) Crohn's Disease Maintenance Adult Subcutaneous Recommended Dosage ( 2.3 ): A subcutaneous 90 mg dose 8 weeks after the initial intravenous dose, then every 8 weeks thereafter. Subcutaneous Adult Dosage Regimen For patients weighing 100 kg or less, the recommended dose is 45 mg initially and 4 weeks later, followed by 45 mg every 12 weeks. For patients weighing more than 100 kg, the recommended dose is 90 mg initially and 4 weeks later, followed by 90 mg every 12 weeks. In subjects weighing more than 100 kg, 45 mg was also shown to be efficacious. However, 90 mg resulted in greater efficacy in these subjects [see Clinical Studies (14) ] . Subcutaneous Adolescent Dosage Regimen Administer STELARA ® subcutaneously at Weeks 0 and 4, then every 12 weeks thereafter. The recommended dose of STELARA ® for adolescents (12–17 years old) based on body weight is shown below (Table 1). Table 1: Recommended Dose of STELARA ® for Subcutaneous Injection in Adolescent Patients with Psoriasis Body Weight of Patient at the Time of Dosing Recommended Dose less than 60 kg 0.75 mg/kg 60 kg to 100 kg 45 mg more than 100 kg 90 mg For adolescent patients weighing less than 60 kg, the administration volume for the recommended dose (0.75 mg/kg) is shown in Table 2; withdraw the appropriate volume from the single-dose vial. Table 2: Injection volumes of STELARA ® 45 mg/0.5mL single-dose vials for adolescent psoriasis patients less than 60 kg Body Weight (kg) at the time of dosing Dose (mg) Volume of injection (mL) 30 22.5 0.25 31 23.3 0.26 32 24.0 0.27 33 24.8 0.27 34 25.5 0.28 35 26.3 0.29 36 27.0 0.30 37 27.8 0.31 38 28.5 0.32 39 29.3 0.32 40 30.0 0.33 41 30.8 0.34 42 31.5 0.35 43 32.3 0.36 44 33.0 0.37 45 33.8 0.37 46 34.5 0.38 47 35.3 0.39 48 36.0 0.40 49 36.8 0.41 50 37.5 0.42 51 38.3 0.42 52 39.0 0.43 53 39.8 0.44 54 40.5 0.45 55 41.3 0.46 56 42.0 0.46 57 42.8 0.47 58 43.5 0.48 59 44.3 0.49 Subcutaneous Adult Dosage Regimen The recommended dose is 45 mg initially and 4 weeks later, followed by 45 mg every 12 weeks. For patients with co-existent moderate-to-severe plaque psoriasis weighing more than 100 kg, the recommended dose is 90 mg initially and 4 weeks later, followed by 90 mg every 12 weeks. Intravenous Induction Adult Dosage Regimen A single intravenous infusion dose of STELARA ® using the weight-based dosage regimen specified in Table 3 [see Instructions for dilution of STELARA® 130 mg vial for intravenous infusion (2.6) ] . Table 3: Initial Intravenous Dosage of STELARA ® Body Weight of Patient at the time of dosing Dose Number of 130 mg/26 mL (5 mg/mL) STELARA ® vials 55 kg or less 260 mg 2 more than 55 kg to 85 kg 390 mg 3 more than 85 kg 520 mg 4 Subcutaneous Maintenance Adult Dosage Regimen The recommended maintenance dosage is a subcutaneous 90 mg dose administered 8 weeks after the initial intravenous dose, then every 8 weeks thereafter. STELARA ® is intended for use under the guidance and supervision of a physician. STELARA ® should only be administered to patients who will be closely monitored and have regular follow-up visits with a physician. The appropriate dose should be determined by a healthcare provider using the patient's current weight at the time of dosing. In adolescent patients, it is recommended that STELARA ® be administered by a health care provider. If a physician determines that it is appropriate, a patient may self-inject or a caregiver may inject STELARA ® after proper training in subcutaneous injection technique. Patients should be instructed to follow the directions provided in the Medication Guide [see Medication Guide ] . The needle cover on the prefilled syringe contains dry natural rubber (a derivative of latex). The needle cover should not be handled by persons sensitive to latex. It is recommended that each injection be administered at a different anatomic location (such as upper arms, gluteal regions, thighs, or any quadrant of abdomen) than the previous injection, and not into areas where the skin is tender, bruised, erythematous, or indurated. When using the single-dose vial, a 1 mL syringe with a 27 gauge, ½ inch needle is recommended. Prior to administration, visually inspect STELARA ® for particulate matter and discoloration. STELARA ® is a colorless to light yellow solution and may contain a few small translucent or white particles. Do not use STELARA ® if it is discolored or cloudy, or if other particulate matter is present. STELARA ® does not contain preservatives; therefore, discard any unused product remaining in the vial and/or syringe. Refer to the diagram below for the provided instructions. To prevent premature activation of the needle safety guard, do not touch the NEEDLE GUARD ACTIVATION CLIPS at any time during use. Hold the BODY and remove the NEEDLE COVER. Do not hold the PLUNGER or PLUNGER HEAD while removing the NEEDLE COVER or the PLUNGER may move. Do not use the prefilled syringe if it is dropped without the NEEDLE COVER in place . Inject STELARA ® subcutaneously as recommended [see Dosage and Administration (2.1 , 2.2 , 2.3) ] . Inject all of the medication by pushing in the PLUNGER until the PLUNGER HEAD is completely between the needle guard wings. Injection of the entire prefilled syringe contents is necessary to activate the needle guard . After injection, maintain the pressure on the PLUNGER HEAD and remove the needle from the skin. Slowly take your thumb off the PLUNGER HEAD to allow the empty syringe to move up until the entire needle is covered by the needle guard, as shown by the illustration below: Used syringes should be placed in a puncture-resistant container. Image Image Image STELARA ® solution for intravenous infusion must be diluted, prepared and infused by a healthcare professional using aseptic technique. Calculate the dose and the number of STELARA ® vials needed based on patient weight (Table 3). Each 26 mL vial of STELARA ® contains 130 mg of ustekinumab. Withdraw, and then discard a volume of the 0.9% Sodium Chloride Injection, USP from the 250 mL infusion bag equal to the volume of STELARA ® to be added (discard 26 mL sodium chloride for each vial of STELARA ® needed, for 2 vials- discard 52 mL, for 3 vials- discard 78 mL, 4 vials- discard 104 mL). Withdraw 26 mL of STELARA ® from each vial needed and add it to the 250 mL infusion bag. The final volume in the infusion bag should be 250 mL. Gently mix. Visually inspect the diluted solution before infusion. Do not use if visibly opaque particles, discoloration or foreign particles are observed. Infuse the diluted solution over a period of at least one hour. Once diluted, the infusion solution may be stored for up to four hours prior to infusion. Use only an infusion set with an in-line, sterile, non-pyrogenic, low protein-binding filter (pore size 0.2 micrometer). Do not infuse STELARA ® concomitantly in the same intravenous line with other agents. STELARA ® does not contain preservatives. Each vial is for single use only. Discard any remaining solution. Dispose any unused medicinal product in accordance with local requirements. Storage If necessary, the diluted infusion solution may be stored for up to 4 hours at room temperature up to 25°C (77°F). Do not freeze. Discard any unused portion of the infusion solution.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
Avoid use of live vaccines with STELARA ® [see Warnings and Precautions (5.7) ] . In psoriasis studies the safety of STELARA ® in combination with immunosuppressive agents or phototherapy has not been evaluated [see Warnings and Precautions (5.8) ] . In psoriatic arthritis studies, concomitant methotrexate use did not appear to influence the safety or efficacy of STELARA ® . In Crohn's disease studies, immunomodulators (6-mercaptopurine, azathioprine, methotrexate) were used concomitantly in approximately 30% of patients and corticosteroids were used concomitantly in approximately 40% of patients. Use of these concomitant therapies did not appear to influence the overall safety or efficacy of STELARA ® . The formation of CYP450 enzymes can be altered by increased levels of certain cytokines (e.g., IL-1, IL-6, IL-10, TNFα, IFN) during chronic inflammation. Thus, STELARA ® , an antagonist of IL-12 and IL-23, could normalize the formation of CYP450 enzymes. Upon initiation of STELARA ® in patients who are receiving concomitant CYP450 substrates, particularly those with a narrow therapeutic index, monitoring for therapeutic effect (e.g., for warfarin) or drug concentration (e.g., for cyclosporine) should be considered and the individual dose of the drug adjusted as needed [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3) ] . STELARA ® has not been evaluated in patients who have undergone allergy immunotherapy. STELARA ® may decrease the protective effect of allergen immunotherapy (decrease tolerance) which may increase the risk of an allergic reaction to a dose of allergen immunotherapy. Therefore, caution should be exercised in patients receiving or who have received allergen immunotherapy, particularly for anaphylaxis.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
Infections: Serious infections have occurred. Do not start STELARA ® during any clinically important active infection. If a serious infection or clinically significant infection develops, consider discontinuing STELARA ® until the infection resolves. ( 5.1 ) Theoretical Risk for Particular Infections: Serious infections from mycobacteria, salmonella and Bacillus Calmette-Guerin (BCG) vaccinations have been reported in patients genetically deficient in IL-12/IL-23. Diagnostic tests for these infections should be considered as dictated by clinical circumstances. ( 5.2 ) Tuberculosis (TB): Evaluate patients for TB prior to initiating treatment with STELARA ® . Initiate treatment of latent TB before administering STELARA ® . ( 5.3 ) Malignancies: STELARA ® may increase risk of malignancy. The safety of STELARA ® in patients with a history of or a known malignancy has not been evaluated. ( 5.4 ) Hypersensitivity Reactions: Anaphylaxis or other clinically significant hypersensitivity reactions may occur. ( 5.5 ) Reversible Posterior Leukoencephalopathy Syndrome (RPLS): One case was reported. If suspected, treat promptly and discontinue STELARA ® . ( 5.6 ) Noninfectious Pneumonia: Cases of interstitial pneumonia, eosinophilic pneumonia and cryptogenic organizing pneumonia have been reported during post-approval use of STELARA ® . If diagnosis is confirmed, discontinue STELARA ® and institute appropriate treatment. ( 5.9 ) STELARA ® may increase the risk of infections and reactivation of latent infections. Serious bacterial, fungal, and viral infections were observed in subjects receiving STELARA ® [see Adverse Reactions (6.1) ] . Serious infections requiring hospitalization occurred in patients with psoriasis, psoriatic arthritis and Crohn's disease in clinical studies. In patients with psoriasis, serious infections included diverticulitis, cellulitis, pneumonia, appendicitis, cholecystitis, sepsis, osteomyelitis, viral infections, gastroenteritis and urinary tract infections. In patients with psoriatic arthritis, serious infections included cholecystitis. In patients with Crohn's disease, serious or other clinically significant infections included anal abscess, gastroenteritis, ophthalmic herpes, pneumonia, and listeria meningitis. Treatment with STELARA ® should not be initiated in patients with any clinically important active infection until the infection resolves or is adequately treated. Consider the risks and benefits of treatment prior to initiating use of STELARA ® in patients with a chronic infection or a history of recurrent infection. Instruct patients to seek medical advice if signs or symptoms suggestive of an infection occur while on treatment with STELARA ® and consider discontinuing STELARA ® for serious or clinically significant infections until the infection resolves or is adequately treated. Individuals genetically deficient in IL-12/IL-23 are particularly vulnerable to disseminated infections from mycobacteria (including nontuberculous, environmental mycobacteria), salmonella (including nontyphi strains), and Bacillus Calmette-Guerin (BCG) vaccinations. Serious infections and fatal outcomes have been reported in such patients. It is not known whether patients with pharmacologic blockade of IL-12/IL-23 from treatment with STELARA ® may be susceptible to these types of infections. Appropriate diagnostic testing should be considered, e.g., tissue culture, stool culture, as dictated by clinical circumstances. Evaluate patients for tuberculosis infection prior to initiating treatment with STELARA ® . Do not administer STELARA ® to patients with active tuberculosis infection. Initiate treatment of latent tuberculosis prior to administering STELARA ® . Consider anti-tuberculosis therapy prior to initiation of STELARA ® in patients with a past history of latent or active tuberculosis in whom an adequate course of treatment cannot be confirmed. Closely monitor patients receiving STELARA ® for signs and symptoms of active tuberculosis during and after treatment. STELARA ® is an immunosuppressant and may increase the risk of malignancy. Malignancies were reported among subjects who received STELARA ® in clinical studies [see Adverse Reactions (6.1) ] . In rodent models, inhibition of IL-12/IL-23p40 increased the risk of malignancy [see Nonclinical Toxicology (13) ] . The safety of STELARA ® has not been evaluated in patients who have a history of malignancy or who have a known malignancy. There have been post-marketing reports of the rapid appearance of multiple cutaneous squamous cell carcinomas in patients receiving STELARA ® who had pre-existing risk factors for developing non-melanoma skin cancer. All patients receiving STELARA ® should be monitored for the appearance of non-melanoma skin cancer. Patients greater than 60 years of age, those with a medical history of prolonged immunosuppressant therapy and those with a history of PUVA treatment should be followed closely [see Adverse Reactions (6.1) ] . Hypersensitivity reactions, including anaphylaxis and angioedema, have been reported with STELARA ® [see Adverse Reactions (6.1 , 6.3) ] . If an anaphylactic or other clinically significant hypersensitivity reaction occurs, institute appropriate therapy and discontinue STELARA ® . One case of reversible posterior leukoencephalopathy syndrome (RPLS) was observed in clinical studies of psoriasis and psoriatic arthritis. The subject, who had received 12 doses of STELARA ® over approximately two years, presented with headache, seizures and confusion. No additional STELARA ® injections were administered and the subject fully recovered with appropriate treatment. No cases of RPLS were observed in clinical studies of Crohn's disease. RPLS is a neurological disorder, which is not caused by demyelination or a known infectious agent. RPLS can present with headache, seizures, confusion and visual disturbances. Conditions with which it has been associated include preeclampsia, eclampsia, acute hypertension, cytotoxic agents and immunosuppressive therapy. Fatal outcomes have been reported. If RPLS is suspected, administer appropriate treatment and discontinue STELARA ® . Prior to initiating therapy with STELARA ® , patients should receive all age-appropriate immunizations as recommended by current immunization guidelines. Patients being treated with STELARA ® should not receive live vaccines. BCG vaccines should not be given during treatment with STELARA ® or for one year prior to initiating treatment or one year following discontinuation of treatment. Caution is advised when administering live vaccines to household contacts of patients receiving STELARA ® because of the potential risk for shedding from the household contact and transmission to patient. Non-live vaccinations received during a course of STELARA ® may not elicit an immune response sufficient to prevent disease. In clinical studies of psoriasis the safety of STELARA ® in combination with other immunosuppressive agents or phototherapy was not evaluated. Ultraviolet-induced skin cancers developed earlier and more frequently in mice genetically manipulated to be deficient in both IL-12 and IL-23 or IL-12 alone [see Nonclinical Toxicology (13.1) ] . Cases of interstitial pneumonia, eosinophilic pneumonia and cryptogenic organizing pneumonia have been reported during post-approval use of STELARA ® . Clinical presentations included cough, dyspnea, and interstitial infiltrates following one to three doses. Serious outcomes have included respiratory failure and prolonged hospitalization. Patients improved with discontinuation of therapy and in certain cases administration of corticosteroids. If diagnosis is confirmed, discontinue STELARA ® and institute appropriate treatment [see Postmarketing Experience (6.3) ] .</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Ustekinumab is a human IgG1қ monoclonal antibody that binds with specificity to the p40 protein subunit used by both the IL-12 and IL-23 cytokines. IL-12 and IL-23 are naturally occurring cytokines that are involved in inflammatory and immune responses, such as natural killer cell activation and CD4+ T-cell differentiation and activation. In in vitro models, ustekinumab was shown to disrupt IL-12 and IL-23 mediated signaling and cytokine cascades by disrupting the interaction of these cytokines with a shared cell-surface receptor chain, IL-12Rβ1. The cytokines IL-12 and IL-23 have been implicated as important contributors to the chronic inflammation that is a hallmark of Crohn's disease. In animal models of colitis, genetic absence or antibody blockade of the p40 subunit of IL-12 and IL-23, the target of ustekinumab, was shown to be protective. In a small exploratory study, a decrease was observed in the expression of mRNA of its molecular targets IL-12 and IL-23 in lesional skin biopsies measured at baseline and up to two weeks post-treatment in subjects with psoriasis. Absorption In adult subjects with psoriasis, the median time to reach the maximum serum concentration (T max ) was 13.5 days and 7 days, respectively, after a single subcutaneous administration of 45 mg (N=22) and 90 mg (N=24) of ustekinumab. In healthy subjects (N=30), the median T max value (8.5 days) following a single subcutaneous administration of 90 mg of ustekinumab was comparable to that observed in subjects with psoriasis. Following multiple subcutaneous doses of STELARA ® in adult subjects with psoriasis, steady-state serum concentrations of ustekinumab were achieved by Week 28. The mean (±SD) steady-state trough serum ustekinumab concentrations were 0.69 ± 0.69 mcg/mL for patients less than or equal to 100 kg receiving a 45 mg dose and 0.74 ± 0.78 mcg/mL for patients greater than 100 kg receiving a 90 mg dose. There was no apparent accumulation in serum ustekinumab concentration over time when given subcutaneously every 12 weeks. In patients with Crohn's disease, following the recommended intravenous induction dose, mean ±SD peak serum ustekinumab concentration was 125.2 ± 33.6 mcg/mL. Starting at Week 8, the recommended subcutaneous maintenance dosing of 90 mg ustekinumab was administered every 8 weeks. Steady state ustekinumab concentration was achieved by the start of the second maintenance dose. There was no apparent accumulation in ustekinumab concentration over time when given subcutaneously every 8 weeks. Mean ±SD steady-state trough concentration was 2.51 ± 2.06 mcg/mL for 90 mg ustekinumab administered every 8 weeks. Distribution In a population pharmacokinetic analysis of ustekinumab, the volume of distribution of the central compartment was 2.74 L (95% CI: 2.69, 2.78), and the total volume of distribution at steady-state was 4.62 L in patients with Crohn's disease. Elimination The mean (±SD) half-life ranged from 14.9 ± 4.6 to 45.6 ± 80.2 days across all psoriasis studies following subcutaneous administration. In a population pharmacokinetic analysis of ustekinumab, the clearance was 0.19 L/day (95% CI: 0.185, 0.197) with an estimated median terminal half-life of approximately 19 days in patients with Crohn's disease. Metabolism The metabolic pathway of ustekinumab has not been characterized. As a human IgG1κ monoclonal antibody, ustekinumab is expected to be degraded into small peptides and amino acids via catabolic pathways in the same manner as endogenous IgG. Specific Populations Weight When given the same dose, subjects with psoriasis or psoriatic arthritis weighing more than 100 kg had lower median serum ustekinumab concentrations compared with those subjects weighing 100 kg or less. The median trough serum concentrations of ustekinumab in subjects of higher weight (greater than 100 kg) in the 90 mg group were comparable to those in subjects of lower weight (100 kg or less) in the 45 mg group. Age: Geriatric Population A population pharmacokinetic analysis (N=106/1937 patients with psoriasis greater than or equal to 65 years old) was performed to evaluate the effect of age on the pharmacokinetics of ustekinumab. There were no apparent changes in pharmacokinetic parameters (clearance and volume of distribution) in subjects older than 65 years old. Age: Pediatric Population Following multiple recommended doses of STELARA ® in adolescent subjects 12 to 17 years of age with psoriasis, steady-state serum concentrations of ustekinumab were achieved by Week 28. At Week 28, the mean ±SD steady-state trough serum ustekinumab concentration was 0.54 ± 0.43 mcg/mL. Drug Interaction Studies The effects of IL-12 or IL-23 on the regulation of CYP450 enzymes were evaluated in an in vitro study using human hepatocytes, which showed that IL-12 and/or IL-23 at levels of 10 ng/mL did not alter human CYP450 enzyme activities (CYP1A2, 2B6, 2C9, 2C19, 2D6, or 3A4). However, the clinical relevance of in vitro data has not been established [see Drug Interactions (7.3) ] . No in vivo drug interaction studies have been conducted with STELARA ® . Population pharmacokinetic data analyses indicated that the clearance of ustekinumab was not impacted by concomitant MTX, NSAIDs, and oral corticosteroids, or prior exposure to a TNF blocker in patients with psoriatic arthritis.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="2365" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>STELARA® is contraindicated in patients with clinically significant hypersensitivity to ustekinumab or to any of the excipients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2366" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Clinically significant hypersensitivity to ustekinumab or to any of the excipients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2367" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Psoriasis Adult Subcutaneous Recommended Dosage (2.1): Weight Range (kilogram) Dosage Regimen less than or equal to 100 kg 45 mg administered subcutaneously initially and 4 weeks later, followed by 45 mg administered subcutaneously every 12 weeks greater than 100 kg 90 mg administered subcutaneously initially and 4 weeks later, followed by 90 mg administered subcutaneously every 12 weeks Psoriasis Adolescent (12 years and older) Subcutaneous Recommended Dosage (2.1): Weight based dosing is recommended at the initial dose, 4 weeks later, then every 12 weeks thereafter.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2368" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Weight Range (kilogram) Dosage Regimen less than 60 kg 0.75 mg/kg 60 kg to 100 kg 45 mg greater than 100 kg 90 mg Psoriatic Arthritis Adult Subcutaneous Recommended Dosage (2.2): The recommended dosage is 45 mg administered subcutaneously initially and 4 weeks later, followed by 45 mg administered subcutaneously every 12 weeks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2369" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For patients with co-existent moderate-to-severe plaque psoriasis weighing greater than 100 kg, the recommended dosage is 90 mg administered subcutaneously initially and 4 weeks later, followed by 90 mg administered subcutaneously every 12 weeks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2370" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Crohn's Disease Initial Adult Intravenous Recommended Dosage (2.3): A single intravenous infusion using weight-based dosing: Weight Range (kilogram) Recommended Dosage up to 55 kg 260 mg (2 vials) greater than 55 kg to 85 kg 390 mg (3 vials) greater than 85 kg 520 mg (4 vials) Crohn's Disease Maintenance Adult Subcutaneous Recommended Dosage (2.3): A subcutaneous 90 mg dose 8 weeks after the initial intravenous dose, then every 8 weeks thereafter.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2371" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Subcutaneous Adult Dosage Regimen For patients weighing 100 kg or less, the recommended dose is 45 mg initially and 4 weeks later, followed by 45 mg every 12 weeks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2372" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For patients weighing more than 100 kg, the recommended dose is 90 mg initially and 4 weeks later, followed by 90 mg every 12 weeks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2373" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In subjects weighing more than 100 kg, 45 mg was also shown to be efficacious.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2374" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>However, 90 mg resulted in greater efficacy in these subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2375" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Subcutaneous Adolescent Dosage Regimen Administer STELARA® subcutaneously at Weeks 0 and 4, then every 12 weeks thereafter.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2376" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommended dose of STELARA® for adolescents (12–17 years old) based on body weight is shown below (Table 1).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2377" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Table 1: Recommended Dose of STELARA® for Subcutaneous Injection in Adolescent Patients with Psoriasis Body Weight of Patient at the Time of Dosing Recommended Dose less than 60 kg 0.75 mg/kg 60 kg to 100 kg 45 mg more than 100 kg 90 mg For adolescent patients weighing less than 60 kg, the administration volume for the recommended dose (0.75 mg/kg) is shown in Table 2; withdraw the appropriate volume from the single-dose vial.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2378" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Table 2: Injection volumes of STELARA® 45 mg/0.5mL single-dose vials for adolescent psoriasis patients less than 60 kg Body Weight (kg) at the time of dosing Dose (mg) Volume of injection (mL) 30 22.5 0.25 31 23.3 0.26 32 24.0 0.27 33 24.8 0.27 34 25.5 0.28 35 26.3 0.29 36 27.0 0.30 37 27.8 0.31 38 28.5 0.32 39 29.3 0.32 40 30.0 0.33 41 30.8 0.34 42 31.5 0.35 43 32.3 0.36 44 33.0 0.37 45 33.8 0.37 46 34.5 0.38 47 35.3 0.39 48 36.0 0.40 49 36.8 0.41 50 37.5 0.42 51 38.3 0.42 52 39.0 0.43 53 39.8 0.44 54 40.5 0.45 55 41.3 0.46 56 42.0 0.46 57 42.8 0.47 58 43.5 0.48 59 44.3 0.49 Subcutaneous Adult Dosage Regimen The recommended dose is 45 mg initially and 4 weeks later, followed by 45 mg every 12 weeks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2379" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For patients with co-existent moderate-to-severe plaque psoriasis weighing more than 100 kg, the recommended dose is 90 mg initially and 4 weeks later, followed by 90 mg every 12 weeks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2380" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Intravenous Induction Adult Dosage Regimen A single intravenous infusion dose of STELARA® using the weight-based dosage regimen specified in Table 3.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2381" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Table 3: Initial Intravenous Dosage of STELARA® Body Weight of Patient at the time of dosing Dose Number of 130 mg/26 mL (5 mg/mL) STELARA® vials 55 kg or less 260 mg 2 more than 55 kg to 85 kg 390 mg 3 more than 85 kg 520 mg 4 Subcutaneous Maintenance Adult Dosage Regimen The recommended maintenance dosage is a subcutaneous 90 mg dose administered 8 weeks after the initial intravenous dose, then every 8 weeks thereafter.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2382" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>STELARA® is intended for use under the guidance and supervision of a physician.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2383" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>STELARA® should only be administered to patients who will be closely monitored and have regular follow-up visits with a physician.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2384" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The appropriate dose should be determined by a healthcare provider using the patient's current weight at the time of dosing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2385" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In adolescent patients, it is recommended that STELARA® be administered by a health care provider.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2386" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If a physician determines that it is appropriate, a patient may self-inject or a caregiver may inject STELARA® after proper training in subcutaneous injection technique.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2387" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Patients should be instructed to follow the directions provided in the Medication Guide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2388" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The needle cover on the prefilled syringe contains dry natural rubber (a derivative of latex).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2389" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The needle cover should not be handled by persons sensitive to latex.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2390" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>It is recommended that each injection be administered at a different anatomic location (such as upper arms, gluteal regions, thighs, or any quadrant of abdomen) than the previous injection, and not into areas where the skin is tender, bruised, erythematous, or indurated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2391" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>When using the single-dose vial, a 1 mL syringe with a 27 gauge, ½ inch needle is recommended.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2392" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Prior to administration, visually inspect STELARA® for particulate matter and discoloration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2393" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>STELARA® is a colorless to light yellow solution and may contain a few small translucent or white particles.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2394" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not use STELARA® if it is discolored or cloudy, or if other particulate matter is present.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2395" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>STELARA® does not contain preservatives; therefore, discard any unused product remaining in the vial and/or syringe.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2396" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Refer to the diagram below for the provided instructions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2397" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>To prevent premature activation of the needle safety guard, do not touch the NEEDLE GUARD ACTIVATION CLIPS at any time during use.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2398" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Hold the BODY and remove the NEEDLE COVER.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2399" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not hold the PLUNGER or PLUNGER HEAD while removing the NEEDLE COVER or the PLUNGER may move.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2400" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not use the prefilled syringe if it is dropped without the NEEDLE COVER in place.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2401" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Inject STELARA® subcutaneously as recommended.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2402" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Inject all of the medication by pushing in the PLUNGER until the PLUNGER HEAD is completely between the needle guard wings.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2403" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Injection of the entire prefilled syringe contents is necessary to activate the needle guard.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2404" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>After injection, maintain the pressure on the PLUNGER HEAD and remove the needle from the skin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2405" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Slowly take your thumb off the PLUNGER HEAD to allow the empty syringe to move up until the entire needle is covered by the needle guard, as shown by the illustration below: Used syringes should be placed in a puncture-resistant container.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2406" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Image Image Image STELARA® solution for intravenous infusion must be diluted, prepared and infused by a healthcare professional using aseptic technique.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2407" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Calculate the dose and the number of STELARA® vials needed based on patient weight (Table 3).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2408" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Each 26 mL vial of STELARA® contains 130 mg of ustekinumab.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2409" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Withdraw, and then discard a volume of the 0.9% Sodium Chloride Injection, USP from the 250 mL infusion bag equal to the volume of STELARA® to be added (discard 26 mL sodium chloride for each vial of STELARA® needed, for 2 vials- discard 52 mL, for 3 vials- discard 78 mL, 4 vials- discard 104 mL).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2410" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Withdraw 26 mL of STELARA® from each vial needed and add it to the 250 mL infusion bag.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2411" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The final volume in the infusion bag should be 250 mL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2412" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Visually inspect the diluted solution before infusion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2413" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not use if visibly opaque particles, discoloration or foreign particles are observed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2414" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Infuse the diluted solution over a period of at least one hour.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2415" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Once diluted, the infusion solution may be stored for up to four hours prior to infusion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2416" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Use only an infusion set with an in-line, sterile, non-pyrogenic, low protein-binding filter (pore size 0.2 micrometer).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2417" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not infuse STELARA® concomitantly in the same intravenous line with other agents.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2418" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dispose any unused medicinal product in accordance with local requirements.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2419" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Storage If necessary, the diluted infusion solution may be stored for up to 4 hours at room temperature up to 25°C (77°F).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2420" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Discard any unused portion of the infusion solution.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2421" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Avoid use of live vaccines with STELARA®.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M1" type="Trigger" span="0 5" str="Avoid"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="13 13" str="live vaccines" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M1" precipitant="M2"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2422" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>In psoriasis studies the safety of STELARA® in combination with immunosuppressive agents or phototherapy has not been evaluated.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M3" type="Trigger" span="25 6;105 22" str="safety | has not been evaluated"/>
<Mention id="M4" type="Precipitant" span="64 24" str="immunosuppressive agents" code="N0000175550"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M3" precipitant="M4"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2423" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>In psoriatic arthritis studies, concomitant methotrexate use did not appear to influence the safety or efficacy of STELARA®.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2424" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>In Crohn's disease studies, immunomodulators (6-mercaptopurine, azathioprine, methotrexate) were used concomitantly in approximately 30% of patients and corticosteroids were used concomitantly in approximately 40% of patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2425" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Use of these concomitant therapies did not appear to influence the overall safety or efficacy of STELARA®.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2426" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The formation of CYP450 enzymes can be altered by increased levels of certain cytokines (e.g., IL-1, IL-6, IL-10, TNFα, IFN) during chronic inflammation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2427" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Thus, STELARA®, an antagonist of IL-12 and IL-23, could normalize the formation of CYP450 enzymes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2428" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Upon initiation of STELARA® in patients who are receiving concomitant CYP450 substrates, particularly those with a narrow therapeutic index, monitoring for therapeutic effect (e.g., for warfarin) or drug concentration (e.g., for cyclosporine) should be considered and the individual dose of the drug adjusted as needed.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M11" type="Trigger" span="141 10" str="monitoring "/>
<Mention id="M12" type="Trigger" span="283 4;300 8" str=" dose | adjusted"/>
<Mention id="M7" type="Precipitant" span="229 12" str="cyclosporine" code="83HN0GTJ6D | N0000007346"/>
<Mention id="M10" type="Precipitant" span="70 17" str="CYP450 substrates" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M13" type="Precipitant" span="186 8" str="warfarin" code="5Q7ZVV76EI | N0000006403"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M11;M12" precipitant="M7"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M11;M12" precipitant="M10"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M11;M12" precipitant="M13"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2429" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>STELARA® has not been evaluated in patients who have undergone allergy immunotherapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2430" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>STELARA® may decrease the protective effect of allergen immunotherapy (decrease tolerance) which may increase the risk of an allergic reaction to a dose of allergen immunotherapy.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M14" type="Trigger" span="71 18" str="decrease tolerance"/>
<Mention id="M21" type="Precipitant" span="47 22" str="allergen immunotherapy" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M16" type="SpecificInteraction" span="47 8;71 18" str="allergen | decrease tolerance" code="102460003: Decreased tolerance (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M17" type="Trigger" span="101 17" str="increase the risk"/>
<Mention id="M19" type="SpecificInteraction" span="125 17" str="allergic reaction" code="419076005: Allergic reaction (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M20" type="Trigger" span="13 8;37 6" str="decrease | effect"/>
<Mention id="M22" type="SpecificInteraction" span="13 56" str="decrease the protective effect of allergen immunotherapy" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M14" precipitant="M21" effect="M16" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M17" precipitant="M21" effect="M19" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M20" precipitant="M21" effect="M22" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2431" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Therefore, caution should be exercised in patients receiving or who have received allergen immunotherapy, particularly for anaphylaxis.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M23" type="Trigger" span="11 7" str="caution"/>
<Mention id="M24" type="Precipitant" span="82 22" str="allergen immunotherapy" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M23" precipitant="M24"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2432" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Infections: Serious infections have occurred.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2433" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Do not start STELARA® during any clinically important active infection.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2434" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If a serious infection or clinically significant infection develops, consider discontinuing STELARA® until the infection resolves.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2435" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Theoretical Risk for Particular Infections: Serious infections from mycobacteria, salmonella and Bacillus Calmette-Guerin (BCG) vaccinations have been reported in patients genetically deficient in IL-12/IL-23.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M52" type="Trigger" span="12 8" str="Risk for"/>
<Mention id="M29" type="Precipitant" span="97 43" str="Bacillus Calmette-Guerin (BCG) vaccinations" code="N0000183904"/>
<Mention id="M51" type="SpecificInteraction" span="21 21" str="Particular Infections" code="40733004: Infectious disease (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M54" type="SpecificInteraction" span="44 18" str="Serious infections" code="40733004: Infectious disease (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M35" type="Precipitant" span="97 24;128 12" str="Bacillus Calmette-Guerin | vaccinations" code="N0000183904"/>
<Mention id="M41" type="Precipitant" span="123 3;128 12" str="BCG | vaccinations" code="N0000183904"/>
<Mention id="M47" type="Precipitant" span="68 12;128 12" str="mycobacteria | vaccinations" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M53" type="Precipitant" span="82 10;128 12" str="salmonella | vaccinations" code="N0000183901"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M52" precipitant="M29" effect="M51" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M52" precipitant="M29" effect="M54" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M52" precipitant="M35" effect="M51" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M52" precipitant="M35" effect="M54" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M52" precipitant="M41" effect="M51" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M52" precipitant="M41" effect="M54" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M52" precipitant="M47" effect="M51" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M52" precipitant="M47" effect="M54" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M52" precipitant="M53" effect="M51" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M52" precipitant="M53" effect="M54" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2436" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Diagnostic tests for these infections should be considered as dictated by clinical circumstances.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2437" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Tuberculosis (TB): Evaluate patients for TB prior to initiating treatment with STELARA®.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2438" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Initiate treatment of latent TB before administering STELARA®.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2439" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Malignancies: STELARA® may increase risk of malignancy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2440" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The safety of STELARA® in patients with a history of or a known malignancy has not been evaluated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2441" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hypersensitivity Reactions: Anaphylaxis or other clinically significant hypersensitivity reactions may occur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2442" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Reversible Posterior Leukoencephalopathy Syndrome (RPLS): One case was reported.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2443" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If suspected, treat promptly and discontinue STELARA®.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2444" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Noninfectious Pneumonia: Cases of interstitial pneumonia, eosinophilic pneumonia and cryptogenic organizing pneumonia have been reported during post-approval use of STELARA®.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2445" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If diagnosis is confirmed, discontinue STELARA® and institute appropriate treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2446" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>STELARA® may increase the risk of infections and reactivation of latent infections.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2447" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Serious bacterial, fungal, and viral infections were observed in subjects receiving STELARA®.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2448" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Serious infections requiring hospitalization occurred in patients with psoriasis, psoriatic arthritis and Crohn's disease in clinical studies.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2449" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In patients with psoriasis, serious infections included diverticulitis, cellulitis, pneumonia, appendicitis, cholecystitis, sepsis, osteomyelitis, viral infections, gastroenteritis and urinary tract infections.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2450" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In patients with psoriatic arthritis, serious infections included cholecystitis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2451" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In patients with Crohn's disease, serious or other clinically significant infections included anal abscess, gastroenteritis, ophthalmic herpes, pneumonia, and listeria meningitis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2452" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Treatment with STELARA® should not be initiated in patients with any clinically important active infection until the infection resolves or is adequately treated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2453" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Consider the risks and benefits of treatment prior to initiating use of STELARA® in patients with a chronic infection or a history of recurrent infection.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2454" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Instruct patients to seek medical advice if signs or symptoms suggestive of an infection occur while on treatment with STELARA® and consider discontinuing STELARA® for serious or clinically significant infections until the infection resolves or is adequately treated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2455" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Individuals genetically deficient in IL-12/IL-23 are particularly vulnerable to disseminated infections from mycobacteria (including nontuberculous, environmental mycobacteria), salmonella (including nontyphi strains), and Bacillus Calmette-Guerin (BCG) vaccinations.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M67" type="Trigger" span="66 13" str="vulnerable to"/>
<Mention id="M56" type="Precipitant" span="223 43" str="Bacillus Calmette-Guerin (BCG) vaccinations" code="N0000183904"/>
<Mention id="M69" type="SpecificInteraction" span="80 23" str="disseminated infections" code="40733004: Infectious disease (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M59" type="Precipitant" span="223 24;254 12" str="Bacillus Calmette-Guerin | vaccinations" code="N0000183904"/>
<Mention id="M62" type="Precipitant" span="249 3;254 12" str="BCG | vaccinations" code="N0000183904"/>
<Mention id="M65" type="Precipitant" span="109 12;254 12" str="mycobacteria | vaccinations" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M68" type="Precipitant" span="178 10;254 12" str="salmonella | vaccinations" code="N0000183901"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M67" precipitant="M56" effect="M69" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M67" precipitant="M59" effect="M69" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M67" precipitant="M62" effect="M69" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M67" precipitant="M65" effect="M69" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M67" precipitant="M68" effect="M69" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2456" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Serious infections and fatal outcomes have been reported in such patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2457" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>It is not known whether patients with pharmacologic blockade of IL-12/IL-23 from treatment with STELARA® may be susceptible to these types of infections.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2458" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Appropriate diagnostic testing should be considered, e.g., tissue culture, stool culture, as dictated by clinical circumstances.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2459" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Evaluate patients for tuberculosis infection prior to initiating treatment with STELARA®.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2460" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Do not administer STELARA® to patients with active tuberculosis infection.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2461" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Initiate treatment of latent tuberculosis prior to administering STELARA®.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2462" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Consider anti-tuberculosis therapy prior to initiation of STELARA® in patients with a past history of latent or active tuberculosis in whom an adequate course of treatment cannot be confirmed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2463" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Closely monitor patients receiving STELARA® for signs and symptoms of active tuberculosis during and after treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2464" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>STELARA® is an immunosuppressant and may increase the risk of malignancy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2465" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Malignancies were reported among subjects who received STELARA® in clinical studies.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2466" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In rodent models, inhibition of IL-12/IL-23p40 increased the risk of malignancy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2467" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The safety of STELARA® has not been evaluated in patients who have a history of malignancy or who have a known malignancy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2468" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There have been post-marketing reports of the rapid appearance of multiple cutaneous squamous cell carcinomas in patients receiving STELARA® who had pre-existing risk factors for developing non-melanoma skin cancer.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2469" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>All patients receiving STELARA® should be monitored for the appearance of non-melanoma skin cancer.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2470" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients greater than 60 years of age, those with a medical history of prolonged immunosuppressant therapy and those with a history of PUVA treatment should be followed closely.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2471" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hypersensitivity reactions, including anaphylaxis and angioedema, have been reported with STELARA®.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2472" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If an anaphylactic or other clinically significant hypersensitivity reaction occurs, institute appropriate therapy and discontinue STELARA®.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2473" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>One case of reversible posterior leukoencephalopathy syndrome (RPLS) was observed in clinical studies of psoriasis and psoriatic arthritis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2474" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The subject, who had received 12 doses of STELARA® over approximately two years, presented with headache, seizures and confusion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2475" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>No additional STELARA® injections were administered and the subject fully recovered with appropriate treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2476" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>No cases of RPLS were observed in clinical studies of Crohn's disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2477" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>RPLS is a neurological disorder, which is not caused by demyelination or a known infectious agent.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2478" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>RPLS can present with headache, seizures, confusion and visual disturbances.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2479" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Conditions with which it has been associated include preeclampsia, eclampsia, acute hypertension, cytotoxic agents and immunosuppressive therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2480" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If RPLS is suspected, administer appropriate treatment and discontinue STELARA®.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2481" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Prior to initiating therapy with STELARA®, patients should receive all age-appropriate immunizations as recommended by current immunization guidelines.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2482" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients being treated with STELARA® should not receive live vaccines.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M70" type="Trigger" span="37 18" str="should not receive"/>
<Mention id="M71" type="Precipitant" span="56 13" str="live vaccines" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M70" precipitant="M71"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2483" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>BCG vaccines should not be given during treatment with STELARA® or for one year prior to initiating treatment or one year following discontinuation of treatment.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M72" type="Trigger" span="13 19" str="should not be given"/>
<Mention id="M73" type="Precipitant" span="0 12" str="BCG vaccines" code="N0000183904"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M72" precipitant="M73"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2484" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Caution is advised when administering live vaccines to household contacts of patients receiving STELARA® because of the potential risk for shedding from the household contact and transmission to patient.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M74" type="Trigger" span="0 7" str="Caution"/>
<Mention id="M75" type="Precipitant" span="38 13" str="live vaccines" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M74" precipitant="M75"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2485" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Non-live vaccinations received during a course of STELARA® may not elicit an immune response sufficient to prevent disease.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M76" type="Trigger" span="59 14;84 8" str="may not elicit | response"/>
<Mention id="M77" type="Precipitant" span="0 21" str="Non-live vaccinations" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M78" type="SpecificInteraction" span="59 63" str="may not elicit an immune response sufficient to prevent disease" code="71922006: Immune defect (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M76" precipitant="M77" effect="M78" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2486" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In clinical studies of psoriasis the safety of STELARA® in combination with other immunosuppressive agents or phototherapy was not evaluated.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M79" type="Trigger" span="37 6;127 13" str="safety | not evaluated"/>
<Mention id="M80" type="Precipitant" span="82 24" str="immunosuppressive agents" code="N0000175550"/>
<Interaction id="I29" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M79" precipitant="M80"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2487" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Ultraviolet-induced skin cancers developed earlier and more frequently in mice genetically manipulated to be deficient in both IL-12 and IL-23 or IL-12 alone.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2488" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Cases of interstitial pneumonia, eosinophilic pneumonia and cryptogenic organizing pneumonia have been reported during post-approval use of STELARA®.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2489" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Clinical presentations included cough, dyspnea, and interstitial infiltrates following one to three doses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2490" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Serious outcomes have included respiratory failure and prolonged hospitalization.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2491" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients improved with discontinuation of therapy and in certain cases administration of corticosteroids.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2492" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Ustekinumab is a human IgG1қ monoclonal antibody that binds with specificity to the p40 protein subunit used by both the IL-12 and IL-23 cytokines.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2493" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>IL-12 and IL-23 are naturally occurring cytokines that are involved in inflammatory and immune responses, such as natural killer cell activation and CD4+ T-cell differentiation and activation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2494" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In in vitro models, ustekinumab was shown to disrupt IL-12 and IL-23 mediated signaling and cytokine cascades by disrupting the interaction of these cytokines with a shared cell-surface receptor chain, IL-12Rβ1.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2495" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The cytokines IL-12 and IL-23 have been implicated as important contributors to the chronic inflammation that is a hallmark of Crohn's disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2496" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In animal models of colitis, genetic absence or antibody blockade of the p40 subunit of IL-12 and IL-23, the target of ustekinumab, was shown to be protective.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2497" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In a small exploratory study, a decrease was observed in the expression of mRNA of its molecular targets IL-12 and IL-23 in lesional skin biopsies measured at baseline and up to two weeks post-treatment in subjects with psoriasis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2498" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Absorption In adult subjects with psoriasis, the median time to reach the maximum serum concentration (Tmax) was 13.5 days and 7 days, respectively, after a single subcutaneous administration of 45 mg (N=22) and 90 mg (N=24) of ustekinumab.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2499" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In healthy subjects (N=30), the median Tmax value (8.5 days) following a single subcutaneous administration of 90 mg of ustekinumab was comparable to that observed in subjects with psoriasis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2500" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following multiple subcutaneous doses of STELARA® in adult subjects with psoriasis, steady-state serum concentrations of ustekinumab were achieved by Week 28.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2501" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mean (±SD) steady-state trough serum ustekinumab concentrations were 0.69 ± 0.69 mcg/mL for patients less than or equal to 100 kg receiving a 45 mg dose and 0.74 ± 0.78 mcg/mL for patients greater than 100 kg receiving a 90 mg dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2502" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There was no apparent accumulation in serum ustekinumab concentration over time when given subcutaneously every 12 weeks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2503" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In patients with Crohn's disease, following the recommended intravenous induction dose, mean ±SD peak serum ustekinumab concentration was 125.2 ± 33.6 mcg/mL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2504" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Starting at Week 8, the recommended subcutaneous maintenance dosing of 90 mg ustekinumab was administered every 8 weeks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2505" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Steady state ustekinumab concentration was achieved by the start of the second maintenance dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2506" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There was no apparent accumulation in ustekinumab concentration over time when given subcutaneously every 8 weeks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2507" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Mean ±SD steady-state trough concentration was 2.51 ± 2.06 mcg/mL for 90 mg ustekinumab administered every 8 weeks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2508" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Distribution In a population pharmacokinetic analysis of ustekinumab, the volume of distribution of the central compartment was 2.74 L (95% CI: 2.69, 2.78), and the total volume of distribution at steady-state was 4.62 L in patients with Crohn's disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2509" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Elimination The mean (±SD) half-life ranged from 14.9 ± 4.6 to 45.6 ± 80.2 days across all psoriasis studies following subcutaneous administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2510" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In a population pharmacokinetic analysis of ustekinumab, the clearance was 0.19 L/day (95% CI: 0.185, 0.197) with an estimated median terminal half-life of approximately 19 days in patients with Crohn's disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2511" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Metabolism The metabolic pathway of ustekinumab has not been characterized.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2512" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>As a human IgG1κ monoclonal antibody, ustekinumab is expected to be degraded into small peptides and amino acids via catabolic pathways in the same manner as endogenous IgG.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2513" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Specific Populations Weight When given the same dose, subjects with psoriasis or psoriatic arthritis weighing more than 100 kg had lower median serum ustekinumab concentrations compared with those subjects weighing 100 kg or less.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2514" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The median trough serum concentrations of ustekinumab in subjects of higher weight (greater than 100 kg) in the 90 mg group were comparable to those in subjects of lower weight (100 kg or less) in the 45 mg group.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2515" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Age: Geriatric Population A population pharmacokinetic analysis (N=106/1937 patients with psoriasis greater than or equal to 65 years old) was performed to evaluate the effect of age on the pharmacokinetics of ustekinumab.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2516" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There were no apparent changes in pharmacokinetic parameters (clearance and volume of distribution) in subjects older than 65 years old.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2517" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Age: Pediatric Population Following multiple recommended doses of STELARA® in adolescent subjects 12 to 17 years of age with psoriasis, steady-state serum concentrations of ustekinumab were achieved by Week 28.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2518" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>At Week 28, the mean ±SD steady-state trough serum ustekinumab concentration was 0.54 ± 0.43 mcg/mL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2519" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Drug Interaction Studies The effects of IL-12 or IL-23 on the regulation of CYP450 enzymes were evaluated in an in vitro study using human hepatocytes, which showed that IL-12 and/or IL-23 at levels of 10 ng/mL did not alter human CYP450 enzyme activities (CYP1A2, 2B6, 2C9, 2C19, 2D6, or 3A4).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2520" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>However, the clinical relevance of in vitro data has not been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2521" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No in vivo drug interaction studies have been conducted with STELARA®.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2522" LabelDrug="STELARA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Population pharmacokinetic data analyses indicated that the clearance of ustekinumab was not impacted by concomitant MTX, NSAIDs, and oral corticosteroids, or prior exposure to a TNF blocker in patients with psoriatic arthritis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="live vaccines" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="immunosuppressive agents" precipitantCode="N0000175550"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="cyclosporine" precipitantCode="83HN0GTJ6D | N0000007346"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="cyp450 substrates" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="warfarin" precipitantCode="5Q7ZVV76EI | N0000006403"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="allergen immunotherapy" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="102460003: Decreased tolerance (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="allergen immunotherapy" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="419076005: Allergic reaction (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="allergen immunotherapy" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="allergen immunotherapy" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="bacillus calmette-guerin (bcg) vaccinations" precipitantCode="N0000183904" effect="40733004: Infectious disease (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="bacillus calmette-guerin | vaccinations" precipitantCode="N0000183904" effect="40733004: Infectious disease (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="bcg | vaccinations" precipitantCode="N0000183904" effect="40733004: Infectious disease (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="mycobacteria | vaccinations" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="40733004: Infectious disease (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="salmonella | vaccinations" precipitantCode="N0000183901" effect="40733004: Infectious disease (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="bcg vaccines" precipitantCode="N0000183904"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="non-live vaccinations" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="71922006: Immune defect (finding)"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>