<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" setid="caf22ccb-df75-45ea-a1d0-ccb2d37272fb">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection is contraindicated in patients with known hypersensitivity to vancomycin. Hypersensitivity to vancomycin ( 4 )</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
• Administer Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection in a diluted solution over 60 minutes or greater to reduce the risk of infusion reactions. • See full prescribing information for further important administration and preparation instructions ( 2.1 , 2.5 ) • Adult Patients: 2 g divided either as 0.5 grams (g) every 6 hours or 1 g every 12 hours ( 2.2 ) • Pediatric Patients (1 month and older): 10 mg/kg per dose given every 6 hours ( 2.3 ) • Neonates: See full prescribing information for recommended doses in neonates ( 2.3 ) • Patients with renal impairment: See full prescribing information for recommended doses in patients with renal impairment ( 2.4 ) To reduce the risk of infusion related adverse reactions, administer Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection in a diluted solution over 60 minutes or greater [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1 ) and Adverse Reactions (6.1)] . Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection concentrations of no more than 5 mg/mL are recommended in adults [see Dosage and Administration (2.2 )]. See also age-specific recommendations [see Dosage and Administration (2.3 )] . In selected patients in need of fluid restriction, a concentration up to 10 mg/mL may be used [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1 )] . Administer Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection prior to intravenous anesthetic agents to reduce the risk of infusion related adverse reactions [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1 )]. Administer Vancomycin Hydrochloride by a secure intravenous route of administration to avoid local irritation and phlebitis reactions [see Warnings and Precautions (5.7 )] . The supplied lyophilized powder must be reconstituted and subsequently diluted prior to intravenous use [see Dosage and Administration (2.5 )]. The usual daily intravenous dose is 2 grams divided either as 500 mg every 6 hours or 1 g every 12 hours. Administer each dose over a period of 60 minutes or greater. Other patient factors, such as age or obesity, may call for modification of the usual intravenous daily dose. Pediatric Patients (Aged 1 month and older) The usual intravenous dosage of vancomycin is 10 mg/kg per dose given every 6 hours. Each dose should be administered over a period of at least 60 minutes. Close monitoring of serum concentrations of vancomycin may be warranted in these patients. Neonates (Up to 1 month old ) In pediatric patients, up to the age of 1 month, the total daily intravenous dosage may be lower. In neonates, an initial dose of 15 mg/kg is suggested, followed by 10 mg/kg every 12 hours for neonates in the 1st week of life and every 8 hours thereafter up to the age of 1 month. Each dose should be administered over 60 minutes. In premature infants, vancomycin clearance decreases as postconceptional age decreases. Therefore, longer dosing intervals may be necessary in premature infants. Close monitoring of serum concentrations of vancomycin is recommended in these patients. Dosage adjustment must be made in patients with renal impairment. The initial dose should be no less than 15 mg/kg, in patients with any degree of renal impairment. In premature infants and the elderly, greater dosage reductions than expected may be necessary because of decreased renal function. Measure trough vancomycin serum concentrations to guide therapy, especially in seriously ill patients with changing renal function. For functionally anephric patients, an initial dose of 15 mg/kg of body weight should be given to achieve prompt therapeutic serum concentration. A dose of 1.9 mg/kg/24 hr should be given after the initial dose of 15 mg/kg. Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection must be reconstituted and further diluted. Reconstitution of the Lyophilized Powder and further dilution At the time of use, reconstitute the vials of Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection (lyophilized powder) with Sterile Water for Injection to a concentration of 50 mg of vancomycin/mL then further dilute with an infusion solution to a final concentration of 5 mg/mL (see Table 1 for the appropriate volumes). Discard any reconstituted solution remaining in the vial. Table 1 Volume of Sterile Water for Injection to be Added for Reconstitution and Volume of Infusion Solution to be Used for Further Dilution Vancomycin Strength per Vial Volume of Sterile Water for Injection for reconstitution a Volume of infusion solution b to further dilute to a final concentration of 5 mg/mL 250 mg 5 mL 50 mL 750 mg 15 mL 150 mL 1.25 g 25 mL 250 mL 1.5 g 30 mL 300 mL a After reconstitution, the vials may be stored in a refrigerator for 14 days without significant loss of potency. b Use an infusion solution from the list of the compatible infusion solutions below [see Dosage and Administration (2.6 )] . The desired dose diluted in this manner should be administered by intermittent IV infusion over a period of 60 minutes or greater. Parenteral drug products should be visually inspected for particulate matter and discoloration prior to administration, whenever solution and container permit. Discard reconstituted and diluted solutions 14 days after initial reconstitution. The following diluents are physically and chemically compatible with 5 g/L vancomycin hydrochloride-: 5% Dextrose Injection, USP 5% Dextrose Injection and 0.9% Sodium Chloride Injection, USP Lactated Ringer’s Injection, USP Lactated Ringer’s and 5% Dextrose Injection, USP 0.9% Sodium Chloride Injection, USP Storage of Diluted Solutions: Solutions that are diluted with 5% Dextrose Injection, USP or 0.9% Sodium Chloride Injection, USP may be stored in a refrigerator for 14 days without significant loss of potency. Solutions that are diluted with the following infusion fluids may be stored in a refrigerator for 96 hours: 5% Dextrose Injection and 0.9% Sodium Chloride Injection, USP Lactated Ringer’s Injection, USP Lactated Ringer’s and 5% Dextrose Injection, USP Vancomycin solution has a low pH and may cause chemical or physical instability when it is mixed with other compounds. Mixtures of solutions of vancomycin and beta-lactam antibacterial drugs have been shown to be physically incompatible. The likelihood of precipitation increases with higher concentrations of vancomycin. It is recommended to adequately flush the intravenous lines between the administration of these antibacterial drugs. It is also recommended to dilute solutions of vancomycin to 5 mg/mL or less.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
Anesthetic Agents : Concomitant administration of vancomycin and anesthetic agents has been associated with erythema and histamine-like flushing. ( 2.1 , 7.1 ) Piperacillin/Tazobactam: Increased incidence of acute kidney injury in patients receiving concomitant piperacillin/tazobactam and vancomycin as compared to vancomycin alone. Monitor kidney function in patients ( 7.2 ) Concomitant administration of vancomycin and anesthetic agents has been associated with erythema and histamine-like flushing [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1) and Use in Specific Populations (8.4 )] . Studies have detected an increased incidence of acute kidney injury in patients administered concomitant piperacillin/tazobactam and vancomycin as compared to vancomycin alone. Monitor kidney function in patients receiving concomitant piperacillin/tazobactam and vancomycin. No pharmacokinetic interactions have been noted between piperacillin/tazobactam and vancomycin. Concurrent and/or sequential systemic or topical use of other potentially, neurotoxic and/or nephrotoxic drugs requires more frequent monitoring of renal function.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
Infusion Reactions : Hypotension, including shock and cardiac arrest, wheezing, dyspnea, urticaria, muscular, chest pain and “red man syndrome” which manifests as pruritus and erythema that involves the face, neck and upper torso may occur with rapid intravenous administration. To reduce the risk of infusion reactions, administer Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection in a diluted solution over a period of 60 minutes or greater and also prior to intravenous anesthetic agents. ( 2.1 , 5.1 ) Nephrotoxicity : Systemic vancomycin exposure may result in acute kidney injury (AKI) including acute renal failure, mainly due to interstitial nephritis or less commonly acute tubular necrosis. Monitor serum vancomycin concentrations and renal function. ( 5.2 ) Ototoxicity : Ototoxicity has occurred in patients receiving vancomycin hydrochloride. Monitor for signs and symptoms of ototoxicity during therapy. Monitor serum vancomycin concentrations and renal function. Assessment of auditory function may be appropriate in some instances. ( 5.3 ) Clostridium Difficile Associated Diarrhea : Evaluate patients if diarrhea occurs. ( 5.4 ) Neutropenia : Periodically monitor leukocyte count. ( 5.6 ) Phlebitis: To reduce the risk of local irritation and phlebitis administer Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection by a secure intravenous route of administration. ( 5.7 ) Development of Drug-Resistant Bacteria: Prescribing Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection in the absence of a proven or strongly suspected bacterial infection is unlikely to provide benefit to the patient and increases the risk of the development of drug resistant bacteria. ( 5.8 ) Hypotension, including shock and cardiac arrest, wheezing, dyspnea, urticaria, muscular and chest pain may occur with rapid Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection administration. The reactions may be more severe in younger patients, particularly children, and in patients receiving concomitant muscle relaxant anesthetics. Rapid intravenous administration of Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection may also be associated with “red man syndrome”, which manifests as pruritus and erythema that involves the face, neck and upper torso. Infusion-related adverse reactions are related to both the concentration and the rate of administration of vancomycin. Infusion-related adverse reactions may occur, however, at any rate or concentration. Administer Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection in a diluted solution over a period of 60 minutes or greater to reduce the risk of infusion-related adverse reactions. In selected patients in need of fluid restriction, a concentration up to 10 mg/mL may be used; use of such higher concentrations may increase the risk of infusion-related adverse reactions. Administer prior to intravenous anesthetic agents when feasible. Stop the infusion if a reaction occurs. Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection can result in acute kidney injury (AKI), including acute renal failure, mainly due to interstitial nephritis or less commonly acute tubular necrosis. AKI is manifested by increasing blood urea nitrogen (BUN) and serum creatinine (Cr). The risk of AKI increases with higher vancomycin serum levels, prolonged exposure, concomitant administration of other nephrotoxic drugs, concomitant administration of piperacillin-tazobactam [see Drug Interactions (7.2) ] , volume depletion, pre-existing renal impairment and in critically ill patients and patients with co-morbid conditions that predispose to renal impairment. Monitor serum vancomycin concentrations and renal function in all patients receiving Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection. More frequent monitoring is recommended in patients with comorbidities that predispose to impairment in renal function or are concomitantly receiving other nephrotoxic drugs, in critically ill patients, in patients with changing renal function, and in patients requiring higher therapeutic vancomycin levels. If acute kidney injury occurs, discontinue Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection or reduce the dose. Ototoxicity has occurred in patients receiving Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection. It may be transient or permanent. Ototoxicity manifests as tinnitus, hearing loss, dizziness or vertigo. The risk is higher in older patients, patients who are receiving higher doses, who have an underlying hearing loss, who are receiving concomitant therapy with another ototoxic agent, such as an aminoglycoside or who have underlying renal impairment. Monitor for signs and symptoms of ototoxicity during therapy. Monitor serum vancomycin concentrations and renal function in all patients receiving parenteral vancomycin. Discontinue Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection if ototoxicity occurs. Dosage of Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection must be adjusted for patients with renal impairment [see Dosage and Administration (2.3) ] . Serial tests of auditory function may be helpful in order to minimize the risk of ototoxicity. Clostridium difficile- associated diarrhea (CDAD) has been reported with use of nearly all antibacterial agents, including Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection, and may range in severity from mild diarrhea to fatal colitis. Treatment with antibacterial agents alters the normal flora of the colon leading to overgrowth of C. difficile . C. difficile produces toxins A and B which contribute to the development of CDAD. Hypertoxin producing strains of C. difficile cause increased morbidity and mortality, as these infections can be refractory to antimicrobial therapy and may require colectomy. CDAD must be considered in all patients who present with diarrhea following antibacterial use. Careful medical history is necessary since CDAD has been reported to occur over two months after the administration of antibacterial agents. If CDAD is suspected or confirmed, ongoing antibacterial use not directed against C. difficile may need to be discontinued. Appropriate fluid and electrolyte management, protein supplementation, antibacterial treatment of C. difficile , and surgical evaluation should be instituted as clinically indicated. Clinically significant serum concentrations have been reported in some patients being treated for active C. difficile -induced pseudomembranous colitis after multiple oral doses of vancomycin. Prolonged use of Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection may result in the overgrowth of nonsusceptible microorganisms. Careful observation of the patient is essential. If superinfection occurs during therapy, appropriate measures should be taken. In rare instances, there have been reports of pseudomembranous colitis due to C. difficile developing in patients who received intravenous Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection. Hemorrhagic occlusive retinal vasculitis, including permanent loss of vision, occurred in patients receiving intracameral or intravitreal administration of vancomycin during or after cataract surgery. The safety and efficacy of vancomycin administered by the intracameral or the intravitreal route have not been established by adequate and well-controlled trials. Vancomycin is not indicated for the prophylaxis of endophthalmitis. Reversible neutropenia has been reported in patients receiving Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection [see Adverse Reactions (6.1) ] . Patients who will undergo prolonged therapy with Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection or those who are receiving concomitant drugs which may cause neutropenia should have periodic monitoring of the leukocyte count. Inflammation at the site of injection of Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection has been reported. Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection is irritating to tissue and must be given by a secure intravenous route of administration to reduce the risk of local irritation and phlebitis. Administration of Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection by intramuscular (IM), intraperitoneal, intrathecal (intralumbar or intraventricular), or intravitreal routes has not been approved and is not recommended. The safety and efficacy of vancomycin administered by the intrathecal (intralumbar or intraventricular) route or by the intraperitoneal route have not been established by adequate and well controlled trials. Pain, tenderness, and necrosis occur with IM injection of Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection or with inadvertent extravasation. Thrombophlebitis may occur, the frequency and severity of which can be minimized by administering the drug slowly as a dilute solution (2.5 to 5 g/L) and by rotation of venous access sites. Intraperitoneal administration during continuous ambulatory peritoneal dialysis (CAPD) can result in chemical peritonitis. Manifestations range from cloudy dialysate alone to a cloudy dialysate accompanied by variable degrees of abdominal pain and fever. This syndrome appears to be resolve after discontinuation of intraperitoneal vancomycin. Prescribing Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection in the absence of a proven or strongly suspected bacterial infection or a prophylactic indication is unlikely to provide benefit to the patient and increases the risk of the development of drug-resistant bacteria.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Vancomycin is an antibacterial drug [see Microbiology (12.4) ] . The pharmacodynamics of vancomycin is unknown. In subjects with normal kidney function, multiple intravenous dosing of 1 g of vancomycin (15 mg/kg) infused over 60 minutes produces mean plasma concentrations of approximately 63 mcg/mL immediately after the completion of infusion, mean plasma concentrations of approximately 23 mcg/mL 2 hours after infusion, and mean plasma concentrations of approximately 8 mcg/mL 11 hours after the end of the infusion. Multiple dosing of 500 mg infused over 30 minutes produces mean plasma concentrations of about 49 mcg/mL at the completion of infusion, mean plasma concentrations of about 19 mcg/mL 2 hours after infusion, and mean plasma concentrations of about 10 mcg/mL 6 hours after infusion. The plasma concentrations during multiple dosing are like those after a single dose. Distribution The volume of distribution ranges from 0.3 to 0.43 L/kg after intravenous administration. Vancomycin is approximately 55% serum protein bound as measured by ultrafiltration at vancomycin serum concentrations of 10 to 100 mcg/mL. After intravenous administration of vancomycin, inhibitory concentrations are present in pleural, pericardial, ascitic, and synovial fluids; in urine; in peritoneal dialysis fluid; and in atrial appendage tissue. Vancomycin does not readily diffuse across normal meninges into the spinal fluid; but, when the meninges are inflamed, penetration into the spinal fluid occurs. Elimination Mean plasma clearance is about 0.058 L/kg/h, and mean renal clearance is about 0.048 L/kg/h.The mean elimination half-life of vancomycin from plasma is 4 to 6 hours in subjects with normal renal function. In anephric patients, the mean elimination half-life is 7.5 days. Total body and renal clearance of vancomycin may be reduced in the elderly. Metabolism There is no apparent metabolism of the vancomycin. Excretion In the first 24 hours after intravenous administration, about 75% of an administered dose of vancomycin is excreted in urine by glomerular filtration. Renal impairment slows excretion of vancomycin. About 60% of an intraperitoneal dose of vancomycin administered during peritoneal dialysis is absorbed systemically in 6 hours. Serum concentrations of about 10 mcg/mL are achieved by intraperitoneal injection of 30 mg/kg of vancomycin. However, the safety and efficacy of the intraperitoneal use of vancomycin has not been established in adequate and well-controlled trials [see Warnings and Precautions (5.6 )] . Mechanism of Action The bactericidal action of vancomycin results primarily from inhibition of cell-wall biosynthesis. In addition, vancomycin alters bacterial-cell-membrane permeability and RNA synthesis. Resistance Vancomycin is not active in vitro against gram-negative bacilli, mycobacteria, or fungi. There is no cross-resistance between vancomycin and other antibacterials. Interaction With Other Antimicrobials The combination of vancomycin and an aminoglycoside acts synergistically in vitro against many isolates of Staphylococcus aureus , Streptococcus gallolyticus ( previously known as Streptococcus bovis) , enterococcus spp, and the viridans group streptococci. Antimicrobial Activity Vancomycin has been shown to be active against most isolates of the following microorganisms, both in vitro and in clinical infections [see Indications and Usage (1) ]. Aerobic Gram-Positive Bacteria Corynebacterium spp. Enterococcus spp. (including Enterococcus faecalis ) Staphylococcus aureus (including methicillin-resistant and methicillin-susceptible isolates) Coagulase negative staphylococci (including S. epidermidis and methicillin-resistant isolates) Streptococcus gallolyticus ( previously known as Streptococcus bovis) Viridans group streptococci The following in vitro data are available, but their clinical significance is unknown. At least 90 percent of the following bacteria exhibit an in vitro minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) less than or equal to the susceptible breakpoint for vancomycin against isolates of similar genus or organism group. However, the efficacy of vancomycin in treating clinical infections caused by these bacteria has not been established in adequate and well-controlled clinical trials. Aerobic Gram-Positive Bacteria Listeria monocytogenes Streptococcus pyogenes Streptococcus pneumoniae Streptococcus agalactiae Anaerobic Gram-Positive Bacteria Actinomyces species Lactobacillus species Susceptibility Testing For specific information regarding susceptibility test interpretive criteria and associated test methods and quality control standards recognized by FDA for this drug, please see: https://www.fda.gov/STIC.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="1127" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection is contraindicated in patients with known hypersensitivity to vancomycin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1128" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Administer Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection in a diluted solution over 60 minutes or greater to reduce the risk of infusion reactions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1129" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>See full prescribing information for further important administration and preparation instructions (2.1, 2.5) Adult Patients: 2 g divided either as 0.5 grams (g) every 6 hours or 1 g every 12 hours (2.2) Pediatric Patients (1 month and older): 10 mg/kg per dose given every 6 hours (2.3) Neonates: See full prescribing information for recommended doses in neonates (2.3) Patients with renal impairment: See full prescribing information for recommended doses in patients with renal impairment (2.4) To reduce the risk of infusion related adverse reactions, administer Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection in a diluted solution over 60 minutes or greater.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1130" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection concentrations of no more than 5 mg/mL are recommended in adults.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1131" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>See also age-specific recommendations.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1132" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In selected patients in need of fluid restriction, a concentration up to 10 mg/mL may be used.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1133" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Administer Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection prior to intravenous anesthetic agents to reduce the risk of infusion related adverse reactions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1134" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Administer Vancomycin Hydrochloride by a secure intravenous route of administration to avoid local irritation and phlebitis reactions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1135" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The supplied lyophilized powder must be reconstituted and subsequently diluted prior to intravenous use.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1136" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The usual daily intravenous dose is 2 grams divided either as 500 mg every 6 hours or 1 g every 12 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1137" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Administer each dose over a period of 60 minutes or greater.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1138" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Other patient factors, such as age or obesity, may call for modification of the usual intravenous daily dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1139" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Pediatric Patients (Aged 1 month and older) The usual intravenous dosage of vancomycin is 10 mg/kg per dose given every 6 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1140" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Each dose should be administered over a period of at least 60 minutes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1141" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Close monitoring of serum concentrations of vancomycin may be warranted in these patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1142" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Neonates (Up to 1 month old) In pediatric patients, up to the age of 1 month, the total daily intravenous dosage may be lower.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1143" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In neonates, an initial dose of 15 mg/kg is suggested, followed by 10 mg/kg every 12 hours for neonates in the 1st week of life and every 8 hours thereafter up to the age of 1 month.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1144" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Each dose should be administered over 60 minutes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1145" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In premature infants, vancomycin clearance decreases as postconceptional age decreases.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1146" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Therefore, longer dosing intervals may be necessary in premature infants.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1147" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Close monitoring of serum concentrations of vancomycin is recommended in these patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1148" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dosage adjustment must be made in patients with renal impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1149" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The initial dose should be no less than 15 mg/kg, in patients with any degree of renal impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1150" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In premature infants and the elderly, greater dosage reductions than expected may be necessary because of decreased renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1151" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Measure trough vancomycin serum concentrations to guide therapy, especially in seriously ill patients with changing renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1152" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For functionally anephric patients, an initial dose of 15 mg/kg of body weight should be given to achieve prompt therapeutic serum concentration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1153" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>A dose of 1.9 mg/kg/24 hr should be given after the initial dose of 15 mg/kg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1154" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection must be reconstituted and further diluted.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1155" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Reconstitution of the Lyophilized Powder and further dilution At the time of use, reconstitute the vials of Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection (lyophilized powder) with Sterile Water for Injection to a concentration of 50 mg of vancomycin/mL then further dilute with an infusion solution to a final concentration of 5 mg/mL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1156" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Discard any reconstituted solution remaining in the vial.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1157" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Table 1 Volume of Sterile Water for Injection to be Added for Reconstitution and Volume of Infusion Solution to be Used for Further Dilution Vancomycin Strength per Vial Volume of Sterile Water for Injection for reconstitutiona Volume of infusion solutionb to further dilute to a final concentration of 5 mg/mL 250 mg 5 mL 50 mL 750 mg 15 mL 150 mL 1.25 g 25 mL 250 mL 1.5 g 30 mL 300 mL aAfter reconstitution, the vials may be stored in a refrigerator for 14 days without significant loss of potency. b Use an infusion solution from the list of the compatible infusion solutions below.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1158" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The desired dose diluted in this manner should be administered by intermittent IV infusion over a period of 60 minutes or greater.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1159" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Parenteral drug products should be visually inspected for particulate matter and discoloration prior to administration, whenever solution and container permit.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1160" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Discard reconstituted and diluted solutions 14 days after initial reconstitution.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1161" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The following diluents are physically and chemically compatible with 5 g/L vancomycin hydrochloride-: 5% Dextrose Injection, USP 5% Dextrose Injection and 0.9% Sodium Chloride Injection, USP Lactated Ringer’s Injection, USP Lactated Ringer’s and 5% Dextrose Injection, USP 0.9% Sodium Chloride Injection, USP Storage of Diluted Solutions: Solutions that are diluted with 5% Dextrose Injection, USP or 0.9% Sodium Chloride Injection, USP may be stored in a refrigerator for 14 days without significant loss of potency.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1162" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Solutions that are diluted with the following infusion fluids may be stored in a refrigerator for 96 hours: 5% Dextrose Injection and 0.9% Sodium Chloride Injection, USP Lactated Ringer’s Injection, USP Lactated Ringer’s and 5% Dextrose Injection, USP Vancomycin solution has a low pH and may cause chemical or physical instability when it is mixed with other compounds.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1163" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Mixtures of solutions of vancomycin and beta-lactam antibacterial drugs have been shown to be physically incompatible.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M1" type="Trigger" span="105 12" str="incompatible"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="40 31" str="beta-lactam antibacterial drugs" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M3" type="SpecificInteraction" span="94 23" str="physically incompatible" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M1" precipitant="M2" effect="M3" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1164" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The likelihood of precipitation increases with higher concentrations of vancomycin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1165" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>It is recommended to adequately flush the intravenous lines between the administration of these antibacterial drugs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1166" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>It is also recommended to dilute solutions of vancomycin to 5 mg/mL or less.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1167" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Anesthetic Agents: Concomitant administration of vancomycin and anesthetic agents has been associated with erythema and histamine-like flushing.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M7" type="Trigger" span="91 15" str="associated with"/>
<Mention id="M8" type="Precipitant" span="0 17" str="anesthetic agents" code="N0000175681"/>
<Mention id="M6" type="SpecificInteraction" span="107 8" str="erythema" code="247441003: Erythema (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M9" type="SpecificInteraction" span="120 23" str="histamine-like flushing" code="238810007: Flushing (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M7" precipitant="M8" effect="M6" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M7" precipitant="M8" effect="M9" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1168" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Piperacillin/Tazobactam: Increased incidence of acute kidney injury in patients receiving concomitant piperacillin/tazobactam and vancomycin as compared to vancomycin alone.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M10" type="Trigger" span="25 19" str="Increased incidence"/>
<Mention id="M11" type="Precipitant" span="0 23" str="piperacillin/tazobactam" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M12" type="SpecificInteraction" span="48 19" str="acute kidney injury" code="14350001000004108: Acute injury of kidney (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M10" precipitant="M11" effect="M12" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1169" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor kidney function in patients (7.2) Concomitant administration of vancomycin and anesthetic agents has been associated with erythema and histamine-like flushing.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M16" type="Trigger" span="114 15" str="associated with"/>
<Mention id="M17" type="Precipitant" span="87 17" str="anesthetic agents" code="N0000175681"/>
<Mention id="M15" type="SpecificInteraction" span="130 8" str="erythema" code="247441003: Erythema (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M18" type="SpecificInteraction" span="143 23" str="histamine-like flushing" code="238810007: Flushing (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M16" precipitant="M17" effect="M15" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M16" precipitant="M17" effect="M18" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1170" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Studies have detected an increased incidence of acute kidney injury in patients administered concomitant piperacillin/tazobactam and vancomycin as compared to vancomycin alone.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M19" type="Trigger" span="25 19" str="increased incidence"/>
<Mention id="M20" type="Precipitant" span="105 23" str="piperacillin/tazobactam" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M21" type="SpecificInteraction" span="48 19" str="acute kidney injury" code="14350001000004108: Acute injury of kidney (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M19" precipitant="M20" effect="M21" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1171" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor kidney function in patients receiving concomitant piperacillin/tazobactam and vancomycin.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M22" type="Trigger" span="0 7" str="Monitor"/>
<Mention id="M23" type="Precipitant" span="58 23" str="piperacillin/tazobactam" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M24" type="SpecificInteraction" span="8 15" str="kidney function" code="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M22" precipitant="M23" effect="M24" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1172" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>No pharmacokinetic interactions have been noted between piperacillin/tazobactam and vancomycin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1173" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Concurrent and/or sequential systemic or topical use of other potentially, neurotoxic and/or nephrotoxic drugs requires more frequent monitoring of renal function.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M28" type="Trigger" span="120 24" str="more frequent monitoring"/>
<Mention id="M26" type="Precipitant" span="93 17" str="nephrotoxic drugs" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M30" type="SpecificInteraction" span="148 14" str="renal function" code="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M29" type="Precipitant" span="75 10;105 5" str="neurotoxic | drugs" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M28" precipitant="M26" effect="M30" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M28" precipitant="M29" effect="M30" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1174" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Infusion Reactions: Hypotension, including shock and cardiac arrest, wheezing, dyspnea, urticaria, muscular, chest pain and “red man syndrome” which manifests as pruritus and erythema that involves the face, neck and upper torso may occur with rapid intravenous administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1175" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>To reduce the risk of infusion reactions, administer Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection in a diluted solution over a period of 60 minutes or greater and also prior to intravenous anesthetic agents.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M31" type="Trigger" span="14 7" str="risk of"/>
<Mention id="M32" type="Precipitant" span="183 17" str="anesthetic agents" code="N0000175681"/>
<Mention id="M33" type="SpecificInteraction" span="22 18" str="infusion reactions" code="441940003: Adverse reaction caused by drug or medicament administered by infusion (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M31" precipitant="M32" effect="M33" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1176" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Nephrotoxicity: Systemic vancomycin exposure may result in acute kidney injury (AKI) including acute renal failure, mainly due to interstitial nephritis or less commonly acute tubular necrosis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1177" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor serum vancomycin concentrations and renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1178" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Ototoxicity: Ototoxicity has occurred in patients receiving vancomycin hydrochloride.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1179" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor for signs and symptoms of ototoxicity during therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1180" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Assessment of auditory function may be appropriate in some instances.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1181" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Clostridium Difficile Associated Diarrhea: Evaluate patients if diarrhea occurs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1182" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Neutropenia: Periodically monitor leukocyte count.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1183" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Phlebitis: To reduce the risk of local irritation and phlebitis administer Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection by a secure intravenous route of administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1184" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Development of Drug-Resistant Bacteria: Prescribing Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection in the absence of a proven or strongly suspected bacterial infection is unlikely to provide benefit to the patient and increases the risk of the development of drug resistant bacteria.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1185" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hypotension, including shock and cardiac arrest, wheezing, dyspnea, urticaria, muscular and chest pain may occur with rapid Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1186" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The reactions may be more severe in younger patients, particularly children, and in patients receiving concomitant muscle relaxant anesthetics.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M34" type="Trigger" span="4 28" str="reactions may be more severe"/>
<Mention id="M35" type="Precipitant" span="115 27" str="muscle relaxant anesthetics" code="N0000175737"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M34" precipitant="M35"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1187" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Rapid intravenous administration of Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection may also be associated with “red man syndrome”, which manifests as pruritus and erythema that involves the face, neck and upper torso.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1188" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Infusion-related adverse reactions are related to both the concentration and the rate of administration of vancomycin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1189" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Infusion-related adverse reactions may occur, however, at any rate or concentration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1190" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Administer Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection in a diluted solution over a period of 60 minutes or greater to reduce the risk of infusion-related adverse reactions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1191" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In selected patients in need of fluid restriction, a concentration up to 10 mg/mL may be used; use of such higher concentrations may increase the risk of infusion-related adverse reactions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1192" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Administer prior to intravenous anesthetic agents when feasible.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1193" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection can result in acute kidney injury (AKI), including acute renal failure, mainly due to interstitial nephritis or less commonly acute tubular necrosis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1194" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>AKI is manifested by increasing blood urea nitrogen (BUN) and serum creatinine (Cr).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1195" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The risk of AKI increases with higher vancomycin serum levels, prolonged exposure, concomitant administration of other nephrotoxic drugs, concomitant administration of piperacillin-tazobactam, volume depletion, pre-existing renal impairment and in critically ill patients and patients with co-morbid conditions that predispose to renal impairment.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M39" type="Trigger" span="4 7" str="risk of"/>
<Mention id="M37" type="Precipitant" span="119 17" str="nephrotoxic drugs" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M41" type="SpecificInteraction" span="12 3" str="AKI" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M40" type="Precipitant" span="168 23" str="piperacillin-tazobactam" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M39" precipitant="M37" effect="M41" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M39" precipitant="M40" effect="M41" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1196" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor serum vancomycin concentrations and renal function in all patients receiving Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1197" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>More frequent monitoring is recommended in patients with comorbidities that predispose to impairment in renal function or are concomitantly receiving other nephrotoxic drugs, in critically ill patients, in patients with changing renal function, and in patients requiring higher therapeutic vancomycin levels.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M42" type="Trigger" span="0 24" str="More frequent monitoring"/>
<Mention id="M43" type="Precipitant" span="156 17" str="nephrotoxic drugs" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M44" type="SpecificInteraction" span="104 14" str="renal function" code="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M42" precipitant="M43" effect="M44" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1198" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If acute kidney injury occurs, discontinue Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection or reduce the dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1199" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Ototoxicity has occurred in patients receiving Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1200" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Ototoxicity manifests as tinnitus, hearing loss, dizziness or vertigo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1201" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The risk is higher in older patients, patients who are receiving higher doses, who have an underlying hearing loss, who are receiving concomitant therapy with another ototoxic agent, such as an aminoglycoside or who have underlying renal impairment.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M47" type="Trigger" span="4 14" str="risk is higher"/>
<Mention id="M46" type="Precipitant" span="194 14" str="aminoglycoside" code="N0000175929"/>
<Mention id="M48" type="Precipitant" span="167 14" str="ototoxic agent" code="N0000175828"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M47" precipitant="M46"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M47" precipitant="M48"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1202" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor serum vancomycin concentrations and renal function in all patients receiving parenteral vancomycin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1203" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Discontinue Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection if ototoxicity occurs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1204" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Dosage of Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection must be adjusted for patients with renal impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1205" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Serial tests of auditory function may be helpful in order to minimize the risk of ototoxicity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1206" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Clostridium difficile-associated diarrhea (CDAD) has been reported with use of nearly all antibacterial agents, including Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection, and may range in severity from mild diarrhea to fatal colitis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1207" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Treatment with antibacterial agents alters the normal flora of the colon leading to overgrowth of C. difficile.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1208" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>C. difficile produces toxins A and B which contribute to the development of CDAD.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1209" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hypertoxin producing strains of C. difficile cause increased morbidity and mortality, as these infections can be refractory to antimicrobial therapy and may require colectomy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1210" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>CDAD must be considered in all patients who present with diarrhea following antibacterial use.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1211" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Careful medical history is necessary since CDAD has been reported to occur over two months after the administration of antibacterial agents.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1212" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If CDAD is suspected or confirmed, ongoing antibacterial use not directed against C. difficile may need to be discontinued.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1213" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Appropriate fluid and electrolyte management, protein supplementation, antibacterial treatment of C. difficile, and surgical evaluation should be instituted as clinically indicated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1214" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Clinically significant serum concentrations have been reported in some patients being treated for active C. difficile-induced pseudomembranous colitis after multiple oral doses of vancomycin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1215" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Prolonged use of Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection may result in the overgrowth of nonsusceptible microorganisms.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1216" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Careful observation of the patient is essential.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1217" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If superinfection occurs during therapy, appropriate measures should be taken.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1218" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In rare instances, there have been reports of pseudomembranous colitis due to C. difficile developing in patients who received intravenous Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1219" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hemorrhagic occlusive retinal vasculitis, including permanent loss of vision, occurred in patients receiving intracameral or intravitreal administration of vancomycin during or after cataract surgery.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1220" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The safety and efficacy of vancomycin administered by the intracameral or the intravitreal route have not been established by adequate and well-controlled trials.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1221" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Vancomycin is not indicated for the prophylaxis of endophthalmitis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1222" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Reversible neutropenia has been reported in patients receiving Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1223" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients who will undergo prolonged therapy with Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection or those who are receiving concomitant drugs which may cause neutropenia should have periodic monitoring of the leukocyte count.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M49" type="Trigger" span="182 10" str="monitoring"/>
<Mention id="M50" type="Precipitant" span="127 33" str="drugs which may cause neutropenia" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M51" type="SpecificInteraction" span="200 15" str="leukocyte count" code="165509000: White blood cell count abnormal (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M49" precipitant="M50" effect="M51" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1224" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Inflammation at the site of injection of Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection has been reported.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1225" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection is irritating to tissue and must be given by a secure intravenous route of administration to reduce the risk of local irritation and phlebitis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1226" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Administration of Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection by intramuscular (IM), intraperitoneal, intrathecal (intralumbar or intraventricular), or intravitreal routes has not been approved and is not recommended.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1227" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The safety and efficacy of vancomycin administered by the intrathecal (intralumbar or intraventricular) route or by the intraperitoneal route have not been established by adequate and well controlled trials.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1228" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Pain, tenderness, and necrosis occur with IM injection of Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection or with inadvertent extravasation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1229" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Thrombophlebitis may occur, the frequency and severity of which can be minimized by administering the drug slowly as a dilute solution (2.5 to 5 g/L) and by rotation of venous access sites.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1230" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Intraperitoneal administration during continuous ambulatory peritoneal dialysis (CAPD) can result in chemical peritonitis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1231" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Manifestations range from cloudy dialysate alone to a cloudy dialysate accompanied by variable degrees of abdominal pain and fever.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1232" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>This syndrome appears to be resolve after discontinuation of intraperitoneal vancomycin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1233" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Prescribing Vancomycin Hydrochloride for Injection in the absence of a proven or strongly suspected bacterial infection or a prophylactic indication is unlikely to provide benefit to the patient and increases the risk of the development of drug-resistant bacteria.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1234" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Vancomycin is an antibacterial drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1235" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacodynamics of vancomycin is unknown.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1236" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In subjects with normal kidney function, multiple intravenous dosing of 1 g of vancomycin (15 mg/kg) infused over 60 minutes produces mean plasma concentrations of approximately 63 mcg/mL immediately after the completion of infusion, mean plasma concentrations of approximately 23 mcg/mL 2 hours after infusion, and mean plasma concentrations of approximately 8 mcg/mL 11 hours after the end of the infusion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1237" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Multiple dosing of 500 mg infused over 30 minutes produces mean plasma concentrations of about 49 mcg/mL at the completion of infusion, mean plasma concentrations of about 19 mcg/mL 2 hours after infusion, and mean plasma concentrations of about 10 mcg/mL 6 hours after infusion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1238" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The plasma concentrations during multiple dosing are like those after a single dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1239" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Distribution The volume of distribution ranges from 0.3 to 0.43 L/kg after intravenous administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1240" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Vancomycin is approximately 55% serum protein bound as measured by ultrafiltration at vancomycin serum concentrations of 10 to 100 mcg/mL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1241" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>After intravenous administration of vancomycin, inhibitory concentrations are present in pleural, pericardial, ascitic, and synovial fluids; in urine; in peritoneal dialysis fluid; and in atrial appendage tissue.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1242" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Vancomycin does not readily diffuse across normal meninges into the spinal fluid; but, when the meninges are inflamed, penetration into the spinal fluid occurs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1243" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Elimination Mean plasma clearance is about 0.058 L/kg/h, and mean renal clearance is about 0.048 L/kg/h.The mean elimination half-life of vancomycin from plasma is 4 to 6 hours in subjects with normal renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1244" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In anephric patients, the mean elimination half-life is 7.5 days.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1245" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Total body and renal clearance of vancomycin may be reduced in the elderly.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1246" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Metabolism There is no apparent metabolism of the vancomycin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1247" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Excretion In the first 24 hours after intravenous administration, about 75% of an administered dose of vancomycin is excreted in urine by glomerular filtration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1248" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Renal impairment slows excretion of vancomycin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1249" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>About 60% of an intraperitoneal dose of vancomycin administered during peritoneal dialysis is absorbed systemically in 6 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1250" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Serum concentrations of about 10 mcg/mL are achieved by intraperitoneal injection of 30 mg/kg of vancomycin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1251" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>However, the safety and efficacy of the intraperitoneal use of vancomycin has not been established in adequate and well-controlled trials.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1252" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Mechanism of Action The bactericidal action of vancomycin results primarily from inhibition of cell-wall biosynthesis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1253" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In addition, vancomycin alters bacterial-cell-membrane permeability and RNA synthesis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1254" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Resistance Vancomycin is not active in vitro against gram-negative bacilli, mycobacteria, or fungi.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1255" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There is no cross-resistance between vancomycin and other antibacterials.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1256" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Interaction With Other Antimicrobials The combination of vancomycin and an aminoglycoside acts synergistically in vitro against many isolates of Staphylococcus aureus, Streptococcus gallolyticus (previously known as Streptococcus bovis), enterococcus spp, and the viridans group streptococci.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1257" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Antimicrobial Activity Vancomycin has been shown to be active against most isolates of the following microorganisms, both in vitro and in clinical infections.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1258" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Aerobic Gram-Positive Bacteria Corynebacterium spp.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1259" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>(including Enterococcus faecalis) Staphylococcus aureus (including methicillin-resistant and methicillin-susceptible isolates) Coagulase negative staphylococci (including S. epidermidis and methicillin-resistant isolates) Streptococcus gallolyticus (previously known as Streptococcus bovis) Viridans group streptococci The following in vitro data are available, but their clinical significance is unknown.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1260" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>At least 90 percent of the following bacteria exhibit an in vitro minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) less than or equal to the susceptible breakpoint for vancomycin against isolates of similar genus or organism group.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1261" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>However, the efficacy of vancomycin in treating clinical infections caused by these bacteria has not been established in adequate and well-controlled clinical trials.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="1262" LabelDrug="Vancomycin Hydrochloride" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Aerobic Gram-Positive Bacteria Listeria monocytogenes Streptococcus pyogenes Streptococcus pneumoniae Streptococcus agalactiae Anaerobic Gram-Positive Bacteria Actinomyces species Lactobacillus species Susceptibility Testing For specific information regarding susceptibility test interpretive criteria and associated test methods and quality control standards recognized by FDA for this drug, please see: https://www.fda.gov/STIC.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="beta-lactam antibacterial drugs" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="anesthetic agents" precipitantCode="N0000175681" effect="238810007: Flushing (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="anesthetic agents" precipitantCode="N0000175681" effect="247441003: Erythema (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="anesthetic agents" precipitantCode="N0000175681" effect="441940003: Adverse reaction caused by drug or medicament administered by infusion (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="piperacillin/tazobactam" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="14350001000004108: Acute injury of kidney (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="piperacillin/tazobactam" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nephrotoxic drugs" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nephrotoxic drugs" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="neurotoxic | drugs" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="39539005: Abnormal renal function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="muscle relaxant anesthetics" precipitantCode="N0000175737"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="piperacillin-tazobactam" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="aminoglycoside" precipitantCode="N0000175929"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="ototoxic agent" precipitantCode="N0000175828"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="drugs which may cause neutropenia" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="165509000: White blood cell count abnormal (finding)"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>