<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Arixtra" setid="d3b30c68-cf45-4b46-8ba6-72090f7ba01a">
<Text><Section name="Boxed Warning section" id="34066-1">
Epidural or spinal hematomas may occur in patients who are anticoagulated with low molecular weight heparins (LMWH), heparinoids, or fondaparinux sodium and are receiving neuraxial anesthesia or undergoing spinal puncture. These hematomas may result in long-term or permanent paralysis. Consider these risks when scheduling patients for spinal procedures. Factors that can increase the risk of developing epidural or spinal hematomas in these patients include: • use of indwelling epidural catheters • concomitant use of other drugs that affect hemostasis, such as non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), platelet inhibitors, or other anticoagulants • a history of traumatic or repeated epidural or spinal puncture • a history of spinal deformity or spinal surgery • Optimal timing between the administration of ARIXTRA and neuraxial procedures is not known. Monitor patients frequently for signs and symptoms of neurologic impairment. If neurologic compromise is noted, urgent treatment is necessary. Consider the benefit and risks before neuraxial intervention in patients anticoagulated or to be anticoagulated for thromboprophylaxis. [See Warnings and Precautions (5.1) and Drug Interactions (7) .] WARNING: SPINAL/EPIDURAL HEMATOMAS See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning. Epidural or spinal hematomas may occur in patients who are anticoagulated with low molecular weight heparins (LMWH), heparinoids, or fondaparinux sodium and are receiving neuraxial anesthesia or undergoing spinal puncture. These hematomas may result in long-term or permanent paralysis. Consider these risks when scheduling patients for spinal procedures. Factors that can increase the risk of developing epidural or spinal hematomas in these patients include: • use of indwelling epidural catheters • concomitant use of other drugs that affect hemostasis, such as non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), platelet inhibitors, or other anticoagulants • a history of traumatic or repeated epidural or spinal puncture • a history of spinal deformity or spinal surgery Monitor patients frequently for signs and symptoms of neurologic impairment. If neurologic compromise is noted, urgent treatment is necessary. Consider the benefit and risks before neuraxial intervention in patients anticoagulated or to be anticoagulated for thromboprophylaxis. [See Warnings and Precautions (5.1) and Drug Interactions (7) .]</Section>
<Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
ARIXTRA is contraindicated in the following conditions: • Severe renal impairment (creatinine clearance [CrCl] &amp;lt;30 mL/min). [See Warnings and Precautions (5.3) and Use in Specific Populations (8.6) .] • Active major bleeding. • Bacterial endocarditis. • Thrombocytopenia associated with a positive in vitro test for anti-platelet antibody in the presence of fondaparinux sodium. • Body weight &amp;lt;50 kg (venous thromboembolism [VTE] prophylaxis only) [see Warnings and Precautions (5.4) ]. • History of serious hypersensitivity reaction (e.g., angioedema, anaphylactoid/anaphylactic reactions) to ARIXTRA. ARIXTRA is contraindicated in the following conditions: ( 4 ) • Severe renal impairment (creatinine clearance &amp;lt;30 mL/min) in prophylaxis or treatment of venous thromboembolism. • Active major bleeding. • Bacterial endocarditis. • Thrombocytopenia associated with a positive in vitro test for anti-platelet antibody in the presence of fondaparinux sodium. • Body weight &amp;lt;50 kg (venous thromboembolism prophylaxis only). • History of serious hypersensitivity reaction (e.g., angioedema, anaphylactoid/anaphylactic reactions) to ARIXTRA.</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
Do not mix other medications or solutions with ARIXTRA. Administer ARIXTRA only subcutaneously. • Prophylaxis of deep vein thrombosis: ARIXTRA 2.5 mg subcutaneously once daily after hemostasis has been established. The initial dose should be given no earlier than 6 to 8 hours after surgery and continued for 5 to 9 days. For patients undergoing hip fracture surgery, extended prophylaxis up to 24 additional days is recommended. ( 2.1 , 2.2 ) • Treatment of deep vein thrombosis and pulmonary embolism: ARIXTRA 5 mg (body weight &amp;lt;50 kg), 7.5 mg (50 to 100 kg), or 10 mg (&amp;gt;100 kg) subcutaneously once daily. Treatment should continue for at least 5 days until INR 2 to 3 achieved with warfarin sodium. ( 2.3 ) Do not use as intramuscular injection. For subcutaneous use, do not mix with other injections or infusions. In patients undergoing hip fracture, hip replacement, or knee replacement surgery, the recommended dose of ARIXTRA is 2.5 mg administered by subcutaneous injection once daily after hemostasis has been established. Administer the initial dose no earlier than 6 to 8 hours after surgery. Administration of ARIXTRA earlier than 6 hours after surgery increases the risk of major bleeding. The usual duration of therapy is 5 to 9 days; up to 11 days of therapy was administered in clinical trials. In patients undergoing hip fracture surgery, an extended prophylaxis course of up to 24 additional days is recommended. In patients undergoing hip fracture surgery, a total of 32 days (peri-operative and extended prophylaxis) was administered in clinical trials. [See Warnings and Precautions (5.6) , Adverse Reactions (6) , and Clinical Studies (14) .] In patients undergoing abdominal surgery, the recommended dose of ARIXTRA is 2.5 mg administered by subcutaneous injection once daily after hemostasis has been established. Administer the initial dose no earlier than 6 to 8 hours after surgery. Administration of ARIXTRA earlier than 6 hours after surgery increases the risk of major bleeding. The usual duration of administration is 5 to 9 days, and up to 10 days of ARIXTRA was administered in clinical trials. In patients with acute symptomatic DVT and in patients with acute symptomatic PE, the recommended dose of ARIXTRA is 5 mg (body weight &amp;lt;50 kg), 7.5 mg (body weight 50 to 100 kg), or 10 mg (body weight &amp;gt;100 kg) by subcutaneous injection once daily (ARIXTRA treatment regimen). Initiate concomitant treatment with warfarin sodium as soon as possible, usually within 72 hours. Continue treatment with ARIXTRA for at least 5 days and until a therapeutic oral anticoagulant effect is established (INR 2 to 3). The usual duration of administration of ARIXTRA is 5 to 9 days; up to 26 days of ARIXTRA injection was administered in clinical trials. [See Warnings and Precautions (5.6) , Adverse Reactions (6) , and Clinical Studies (14) .] No dose adjustment is recommended in patients with mild to moderate hepatic impairment, based upon single-dose pharmacokinetic data. Pharmacokinetic data are not available for patients with severe hepatic impairment. Patients with hepatic impairment may be particularly vulnerable to bleeding during ARIXTRA therapy. Observe these patients closely for signs and symptoms of bleeding. [See Clinical Pharmacology (12.4) .] ARIXTRA Injection is provided in a single-dose, prefilled syringe affixed with an automatic needle protection system. ARIXTRA is administered by subcutaneous injection. It must not be administered by intramuscular injection. ARIXTRA is intended for use under a physician’s guidance. Patients may self-inject only if their physician determines that it is appropriate and the patients are trained in subcutaneous injection techniques. Prior to administration, visually inspect ARIXTRA to ensure the solution is clear and free of particulate matter. To avoid the loss of drug when using the prefilled syringe, do not expel the air bubble from the syringe before the injection. Administration should be made in the fatty tissue, alternating injection sites (e.g., between the left and right anterolateral or the left and right posterolateral abdominal wall). To administer ARIXTRA: 1. Wipe the surface of the injection site with an alcohol swab. 2. Hold the syringe with either hand and use your other hand to twist the rigid needle guard (covers the needle) counter-clockwise. Pull the rigid needle guard straight off the needle (Figure 1). Discard the needle guard. 3. Do not try to remove the air bubbles from the syringe before giving the injection. 4. Pinch a fold of skin at the injection site between your thumb and forefinger and hold it throughout the injection. 5. Hold the syringe with your thumb on the top pad of the plunger rod and your next 2 fingers on the finger grips on the syringe barrel. Pay attention to avoid sticking yourself with the exposed needle (Figure 2). 6. Insert the full length of the syringe needle perpendicularly into the skin fold held between the thumb and forefinger (Figure 3). 7. Push the plunger rod firmly with your thumb as far as it will go. This will ensure you have injected all the contents of the syringe (Figure 4). 8. When you have injected all the contents of the syringe, the plunger should be released. The plunger will then rise automatically while the needle withdraws from the skin and retracts into the security sleeve. Discard the syringe into the sharps container. 9. You will know that the syringe has worked when: • The needle is pulled back into the security sleeve and the white safety indicator appears above the upper body. • You may also hear or feel a soft click when the plunger rod is released fully. Figure 1 and 2 Figure 3 and 4</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
In clinical studies performed with ARIXTRA, the concomitant use of oral anticoagulants (warfarin), platelet inhibitors (acetylsalicylic acid), NSAIDs (piroxicam), and digoxin did not significantly affect the pharmacokinetics/pharmacodynamics of fondaparinux sodium. In addition, ARIXTRA neither influenced the pharmacodynamics of warfarin, acetylsalicylic acid, piroxicam, and digoxin, nor the pharmacokinetics of digoxin at steady state. Agents that may enhance the risk of hemorrhage should be discontinued prior to initiation of therapy with ARIXTRA unless these agents are essential. If co-administration is necessary, monitor patients closely for hemorrhage. [See Warnings and Precautions (5.2) .] In an in vitro study in human liver microsomes, inhibition of CYP2A6 hydroxylation of coumarin by fondaparinux (200 micromolar i.e., 350 mg/L) was 17 to 28%. Inhibition of the other isozymes evaluated (CYPs 1A2, 2C9, 2C19, 2D6, 3A4, and 3E1) was 0 to 16%. Since fondaparinux does not markedly inhibit CYP450s (CYP1A2, CYP2A6, CYP2C9, CYP2C19, CYP2D6, CYP2E1, or CYP3A4) in vitro , fondaparinux sodium is not expected to significantly interact with other drugs in vivo by inhibition of metabolism mediated by these isozymes. Since fondaparinux sodium does not bind significantly to plasma proteins other than ATIII, no drug interactions by protein-binding displacement are expected. Discontinue agents that may enhance the risk of hemorrhage prior to initiation of therapy with ARIXTRA unless essential. If co-administration is necessary, monitor patients closely for hemorrhage. ( 7 )</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
• Spinal or epidural hematomas, which may result in long-term or permanent paralysis, can occur. ( 5.1 ) • Patients taking ARIXTRA with risk factors for bleeding are at increased risk of hemorrhage. ( 5.2 ) • Bleeding risk is increased in renal impairment and in patients with low body weight &amp;lt;50 kg. ( 5.3 , 5.4 ) • Thrombocytopenia can occur with administration of ARIXTRA. ( 5.5 ) • Periodic routine complete blood counts (including platelet counts), serum creatinine level, and stool occult blood tests are recommended ( 5.6 ) • The packaging (needle guard) contains dry natural rubber and may cause allergic reactions in latex sensitive individuals ( 5.7 ) Spinal or epidural hematomas, which may result in long-term or permanent paralysis, can occur with the use of anticoagulants and neuraxial (spinal/epidural) anesthesia or spinal puncture. The risk of these events may be higher with post-operative use of indwelling epidural catheters or concomitant use of other drugs affecting hemostasis such as NSAIDs [see Boxed Warning ] . In the postmarketing experience, epidural or spinal hematoma has been reported in association with the use of ARIXTRA by subcutaneous (SC) injection. Optimal timing between the administration of ARIXTRA and neuraxial procedures is not known. Monitor patients undergoing these procedures for signs and symptoms of neurologic impairment such as midline back pain, sensory and motor deficits (numbness, tingling, or weakness in lower limbs), and bowel or bladder dysfunction. Consider the potential risks and benefits before neuraxial intervention in patients anticoagulated or who may be anticoagulated for thromboprophylaxis. ARIXTRA increases the risk of hemorrhage in patients at risk for bleeding, including conditions such as congenital or acquired bleeding disorders, active ulcerative and angiodysplastic gastrointestinal disease, hemorrhagic stroke, uncontrolled arterial hypertension, diabetic retinopathy, or shortly after brain, spinal, or ophthalmological surgery. Cases of elevated aPTT temporally associated with bleeding events have been reported following administration of ARIXTRA (with or without concomitant administration of other anticoagulants) [see Adverse Reactions (6.5) ]. Do not administer agents that enhance the risk of hemorrhage with ARIXTRA unless essential for the management of the underlying condition, such as vitamin K antagonists for the treatment of VTE. If co-administration is essential, closely monitor patients for signs and symptoms of bleeding. Do not administer the initial dose of ARIXTRA earlier than 6 to 8 hours after surgery. Administration earlier than 6 hours after surgery increases risk of major bleeding [see Dosage and Administration (2) and Adverse Reactions (6.1) ]. ARIXTRA increases the risk of bleeding in patients with impaired renal function due to reduced clearance [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.4) ]. The incidence of major bleeding by renal function status reported in clinical trials of patients receiving ARIXTRA for VTE surgical prophylaxis is provided in Table 1. In these patient populations, the following is recommended: • Do not use ARIXTRA for VTE prophylaxis and treatment in patients with CrCl &amp;lt;30 mL/min [see Contraindications (4) ]. • ARIXTRA may cause prolonged anticoagulation in patients with CrCl 30 to 50 mL/min. Table 1. Incidence of Major Bleeding in Patients Treated With ARIXTRA by Renal Function Status for Surgical Prophylaxis and Treatment of Deep Vein Thrombosis (DVT) and Pulmonary Embolism (PE) CrCl = creatinine clearance. Degree of Renal Impairment Population Timing of Dose Normal % (n/N) Mild % (n/N) Moderate % (n/N) Severe % (n/N) CrCl (mL/min) ≥80 ≥50 - &amp;lt;80 ≥30 - &amp;lt;50 &amp;lt;30 Orthopedic surgery Hip fracture, hip replacement, and knee replacement surgery prophylaxis. Overall 1.6% (25/1,565) 2.4% (31/1,288) 3.8% (19/504) 4.8% (4/83) 6-8 hours after surgery 1.8% (16/905) 2.2% (15/675) 2.3% (6/265) 0% (0/40) Abdominal surgery Overall 2.1% (13/606) 3.6% (22/613) 6.7% (12/179) 7.1% (1/14) 6-8 hours after surgery 2.1% (10/467) 3.3% (16/481) 5.8% (8/137) 7.7% (1/13) DVT and PE Treatment 0.4% (4/1,132) 1.6% (12/733) 2.2% (7/318) 7.3% (4/55) Assess renal function periodically in patients receiving ARIXTRA. Discontinue the drug immediately in patients who develop severe renal impairment while on therapy. After discontinuation of ARIXTRA, its anticoagulant effects may persist for 2 to 4 days in patients with normal renal function (i.e., at least 3 to 5 half-lives). The anticoagulant effects of ARIXTRA may persist even longer in patients with renal impairment [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.4) ]. ARIXTRA increases the risk for bleeding in patients who weigh less than 50 kg, compared to patients with higher weights. In patients who weigh less than 50 kg: • Do not administer ARIXTRA as prophylactic therapy for patients undergoing hip fracture, hip replacement, or knee replacement surgery and abdominal surgery [see Contraindications (4) ]. During the randomized clinical trials of VTE prophylaxis in the peri-operative period following hip fracture, hip replacement, or knee replacement surgery and abdominal surgery, major bleeding occurred at a higher rate among patients with a body weight &amp;lt;50 kg compared to those with a body weight &amp;gt;50 kg (5.4% versus 2.1% in patients undergoing hip fracture, hip replacement, or knee replacement surgery; 5.3% versus 3.3% in patients undergoing abdominal surgery). Thrombocytopenia can occur with the administration of ARIXTRA. Thrombocytopenia of any degree should be monitored closely. Discontinue ARIXTRA if the platelet count falls below 100,000/mm 3 . Moderate thrombocytopenia (platelet counts between 100,000/mm 3 and 50,000/mm 3 ) occurred at a rate of 3.0% in patients given ARIXTRA 2.5 mg in the peri-operative hip fracture, hip replacement, or knee replacement surgery and abdominal surgery clinical trials. Severe thrombocytopenia (platelet counts less than 50,000/mm 3 ) occurred at a rate of 0.2% in patients given ARIXTRA 2.5 mg in these clinical trials. During extended prophylaxis, no cases of moderate or severe thrombocytopenia were reported. Moderate thrombocytopenia occurred at a rate of 0.5% in patients given the ARIXTRA treatment regimen in the DVT and PE treatment clinical trials. Severe thrombocytopenia occurred at a rate of 0.04% in patients given the ARIXTRA treatment regimen in the DVT and PE treatment clinical trials. Occurrences of thrombocytopenia with thrombosis that manifested similar to heparin-induced thrombocytopenia have been reported with the use of ARIXTRA in postmarketing experience. [See Adverse Reactions (6.5) .] Routine coagulation tests such as Prothrombin Time (PT) and Activated Partial Thromboplastin Time (aPTT) are relatively insensitive measures of the activity of ARIXTRA and international standards of heparin or LMWH are not calibrators to measure anti-Factor Xa activity of ARIXTRA. If unexpected changes in coagulation parameters or major bleeding occur during therapy with ARIXTRA, discontinue ARIXTRA. In postmarketing experience, occurrences of aPTT elevations have been reported following administration of ARIXTRA [see Adverse Reactions (6.5) ] . Periodic routine complete blood counts (including platelet count), serum creatinine level, and stool occult blood tests are recommended during the course of treatment with ARIXTRA. The anti-Factor Xa activity of fondaparinux sodium can be measured by anti-Xa assay using the appropriate calibrator (fondaparinux). The activity of fondaparinux sodium is expressed in milligrams (mg) of the fondaparinux and cannot be compared with activities of heparin or low molecular weight heparins. [See Clinical Pharmacology (12.2 , 12.3) .] The packaging (needle guard) of the prefilled syringe of ARIXTRA contains dry natural latex rubber that may cause allergic reactions in latex sensitive individuals.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
The antithrombotic activity of fondaparinux sodium is the result of antithrombin III (ATIII)-mediated selective inhibition of Factor Xa. By selectively binding to ATIII, fondaparinux sodium potentiates (about 300 times) the innate neutralization of Factor Xa by ATIII. Neutralization of Factor Xa interrupts the blood coagulation cascade and thus inhibits thrombin formation and thrombus development. Fondaparinux sodium does not inactivate thrombin (activated Factor II) and has no known effect on platelet function. At the recommended dose, fondaparinux sodium does not affect fibrinolytic activity or bleeding time. The pharmacodynamics/pharmacokinetics of fondaparinux sodium are derived from fondaparinux plasma concentrations quantified via anti-Factor Xa activity. Only fondaparinux can be used to calibrate the anti-Xa assay. (The international standards of heparin or LMWH are not appropriate for this use.) As a result, the activity of fondaparinux sodium is expressed as milligrams (mg) of the fondaparinux calibrator. The anti-Xa activity of the drug increases with increasing drug concentration, reaching maximum values in approximately three hours. Fondaparinux sodium administered by subcutaneous injection is rapidly and completely absorbed (absolute bioavailability is 100%). Following a single subcutaneous dose of fondaparinux sodium 2.5 mg in young male subjects, C max of 0.34 mg/L is reached in approximately 2 hours. In patients undergoing treatment with fondaparinux sodium injection 2.5 mg, once daily, the peak steady-state plasma concentration is, on average, 0.39 to 0.50 mg/L and is reached approximately 3 hours post-dose. In these patients, the minimum steady-state plasma concentration is 0.14 to 0.19 mg/L. In patients with symptomatic deep vein thrombosis and pulmonary embolism undergoing treatment with fondaparinux sodium injection 5 mg (body weight &amp;lt;50 kg), 7.5 mg (body weight 50 to 100 kg), and 10 mg (body weight &amp;gt;100 kg) once daily, the body–weight-adjusted doses provide similar mean steady-state peaks and minimum plasma concentrations across all body weight categories. The mean peak steady-state plasma concentration is in the range of 1.20 to 1.26 mg/L. In these patients, the mean minimum steady-state plasma concentration is in the range of 0.46 to 0.62 mg/L. In healthy adults, intravenously or subcutaneously administered fondaparinux sodium distributes mainly in blood and only to a minor extent in extravascular fluid as evidenced by steady state and non-steady state apparent volume of distribution of 7 to 11 L. Similar fondaparinux distribution occurs in patients undergoing elective hip surgery or hip fracture surgery. In vitro, fondaparinux sodium is highly (at least 94%) and specifically bound to antithrombin III (ATIII) and does not bind significantly to other plasma proteins (including platelet Factor 4 [PF4]) or red blood cells. In vivo metabolism of fondaparinux has not been investigated since the majority of the administered dose is eliminated unchanged in urine in individuals with normal kidney function. In individuals with normal kidney function, fondaparinux is eliminated in urine mainly as unchanged drug. In healthy individuals up to 75 years of age, up to 77% of a single subcutaneous or intravenous fondaparinux dose is eliminated in urine as unchanged drug in 72 hours. The elimination half-life is 17 to 21 hours. Fondaparinux elimination is prolonged in patients with renal impairment since the major route of elimination is urinary excretion of unchanged drug. In patients undergoing prophylaxis following elective hip surgery or hip fracture surgery, the total clearance of fondaparinux is approximately 25% lower in patients with mild renal impairment (CrCl 50 to 80 mL/min), approximately 40% lower in patients with moderate renal impairment (CrCl 30 to 50 mL/min), and approximately 55% lower in patients with severe renal impairment (&amp;lt;30 mL/min) compared to patients with normal renal function. A similar relationship between fondaparinux clearance and extent of renal impairment was observed in DVT treatment patients. [See Contraindications (4) and Warnings and Precautions (5.3) .] Following a single, subcutaneous dose of 7.5 mg of ARIXTRA in patients with moderate hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh Category B), C max and AUC were decreased by 22% and 39%, respectively, compared to subjects with normal liver function. The changes from baseline in pharmacodynamic parameters, such as aPTT, PT/INR, and antithrombin III, were similar in normal subjects and in patients with moderate hepatic impairment. Based on these data, no dosage adjustment is recommended in these patients. However, a higher incidence of hemorrhage was observed in subjects with moderate hepatic impairment than in normal subjects [see Use in Specific Populations (8.7) ] . The pharmacokinetics of fondaparinux have not been studied in patients with severe hepatic impairment. [See Dosage and Administration (2.4) .] The pharmacokinetics of fondaparinux have not been investigated in pediatric patients. [See Contraindications (4) , Warnings and Precautions (5.4) , and Pediatric Use (8.4) .] Fondaparinux elimination is prolonged in patients older than 75 years. In studies evaluating fondaparinux sodium 2.5 mg prophylaxis in hip fracture surgery or elective hip surgery, the total clearance of fondaparinux was approximately 25% lower in patients older than 75 years as compared to patients younger than 65 years. A similar relationship between fondaparinux clearance and age was observed in DVT treatment patients. [See Use in Specific Populations (8.5) .] Total clearance of fondaparinux sodium is decreased by approximately 30% in patients weighing less than 50 kg [see Dosage and Administration (2.3) and Contraindications (4) ] . The pharmacokinetic properties of fondaparinux sodium are not significantly affected by gender. Pharmacokinetic differences due to race have not been studied prospectively. However, studies performed in Asian (Japanese) healthy subjects did not reveal a different pharmacokinetic profile compared to Caucasian healthy subjects. Similarly, no plasma clearance differences were observed between black and Caucasian patients undergoing orthopedic surgery.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="2136" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Epidural or spinal hematomas may occur in patients who are anticoagulated with low molecular weight heparins (LMWH), heparinoids, or fondaparinux sodium and are receiving neuraxial anesthesia or undergoing spinal puncture.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M4" type="Trigger" span="33 5" str="occur"/>
<Mention id="M5" type="Precipitant" span="171 20" str="neuraxial anesthesia" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M3" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 8;19 9" str="epidural | hematomas" code="703861005: Spinal epidural hematoma (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M6" type="SpecificInteraction" span="12 16" str="spinal hematomas" code="674481000119100: Spontaneous hematoma of spinal cord (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M4" precipitant="M5" effect="M3" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M4" precipitant="M5" effect="M6" effectCodeMatch="Close Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2137" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>These hematomas may result in long-term or permanent paralysis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2138" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Consider these risks when scheduling patients for spinal procedures.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2139" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Factors that can increase the risk of developing epidural or spinal hematomas in these patients include: use of indwelling epidural catheters concomitant use of other drugs that affect hemostasis, such as non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), platelet inhibitors, or other anticoagulants a history of traumatic or repeated epidural or spinal puncture a history of spinal deformity or spinal surgery Optimal timing between the administration of ARIXTRA and neuraxial procedures is not known.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M34" type="Trigger" span="17 17" str="increase the risk"/>
<Mention id="M11" type="Precipitant" span="283 14" str="anticoagulants" code="N0000029110 | N0000175980"/>
<Mention id="M33" type="SpecificInteraction" span="49 8;68 9" str="epidural | hematomas" code="703861005: Spinal epidural hematoma (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M36" type="SpecificInteraction" span="61 16" str="spinal hematomas" code="674481000119100: Spontaneous hematoma of spinal cord (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M17" type="Precipitant" span="167 28" str="drugs that affect hemostasis" code="N0000009070"/>
<Mention id="M23" type="Precipitant" span="205 37" str="non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M29" type="Precipitant" span="244 6" str="NSAIDs" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M35" type="Precipitant" span="253 19" str="platelet inhibitors" code="N0000182142 | N0000175578"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M34" precipitant="M11" effect="M33" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M34" precipitant="M11" effect="M36" effectCodeMatch="Close Match"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M34" precipitant="M17" effect="M33" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M34" precipitant="M17" effect="M36" effectCodeMatch="Close Match"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M34" precipitant="M23" effect="M33" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M34" precipitant="M23" effect="M36" effectCodeMatch="Close Match"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M34" precipitant="M29" effect="M33" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M34" precipitant="M29" effect="M36" effectCodeMatch="Close Match"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M34" precipitant="M35" effect="M33" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M34" precipitant="M35" effect="M36" effectCodeMatch="Close Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2140" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Monitor patients frequently for signs and symptoms of neurologic impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2141" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>If neurologic compromise is noted, urgent treatment is necessary.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2142" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Consider the benefit and risks before neuraxial intervention in patients anticoagulated or to be anticoagulated for thromboprophylaxis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2143" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>WARNING: SPINAL/EPIDURAL HEMATOMAS See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2144" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Factors that can increase the risk of developing epidural or spinal hematomas in these patients include: use of indwelling epidural catheters concomitant use of other drugs that affect hemostasis, such as non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), platelet inhibitors, or other anticoagulants a history of traumatic or repeated epidural or spinal puncture a history of spinal deformity or spinal surgery Monitor patients frequently for signs and symptoms of neurologic impairment.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M64" type="Trigger" span="17 17" str="increase the risk"/>
<Mention id="M41" type="Precipitant" span="283 14" str="anticoagulants" code="N0000029110 | N0000175980"/>
<Mention id="M63" type="SpecificInteraction" span="49 8;68 9" str="epidural | hematomas" code="703861005: Spinal epidural hematoma (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M66" type="SpecificInteraction" span="61 16" str="spinal hematomas" code="674481000119100: Spontaneous hematoma of spinal cord (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M47" type="Precipitant" span="167 28" str="drugs that affect hemostasis" code="N0000009070"/>
<Mention id="M53" type="Precipitant" span="205 37" str="non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M59" type="Precipitant" span="244 6" str="NSAIDs" code="N0000175722"/>
<Mention id="M65" type="Precipitant" span="253 19" str="platelet inhibitors" code="N0000182142 | N0000175578"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M64" precipitant="M41" effect="M63" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M64" precipitant="M41" effect="M66" effectCodeMatch="Close Match"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M64" precipitant="M47" effect="M63" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M64" precipitant="M47" effect="M66" effectCodeMatch="Close Match"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M64" precipitant="M53" effect="M63" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M64" precipitant="M53" effect="M66" effectCodeMatch="Close Match"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M64" precipitant="M59" effect="M63" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M64" precipitant="M59" effect="M66" effectCodeMatch="Close Match"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M64" precipitant="M65" effect="M63" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M64" precipitant="M65" effect="M66" effectCodeMatch="Close Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2145" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>ARIXTRA is contraindicated in the following conditions: Severe renal impairment (creatinine clearance [CrCl] &lt;30 mL/min).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2146" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Thrombocytopenia associated with a positive in vitro test for anti-platelet antibody in the presence of fondaparinux sodium.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2147" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Body weight &lt;50 kg (venous thromboembolism [VTE] prophylaxis only).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2148" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>History of serious hypersensitivity reaction (e.g., angioedema, anaphylactoid/anaphylactic reactions) to ARIXTRA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2149" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>ARIXTRA is contraindicated in the following conditions: (4) Severe renal impairment (creatinine clearance &lt;30 mL/min) in prophylaxis or treatment of venous thromboembolism.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2150" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Body weight &lt;50 kg (venous thromboembolism prophylaxis only).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2151" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not mix other medications or solutions with ARIXTRA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2152" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Prophylaxis of deep vein thrombosis: ARIXTRA 2.5 mg subcutaneously once daily after hemostasis has been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2153" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The initial dose should be given no earlier than 6 to 8 hours after surgery and continued for 5 to 9 days.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2154" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For patients undergoing hip fracture surgery, extended prophylaxis up to 24 additional days is recommended.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2155" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Treatment of deep vein thrombosis and pulmonary embolism: ARIXTRA 5 mg (body weight &lt;50 kg), 7.5 mg (50 to 100 kg), or 10 mg (&gt;100 kg) subcutaneously once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2156" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Treatment should continue for at least 5 days until INR 2 to 3 achieved with warfarin sodium.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2157" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Do not use as intramuscular injection.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2158" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For subcutaneous use, do not mix with other injections or infusions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2159" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In patients undergoing hip fracture, hip replacement, or knee replacement surgery, the recommended dose of ARIXTRA is 2.5 mg administered by subcutaneous injection once daily after hemostasis has been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2160" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Administer the initial dose no earlier than 6 to 8 hours after surgery.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2161" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Administration of ARIXTRA earlier than 6 hours after surgery increases the risk of major bleeding.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2162" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The usual duration of therapy is 5 to 9 days; up to 11 days of therapy was administered in clinical trials.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2163" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In patients undergoing hip fracture surgery, an extended prophylaxis course of up to 24 additional days is recommended.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2164" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In patients undergoing hip fracture surgery, a total of 32 days (peri-operative and extended prophylaxis) was administered in clinical trials.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2165" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In patients undergoing abdominal surgery, the recommended dose of ARIXTRA is 2.5 mg administered by subcutaneous injection once daily after hemostasis has been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2166" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The usual duration of administration is 5 to 9 days, and up to 10 days of ARIXTRA was administered in clinical trials.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2167" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In patients with acute symptomatic DVT and in patients with acute symptomatic PE, the recommended dose of ARIXTRA is 5 mg (body weight &lt;50 kg), 7.5 mg (body weight 50 to 100 kg), or 10 mg (body weight &gt;100 kg) by subcutaneous injection once daily (ARIXTRA treatment regimen).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2168" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Initiate concomitant treatment with warfarin sodium as soon as possible, usually within 72 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2169" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Continue treatment with ARIXTRA for at least 5 days and until a therapeutic oral anticoagulant effect is established (INR 2 to 3).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2170" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The usual duration of administration of ARIXTRA is 5 to 9 days; up to 26 days of ARIXTRA injection was administered in clinical trials.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2171" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>No dose adjustment is recommended in patients with mild to moderate hepatic impairment, based upon single-dose pharmacokinetic data.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2172" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Pharmacokinetic data are not available for patients with severe hepatic impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2173" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Patients with hepatic impairment may be particularly vulnerable to bleeding during ARIXTRA therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2174" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Observe these patients closely for signs and symptoms of bleeding.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2175" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>ARIXTRA Injection is provided in a single-dose, prefilled syringe affixed with an automatic needle protection system.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2176" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>ARIXTRA is administered by subcutaneous injection.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2177" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>It must not be administered by intramuscular injection.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2178" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>ARIXTRA is intended for use under a physician’s guidance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2179" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Patients may self-inject only if their physician determines that it is appropriate and the patients are trained in subcutaneous injection techniques.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2180" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Prior to administration, visually inspect ARIXTRA to ensure the solution is clear and free of particulate matter.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2181" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>To avoid the loss of drug when using the prefilled syringe, do not expel the air bubble from the syringe before the injection.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2182" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Administration should be made in the fatty tissue, alternating injection sites (e.g., between the left and right anterolateral or the left and right posterolateral abdominal wall).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2183" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>To administer ARIXTRA: 1.Wipe the surface of the injection site with an alcohol swab.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2184" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>2.Hold the syringe with either hand and use your other hand to twist the rigid needle guard (covers the needle) counter-clockwise.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2185" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Pull the rigid needle guard straight off the needle (Figure 1).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2186" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>3.Do not try to remove the air bubbles from the syringe before giving the injection.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2187" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>4.Pinch a fold of skin at the injection site between your thumb and forefinger and hold it throughout the injection.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2188" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>5.Hold the syringe with your thumb on the top pad of the plunger rod and your next 2 fingers on the finger grips on the syringe barrel.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2189" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Pay attention to avoid sticking yourself with the exposed needle (Figure 2).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2190" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>6.Insert the full length of the syringe needle perpendicularly into the skin fold held between the thumb and forefinger (Figure 3).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2191" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>7.Push the plunger rod firmly with your thumb as far as it will go.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2192" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>This will ensure you have injected all the contents of the syringe (Figure 4).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2193" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>8.When you have injected all the contents of the syringe, the plunger should be released.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2194" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The plunger will then rise automatically while the needle withdraws from the skin and retracts into the security sleeve.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2195" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Discard the syringe into the sharps container.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2196" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>9.You will know that the syringe has worked when: The needle is pulled back into the security sleeve and the white safety indicator appears above the upper body.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2197" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>You may also hear or feel a soft click when the plunger rod is released fully.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2198" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Figure 1 and 2 Figure 3 and 4</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2199" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>In clinical studies performed with ARIXTRA, the concomitant use of oral anticoagulants (warfarin), platelet inhibitors (acetylsalicylic acid), NSAIDs (piroxicam), and digoxin did not significantly affect the pharmacokinetics/pharmacodynamics of fondaparinux sodium.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2200" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>In addition, ARIXTRA neither influenced the pharmacodynamics of warfarin, acetylsalicylic acid, piroxicam, and digoxin, nor the pharmacokinetics of digoxin at steady state.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2201" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Agents that may enhance the risk of hemorrhage should be discontinued prior to initiation of therapy with ARIXTRA unless these agents are essential.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M67" type="Trigger" span="47 22" str="should be discontinued "/>
<Mention id="M68" type="Trigger" span="16 16" str=" enhance the risk"/>
<Mention id="M69" type="Precipitant" span="0 46" str="Agents that may enhance the risk of hemorrhage" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M70" type="SpecificInteraction" span="36 10" str="hemorrhage" code="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M67;M68" precipitant="M69" effect="M70" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2202" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>If co-administration is necessary, monitor patients closely for hemorrhage.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2203" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>In an in vitro study in human liver microsomes, inhibition of CYP2A6 hydroxylation of coumarin by fondaparinux (200 micromolar i.e., 350 mg/L) was 17 to 28%.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M71" type="Trigger" span="48 34" str="inhibition of CYP2A6 hydroxylation"/>
<Mention id="M72" type="Precipitant" span="86 8" str="coumarin" code="A4VZ22K1WT"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M71" precipitant="M72" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2204" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Inhibition of the other isozymes evaluated (CYPs 1A2, 2C9, 2C19, 2D6, 3A4, and 3E1) was 0 to 16%.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2205" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Since fondaparinux does not markedly inhibit CYP450s (CYP1A2, CYP2A6, CYP2C9, CYP2C19, CYP2D6, CYP2E1, or CYP3A4) in vitro,fondaparinux sodium is not expected to significantly interact with other drugs in vivo by inhibition of metabolism mediated by these isozymes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2206" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Since fondaparinux sodium does not bind significantly to plasma proteins other than ATIII, no drug interactions by protein-binding displacement are expected.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2207" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Discontinue agents that may enhance the risk of hemorrhage prior to initiation of therapy with ARIXTRA unless essential.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M73" type="Trigger" span="0 11" str="Discontinue "/>
<Mention id="M74" type="Trigger" span="28 16" str=" enhance the risk"/>
<Mention id="M75" type="Precipitant" span="12 46" str="agents that may enhance the risk of hemorrhage" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M76" type="SpecificInteraction" span="48 10" str="hemorrhage" code="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M73;M74" precipitant="M75" effect="M76" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2208" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Spinal or epidural hematomas, which may result in long-term or permanent paralysis, can occur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2209" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients taking ARIXTRA with risk factors for bleeding are at increased risk of hemorrhage.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2210" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Bleeding risk is increased in renal impairment and in patients with low body weight &lt;50 kg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2211" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Thrombocytopenia can occur with administration of ARIXTRA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2212" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Periodic routine complete blood counts (including platelet counts), serum creatinine level, and stool occult blood tests are recommended (5.6) The packaging (needle guard) contains dry natural rubber and may cause allergic reactions in latex sensitive individuals (5.7) Spinal or epidural hematomas, which may result in long-term or permanent paralysis, can occur with the use of anticoagulants and neuraxial (spinal/epidural) anesthesia or spinal puncture.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M134" type="Trigger" span="358 5" str="occur"/>
<Mention id="M87" type="Precipitant" span="380 14" str="anticoagulants" code="N0000029110 | N0000175980"/>
<Mention id="M127" type="SpecificInteraction" span="280 18" str="epidural hematomas" code="703861005: Spinal epidural hematoma (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M131" type="Trigger" span="310 9" str="result in"/>
<Mention id="M130" type="SpecificInteraction" span="320 9;343 9" str="long-term | paralysis" code="44695005: Paralysis (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M133" type="SpecificInteraction" span="333 19" str="permanent paralysis" code="44695005: Paralysis (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M136" type="SpecificInteraction" span="270 6;289 9" str="Spinal | hematomas" code="299736000:  Intraspinal space-occupying lesion (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M99" type="Precipitant" span="280 8;427 10" str="epidural | anesthesia" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M111" type="Precipitant" span="399 9;427 10" str="neuraxial | anesthesia" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M123" type="Precipitant" span="270 6;427 10" str="spinal | anesthesia" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M135" type="Precipitant" span="410 15;427 10" str="spinal/epidural | anesthesia" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M134" precipitant="M87" effect="M127" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M131" precipitant="M87" effect="M130" effectCodeMatch="Close Match"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M131" precipitant="M87" effect="M133" effectCodeMatch="Close Match"/>
<Interaction id="I29" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M134" precipitant="M87" effect="M136" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I30" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M134" precipitant="M99" effect="M127" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I31" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M131" precipitant="M99" effect="M130" effectCodeMatch="Close Match"/>
<Interaction id="I32" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M131" precipitant="M99" effect="M133" effectCodeMatch="Close Match"/>
<Interaction id="I33" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M134" precipitant="M99" effect="M136" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I34" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M134" precipitant="M111" effect="M127" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I35" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M131" precipitant="M111" effect="M130" effectCodeMatch="Close Match"/>
<Interaction id="I36" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M131" precipitant="M111" effect="M133" effectCodeMatch="Close Match"/>
<Interaction id="I37" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M134" precipitant="M111" effect="M136" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I38" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M134" precipitant="M123" effect="M127" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I39" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M131" precipitant="M123" effect="M130" effectCodeMatch="Close Match"/>
<Interaction id="I40" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M131" precipitant="M123" effect="M133" effectCodeMatch="Close Match"/>
<Interaction id="I41" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M134" precipitant="M123" effect="M136" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I42" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M134" precipitant="M135" effect="M127" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I43" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M131" precipitant="M135" effect="M130" effectCodeMatch="Close Match"/>
<Interaction id="I44" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M131" precipitant="M135" effect="M133" effectCodeMatch="Close Match"/>
<Interaction id="I45" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M134" precipitant="M135" effect="M136" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2213" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The risk of these events may be higher with post-operative use of indwelling epidural catheters or concomitant use of other drugs affecting hemostasis such as NSAIDs.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M139" type="Trigger" span="4 4;32 6" str="risk | higher"/>
<Mention id="M138" type="Precipitant" span="124 26" str="drugs affecting hemostasis" code="N0000009070"/>
<Mention id="M140" type="Precipitant" span="159 6" str="NSAIDs" code="N0000175722"/>
<Interaction id="I46" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M139" precipitant="M138"/>
<Interaction id="I47" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M139" precipitant="M140"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2214" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In the postmarketing experience, epidural or spinal hematoma has been reported in association with the use of ARIXTRA by subcutaneous (SC) injection.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2215" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Optimal timing between the administration of ARIXTRA and neuraxial procedures is not known.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2216" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor patients undergoing these procedures for signs and symptoms of neurologic impairment such as midline back pain, sensory and motor deficits (numbness, tingling, or weakness in lower limbs), and bowel or bladder dysfunction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2217" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Consider the potential risks and benefits before neuraxial intervention in patients anticoagulated or who may be anticoagulated for thromboprophylaxis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2218" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>ARIXTRA increases the risk of hemorrhage in patients at risk for bleeding, including conditions such as congenital or acquired bleeding disorders, active ulcerative and angiodysplastic gastrointestinal disease, hemorrhagic stroke, uncontrolled arterial hypertension, diabetic retinopathy, or shortly after brain, spinal, or ophthalmological surgery.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2219" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Cases of elevated aPTT temporally associated with bleeding events have been reported following administration of ARIXTRA (with or without concomitant administration of other anticoagulants).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2220" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Do not administer agents that enhance the risk of hemorrhage with ARIXTRA unless essential for the management of the underlying condition, such as vitamin K antagonists for the treatment of VTE.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M145" type="Trigger" span="0 17" str="Do not administer "/>
<Mention id="M146" type="Trigger" span="30 16" str=" enhance the risk"/>
<Mention id="M143" type="Precipitant" span="18 42" str="agents that enhance the risk of hemorrhage" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M148" type="SpecificInteraction" span="50 10" str="hemorrhage" code="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M147" type="Precipitant" span="147 21" str="vitamin K antagonists" code="N0000175476"/>
<Interaction id="I48" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M145;M146" precipitant="M143" effect="M148" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I49" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M145;M146" precipitant="M147" effect="M148" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2221" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If co-administration is essential, closely monitor patients for signs and symptoms of bleeding.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2222" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Do not administer the initial dose of ARIXTRA earlier than 6 to 8 hours after surgery.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2223" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Administration earlier than 6 hours after surgery increases risk of major bleeding.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2224" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>ARIXTRA increases the risk of bleeding in patients with impaired renal function due to reduced clearance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2225" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The incidence of major bleeding by renal function status reported in clinical trials of patients receiving ARIXTRA for VTE surgical prophylaxis is provided in Table 1.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2226" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In these patient populations, the following is recommended: Do not use ARIXTRA for VTE prophylaxis and treatment in patients with CrCl &lt;30 mL/min.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2227" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>ARIXTRA may cause prolonged anticoagulation in patients with CrCl 30 to 50 mL/min.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2228" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Incidence of Major Bleeding in Patients Treated With ARIXTRA by Renal Function Status for Surgical Prophylaxis and Treatment of Deep Vein Thrombosis (DVT) and Pulmonary Embolism (PE) CrCl = creatinine clearance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2229" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Degree of Renal Impairment Population Timing of Dose Normal % (n/N) Mild % (n/N) Moderate % (n/N) Severe % (n/N) CrCl (mL/min) ≥80 ≥50 - &lt;80 ≥30 - &lt;50 &lt;30 Orthopedic surgeryHip fracture, hip replacement, and knee replacement surgery prophylaxis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2230" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Overall 1.6% (25/1,565) 2.4% (31/1,288) 3.8% (19/504) 4.8% (4/83) 6-8 hours after surgery 1.8% (16/905) 2.2% (15/675) 2.3% (6/265) 0% (0/40) Abdominal surgery Overall 2.1% (13/606) 3.6% (22/613) 6.7% (12/179) 7.1% (1/14) 6-8 hours after surgery 2.1% (10/467) 3.3% (16/481) 5.8% (8/137) 7.7% (1/13) DVT and PE Treatment 0.4% (4/1,132) 1.6% (12/733) 2.2% (7/318) 7.3% (4/55) Assess renal function periodically in patients receiving ARIXTRA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2231" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Discontinue the drug immediately in patients who develop severe renal impairment while on therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2232" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>After discontinuation of ARIXTRA, its anticoagulant effects may persist for 2 to 4 days in patients with normal renal function (i.e., at least 3 to 5 half-lives).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2233" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The anticoagulant effects of ARIXTRA may persist even longer in patients with renal impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2234" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>ARIXTRA increases the risk for bleeding in patients who weigh less than 50 kg, compared to patients with higher weights.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2235" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In patients who weigh less than 50 kg: Do not administer ARIXTRA as prophylactic therapy for patients undergoing hip fracture, hip replacement, or knee replacement surgery and abdominal surgery.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2236" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>During the randomized clinical trials of VTE prophylaxis in the peri-operative period following hip fracture, hip replacement, or knee replacement surgery and abdominal surgery, major bleeding occurred at a higher rate among patients with a body weight &lt;50 kg compared to those with a body weight &gt;50 kg (5.4% versus 2.1% in patients undergoing hip fracture, hip replacement, or knee replacement surgery; 5.3% versus 3.3% in patients undergoing abdominal surgery).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2237" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Thrombocytopenia can occur with the administration of ARIXTRA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2238" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Thrombocytopenia of any degree should be monitored closely.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2239" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Discontinue ARIXTRA if the platelet count falls below 100,000/mm3.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2240" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Moderate thrombocytopenia (platelet counts between 100,000/mm3 and 50,000/mm3) occurred at a rate of 3.0% in patients given ARIXTRA 2.5 mg in the peri-operative hip fracture, hip replacement, or knee replacement surgery and abdominal surgery clinical trials.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2241" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Severe thrombocytopenia (platelet counts less than 50,000/mm3) occurred at a rate of 0.2% in patients given ARIXTRA 2.5 mg in these clinical trials.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2242" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>During extended prophylaxis, no cases of moderate or severe thrombocytopenia were reported.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2243" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Moderate thrombocytopenia occurred at a rate of 0.5% in patients given the ARIXTRA treatment regimen in the DVT and PE treatment clinical trials.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2244" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Severe thrombocytopenia occurred at a rate of 0.04% in patients given the ARIXTRA treatment regimen in the DVT and PE treatment clinical trials.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2245" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Occurrences of thrombocytopenia with thrombosis that manifested similar to heparin-induced thrombocytopenia have been reported with the use of ARIXTRA in postmarketing experience.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2246" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Routine coagulation tests such as Prothrombin Time (PT) and Activated Partial Thromboplastin Time (aPTT) are relatively insensitive measures of the activity of ARIXTRA and international standards of heparin or LMWH are not calibrators to measure anti-Factor Xa activity of ARIXTRA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2247" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If unexpected changes in coagulation parameters or major bleeding occur during therapy with ARIXTRA, discontinue ARIXTRA.In postmarketing experience, occurrences of aPTT elevations have been reported following administration of ARIXTRA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2248" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Periodic routine complete blood counts (including platelet count), serum creatinine level, and stool occult blood tests are recommended during the course of treatment with ARIXTRA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2249" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The anti-Factor Xa activity of fondaparinux sodium can be measured by anti-Xa assay using the appropriate calibrator (fondaparinux).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2250" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The activity of fondaparinux sodium is expressed in milligrams (mg) of the fondaparinux and cannot be compared with activities of heparin or low molecular weight heparins.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2251" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The packaging (needle guard) of the prefilled syringe of ARIXTRA contains dry natural latex rubber that may cause allergic reactions in latex sensitive individuals.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2252" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The antithrombotic activity of fondaparinux sodium is the result of antithrombin III (ATIII)-mediated selective inhibition of Factor Xa.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2253" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>By selectively binding to ATIII, fondaparinux sodium potentiates (about 300 times) the innate neutralization of Factor Xa by ATIII.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2254" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Neutralization of Factor Xa interrupts the blood coagulation cascade and thus inhibits thrombin formation and thrombus development.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2255" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Fondaparinux sodium does not inactivate thrombin (activated Factor II) and has no known effect on platelet function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2256" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>At the recommended dose, fondaparinux sodium does not affect fibrinolytic activity or bleeding time.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2257" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacodynamics/pharmacokinetics of fondaparinux sodium are derived from fondaparinux plasma concentrations quantified via anti-Factor Xa activity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2258" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Only fondaparinux can be used to calibrate the anti-Xa assay.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2259" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>(The international standards of heparin or LMWH are not appropriate for this use.)</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2260" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>As a result, the activity of fondaparinux sodium is expressed as milligrams (mg) of the fondaparinux calibrator.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2261" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The anti-Xa activity of the drug increases with increasing drug concentration, reaching maximum values in approximately three hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2262" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Fondaparinux sodium administered by subcutaneous injection is rapidly and completely absorbed (absolute bioavailability is 100%).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2263" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following a single subcutaneous dose of fondaparinux sodium 2.5 mg in young male subjects, Cmax of 0.34 mg/L is reached in approximately 2 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2264" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In patients undergoing treatment with fondaparinux sodium injection 2.5 mg, once daily, the peak steady-state plasma concentration is, on average, 0.39 to 0.50 mg/L and is reached approximately 3 hours post-dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2265" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In these patients, the minimum steady-state plasma concentration is 0.14 to 0.19 mg/L.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2266" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In patients with symptomatic deep vein thrombosis and pulmonary embolism undergoing treatment with fondaparinux sodium injection 5 mg (body weight &lt;50 kg), 7.5 mg (body weight 50 to 100 kg), and 10 mg (body weight &gt;100 kg) once daily, the body–weight-adjusted doses provide similar mean steady-state peaks and minimum plasma concentrations across all body weight categories.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2267" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mean peak steady-state plasma concentration is in the range of 1.20 to 1.26 mg/L.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2268" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In these patients, the mean minimum steady-state plasma concentration is in the range of 0.46 to 0.62 mg/L.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2269" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In healthy adults, intravenously or subcutaneously administered fondaparinux sodium distributes mainly in blood and only to a minor extent in extravascular fluid as evidenced by steady state and non-steady state apparent volume of distribution of 7 to 11 L. Similar fondaparinux distribution occurs in patients undergoing elective hip surgery or hip fracture surgery.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2270" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In vitro, fondaparinux sodium is highly (at least 94%) and specifically bound to antithrombin III (ATIII) and does not bind significantly to other plasma proteins (including platelet Factor 4 [PF4]) or red blood cells.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2271" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In vivo metabolism of fondaparinux has not been investigated since the majority of the administered dose is eliminated unchanged in urine in individuals with normal kidney function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2272" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In individuals with normal kidney function, fondaparinux is eliminated in urine mainly as unchanged drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2273" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In healthy individuals up to 75 years of age, up to 77% of a single subcutaneous or intravenous fondaparinux dose is eliminated in urine as unchanged drug in 72 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2274" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The elimination half-life is 17 to 21 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2275" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Fondaparinux elimination is prolonged in patients with renal impairment since the major route of elimination is urinary excretion of unchanged drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2276" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In patients undergoing prophylaxis following elective hip surgery or hip fracture surgery, the total clearance of fondaparinux is approximately 25% lower in patients with mild renal impairment (CrCl 50 to 80 mL/min), approximately 40% lower in patients with moderate renal impairment (CrCl 30 to 50 mL/min), and approximately 55% lower in patients with severe renal impairment (&lt;30 mL/min) compared to patients with normal renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2277" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A similar relationship between fondaparinux clearance and extent of renal impairment was observed in DVT treatment patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2278" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following a single, subcutaneous dose of 7.5 mg of ARIXTRA in patients with moderate hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh Category B), Cmax and AUC were decreased by 22% and 39%, respectively, compared to subjects with normal liver function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2279" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The changes from baseline in pharmacodynamic parameters, such as aPTT, PT/INR, and antithrombin III, were similar in normal subjects and in patients with moderate hepatic impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2280" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Based on these data, no dosage adjustment is recommended in these patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2281" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>However, a higher incidence of hemorrhage was observed in subjects with moderate hepatic impairment than in normal subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2282" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacokinetics of fondaparinux have not been studied in patients with severe hepatic impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2283" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacokinetics of fondaparinux have not been investigated in pediatric patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2284" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Fondaparinux elimination is prolonged in patients older than 75 years.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2285" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In studies evaluating fondaparinux sodium 2.5 mg prophylaxis in hip fracture surgery or elective hip surgery, the total clearance of fondaparinux was approximately 25% lower in patients older than 75 years as compared to patients younger than 65 years.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2286" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A similar relationship between fondaparinux clearance and age was observed in DVT treatment patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2287" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Total clearance of fondaparinux sodium is decreased by approximately 30% in patients weighing less than 50 kg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2288" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacokinetic properties of fondaparinux sodium are not significantly affected by gender.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2289" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Pharmacokinetic differences due to race have not been studied prospectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2290" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>However, studies performed in Asian (Japanese) healthy subjects did not reveal a different pharmacokinetic profile compared to Caucasian healthy subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="2291" LabelDrug="Arixtra" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Similarly, no plasma clearance differences were observed between black and Caucasian patients undergoing orthopedic surgery.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="neuraxial anesthesia" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="674481000119100: Spontaneous hematoma of spinal cord (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="neuraxial anesthesia" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="703861005: Spinal epidural hematoma (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="anticoagulants" precipitantCode="N0000029110 | N0000175980" effect="299736000:  Intraspinal space-occupying lesion (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="anticoagulants" precipitantCode="N0000029110 | N0000175980" effect="44695005: Paralysis (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="anticoagulants" precipitantCode="N0000029110 | N0000175980" effect="674481000119100: Spontaneous hematoma of spinal cord (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="anticoagulants" precipitantCode="N0000029110 | N0000175980" effect="703861005: Spinal epidural hematoma (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="drugs that affect hemostasis" precipitantCode="N0000009070" effect="674481000119100: Spontaneous hematoma of spinal cord (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="drugs that affect hemostasis" precipitantCode="N0000009070" effect="703861005: Spinal epidural hematoma (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="674481000119100: Spontaneous hematoma of spinal cord (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="703861005: Spinal epidural hematoma (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nsaids" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="674481000119100: Spontaneous hematoma of spinal cord (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nsaids" precipitantCode="N0000175722" effect="703861005: Spinal epidural hematoma (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="nsaids" precipitantCode="N0000175722"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="platelet inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000182142 | N0000175578" effect="674481000119100: Spontaneous hematoma of spinal cord (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="platelet inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000182142 | N0000175578" effect="703861005: Spinal epidural hematoma (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="agents that may enhance the risk of hemorrhage" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="coumarin" precipitantCode="A4VZ22K1WT" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="epidural | anesthesia" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="299736000:  Intraspinal space-occupying lesion (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="epidural | anesthesia" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="44695005: Paralysis (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="epidural | anesthesia" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="703861005: Spinal epidural hematoma (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="neuraxial | anesthesia" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="299736000:  Intraspinal space-occupying lesion (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="neuraxial | anesthesia" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="44695005: Paralysis (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="neuraxial | anesthesia" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="703861005: Spinal epidural hematoma (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="spinal | anesthesia" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="299736000:  Intraspinal space-occupying lesion (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="spinal | anesthesia" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="44695005: Paralysis (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="spinal | anesthesia" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="703861005: Spinal epidural hematoma (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="spinal/epidural | anesthesia" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="299736000:  Intraspinal space-occupying lesion (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="spinal/epidural | anesthesia" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="44695005: Paralysis (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="spinal/epidural | anesthesia" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="703861005: Spinal epidural hematoma (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="drugs affecting hemostasis" precipitantCode="N0000009070"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="agents that enhance the risk of hemorrhage" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="vitamin k antagonists" precipitantCode="N0000175476" effect="131148009: Bleeding (finding)"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>