<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Nuvigil" setid="d878aed0-ddbf-8fa1-abf7-d3e480260845">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
NUVIGIL is contraindicated in patients with known hypersensitivity to modafinil or armodafinil or its inactive ingredients [see Warnings and Precautions ( 5.1 , 5.2 , 5.3 )] . NUVIGIL is contraindicated in patients with known hypersensitivity to modafinil or armodafinil. ( 4 )</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
The recommended dosage of NUVIGIL for each indication is as follows: OSA or Narcolepsy: 150 mg to 250 mg once a day in the morning. ( 2.1 ) SWD: 150 mg once a day, taken approximately one hour prior to start of the work shift. ( 2.2 ) Hepatic Impairment: reduced dose in patients with severe hepatic impairment. ( 2.3 , 12.3 ) Geriatric Patients: consider lower dose. ( 2.4 , 12.3 ) The recommended dosage of NUVIGIL for patients with OSA or narcolepsy is 150 mg to 250 mg taken orally once a day as a single dose in the morning. In patients with OSA, doses up to 250 mg/day, given as a single dose, have been well tolerated, but there is no consistent evidence that these doses confer additional benefit beyond that of the 150 mg/day dose [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3) and Clinical Studies (14.1, 14.2)] . The recommended dosage of NUVIGIL for patients with SWD is 150 mg taken orally once a day as a single dose approximately 1 hour prior to the start of their work shift. In patients with severe hepatic impairment, the dosage of NUVIGIL should be reduced [see Use in Specific Populations ( 8.6 ) and Clinical Pharmacology ( 12.3 )]. Consideration should be given to the use of lower doses and close monitoring in geriatric patients [see Use in Specific Populations (8.5)] . The recommended dosage of NUVIGIL for patients with OSA or narcolepsy is 150 mg to 250 mg taken orally once a day as a single dose in the morning. In patients with OSA, doses up to 250 mg/day, given as a single dose, have been well tolerated, but there is no consistent evidence that these doses confer additional benefit beyond that of the 150 mg/day dose [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3) and Clinical Studies (14.1, 14.2)] . The recommended dosage of NUVIGIL for patients with SWD is 150 mg taken orally once a day as a single dose approximately 1 hour prior to the start of their work shift. In patients with severe hepatic impairment, the dosage of NUVIGIL should be reduced [see Use in Specific Populations ( 8.6 ) and Clinical Pharmacology ( 12.3 )]. Consideration should be given to the use of lower doses and close monitoring in geriatric patients [see Use in Specific Populations (8.5)] .</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
Effects of NUVIGIL on CYP3A4/5 Substrates The clearance of drugs that are substrates for CYP3A4/5 (e.g., steroidal contraceptives, cyclosporine, midazolam, and triazolam) may be increased by NUVIGIL via induction of metabolic enzymes, which results in lower systemic exposure. Dosage adjustment of these drugs should be considered when these drugs are used concomitantly with NUVIGIL [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)] . The effectiveness of steroidal contraceptives may be reduced when used with NUVIGIL and for one month after discontinuation of therapy. Alternative or concomitant methods of contraception are recommended for patients taking steroidal contraceptives (e.g., ethinyl estradiol) when treated concomitantly with NUVIGIL and for one month after discontinuation of NUVIGIL treatment. Blood levels of cyclosporine may be reduced when used with NUVIGIL. Monitoring of circulating cyclosporine concentrations and appropriate dosage adjustment for cyclosporine should be considered when used concomitantly with NUVIGIL. Effects of NUVIGIL on CYP2C19 Substrates Elimination of drugs that are substrates for CYP2C19 (e.g., phenytoin, diazepam, propranolol, omeprazole, and clomipramine) may be prolonged by NUVIGIL via inhibition of metabolic enzymes, with resultant higher systemic exposure. Dose reduction of these drugs may be required when these drugs are used concomitantly with NUVIGIL. Warfarin More frequent monitoring of prothrombin times/INR should be considered whenever NUVIGIL is coadministered with warfarin [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)] . Monoamine Oxidase (MAO) Inhibitors Caution should be used when concomitantly administering MAO inhibitors and NUVIGIL. Steroidal contraceptives (e.g., ethinyl estradiol): use alternative or concomitant methods of contraception while taking NUVIGIL and for one month after discontinuation of NUVIGIL treatment. ( 7 ) Cyclosporine: blood concentrations of cyclosporine may be reduced. ( 7 ) CYP2C19 substrates, such as omeprazole, phenytoin, and diazepam: exposure of these medications may be increased. ( 7 )</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
Serious Rash, including Stevens-Johnson Syndrome: discontinue NUVIGIL at the first sign of rash, unless the rash is clearly not drug-related. ( 5.1 ) DRESS/Multi-organ Hypersensitivity Reactions: if suspected, discontinue NUVIGIL. ( 5.2 ) Angioedema and Anaphylaxis Reactions: if suspected, discontinue NUVIGIL. ( 5.3 ) Persistent Sleepiness: assess patients frequently for degree of sleepiness and, if appropriate, advise patients to avoid driving or engaging in any other potentially dangerous activity. ( 5.4 ) Psychiatric Symptoms: use particular caution in treating patients with a history of psychosis, depression, or mania. Consider discontinuing NUVIGIL if psychiatric symptoms develop. ( 5.5 ) Known Cardiovascular Disease: consider increased monitoring. ( 5.7 ) Serious rash requiring hospitalization and discontinuation of treatment has been reported in association with the use of NUVIGIL (armodafinil) or modafinil (the racemic mixture of S- and R-enantiomers). NUVIGIL has not been studied in pediatric patients in any setting and is not approved for use in pediatric patients for any indication. In clinical trials of modafinil, the incidence of rash resulting in discontinuation was approximately 0.8% (13 per 1,585) in pediatric patients (age &amp;lt;17 years); these rashes included 1 case of possible Stevens-Johnson syndrome (SJS) and 1 case of apparent multi-organ hypersensitivity reaction/ Drug Rash with Eosinophilia and Systemic Symptoms (DRESS) [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)] . Several of the cases were associated with fever and other abnormalities (e.g., vomiting, leukopenia). The median time to rash that resulted in discontinuation was 13 days. No such cases were observed among 380 pediatric patients who received placebo. Skin and mouth sores, blistering, and ulceration have been reported with modafinil and NUVIGIL in the postmarketing setting. Recurrence of signs and symptoms of serious dermatologic reactions following rechallenge has been reported in some cases. Rare cases of serious or life-threatening rash, including SJS and toxic epidermal necrolysis (TEN), have been reported in adults and children in worldwide postmarketing experience with modafinil and NUVIGIL. There are no factors, including duration of therapy, that are known to predict the risk of occurrence or the severity of rash associated with modafinil or NUVIGIL. In cases where the time to onset was reported, serious rash occurred 1 day to 2 months after initiation of treatment, but isolated cases of serious dermatologic reactions have been reported with symptoms beginning after prolonged treatment (e.g., 3 months). Although benign rashes also occur with NUVIGIL, it is not possible to reliably predict which rashes will prove to be serious. Accordingly, NUVIGIL should be discontinued at the first sign of rash, skin or mouth sores, or blistering or ulceration, unless the rash is clearly not drug-related. Discontinuation of treatment may not prevent a rash from becoming life-threatening or permanently disabling or disfiguring. DRESS, also known as multi-organ hypersensitivity, has been reported with NUVIGIL. DRESS typically, although not exclusively, presents with fever, rash, lymphadenopathy, and/or facial swelling, in association with other organ system involvement, such as hepatitis, nephritis, hematologic abnormalities, myocarditis, or myositis, sometimes resembling an acute viral infection. Eosinophilia is often present. This disorder is variable in its expression, and other organ systems not noted here may be involved. It is important to note that early manifestations of hypersensitivity (e.g., fever, lymphadenopathy) may be present even though rash is not evident. One fatal case of DRESS that occurred in close temporal association (3 weeks) with the initiation of NUVIGIL treatment has been reported in the postmarketing setting. In addition, multi-organ hypersensitivity reactions, including at least one fatality in postmarketing experience, have occurred in close temporal association (median time to detection 13 days; range 4-33) to the initiation of modafinil. Although there have been a limited number of reports, multi-organ hypersensitivity reactions may result in hospitalization or be life-threatening. If a multi-organ hypersensitivity reaction is suspected, NUVIGIL should be discontinued. Although there are no case reports to indicate cross-sensitivity with other drugs that produce this syndrome, the experience with drugs associated with multi-organ hypersensitivity would indicate this to be a possibility. Angioedema and hypersensitivity (with rash, dysphagia, and bronchospasm), were observed with NUVIGIL. Patients should be advised to discontinue therapy and immediately report to their physician any signs or symptoms suggesting angioedema or anaphylaxis (e.g., swelling of face, eyes, lips, tongue or larynx; difficulty in swallowing or breathing; hoarseness). Patients with abnormal levels of sleepiness who take NUVIGIL should be advised that their level of wakefulness may not return to normal. Patients with excessive sleepiness, including those taking NUVIGIL, should be frequently reassessed for their degree of sleepiness and, if appropriate, advised to avoid driving or any other potentially dangerous activity. Prescribers should also be aware that patients may not acknowledge sleepiness or drowsiness until directly questioned about drowsiness or sleepiness during specific activities. In pre-approval narcolepsy, OSA and SWD controlled trials of NUVIGIL, anxiety, agitation, nervousness, and irritability were reasons for treatment discontinuation more often in patients on NUVIGIL compared to placebo (NUVIGIL 1.2% and placebo 0.3%). Depression was also a reason for treatment discontinuation more often in patients on NUVIGIL compared to placebo (NUVIGIL 0.6% and placebo 0.2%). Cases of suicidal ideation were observed in clinical trials. Caution should be exercised when NUVIGIL is given to patients with a history of psychosis, depression, or mania. If psychiatric symptoms develop in association with NUVIGIL administration, consider discontinuing NUVIGIL. Psychiatric adverse reactions have been reported in patients treated with modafinil. Modafinil and NUVIGIL (armodafinil) are very closely related. Therefore, the incidence and type of psychiatric symptoms associated with NUVIGIL are expected to be similar to the incidence and type of these events with modafinil. Postmarketing adverse reactions associated with the use of NUVIGIL, some of which have resulted in hospitalization, have included mania, delusions, hallucinations, suicidal ideation, and aggression. Many, but not all, patients who developed psychiatric adverse reactions had a prior psychiatric history. In these cases, reported NUVIGIL total daily doses ranged from 50 mg to 450 mg, which includes doses below and above the recommended dosages. Although NUVIGIL has not been shown to produce functional impairment, any drug affecting the central nervous system (CNS) may alter judgment, thinking or motor skills. Patients should be cautioned about operating an automobile or other hazardous machinery until it is reasonably certain that NUVIGIL therapy will not adversely affect their ability to engage in such activities. In clinical studies of modafinil, cardiovascular adverse reactions, including chest pain, palpitations, dyspnea and transient ischemic T-wave changes on ECG were observed in three subjects in association with mitral valve prolapse or left ventricular hypertrophy. It is recommended that NUVIGIL tablets not be used in patients with a history of left ventricular hypertrophy or in patients with mitral valve prolapse who have experienced the mitral valve prolapse syndrome when previously receiving CNS stimulants. Findings suggestive of mitral valve prolapse syndrome include but are not limited to ischemic ECG changes, chest pain, or arrhythmia. If new onset of any of these findings occurs, consider cardiac evaluation. Blood pressure monitoring in short term (≤ 3 months) pre-approval controlled trials of OSA, SWD, and narcolepsy showed small average increases in mean systolic and diastolic blood pressure in patients receiving NUVIGIL as compared to placebo (1.2 to 4.3 mmHg in the various experimental groups). There was also a slightly greater proportion of patients on NUVIGIL requiring new or increased use of antihypertensive medications (2.9%) compared to patients on placebo (1.8%). There was a small, but consistent, average increase in pulse rate over placebo in pre-approval controlled trials. This increase varied from 0.9 to 3.5 BPM. Increased monitoring of heart rate and blood pressure may be appropriate in patients on NUVIGIL. Caution should be exercised when prescribing NUVIGIL to patients with known cardiovascular disease. Serious rash requiring hospitalization and discontinuation of treatment has been reported in association with the use of NUVIGIL (armodafinil) or modafinil (the racemic mixture of S- and R-enantiomers). NUVIGIL has not been studied in pediatric patients in any setting and is not approved for use in pediatric patients for any indication. In clinical trials of modafinil, the incidence of rash resulting in discontinuation was approximately 0.8% (13 per 1,585) in pediatric patients (age &amp;lt;17 years); these rashes included 1 case of possible Stevens-Johnson syndrome (SJS) and 1 case of apparent multi-organ hypersensitivity reaction/ Drug Rash with Eosinophilia and Systemic Symptoms (DRESS) [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)] . Several of the cases were associated with fever and other abnormalities (e.g., vomiting, leukopenia). The median time to rash that resulted in discontinuation was 13 days. No such cases were observed among 380 pediatric patients who received placebo. Skin and mouth sores, blistering, and ulceration have been reported with modafinil and NUVIGIL in the postmarketing setting. Recurrence of signs and symptoms of serious dermatologic reactions following rechallenge has been reported in some cases. Rare cases of serious or life-threatening rash, including SJS and toxic epidermal necrolysis (TEN), have been reported in adults and children in worldwide postmarketing experience with modafinil and NUVIGIL. There are no factors, including duration of therapy, that are known to predict the risk of occurrence or the severity of rash associated with modafinil or NUVIGIL. In cases where the time to onset was reported, serious rash occurred 1 day to 2 months after initiation of treatment, but isolated cases of serious dermatologic reactions have been reported with symptoms beginning after prolonged treatment (e.g., 3 months). Although benign rashes also occur with NUVIGIL, it is not possible to reliably predict which rashes will prove to be serious. Accordingly, NUVIGIL should be discontinued at the first sign of rash, skin or mouth sores, or blistering or ulceration, unless the rash is clearly not drug-related. Discontinuation of treatment may not prevent a rash from becoming life-threatening or permanently disabling or disfiguring. DRESS, also known as multi-organ hypersensitivity, has been reported with NUVIGIL. DRESS typically, although not exclusively, presents with fever, rash, lymphadenopathy, and/or facial swelling, in association with other organ system involvement, such as hepatitis, nephritis, hematologic abnormalities, myocarditis, or myositis, sometimes resembling an acute viral infection. Eosinophilia is often present. This disorder is variable in its expression, and other organ systems not noted here may be involved. It is important to note that early manifestations of hypersensitivity (e.g., fever, lymphadenopathy) may be present even though rash is not evident. One fatal case of DRESS that occurred in close temporal association (3 weeks) with the initiation of NUVIGIL treatment has been reported in the postmarketing setting. In addition, multi-organ hypersensitivity reactions, including at least one fatality in postmarketing experience, have occurred in close temporal association (median time to detection 13 days; range 4-33) to the initiation of modafinil. Although there have been a limited number of reports, multi-organ hypersensitivity reactions may result in hospitalization or be life-threatening. If a multi-organ hypersensitivity reaction is suspected, NUVIGIL should be discontinued. Although there are no case reports to indicate cross-sensitivity with other drugs that produce this syndrome, the experience with drugs associated with multi-organ hypersensitivity would indicate this to be a possibility. Angioedema and hypersensitivity (with rash, dysphagia, and bronchospasm), were observed with NUVIGIL. Patients should be advised to discontinue therapy and immediately report to their physician any signs or symptoms suggesting angioedema or anaphylaxis (e.g., swelling of face, eyes, lips, tongue or larynx; difficulty in swallowing or breathing; hoarseness). Patients with abnormal levels of sleepiness who take NUVIGIL should be advised that their level of wakefulness may not return to normal. Patients with excessive sleepiness, including those taking NUVIGIL, should be frequently reassessed for their degree of sleepiness and, if appropriate, advised to avoid driving or any other potentially dangerous activity. Prescribers should also be aware that patients may not acknowledge sleepiness or drowsiness until directly questioned about drowsiness or sleepiness during specific activities. In pre-approval narcolepsy, OSA and SWD controlled trials of NUVIGIL, anxiety, agitation, nervousness, and irritability were reasons for treatment discontinuation more often in patients on NUVIGIL compared to placebo (NUVIGIL 1.2% and placebo 0.3%). Depression was also a reason for treatment discontinuation more often in patients on NUVIGIL compared to placebo (NUVIGIL 0.6% and placebo 0.2%). Cases of suicidal ideation were observed in clinical trials. Caution should be exercised when NUVIGIL is given to patients with a history of psychosis, depression, or mania. If psychiatric symptoms develop in association with NUVIGIL administration, consider discontinuing NUVIGIL. Psychiatric adverse reactions have been reported in patients treated with modafinil. Modafinil and NUVIGIL (armodafinil) are very closely related. Therefore, the incidence and type of psychiatric symptoms associated with NUVIGIL are expected to be similar to the incidence and type of these events with modafinil. Postmarketing adverse reactions associated with the use of NUVIGIL, some of which have resulted in hospitalization, have included mania, delusions, hallucinations, suicidal ideation, and aggression. Many, but not all, patients who developed psychiatric adverse reactions had a prior psychiatric history. In these cases, reported NUVIGIL total daily doses ranged from 50 mg to 450 mg, which includes doses below and above the recommended dosages. Although NUVIGIL has not been shown to produce functional impairment, any drug affecting the central nervous system (CNS) may alter judgment, thinking or motor skills. Patients should be cautioned about operating an automobile or other hazardous machinery until it is reasonably certain that NUVIGIL therapy will not adversely affect their ability to engage in such activities. In clinical studies of modafinil, cardiovascular adverse reactions, including chest pain, palpitations, dyspnea and transient ischemic T-wave changes on ECG were observed in three subjects in association with mitral valve prolapse or left ventricular hypertrophy. It is recommended that NUVIGIL tablets not be used in patients with a history of left ventricular hypertrophy or in patients with mitral valve prolapse who have experienced the mitral valve prolapse syndrome when previously receiving CNS stimulants. Findings suggestive of mitral valve prolapse syndrome include but are not limited to ischemic ECG changes, chest pain, or arrhythmia. If new onset of any of these findings occurs, consider cardiac evaluation. Blood pressure monitoring in short term (≤ 3 months) pre-approval controlled trials of OSA, SWD, and narcolepsy showed small average increases in mean systolic and diastolic blood pressure in patients receiving NUVIGIL as compared to placebo (1.2 to 4.3 mmHg in the various experimental groups). There was also a slightly greater proportion of patients on NUVIGIL requiring new or increased use of antihypertensive medications (2.9%) compared to patients on placebo (1.8%). There was a small, but consistent, average increase in pulse rate over placebo in pre-approval controlled trials. This increase varied from 0.9 to 3.5 BPM. Increased monitoring of heart rate and blood pressure may be appropriate in patients on NUVIGIL. Caution should be exercised when prescribing NUVIGIL to patients with known cardiovascular disease.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
The mechanism(s) through which armodafinil promotes wakefulness is unknown. Armodafinil (R-modafinil) has pharmacological properties similar to those of modafinil (a mixture of R- and S-modafinil), to the extent tested in animal and in vitro studies. The R- and S-enantiomers have similar pharmacological actions in animals. Armodafinil and modafinil have wake-promoting actions similar to sympathomimetic agents including amphetamine and methylphenidate, although their pharmacologic profile is not identical to that of the sympathomimetic amines. Modafinil-induced wakefulness can be attenuated by the α1-adrenergic receptor antagonist, prazosin; however, modafinil is inactive in other in vitro assay systems known to be responsive to α-adrenergic agonists such as the rat vas deferens preparation. Armodafinil is an indirect dopamine receptor agonist; both armodafinil and modafinil bind in vitro to the dopamine transporter and inhibit dopamine reuptake. For modafinil, this activity has been associated in vivo with increased extracellular dopamine levels in some brain regions of animals. In genetically engineered mice lacking the dopamine transporter (DAT), modafinil lacked wake-promoting activity, suggesting that this activity was DAT-dependent. However, the wake-promoting effects of modafinil, unlike those of amphetamine, were not antagonized by the dopamine receptor antagonist haloperidol in rats. In addition, alpha-methyl-p-tyrosine, a dopamine synthesis inhibitor, blocks the action of amphetamine, but does not block locomotor activity induced by modafinil. In addition to its wake-promoting effects and ability to increase locomotor activity in animals, modafinil produces psychoactive and euphoric effects, alterations in mood, perception, thinking, and feelings typical of other CNS stimulants in humans. Modafinil has reinforcing properties, as evidenced by its self-administration in monkeys previously trained to self-administer cocaine; modafinil was also partially discriminated as stimulant-like. Based on nonclinical studies, two major metabolites, acid and sulfone, of modafinil or armodafinil, do not appear to contribute to the CNS-activating properties of the parent compounds. Armodafinil exhibits linear time-independent kinetics following single and multiple oral dose administration. Increase in systemic exposure is proportional over the dose range of 50 to 400 mg. No time-dependent change in kinetics was observed through 12 weeks of dosing. Apparent steady state for armodafinil was reached within 7 days of dosing. At steady state, the systemic exposure for armodafinil is 1.8 times the exposure observed after a single dose. The concentration-time profiles of the R-enantiomer following administration of a single-dose of 50 mg NUVIGIL or 100 mg PROVIGIL (modafinil, a 1:1 mixture of R- and S-enantiomers) are nearly superimposable. However, the C max and AUC 0-∞ , of armodafinil at steady-state were approximately 37% and 70% higher, respectively, following administration of 200 mg NUVIGIL than the corresponding values of modafinil following administration of 200 mg PROVIGIL due to the more rapid clearance of the S-enantiomer (elimination half-life approximately 4 hours) as compared to the R-enantiomer. Absorption NUVIGIL is readily absorbed after oral administration. The absolute oral bioavailability was not determined due to the aqueous insolubility of armodafinil, which precluded intravenous administration. Peak plasma concentrations are attained at approximately 2 hours in the fasted state. Food effect on the overall bioavailability of NUVIGIL is considered minimal; however, time to reach peak concentration (t max ) may be delayed by approximately 2-4 hours in the fed state. Since the delay in t max is also associated with elevated plasma concentrations later in time, food can potentially affect the onset and time course of pharmacologic action for NUVIGIL. Distribution NUVIGIL has an apparent volume of distribution of approximately 42 L. Data specific to armodafinil protein binding are not available. However, modafinil is moderately bound to plasma protein (approximately 60%), mainly to albumin. The potential for interactions of NUVIGIL with highly protein‑bound drugs is considered to be minimal. Elimination After oral administration of NUVIGIL, armodafinil exhibits an apparent monoexponential decline from the peak plasma concentration. The apparent terminal t ½ is approximately 15 hours. The oral clearance of NUVIGIL is approximately 33 mL/min. Metabolism In vitro and in vivo data show that armodafinil undergoes hydrolytic deamidation, S-oxidation, and aromatic ring hydroxylation, with subsequent glucuronide conjugation of the hydroxylated products. Amide hydrolysis is the single most prominent metabolic pathway, with sulfone formation by cytochrome P450 (CYP) 3A4/5 being next in importance. The other oxidative products are formed too slowly in vitro to enable identification of the enzyme(s) responsible. Only two metabolites reach appreciable concentrations in plasma (i.e., R-modafinil acid and modafinil sulfone). Excretion Data specific to NUVIGIL disposition are not available. However, modafinil is mainly eliminated via metabolism, predominantly in the liver, with less than 10% of the parent compound excreted in the urine. A total of 81% of the administered radioactivity was recovered in 11 days post-dose, predominantly in the urine (80% vs. 1.0% in the feces). Specific Populations Age In a clinical study, systemic exposure of armodafinil was approximately 15% higher in elderly subjects (≥65 years of age, N=24), corresponding to approximately 12% lower oral clearance (CL/F), as compared to young subjects (18-45 years of age, N=25). Systemic exposure of armodafinil acid (metabolite) was approximately 61% and 73% greater for C max and AUC 0-τ , respectively, compared to young subjects. Systemic exposure of the sulfone metabolite was approximately 20% lower for elderly subjects compared with young subjects. A subgroup analysis of elderly subjects demonstrated elderly subjects ≥75 and 65-74 years of age had approximately 21% and 9% lower oral clearance, respectively, compared to young subjects. Systemic exposure was approximately 10% greater in subjects 65-74 years of age (N=17) and 27% greater in subjects ≥75 years of age (N=7), respectively, when compared to young subjects. The change is considered not likely to be clinically significant for elderly patients, however, because some elderly patients have greater exposure to armodafinil, consideration should be given to the use of lower doses. Sex Population pharmacokinetic analysis suggests no gender effect on the pharmacokinetics of armodafinil. Ethnicity The influence of race/ethnicity on the pharmacokinetics of armodafinil has not been studied. Hepatic Impairment The pharmacokinetics and metabolism of modafinil were examined in patients with cirrhosis of the liver (6 men and 3 women). Three patients had stage B or B+ cirrhosis and 6 patients had stage C or C+ cirrhosis (per the Child-Pugh score criteria). Clinically 8 of 9 patients were icteric and all had ascites. In these patients, the oral clearance of modafinil was decreased by about 60% and the steady state concentration was doubled compared to normal patients [see Dosage and Administration ( 2.3 ) and Use in Specific Populations ( 8.6 )] . Renal Impairment In a single dose 200 mg modafinil study, severe chronic renal failure (creatinine clearance ≤20 mL/min) did not significantly influence the pharmacokinetics of modafinil, but exposure to modafinil acid (metabolite) was increased 9-fold. Drug Interactions In vitro data demonstrated that armodafinil weakly induces CYP1A2 and possibly CYP3A activities in a concentration-related manner and that CYP2C19 activity is reversibly inhibited by armodafinil. Other CYP activities did not appear to be affected by armodafinil. An in vitro study demonstrated that armodafinil is a substrate of P-glycoprotein. Potential Interactions with Drugs That Inhibit, Induce, or Are Metabolized by Cytochrome P450 Isoenzymes and Other Hepatic Enzymes The existence of multiple pathways for armodafinil metabolism, as well as the fact that a non-CYP-related pathway is the most rapid in metabolizing armodafinil, suggest that there is a low probability of substantive effects on the overall pharmacokinetic profile of NUVIGIL due to CYP inhibition by concomitant medications. However, due to the partial involvement of CYP3A enzymes in the metabolic elimination of armodafinil, coadministration of potent inducers of CYP3A4/5 (e.g., carbamazepine, phenobarbital, rifampin) or inhibitors of CYP3A4/5 (e.g., ketoconazole, erythromycin) could alter the plasma concentrations of armodafinil. The Potential of NUVIGIL to Alter the Metabolism of Other Drugs by Enzyme Induction or Inhibition Drugs Metabolized by CYP3A4/5 In vitro data demonstrated that armodafinil is a weak inducer of CYP3A activity in a concentration-related manner. In a clinical study, concomitant administration of NUVIGIL 250 mg resulted in a reduction in systemic exposure to midazolam by 32% after a single oral dose (5 mg) and 17% after a single intravenous dose (2 mg). Therefore, the blood levels and effectiveness of drugs that are substrates for CYP3A enzymes (e.g., steroidal contraceptives, cyclosporine, midazolam, and triazolam) may be reduced after initiation of concomitant treatment with NUVIGIL [see Drug Interactions ( 7 )] . In a separate clinical study, concomitant administration of NUVIGIL 250 mg with quetiapine (300 mg to 600 mg daily doses) resulted in a reduction in the mean systemic exposure of quetiapine by approximately 29%. No dose adjustment is required. Drugs Metabolized by CYP1A2 In vitro data demonstrated that armodafinil is a weak inducer of CYP1A2 in a concentration-related manner. However, in a clinical study using caffeine as a probe substrate, no significant effect on CYP1A2 activity was observed. Drugs Metabolized by CYP2C19 In vitro data demonstrated that armodafinil is a reversible inhibitor of CYP2C19 activity. In a clinical study, concomitant administration of NUVIGIL 400 mg resulted in a 40% increase in exposure to omeprazole after a single oral dose (40 mg), as a result of moderate inhibition of CYP2C19 activity [see Drug Interactions ( 7 )] . Interactions with CNS Active Drugs Concomitant administration of NUVIGIL with quetiapine reduced the systemic exposure of quetiapine. Data specific to NUVIGIL drug-drug interaction potential with other CNS active drugs are not available. However, the following available drug-drug interaction information on modafinil should be applicable to NUVIGIL . Concomitant administration of modafinil with methylphenidate or dextroamphetamine produced no significant alterations on the pharmacokinetic profile of modafinil or either stimulant, even though the absorption of modafinil was delayed for approximately one hour. Concomitant modafinil or clomipramine did not alter the pharmacokinetic profile of either drug; however, one incident of increased levels of clomipramine and its active metabolite desmethylclomipramine was reported in a patient with narcolepsy during treatment with modafinil. Data specific to NUVIGIL or modafinil drug-drug interaction potential with monoamine oxidase (MAO) inhibitors are not available [see Drug Interactions ( 7 )] . Interaction with P-Glycoprotein An in vitro study demonstrated that armodafinil is a substrate of P-glycoprotein. The impact of inhibition of P-glycoprotein is not known. Interactions with Other Drugs Data specific to NUVIGIL drug-drug interaction potential for additional other drugs are not available. However, the following available drug-drug interaction information on modafinil should be applicable to NUVIGIL. Warfarin: Concomitant administration of modafinil with warfarin did not produce significant changes in the pharmacokinetic profiles of R- and S-warfarin. However, since only a single dose of warfarin was tested in this study, an interaction cannot be ruled out [see Drug Interactions ( 7 )] .</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="7775" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>NUVIGIL is contraindicated in patients with known hypersensitivity to modafinil or armodafinil or its inactive ingredients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7776" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>NUVIGIL is contraindicated in patients with known hypersensitivity to modafinil or armodafinil.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7777" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommended dosage of NUVIGIL for each indication is as follows: OSA or Narcolepsy: 150 mg to 250 mg once a day in the morning.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7778" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>SWD: 150 mg once a day, taken approximately one hour prior to start of the work shift.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7779" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Hepatic Impairment: reduced dose in patients with severe hepatic impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7780" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Geriatric Patients: consider lower dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7781" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommended dosage of NUVIGIL for patients with OSA or narcolepsy is 150 mg to 250 mg taken orally once a day as a single dose in the morning.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7782" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In patients with OSA, doses up to 250 mg/day, given as a single dose, have been well tolerated, but there is no consistent evidence that these doses confer additional benefit beyond that of the 150 mg/day dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7783" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommended dosage of NUVIGIL for patients with SWD is 150 mg taken orally once a day as a single dose approximately 1 hour prior to the start of their work shift.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7784" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In patients with severe hepatic impairment, the dosage of NUVIGIL should be reduced.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7785" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Consideration should be given to the use of lower doses and close monitoring in geriatric patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7786" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Effects of NUVIGIL on CYP3A4/5 Substrates The clearance of drugs that are substrates for CYP3A4/5 (e.g., steroidal contraceptives, cyclosporine, midazolam, and triazolam) may be increased by NUVIGIL via induction of metabolic enzymes, which results in lower systemic exposure.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M37" type="Trigger" span="46 9;178 9" str="clearance | increased "/>
<Mention id="M38" type="Trigger" span="203 30" str=" induction of metabolic enzymes "/>
<Mention id="M39" type="Trigger" span="252 23" str=" lower systemic exposure"/>
<Mention id="M4" type="Precipitant" span="131 12" str="cyclosporine" code="83HN0GTJ6D | N0000007346"/>
<Mention id="M8" type="Precipitant" span="22 5;29 12" str="CYP3A | 5 Substrates" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M12" type="Precipitant" span="22 6;31 10" str="CYP3A4 | Substrates" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M16" type="Precipitant" span="22 19" str="CYP3A4/5 Substrates" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M20" type="Precipitant" span="145 9" str="midazolam" code="R60L0SM5BC"/>
<Mention id="M24" type="Precipitant" span="105 24" str="steroidal contraceptives" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M28" type="Precipitant" span="74 20;29 1" str="substrates for CYP3A | 5" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M32" type="Precipitant" span="74 21" str="substrates for CYP3A4" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M36" type="Precipitant" span="74 23" str="substrates for CYP3A4/5" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M40" type="Precipitant" span="160 9" str="triazolam" code="1HM943223R"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M37;M38;M39" precipitant="M4" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M37;M38;M39" precipitant="M8" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M37;M38;M39" precipitant="M12" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M37;M38;M39" precipitant="M16" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M37;M38;M39" precipitant="M20" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M37;M38;M39" precipitant="M24" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M37;M38;M39" precipitant="M28" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M37;M38;M39" precipitant="M32" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M37;M38;M39" precipitant="M36" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M37;M38;M39" precipitant="M40" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7787" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Dosage adjustment of these drugs should be considered when these drugs are used concomitantly with NUVIGIL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7788" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The effectiveness of steroidal contraceptives may be reduced when used with NUVIGIL and for one month after discontinuation of therapy.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M41" type="Trigger" span="4 13;53 7" str="effectiveness | reduced"/>
<Mention id="M42" type="Precipitant" span="21 24" str="steroidal contraceptives" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M43" type="SpecificInteraction" span="4 56" str="effectiveness of steroidal contraceptives may be reduced" code="102955006: Contraception failure (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M41" precipitant="M42" effect="M43" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7789" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Alternative or concomitant methods of contraception are recommended for patients taking steroidal contraceptives (e.g., ethinyl estradiol) when treated concomitantly with NUVIGIL and for one month after discontinuation of NUVIGIL treatment.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M46" type="Trigger" span="0 11;56 11" str="Alternative | recommended"/>
<Mention id="M45" type="Precipitant" span="120 17" str="ethinyl estradiol" code="423D2T571U"/>
<Mention id="M47" type="Precipitant" span="88 24" str="steroidal contraceptives" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M46" precipitant="M45"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M46" precipitant="M47"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7790" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Blood levels of cyclosporine may be reduced when used with NUVIGIL.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M48" type="Trigger" span="0 12;36 7" str="Blood levels | reduced"/>
<Mention id="M49" type="Precipitant" span="16 12" str="cyclosporine" code="83HN0GTJ6D | N0000007346"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M48" precipitant="M49" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7791" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Monitoring of circulating cyclosporine concentrations and appropriate dosage adjustment for cyclosporine should be considered when used concomitantly with NUVIGIL.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M50" type="Trigger" span="0 10" str="Monitoring "/>
<Mention id="M51" type="Trigger" span="70 17" str=" dosage adjustment"/>
<Mention id="M52" type="Precipitant" span="26 12" str="cyclosporine" code="83HN0GTJ6D | N0000007346"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M50;M51" precipitant="M52"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7792" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Effects of NUVIGIL on CYP2C19 Substrates Elimination of drugs that are substrates for CYP2C19 (e.g., phenytoin, diazepam, propranolol, omeprazole, and clomipramine) may be prolonged by NUVIGIL via inhibition of metabolic enzymes, with resultant higher systemic exposure.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M77" type="Trigger" span="41 11;172 9" str="Elimination | prolonged "/>
<Mention id="M78" type="Trigger" span="197 31" str=" inhibition of metabolic enzymes "/>
<Mention id="M79" type="Trigger" span="245 24" str=" higher systemic exposure"/>
<Mention id="M56" type="Precipitant" span="151 12" str="clomipramine" code="NUV44L116D"/>
<Mention id="M60" type="Precipitant" span="22 18" str="CYP2C19 Substrates" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M64" type="Precipitant" span="112 8" str="diazepam" code="Q3JTX2Q7TU"/>
<Mention id="M68" type="Precipitant" span="135 10" str="omeprazole" code="KG60484QX9"/>
<Mention id="M72" type="Precipitant" span="101 9" str="phenytoin" code="6158TKW0C5 | N0000006023"/>
<Mention id="M76" type="Precipitant" span="122 11" str="propranolol" code="9Y8NXQ24VQ"/>
<Mention id="M80" type="Precipitant" span="71 22" str="substrates for CYP2C19" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M77;M78;M79" precipitant="M56" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M77;M78;M79" precipitant="M60" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M77;M78;M79" precipitant="M64" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M77;M78;M79" precipitant="M68" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M77;M78;M79" precipitant="M72" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M77;M78;M79" precipitant="M76" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M77;M78;M79" precipitant="M80" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7793" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Dose reduction of these drugs may be required when these drugs are used concomitantly with NUVIGIL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7794" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Warfarin More frequent monitoring of prothrombin times/INR should be considered whenever NUVIGIL is coadministered with warfarin.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M87" type="Trigger" span="9 24" str="More frequent monitoring"/>
<Mention id="M88" type="Precipitant" span="0 8" str="warfarin" code="5Q7ZVV76EI | N0000006403"/>
<Mention id="M83" type="SpecificInteraction" span="55 3" str="INR" code="165583001: International normalized ratio abnormal (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M86" type="SpecificInteraction" span="37 17" str="prothrombin times" code="165568006: Prothrombin time abnormal (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M89" type="SpecificInteraction" span="37 21" str="prothrombin times/INR" code="165568006: Prothrombin time abnormal (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M87" precipitant="M88" effect="M83" effectCodeMatch="Close Match"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M87" precipitant="M88" effect="M86" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M87" precipitant="M88" effect="M89" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7795" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Monoamine Oxidase (MAO) Inhibitors Caution should be used when concomitantly administering MAO inhibitors and NUVIGIL.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M94" type="Trigger" span="35 7" str="Caution"/>
<Mention id="M91" type="Precipitant" span="19 3;24 10" str="MAO | Inhibitors" code="N0000000184 | N0000175744"/>
<Mention id="M93" type="Precipitant" span="91 14" str="MAO inhibitors" code="N0000000184 | N0000175744"/>
<Mention id="M95" type="Precipitant" span="0 17;24 10" str="Monoamine Oxidase | Inhibitors" code="N0000000184 | N0000175744"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M94" precipitant="M91"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M94" precipitant="M93"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M94" precipitant="M95"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7796" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Steroidal contraceptives (e.g., ethinyl estradiol): use alternative or concomitant methods of contraception while taking NUVIGIL and for one month after discontinuation of NUVIGIL treatment.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M98" type="Trigger" span="52 15" str="use alternative"/>
<Mention id="M97" type="Precipitant" span="32 17" str="ethinyl estradiol" code="423D2T571U"/>
<Mention id="M99" type="Precipitant" span="0 24" str="Steroidal contraceptives" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I29" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M98" precipitant="M97"/>
<Interaction id="I30" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M98" precipitant="M99"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7797" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Cyclosporine: blood concentrations of cyclosporine may be reduced.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M100" type="Trigger" span="14 20;58 7" str="blood concentrations | reduced"/>
<Mention id="M101" type="Precipitant" span="0 12" str="cyclosporine" code="83HN0GTJ6D | N0000007346"/>
<Interaction id="I31" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M100" precipitant="M101" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7798" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>CYP2C19 substrates, such as omeprazole, phenytoin, and diazepam: exposure of these medications may be increased.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M108" type="Trigger" span="65 8;102 9" str="exposure | increased"/>
<Mention id="M103" type="Precipitant" span="0 18" str="CYP2C19 substrates" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M105" type="Precipitant" span="55 8" str="diazepam" code="Q3JTX2Q7TU"/>
<Mention id="M107" type="Precipitant" span="28 10" str="omeprazole" code="KG60484QX9"/>
<Mention id="M109" type="Precipitant" span="40 9" str="phenytoin" code="6158TKW0C5 | N0000006023"/>
<Interaction id="I32" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M108" precipitant="M103" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I33" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M108" precipitant="M105" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I34" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M108" precipitant="M107" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I35" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M108" precipitant="M109" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7799" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Serious Rash, including Stevens-Johnson Syndrome: discontinue NUVIGIL at the first sign of rash, unless the rash is clearly not drug-related.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7800" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>DRESS/Multi-organ Hypersensitivity Reactions: if suspected, discontinue NUVIGIL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7801" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Angioedema and Anaphylaxis Reactions: if suspected, discontinue NUVIGIL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7802" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Persistent Sleepiness: assess patients frequently for degree of sleepiness and, if appropriate, advise patients to avoid driving or engaging in any other potentially dangerous activity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7803" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Psychiatric Symptoms: use particular caution in treating patients with a history of psychosis, depression, or mania.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7804" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Consider discontinuing NUVIGIL if psychiatric symptoms develop.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7805" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Known Cardiovascular Disease: consider increased monitoring.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7806" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Serious rash requiring hospitalization and discontinuation of treatment has been reported in association with the use of NUVIGIL (armodafinil) or modafinil (the racemic mixture of S- and R-enantiomers).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7807" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>NUVIGIL has not been studied in pediatric patients in any setting and is not approved for use in pediatric patients for any indication.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7808" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In clinical trials of modafinil, the incidence of rash resulting in discontinuation was approximately 0.8% (13 per 1,585) in pediatric patients (age &lt;17 years); these rashes included 1 case of possible Stevens-Johnson syndrome (SJS) and 1 case of apparent multi-organ hypersensitivity reaction/ Drug Rash with Eosinophilia and Systemic Symptoms (DRESS).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7809" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Several of the cases were associated with fever and other abnormalities (e.g., vomiting, leukopenia).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7810" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The median time to rash that resulted in discontinuation was 13 days.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7811" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>No such cases were observed among 380 pediatric patients who received placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7812" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Skin and mouth sores, blistering, and ulceration have been reported with modafinil and NUVIGIL in the postmarketing setting.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7813" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Recurrence of signs and symptoms of serious dermatologic reactions following rechallenge has been reported in some cases.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7814" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Rare cases of serious or life-threatening rash, including SJS and toxic epidermal necrolysis (TEN), have been reported in adults and children in worldwide postmarketing experience with modafinil and NUVIGIL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7815" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There are no factors, including duration of therapy, that are known to predict the risk of occurrence or the severity of rash associated with modafinil or NUVIGIL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7816" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In cases where the time to onset was reported, serious rash occurred 1 day to 2 months after initiation of treatment, but isolated cases of serious dermatologic reactions have been reported with symptoms beginning after prolonged treatment (e.g., 3 months).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7817" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Although benign rashes also occur with NUVIGIL, it is not possible to reliably predict which rashes will prove to be serious.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7818" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Accordingly, NUVIGIL should be discontinued at the first sign of rash, skin or mouth sores, or blistering or ulceration, unless the rash is clearly not drug-related.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7819" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Discontinuation of treatment may not prevent a rash from becoming life-threatening or permanently disabling or disfiguring.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7820" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>DRESS, also known as multi-organ hypersensitivity, has been reported with NUVIGIL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7821" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>DRESS typically, although not exclusively, presents with fever, rash, lymphadenopathy, and/or facial swelling, in association with other organ system involvement, such as hepatitis, nephritis, hematologic abnormalities, myocarditis, or myositis, sometimes resembling an acute viral infection.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7822" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>This disorder is variable in its expression, and other organ systems not noted here may be involved.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7823" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>It is important to note that early manifestations of hypersensitivity (e.g., fever, lymphadenopathy) may be present even though rash is not evident.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7824" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>One fatal case of DRESS that occurred in close temporal association (3 weeks) with the initiation of NUVIGIL treatment has been reported in the postmarketing setting.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7825" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In addition, multi-organ hypersensitivity reactions, including at least one fatality in postmarketing experience, have occurred in close temporal association (median time to detection 13 days; range 4-33) to the initiation of modafinil.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7826" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Although there have been a limited number of reports, multi-organ hypersensitivity reactions may result in hospitalization or be life-threatening.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7827" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If a multi-organ hypersensitivity reaction is suspected, NUVIGIL should be discontinued.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7828" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Although there are no case reports to indicate cross-sensitivity with other drugs that produce this syndrome, the experience with drugs associated with multi-organ hypersensitivity would indicate this to be a possibility.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7829" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Angioedema and hypersensitivity (with rash, dysphagia, and bronchospasm), were observed with NUVIGIL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7830" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients should be advised to discontinue therapy and immediately report to their physician any signs or symptoms suggesting angioedema or anaphylaxis (e.g., swelling of face, eyes, lips, tongue or larynx; difficulty in swallowing or breathing; hoarseness).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7831" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients with abnormal levels of sleepiness who take NUVIGIL should be advised that their level of wakefulness may not return to normal.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7832" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients with excessive sleepiness, including those taking NUVIGIL, should be frequently reassessed for their degree of sleepiness and, if appropriate, advised to avoid driving or any other potentially dangerous activity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7833" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Prescribers should also be aware that patients may not acknowledge sleepiness or drowsiness until directly questioned about drowsiness or sleepiness during specific activities.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7834" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In pre-approval narcolepsy, OSA and SWD controlled trials of NUVIGIL, anxiety, agitation, nervousness, and irritability were reasons for treatment discontinuation more often in patients on NUVIGIL compared to placebo (NUVIGIL 1.2% and placebo 0.3%).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7835" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Depression was also a reason for treatment discontinuation more often in patients on NUVIGIL compared to placebo (NUVIGIL 0.6% and placebo 0.2%).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7836" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Cases of suicidal ideation were observed in clinical trials.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7837" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Caution should be exercised when NUVIGIL is given to patients with a history of psychosis, depression, or mania.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7838" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If psychiatric symptoms develop in association with NUVIGIL administration, consider discontinuing NUVIGIL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7839" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Psychiatric adverse reactions have been reported in patients treated with modafinil.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7840" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Modafinil and NUVIGIL (armodafinil) are very closely related.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7841" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Therefore, the incidence and type of psychiatric symptoms associated with NUVIGIL are expected to be similar to the incidence and type of these events with modafinil.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7842" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Postmarketing adverse reactions associated with the use of NUVIGIL, some of which have resulted in hospitalization, have included mania, delusions, hallucinations, suicidal ideation, and aggression.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7843" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Many, but not all, patients who developed psychiatric adverse reactions had a prior psychiatric history.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7844" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In these cases, reported NUVIGIL total daily doses ranged from 50 mg to 450 mg, which includes doses below and above the recommended dosages.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7845" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Although NUVIGIL has not been shown to produce functional impairment, any drug affecting the central nervous system (CNS) may alter judgment, thinking or motor skills.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7846" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients should be cautioned about operating an automobile or other hazardous machinery until it is reasonably certain that NUVIGIL therapy will not adversely affect their ability to engage in such activities.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7847" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In clinical studies of modafinil, cardiovascular adverse reactions, including chest pain, palpitations, dyspnea and transient ischemic T-wave changes on ECG were observed in three subjects in association with mitral valve prolapse or left ventricular hypertrophy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7848" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>It is recommended that NUVIGIL tablets not be used in patients with a history of left ventricular hypertrophy or in patients with mitral valve prolapse who have experienced the mitral valve prolapse syndrome when previously receiving CNS stimulants.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7849" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Findings suggestive of mitral valve prolapse syndrome include but are not limited to ischemic ECG changes, chest pain, or arrhythmia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7850" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If new onset of any of these findings occurs, consider cardiac evaluation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7851" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Blood pressure monitoring in short term (≤ 3 months) pre-approval controlled trials of OSA, SWD, and narcolepsy showed small average increases in mean systolic and diastolic blood pressure in patients receiving NUVIGIL as compared to placebo (1.2 to 4.3 mmHg in the various experimental groups).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7852" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There was also a slightly greater proportion of patients on NUVIGIL requiring new or increased use of antihypertensive medications (2.9%) compared to patients on placebo (1.8%).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7853" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There was a small, but consistent, average increase in pulse rate over placebo in pre-approval controlled trials.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7854" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>This increase varied from 0.9 to 3.5 BPM.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7855" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Increased monitoring of heart rate and blood pressure may be appropriate in patients on NUVIGIL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7856" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Caution should be exercised when prescribing NUVIGIL to patients with known cardiovascular disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7857" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mechanism(s) through which armodafinil promotes wakefulness is unknown.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7858" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Armodafinil (R-modafinil) has pharmacological properties similar to those of modafinil (a mixture of R- and S-modafinil), to the extent tested in animal and in vitro studies.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7859" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The R- and S-enantiomers have similar pharmacological actions in animals.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7860" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Armodafinil and modafinil have wake-promoting actions similar to sympathomimetic agents including amphetamine and methylphenidate, although their pharmacologic profile is not identical to that of the sympathomimetic amines.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7861" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Modafinil-induced wakefulness can be attenuated by the α1-adrenergic receptor antagonist, prazosin; however, modafinil is inactive in other in vitro assay systems known to be responsive to α-adrenergic agonists such as the rat vas deferens preparation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7862" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Armodafinil is an indirect dopamine receptor agonist; both armodafinil and modafinil bind in vitro to the dopamine transporter and inhibit dopamine reuptake.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7863" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>For modafinil, this activity has been associated in vivo with increased extracellular dopamine levels in some brain regions of animals.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7864" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In genetically engineered mice lacking the dopamine transporter (DAT), modafinil lacked wake-promoting activity, suggesting that this activity was DAT-dependent.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7865" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>However, the wake-promoting effects of modafinil, unlike those of amphetamine, were not antagonized by the dopamine receptor antagonist haloperidol in rats.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7866" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In addition, alpha-methyl-p-tyrosine, a dopamine synthesis inhibitor, blocks the action of amphetamine, but does not block locomotor activity induced by modafinil.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7867" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In addition to its wake-promoting effects and ability to increase locomotor activity in animals, modafinil produces psychoactive and euphoric effects, alterations in mood, perception, thinking, and feelings typical of other CNS stimulants in humans.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7868" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Modafinil has reinforcing properties, as evidenced by its self-administration in monkeys previously trained to self-administer cocaine; modafinil was also partially discriminated as stimulant-like.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7869" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Based on nonclinical studies, two major metabolites, acid and sulfone, of modafinil or armodafinil, do not appear to contribute to the CNS-activating properties of the parent compounds.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7870" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Armodafinil exhibits linear time-independent kinetics following single and multiple oral dose administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7871" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Increase in systemic exposure is proportional over the dose range of 50 to 400 mg. No time-dependent change in kinetics was observed through 12 weeks of dosing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7872" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Apparent steady state for armodafinil was reached within 7 days of dosing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7873" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>At steady state, the systemic exposure for armodafinil is 1.8 times the exposure observed after a single dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7874" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The concentration-time profiles of the R-enantiomer following administration of a single-dose of 50 mg NUVIGIL or 100 mg PROVIGIL (modafinil, a 1:1 mixture of R- and S-enantiomers) are nearly superimposable.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7875" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>However, the Cmax and AUC0-∞, of armodafinil at steady-state were approximately 37% and 70% higher, respectively, following administration of 200 mg NUVIGIL than the corresponding values of modafinil following administration of 200 mg PROVIGIL due to the more rapid clearance of the S-enantiomer (elimination half-life approximately 4 hours) as compared to the R-enantiomer.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7876" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Absorption NUVIGIL is readily absorbed after oral administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7877" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The absolute oral bioavailability was not determined due to the aqueous insolubility of armodafinil, which precluded intravenous administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7878" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Peak plasma concentrations are attained at approximately 2 hours in the fasted state.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7879" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Food effect on the overall bioavailability of NUVIGIL is considered minimal; however, time to reach peak concentration (tmax) may be delayed by approximately 2-4 hours in the fed state.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M110" type="Trigger" span="86 32;133 7" str="time to reach peak concentration | delayed"/>
<Mention id="M113" type="Precipitant" span="0 4" str="Food" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M112" type="Trigger" span="120 4;133 7" str="tmax | delayed"/>
<Interaction id="I36" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M110" precipitant="M113" effect="C54604"/>
<Interaction id="I37" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M112" precipitant="M113" effect="C54604"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7880" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Since the delay in tmax is also associated with elevated plasma concentrations later in time, food can potentially affect the onset and time course of pharmacologic action for NUVIGIL.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M114" type="Trigger" span="115 6;151 20" str="affect | pharmacologic action"/>
<Mention id="M120" type="Precipitant" span="94 4" str="food" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M116" type="SpecificInteraction" span="115 68" str="affect the onset and time course of pharmacologic action for NUVIGIL" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M117" type="Trigger" span="10 13" str="delay in tmax"/>
<Mention id="M119" type="Trigger" span="48 30" str="elevated plasma concentrations"/>
<Interaction id="I38" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M114" precipitant="M120" effect="M116" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I39" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M117" precipitant="M120" effect="C54604"/>
<Interaction id="I40" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M119" precipitant="M120" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7881" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Distribution NUVIGIL has an apparent volume of distribution of approximately 42 L. Data specific to armodafinil protein binding are not available.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7882" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>However, modafinil is moderately bound to plasma protein (approximately 60%), mainly to albumin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7883" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The potential for interactions of NUVIGIL with highly protein‑bound drugs is considered to be minimal.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7884" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Elimination After oral administration of NUVIGIL, armodafinil exhibits an apparent monoexponential decline from the peak plasma concentration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7885" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The apparent terminal t½ is approximately 15 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7886" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The oral clearance of NUVIGIL is approximately 33 mL/min.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7887" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Metabolism In vitro and in vivo data show that armodafinil undergoes hydrolytic deamidation, S-oxidation, and aromatic ring hydroxylation, with subsequent glucuronide conjugation of the hydroxylated products.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7888" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Amide hydrolysis is the single most prominent metabolic pathway, with sulfone formation by cytochrome P450 (CYP) 3A4/5 being next in importance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7889" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The other oxidative products are formed too slowly in vitro to enable identification of the enzyme(s) responsible.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7890" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Only two metabolites reach appreciable concentrations in plasma (i.e., R-modafinil acid and modafinil sulfone).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7891" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Excretion Data specific to NUVIGIL disposition are not available.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7892" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>However, modafinil is mainly eliminated via metabolism, predominantly in the liver, with less than 10% of the parent compound excreted in the urine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7893" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A total of 81% of the administered radioactivity was recovered in 11 days post-dose, predominantly in the urine (80% vs. 1.0% in the feces).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7894" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Specific Populations Age In a clinical study, systemic exposure of armodafinil was approximately 15% higher in elderly subjects (≥65 years of age, N=24), corresponding to approximately 12% lower oral clearance (CL/F), as compared to young subjects (18-45 years of age, N=25).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7895" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Systemic exposure of armodafinil acid (metabolite) was approximately 61% and 73% greater for Cmax and AUC0-τ, respectively, compared to young subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7896" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Systemic exposure of the sulfone metabolite was approximately 20% lower for elderly subjects compared with young subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7897" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A subgroup analysis of elderly subjects demonstrated elderly subjects ≥75 and 65-74 years of age had approximately 21% and 9% lower oral clearance, respectively, compared to young subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7898" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Systemic exposure was approximately 10% greater in subjects 65-74 years of age (N=17) and 27% greater in subjects ≥75 years of age (N=7), respectively, when compared to young subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7899" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The change is considered not likely to be clinically significant for elderly patients, however, because some elderly patients have greater exposure to armodafinil, consideration should be given to the use of lower doses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7900" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Sex Population pharmacokinetic analysis suggests no gender effect on the pharmacokinetics of armodafinil.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7901" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Ethnicity The influence of race/ethnicity on the pharmacokinetics of armodafinil has not been studied.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7902" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Hepatic Impairment The pharmacokinetics and metabolism of modafinil were examined in patients with cirrhosis of the liver (6 men and 3 women).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7903" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Three patients had stage B or B+ cirrhosis and 6 patients had stage C or C+ cirrhosis (per the Child-Pugh score criteria).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7904" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Clinically 8 of 9 patients were icteric and all had ascites.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7905" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In these patients, the oral clearance of modafinil was decreased by about 60% and the steady state concentration was doubled compared to normal patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7906" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Renal Impairment In a single dose 200 mg modafinil study, severe chronic renal failure (creatinine clearance ≤20 mL/min) did not significantly influence the pharmacokinetics of modafinil, but exposure to modafinil acid (metabolite) was increased 9-fold.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7907" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Drug Interactions In vitro data demonstrated that armodafinil weakly induces CYP1A2 and possibly CYP3A activities in a concentration-related manner and that CYP2C19 activity is reversibly inhibited by armodafinil.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7908" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Other CYP activities did not appear to be affected by armodafinil.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7909" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>An in vitro study demonstrated that armodafinil is a substrate of P-glycoprotein.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7910" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Potential Interactions with Drugs That Inhibit, Induce, or Are Metabolized by Cytochrome P450 Isoenzymes and Other Hepatic Enzymes The existence of multiple pathways for armodafinil metabolism, as well as the fact that a non-CYP-related pathway is the most rapid in metabolizing armodafinil, suggest that there is a low probability of substantive effects on the overall pharmacokinetic profile of NUVIGIL due to CYP inhibition by concomitant medications.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7911" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>However, due to the partial involvement of CYP3A enzymes in the metabolic elimination of armodafinil, coadministration of potent inducers of CYP3A4/5 (e.g., carbamazepine, phenobarbital, rifampin) or inhibitors of CYP3A4/5 (e.g., ketoconazole, erythromycin) could alter the plasma concentrations of armodafinil.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M141" type="Trigger" span="264 31" str="alter the plasma concentrations"/>
<Mention id="M122" type="Precipitant" span="157 13" str="carbamazepine" code="33CM23913M | N0000007470"/>
<Mention id="M124" type="Precipitant" span="244 12" str="erythromycin" code="N0000007133 | 63937KV33D"/>
<Mention id="M126" type="Precipitant" span="200 19;148 1" str="inhibitors of CYP3A | 5" code="N0000190115"/>
<Mention id="M128" type="Precipitant" span="200 20" str="inhibitors of CYP3A4" code="N0000182141"/>
<Mention id="M130" type="Precipitant" span="200 22" str="inhibitors of CYP3A4/5" code="N0000190114"/>
<Mention id="M132" type="Precipitant" span="230 12" str="ketoconazole" code="N0000007319 | R9400W927I"/>
<Mention id="M134" type="Precipitant" span="172 13" str="phenobarbital" code="YQE403BP4D | N0000005893"/>
<Mention id="M136" type="Precipitant" span="122 24;148 1" str="potent inducers of CYP3A | 5" code="N0000190118"/>
<Mention id="M138" type="Precipitant" span="122 25" str="potent inducers of CYP3A4" code="N0000185506"/>
<Mention id="M140" type="Precipitant" span="122 27" str="potent inducers of CYP3A4/5" code="N0000190118"/>
<Mention id="M142" type="Precipitant" span="187 8" str="rifampin" code="VJT6J7R4TR | N0000006026"/>
<Interaction id="I41" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M141" precipitant="M122"/>
<Interaction id="I42" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M141" precipitant="M124"/>
<Interaction id="I43" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M141" precipitant="M126"/>
<Interaction id="I44" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M141" precipitant="M128"/>
<Interaction id="I45" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M141" precipitant="M130"/>
<Interaction id="I46" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M141" precipitant="M132"/>
<Interaction id="I47" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M141" precipitant="M134"/>
<Interaction id="I48" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M141" precipitant="M136"/>
<Interaction id="I49" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M141" precipitant="M138"/>
<Interaction id="I50" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M141" precipitant="M140"/>
<Interaction id="I51" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M141" precipitant="M142"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7912" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The Potential of NUVIGIL to Alter the Metabolism of Other Drugs by Enzyme Induction or Inhibition Drugs Metabolized by CYP3A4/5 In vitro data demonstrated that armodafinil is a weak inducer of CYP3A activity in a concentration-related manner.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7913" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In a clinical study, concomitant administration of NUVIGIL 250 mg resulted in a reduction in systemic exposure to midazolam by 32% after a single oral dose (5 mg) and 17% after a single intravenous dose (2 mg).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M143" type="Trigger" span="80 30" str="reduction in systemic exposure"/>
<Mention id="M144" type="Precipitant" span="114 9" str="midazolam" code="R60L0SM5BC"/>
<Interaction id="I52" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M143" precipitant="M144" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7914" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Therefore, the blood levels and effectiveness of drugs that are substrates for CYP3A enzymes (e.g., steroidal contraceptives, cyclosporine, midazolam, and triazolam) may be reduced after initiation of concomitant treatment with NUVIGIL.In a separate clinical study, concomitant administration of NUVIGIL 250 mg with quetiapine (300 mg to 600 mg daily doses) resulted in a reduction in the mean systemic exposure of quetiapine by approximately 29%.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M155" type="Trigger" span="15 12;173 7" str="blood levels | reduced"/>
<Mention id="M146" type="Precipitant" span="126 12" str="cyclosporine" code="83HN0GTJ6D | N0000007346"/>
<Mention id="M148" type="Precipitant" span="140 9" str="midazolam" code="R60L0SM5BC"/>
<Mention id="M149" type="Trigger" span="372 9;394 17" str="reduction | systemic exposure"/>
<Mention id="M150" type="Precipitant" span="316 10" str="quetiapine" code="BGL0JSY5SI"/>
<Mention id="M152" type="Precipitant" span="100 24" str="steroidal contraceptives" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M154" type="Precipitant" span="64 28" str="substrates for CYP3A enzymes" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M156" type="Precipitant" span="155 9" str="triazolam" code="1HM943223R"/>
<Interaction id="I53" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M155" precipitant="M146" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I54" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M155" precipitant="M148" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I55" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M149" precipitant="M150" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I56" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M155" precipitant="M152" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I57" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M155" precipitant="M154" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I58" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M155" precipitant="M156" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7915" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Drugs Metabolized by CYP1A2 In vitro data demonstrated that armodafinil is a weak inducer of CYP1A2 in a concentration-related manner.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7916" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>However, in a clinical study using caffeine as a probe substrate, no significant effect on CYP1A2 activity was observed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7917" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Drugs Metabolized by CYP2C19 In vitro data demonstrated that armodafinil is a reversible inhibitor of CYP2C19 activity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7918" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In a clinical study, concomitant administration of NUVIGIL 400 mg resulted in a 40% increase in exposure to omeprazole after a single oral dose (40 mg), as a result of moderate inhibition of CYP2C19 activity.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M157" type="Trigger" span="84 20" str="increase in exposure"/>
<Mention id="M158" type="Precipitant" span="108 10" str="omeprazole" code="KG60484QX9"/>
<Interaction id="I59" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M157" precipitant="M158" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7919" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Interactions with CNS Active Drugs Concomitant administration of NUVIGIL with quetiapine reduced the systemic exposure of quetiapine.Data specific to NUVIGIL drug-drug interaction potential with other CNS active drugs are not available.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M159" type="Trigger" span="89 29" str="reduced the systemic exposure"/>
<Mention id="M160" type="Precipitant" span="78 10" str="quetiapine" code="BGL0JSY5SI"/>
<Interaction id="I60" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M159" precipitant="M160" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7920" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>However, the following available drug-drug interaction information on modafinil should be applicable to NUVIGIL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7921" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Concomitant administration of modafinil with methylphenidate or dextroamphetamine produced no significant alterations on the pharmacokinetic profile of modafinil or either stimulant, even though the absorption of modafinil was delayed for approximately one hour.Concomitant modafinil or clomipramine did not alter the pharmacokinetic profile of either drug; however, one incident of increased levels of clomipramine and its active metabolite desmethylclomipramine was reported in a patient with narcolepsy during treatment with modafinil.Data specific to NUVIGIL or modafinil drug-drug interaction potential with monoamine oxidase (MAO) inhibitors are not available.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M163" type="Trigger" span="199 10;227 7" str="absorption | delayed"/>
<Mention id="M162" type="Precipitant" span="64 17" str="dextroamphetamine" code="TZ47U051FI"/>
<Mention id="M164" type="Precipitant" span="45 15" str="methylphenidate" code="207ZZ9QZ49"/>
<Interaction id="I61" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M163" precipitant="M162" effect="C54604"/>
<Interaction id="I62" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M163" precipitant="M164" effect="C54604"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7922" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Interaction with P-Glycoprotein An in vitro study demonstrated that armodafinil is a substrate of P-glycoprotein.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7923" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The impact of inhibition of P-glycoprotein is not known.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7924" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Interactions with Other Drugs Data specific to NUVIGIL drug-drug interaction potential for additional other drugs are not available.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7925" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>However, the following available drug-drug interaction information on modafinil should be applicable to NUVIGIL.Warfarin: Concomitant administration of modafinil with warfarin did not produce significant changes in the pharmacokinetic profiles of R- and S-warfarin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7926" LabelDrug="Nuvigil" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>However, since only a single dose of warfarin was tested in this study, an interaction cannot be ruled out.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M165" type="Trigger" span="75 31" str="interaction cannot be ruled out"/>
<Mention id="M166" type="Precipitant" span="37 8" str="warfarin" code="5Q7ZVV76EI | N0000006403"/>
<Interaction id="I63" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M165" precipitant="M166"/>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cyclosporine" precipitantCode="83HN0GTJ6D | N0000007346" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="cyclosporine" precipitantCode="83HN0GTJ6D | N0000007346"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cyp3a | 5 substrates" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cyp3a4 | substrates" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cyp3a4/5 substrates" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="midazolam" precipitantCode="R60L0SM5BC" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="steroidal contraceptives" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="102955006: Contraception failure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="steroidal contraceptives" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="steroidal contraceptives" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="substrates for cyp3a | 5" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="substrates for cyp3a4" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="substrates for cyp3a4/5" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="triazolam" precipitantCode="1HM943223R" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="ethinyl estradiol" precipitantCode="423D2T571U"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="clomipramine" precipitantCode="NUV44L116D" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cyp2c19 substrates" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="diazepam" precipitantCode="Q3JTX2Q7TU" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="omeprazole" precipitantCode="KG60484QX9" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="phenytoin" precipitantCode="6158TKW0C5 | N0000006023" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="propranolol" precipitantCode="9Y8NXQ24VQ" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="substrates for cyp2c19" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="warfarin" precipitantCode="5Q7ZVV76EI | N0000006403" effect=" 413086003: Deviation of international normalized ratio from target range (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="warfarin" precipitantCode="5Q7ZVV76EI | N0000006403" effect="165568006: Prothrombin time abnormal (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="warfarin" precipitantCode="5Q7ZVV76EI | N0000006403" effect="165583001: International normalized ratio abnormal (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="warfarin" precipitantCode="5Q7ZVV76EI | N0000006403"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="mao | inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000000184 | N0000175744"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="mao inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000000184 | N0000175744"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="monoamine oxidase | inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000000184 | N0000175744"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="food" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="food" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="food" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54604"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="carbamazepine" precipitantCode="33CM23913M | N0000007470"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="erythromycin" precipitantCode="N0000007133 | 63937KV33D"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="inhibitors of cyp3a | 5" precipitantCode="N0000190115"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="inhibitors of cyp3a4" precipitantCode="N0000182141"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="inhibitors of cyp3a4/5" precipitantCode="N0000190114"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="ketoconazole" precipitantCode="N0000007319 | R9400W927I"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="phenobarbital" precipitantCode="YQE403BP4D | N0000005893"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="potent inducers of cyp3a | 5" precipitantCode="N0000190118"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="potent inducers of cyp3a4" precipitantCode="N0000185506"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="potent inducers of cyp3a4/5" precipitantCode="N0000190118"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="rifampin" precipitantCode="VJT6J7R4TR | N0000006026"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="quetiapine" precipitantCode="BGL0JSY5SI" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="substrates for cyp3a enzymes" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="dextroamphetamine" precipitantCode="TZ47U051FI" effect="C54604"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="methylphenidate" precipitantCode="207ZZ9QZ49" effect="C54604"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>