<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Seconal Sodium" setid="d892a312-12ba-4d32-a840-2c0ff3dc1d58">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
Seconal Sodium is contraindicated in patients who are hypersensitive to barbiturates. It is also contraindicated in patients with a history of manifest or latent porphyria, marked impairment of liver function, or respiratory disease in which dyspnea or obstruction is evident.</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
Dosages of barbiturates must be individualized with full knowledge of their particular characteristics. Factors of consideration are the patient's age, weight, and condition. Adults As a hypnotic, 100 mg at bedtime. Preoperatively, 200 to 300 mg 1 to 2 hours before surgery. Pediatric Patients Preoperatively, 2 to 6 mg/kg, with a maximum dosage of 100 mg. Special patient population Dosage should be reduced in the elderly or debilitated because these patients may be more sensitive to barbiturates. Dosage should be reduced for patients with impaired renal function or hepatic disease.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
Drug Interactions Most reports of clinically significant drug interactions occurring with the barbiturates have involved phenobarbital. However, the application of these data to other barbiturates appears valid and warrants serial blood level determinations of the relevant drugs when there are multiple therapies. Anticoagulants Phenobarbital lowers the plasma levels of dicumarol and causes a decrease in anticoagulant activity as measured by the prothrombin time. Barbiturates can induce hepatic microsomal enzymes, resulting in increased metabolism and decreased anticoagulant response of oral anticoagulants (eg, warfarin, acenocoumarol, dicumarol, and phenprocoumon). Patients stabilized on anticoagulant therapy may require dosage adjustments if barbiturates are added to or withdrawn from their dosage regimen. Corticosteroids Barbiturates appear to enhance the metabolism of exogenous corticosteroids, probably through the induction of hepatic microsomal enzymes. Patients stabilized on corticosteroid therapy may require dosage adjustments if barbiturates are added to or withdrawn from their dosage regimen. Griseofulvin Phenobarbital appears to interfere with the absorption of orally administered griseofulvin, thus decreasing its blood level. The effect of the resultant decreased blood levels of griseofulvin on therapeutic response has not been established. However, it would be preferable to avoid concomitant administration of these drugs. Doxycycline Phenobarbital has been shown to shorten the half-life of doxycycline for as long as 2 weeks after barbiturate therapy is discontinued. This mechanism is probably through the induction of hepatic microsomal enzymes that metabolize the antibiotic. If barbiturates and doxycycline are administered concurrently, the clinical response to doxycycline should be monitored closely. Phenytoin, Sodium Valproate, Valproic Acid The effect of barbiturates on the metabolism of phenytoin appears to be variable. Some investigators report an accelerating effect, whereas others report no effect. Because the effect of barbiturates on the metabolism of phenytoin is not predictable, phenytoin and barbiturate blood levels should be monitored more frequently if these drugs are given concurrently. Sodium valproate and valproic acid increase the secobarbital sodium serum levels; therefore, secobarbital sodium blood levels should be monitored closely and appropriate dosage adjustments made as clinically indicated. CNS Depressants The concomitant use of other CNS depressants, including other sedatives or hypnotics, antihistamines, tranquilizers, or alcohol, may produce additive depressant effects. Monoamine Oxidase Inhibitors (MAOIs) MAOIs prolong the effects of barbiturates, probably because metabolism of the barbiturate is inhibited. Estradiol, Estrone, Progesterone, and Other Steroidal Hormones Pretreatment with or concurrent administration of phenobarbital may decrease the effect of estradiol by increasing its metabolism. There have been reports of patients treated with antiepileptic drugs (eg, phenobarbital) who become pregnant while taking oral contraceptives. An alternate contraceptive method might be suggested to women taking barbiturates.</Section>
<Section name="PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="42232-9">
General Barbiturates may be habit-forming. Tolerance and psychological and physical dependence may occur with continuing use (see DRUG ABUSE AND DEPENDENCE ). Barbiturates should be administered with caution, if at all, to patients who are mentally depressed, have suicidal tendencies, or have a history of drug abuse. Elderly or debilitated patients may react to barbiturates with marked excitement, depression, or confusion. In some persons, especially pediatric patients, barbiturates repeatedly produce excitement rather than depression. In patients with hepatic damage, barbiturates should be administered with caution and initially in reduced doses. Barbiturates should not be administered to patients showing the premonitory signs of hepatic coma. Information for Patients "Sleep-Driving" and Other Complex Behaviors There have been reports of people getting out of bed after taking a sedative-hypnotic and driving their cars while not fully awake, often with no memory of the event. If a patient experiences such an episode, it should be reported to his or her doctor immediately, since "sleep-driving" can be dangerous. This behavior is more likely to occur when sedative-hypnotics are taken with alcohol or other central nervous system depressants (see WARNINGS ). Other complex behaviors (e.g., preparing and eating food, making phone calls, or having sex) have been reported in patients who are not fully awake after taking a sedative-hypnotic. As with “sleep-driving”, patients usually do not remember these events. The following information should be given to patients receiving Seconal Sodium: 1. The use of Seconal Sodium carries with it an associated risk of psychological and/or physical dependence. The patient should be warned against increasing the dose of the drug without consulting a physician. 2. Seconal Sodium may impair the mental and/or physical abilities required for the performance of potentially hazardous tasks, such as driving a car or operating machinery. The patient should be cautioned accordingly. 3. Alcohol should not be consumed while taking Seconal Sodium. The concurrent use of Seconal Sodium with other CNS depressants (e.g., alcohol, narcotics, tranquilizers, and antihistamines) may result in additional CNS-depressant effects. Laboratory Tests Prolonged therapy with barbiturates should be accompanied by periodic laboratory evaluation of organic systems, including hematopoietic, renal, and hepatic systems (see PRECAUTIONS , General and ADVERSE REACTIONS ). Drug Interactions Most reports of clinically significant drug interactions occurring with the barbiturates have involved phenobarbital. However, the application of these data to other barbiturates appears valid and warrants serial blood level determinations of the relevant drugs when there are multiple therapies. Anticoagulants Phenobarbital lowers the plasma levels of dicumarol and causes a decrease in anticoagulant activity as measured by the prothrombin time. Barbiturates can induce hepatic microsomal enzymes, resulting in increased metabolism and decreased anticoagulant response of oral anticoagulants (eg, warfarin, acenocoumarol, dicumarol, and phenprocoumon). Patients stabilized on anticoagulant therapy may require dosage adjustments if barbiturates are added to or withdrawn from their dosage regimen. Corticosteroids Barbiturates appear to enhance the metabolism of exogenous corticosteroids, probably through the induction of hepatic microsomal enzymes. Patients stabilized on corticosteroid therapy may require dosage adjustments if barbiturates are added to or withdrawn from their dosage regimen. Griseofulvin Phenobarbital appears to interfere with the absorption of orally administered griseofulvin, thus decreasing its blood level. The effect of the resultant decreased blood levels of griseofulvin on therapeutic response has not been established. However, it would be preferable to avoid concomitant administration of these drugs. Doxycycline Phenobarbital has been shown to shorten the half-life of doxycycline for as long as 2 weeks after barbiturate therapy is discontinued. This mechanism is probably through the induction of hepatic microsomal enzymes that metabolize the antibiotic. If barbiturates and doxycycline are administered concurrently, the clinical response to doxycycline should be monitored closely. Phenytoin, Sodium Valproate, Valproic Acid The effect of barbiturates on the metabolism of phenytoin appears to be variable. Some investigators report an accelerating effect, whereas others report no effect. Because the effect of barbiturates on the metabolism of phenytoin is not predictable, phenytoin and barbiturate blood levels should be monitored more frequently if these drugs are given concurrently. Sodium valproate and valproic acid increase the secobarbital sodium serum levels; therefore, secobarbital sodium blood levels should be monitored closely and appropriate dosage adjustments made as clinically indicated. CNS Depressants The concomitant use of other CNS depressants, including other sedatives or hypnotics, antihistamines, tranquilizers, or alcohol, may produce additive depressant effects. Monoamine Oxidase Inhibitors (MAOIs) MAOIs prolong the effects of barbiturates, probably because metabolism of the barbiturate is inhibited. Estradiol, Estrone, Progesterone, and Other Steroidal Hormones Pretreatment with or concurrent administration of phenobarbital may decrease the effect of estradiol by increasing its metabolism. There have been reports of patients treated with antiepileptic drugs (eg, phenobarbital) who become pregnant while taking oral contraceptives. An alternate contraceptive method might be suggested to women taking barbiturates. Carcinogenesis Animal Data Phenobarbital sodium is carcinogenic in mice and rats after lifetime administration. In mice, it produced benign and malignant liver cell tumors. In rats, benign liver cell tumors were observed very late in life. Human Data In a 29-year epidemiologic study of 9,136 patients who were treated on an anticonvulsant protocol that included phenobarbital, results indicated a higher than normal incidence of hepatic carcinoma. Previously, some of these patients had been treated with thorotrast, a drug that is known to produce hepatic carcinomas. Thus, this study did not provide sufficient evidence that phenobarbital sodium is carcinogenic in humans. A retrospective study of 84 pediatric patients with brain tumors matched to 73 normal controls and 78 cancer controls (malignant disease other than brain tumors) suggested an association between exposure to barbiturates prenatally and an increased incidence of brain tumors. Pregnancy Teratogenic Effects See WARNINGS , Usage in Pregnancy . Nonteratogenic Effects Reports of infants suffering from long-term barbiturate exposure in utero included the acute withdrawal syndrome of seizures and hyperirritability from birth to a delayed onset of up to 14 days (see DRUG ABUSE AND DEPENDENCE ). Labor and Delivery Hypnotic doses of barbiturates do not appear to impair uterine activity significantly during labor. Full anesthetic doses of barbiturates decrease the force and frequency of uterine contractions. Administration of sedative-hypnotic barbiturates to the mother during labor may result in respiratory depression in the newborn. Premature infants are particularly susceptible to the depressant effects of barbiturates. If barbiturates are used during labor and delivery, resuscitation equipment should be available. Data are not available to evaluate the effect of barbiturates when forceps delivery or other intervention is necessary or to determine the effect of barbiturates on the later growth, development, and functional maturity of the pediatric patient. Nursing Mothers Caution should be exercised when Seconal Sodium is administered to a nursing woman, because small amounts of barbiturates are excreted in the milk.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS SECTION" id="34071-1">
Because sleep disturbances may be the presenting manifestation of a physical and/or psychiatric disorder, symptomatic treatment of insomnia should be initiated only after a careful evaluation of the patient. The failure of insomnia to remit after 7 to 10 days of treatment may indicate the presence of a primary psychiatric and/or medical illness that should be evaluated. Worsening of insomnia or the emergence of new thinking or behavior abnormalities may be the consequence of an unrecognized psychiatric or physical disorder. Such findings have emerged during the course of treatment with sedative-hypnotic drugs. Because some of the important adverse effects of sedative-hypnotics appear to be dose related (see P RECAUTIONS and DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION ), it is important to use the smallest possible effective dose, especially in the elderly. Complex behaviors such as "sleep-driving" (i.e., driving while not fully awake after ingestion of a sedative-hypnotic, with amnesia for the event) have been reported. These events can occur in sedative-hypnotic-naïve as well as in sedative-hypnotic-experienced persons. Although behaviors such as “sleep-driving” may occur with sedative-hypnotics alone at therapeutic doses, the use of alcohol and other CNS depressants with sedative-hypnotics appears to increase the risk of such behaviors, as does the use of sedative-hypnotics at doses exceeding the maximum recommended dose. Due to the risk to the patient and the community, discontinuation of sedative-hypnotics should be strongly considered for patients who report a "sleep-driving" episode. Other complex behaviors (e.g., preparing and eating food, making phone calls, or having sex) have been reported in patients who are not fully awake after taking a sedative-hypnotic. As with “sleep-driving” patients usually do not remember these events. Habit-Forming Seconal Sodium may be habit-forming. Tolerance and psychological and physical dependence may occur with continued use (see CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY , Pharmacokinetics and DRUG ABUSE AND DEPENDENCE). Patients who have psychological dependence on barbiturates may increase the dosage or decrease the dosage interval without consulting a physician and subsequently may develop a physical dependence on barbiturates. To minimize the possibility of overdosage or development of dependence, the prescribing and dispensing of sedative-hypnotic barbiturates should be limited to the amount required for the interval until the next appointment. The abrupt cessation after prolonged use in a person who is dependent on the drug may result in withdrawal symptoms, including delirium, convulsions, and possibly death. Barbiturates should be withdrawn gradually from any patient known to be taking excessive doses over long periods of time (see DRUG ABUSE AND DEPENDENCE ). Acute or Chronic Pain Caution should be exercised when barbiturates are administered to patients with acute or chronic pain, because paradoxical excitement could be induced or important symptoms could be masked. Usage in Pregnancy Barbiturates can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. Retrospective, case-controlled studies have suggested that there may be a connection between the maternal consumption of barbiturates and a higher than expected incidence of fetal abnormalities. Barbiturates readily cross the placental barrier and are distributed throughout fetal tissues; the highest concentrations are found in the placenta, fetal liver, and brain. Fetal blood levels approach maternal blood levels following parenteral administration. Withdrawal symptoms occur in infants born to women who receive barbiturates throughout the last trimester of pregnancy (see DRUG ABUSE AND DEPENDENCE ). If Seconal Sodium is used during pregnancy or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking this drug, the patient should be apprised of the potential hazard to the fetus. Synergistic Effects The concomitant use of alcohol or other CNS depressants may produce additive CNS-depressant effects.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Barbiturates are capable of producing all levels of CNS mood alteration, from excitation to mild sedation, hypnosis, and deep coma. Overdosage can produce death. In high enough therapeutic doses, barbiturates induce anesthesia. Barbiturates depress the sensory cortex, decrease motor activity, alter cerebellar function, and produce drowsiness, sedation, and hypnosis. Barbiturate-induced sleep differs from physiologic sleep. Sleep laboratory studies have demonstrated that barbiturates reduce the amount of time spent in the rapid eye movement (REM) phase, or dreaming stage of sleep. Also, Stages III and IV sleep are decreased. Following abrupt cessation of regularly used barbiturates, patients may experience markedly increased dreaming, nightmares, and/or insomnia. Therefore, withdrawal of a single therapeutic dose over 5 or 6 days has been recommended to lessen the REM rebound and disturbed sleep that contribute to drug withdrawal syndrome (for example, decreasing the dose from 3 to 2 doses a day for 1 week). In studies, secobarbital sodium and pentobarbital sodium have been found to lose most of their effectiveness for both inducing and maintaining sleep by the end of 2 weeks of continued drug administration, even with the use of multiple doses. As with secobarbital sodium and pentobarbital sodium, other barbiturates (including amobarbital) might be expected to lose their effectiveness for inducing and maintaining sleep after about 2 weeks. The short-, intermediate-, and to a lesser degree, long-acting barbiturates have been widely prescribed for treating insomnia. Although the clinical literature abounds with claims that the short-acting barbiturates are superior for producing sleep whereas the intermediate-acting compounds are more effective in maintaining sleep, controlled studies have failed to demonstrate these differential effects. Therefore, as sleep medications, the barbiturates are of limited value beyond short-term use. Barbiturates have little analgesic action at subanesthetic doses. Rather, in subanesthetic doses, these drugs may increase the reaction to painful stimuli. All barbiturates exhibit anticonvulsant activity in anesthetic doses. However, of the drugs in this class, only phenobarbital, mephobarbital, and metharbital are effective as oral anticonvulsants in subhypnotic doses. Barbiturates are respiratory depressants, and the degree of depression is dependent on the dose. With hypnotic doses, respiratory depression is similar to that which occurs during physiologic sleep accompanied by a slight decrease in blood pressure and heart rate. Studies in laboratory animals have shown that barbiturates cause reduction in the tone and contractility of the uterus, ureters, and urinary bladder. However, concentrations of the drugs required to produce this effect in humans are not reached with sedative-hypnotic doses. Barbiturates do not impair normal hepatic function, but have been shown to induce liver microsomal enzymes, thus increasing and/or altering the metabolism of barbiturates and other drugs (see Precautions , Drug Interactions ). Pharmacokinetics Barbiturates are absorbed in varying degrees following oral or parenteral administration. The salts are more rapidly absorbed than are the acids. The rate of absorption is increased if the sodium salt is ingested as a dilute solution or taken on an empty stomach. Duration of action, which is related to the rate at which the barbiturates are redistributed throughout the body, varies among persons and in the same person from time to time. Seconal Sodium is classified as a short-acting barbiturate when taken orally. Its onset of action is 10 to 15 minutes and its duration of action ranges from 3 to 4 hours. Barbiturates are weak acids that are absorbed and rapidly distributed to all tissues and fluids, with high concentrations in the brain, liver, and kidneys. Lipid solubility of the barbiturates is the dominant factor in their distribution within the body. The more lipid soluble the barbiturate, the more rapidly it penetrates all tissues of the body. Barbiturates are bound to plasma and tissue proteins to a varying degree, with the degree of binding increasing directly as a function of lipid solubility. Phenobarbital has the lowest lipid solubility, lowest plasma binding, lowest brain protein binding, the longest delay in onset of activity, and the longest duration of action. At the opposite extreme is secobarbital, which has the highest lipid solubility, highest plasma protein binding, highest brain protein binding, the shortest delay in onset of activity, and the shortest duration of action. The plasma half-life for secobarbital sodium in adults ranges between 15 to 40 hours, with a mean of 28 hours. No data are available for pediatric patients and newborns. Barbiturates are metabolized primarily by the hepatic microsomal enzyme system, and the metabolic products are excreted in the urine and, less commonly, in the feces. The excretion of unmetabolized barbiturate is 1 feature that distinguishes the long-acting category from those belonging to other categories, which are almost entirely metabolized. The inactive metabolites of the barbiturates are excreted as conjugates of glucuronic acid.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="5850" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Seconal Sodium is contraindicated in patients who are hypersensitive to barbiturates.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5851" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>It is also contraindicated in patients with a history of manifest or latent porphyria, marked impairment of liver function, or respiratory disease in which dyspnea or obstruction is evident.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5852" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dosages of barbiturates must be individualized with full knowledge of their particular characteristics.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5853" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Factors of consideration are the patient's age, weight, and condition.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5854" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Adults As a hypnotic, 100 mg at bedtime.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5855" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Preoperatively, 200 to 300 mg 1 to 2 hours before surgery.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5856" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Pediatric Patients Preoperatively, 2 to 6 mg/kg, with a maximum dosage of 100 mg. Special patient population Dosage should be reduced in the elderly or debilitated because these patients may be more sensitive to barbiturates.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5857" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dosage should be reduced for patients with impaired renal function or hepatic disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5858" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Drug Interactions Most reports of clinically significant drug interactions occurring with the barbiturates have involved phenobarbital.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5859" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>However, the application of these data to other barbiturates appears valid and warrants serial blood level determinations of the relevant drugs when there are multiple therapies.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5860" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Anticoagulants Phenobarbital lowers the plasma levels of dicumarol and causes a decrease in anticoagulant activity as measured by the prothrombin time.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M4" type="Trigger" span="71 6" str="causes"/>
<Mention id="M5" type="Precipitant" span="0 13" str="anticoagulant" code="N0000175980"/>
<Mention id="M3" type="SpecificInteraction" span="80 11;134 16" str="decrease in | prothrombin time" code="165569003: Prothrombin time low (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M6" type="SpecificInteraction" span="80 34" str="decrease in anticoagulant activity" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M7" type="Trigger" span="29 24" str="lowers the plasma levels"/>
<Mention id="M8" type="Precipitant" span="57 9" str="dicumarol" code="7QID3E7BG7"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M4" precipitant="M5" effect="M3" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M4" precipitant="M5" effect="M6" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M7" precipitant="M8" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5861" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Barbiturates can induce hepatic microsomal enzymes, resulting in increased metabolism and decreased anticoagulant response of oral anticoagulants (eg, warfarin, acenocoumarol, dicumarol, and phenprocoumon).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M25" type="Trigger" span="17 33" str="induce hepatic microsomal enzymes "/>
<Mention id="M26" type="Trigger" span="65 20" str=" increased metabolism "/>
<Mention id="M27" type="Trigger" span="90 9;114 8" str=" decreased | response"/>
<Mention id="M12" type="Precipitant" span="161 13" str="acenocoumarol" code="I6WP63U32H"/>
<Mention id="M16" type="Precipitant" span="176 9" str="dicumarol" code="7QID3E7BG7"/>
<Mention id="M20" type="Precipitant" span="126 19" str="oral anticoagulants" code="N0000175980"/>
<Mention id="M24" type="Precipitant" span="191 13" str="phenprocoumon" code="Q08SIO485D"/>
<Mention id="M28" type="Precipitant" span="151 8" str="warfarin" code="5Q7ZVV76EI | N0000006403"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M25;M26;M27" precipitant="M12" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M25;M26;M27" precipitant="M16" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M25;M26;M27" precipitant="M20" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M25;M26;M27" precipitant="M24" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M25;M26;M27" precipitant="M28" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5862" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Patients stabilized on anticoagulant therapy may require dosage adjustments if barbiturates are added to or withdrawn from their dosage regimen.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M29" type="Trigger" span="57 18" str="dosage adjustments"/>
<Mention id="M30" type="Precipitant" span="23 13" str="anticoagulant" code="N0000175980"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M29" precipitant="M30"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5863" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Corticosteroids Barbiturates appear to enhance the metabolism of exogenous corticosteroids, probably through the induction of hepatic microsomal enzymes.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M31" type="Trigger" span="39 22" str="enhance the metabolism "/>
<Mention id="M32" type="Trigger" span="113 39" str=" induction of hepatic microsomal enzymes"/>
<Mention id="M33" type="Precipitant" span="65 25" str="exogenous corticosteroids" code="N0000175576"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M31;M32" precipitant="M33" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5864" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Patients stabilized on corticosteroid therapy may require dosage adjustments if barbiturates are added to or withdrawn from their dosage regimen.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M34" type="Trigger" span="58 18" str="dosage adjustments"/>
<Mention id="M35" type="Precipitant" span="23 14" str="corticosteroid" code="N0000175576"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M34" precipitant="M35"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5865" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Griseofulvin Phenobarbital appears to interfere with the absorption of orally administered griseofulvin, thus decreasing its blood level.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M36" type="Trigger" span="38 29" str="interfere with the absorption "/>
<Mention id="M37" type="Trigger" span="110 26" str=" decreasing its blood level"/>
<Mention id="M38" type="Precipitant" span="71 4;0 12" str="oral | griseofulvin" code="32HRV3E3D5"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M36;M37" precipitant="M38" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5866" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The effect of the resultant decreased blood levels of griseofulvin on therapeutic response has not been established.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M39" type="Trigger" span="28 22" str="decreased blood levels"/>
<Mention id="M40" type="Precipitant" span="54 12" str="griseofulvin" code="32HRV3E3D5"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M39" precipitant="M40" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5867" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>However, it would be preferable to avoid concomitant administration of these drugs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5868" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Doxycycline Phenobarbital has been shown to shorten the half-life of doxycycline for as long as 2 weeks after barbiturate therapy is discontinued.This mechanism is probably through the induction of hepatic microsomal enzymes that metabolize the antibiotic.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M41" type="Trigger" span="185 39" str="induction of hepatic microsomal enzymes"/>
<Mention id="M44" type="Precipitant" span="0 11" str="doxycycline" code="N12000U13O"/>
<Mention id="M43" type="Trigger" span="44 21" str="shorten the half-life"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M41" precipitant="M44" effect="C54358"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M43" precipitant="M44" effect="C54616"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5869" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>If barbiturates and doxycycline are administered concurrently, the clinical response to doxycycline should be monitored closely.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M45" type="Trigger" span="100 19" str="should be monitored"/>
<Mention id="M46" type="Precipitant" span="20 11" str="doxycycline" code="N12000U13O"/>
<Mention id="M47" type="SpecificInteraction" span="76 23" str="response to doxycycline" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M45" precipitant="M46" effect="M47" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5870" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Phenytoin, Sodium Valproate, Valproic Acid The effect of barbiturates on the metabolism of phenytoin appears to be variable.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M48" type="Trigger" span="47 6;115 8" str="effect | variable"/>
<Mention id="M49" type="Precipitant" span="0 9" str="phenytoin" code="6158TKW0C5 | N0000006023"/>
<Mention id="M50" type="SpecificInteraction" span="47 6;77 23" str="effect | metabolism of phenytoin" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M48" precipitant="M49" effect="M50" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5871" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Some investigators report an accelerating effect, whereas others report no effect.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5872" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Because the effect of barbiturates on the metabolism of phenytoin is not predictable, phenytoin and barbiturate blood levels should be monitored more frequently if these drugs are given concurrently.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M54" type="Trigger" span="125 19" str="should be monitored"/>
<Mention id="M55" type="Precipitant" span="56 9" str="phenytoin" code="6158TKW0C5 | N0000006023"/>
<Mention id="M53" type="SpecificInteraction" span="100 24" str="barbiturate blood levels" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M56" type="SpecificInteraction" span="56 9;112 12" str="phenytoin | blood levels" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M54" precipitant="M55" effect="M53" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M54" precipitant="M55" effect="M56" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5873" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Sodium valproate and valproic acid increase the secobarbital sodium serum levels; therefore, secobarbital sodium blood levels should be monitored closely and appropriate dosage adjustments made as clinically indicated.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M59" type="Trigger" span="35 8;68 12" str="increase | serum levels"/>
<Mention id="M58" type="Precipitant" span="0 16" str="Sodium valproate" code="5VOM6GYJ0D"/>
<Mention id="M60" type="Precipitant" span="21 13" str="valproic acid" code="614OI1Z5WI"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M59" precipitant="M58" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M59" precipitant="M60" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5874" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>CNS Depressants The concomitant use of other CNS depressants, including other sedatives or hypnotics, antihistamines, tranquilizers, or alcohol, may produce additive depressant effects.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M81" type="Trigger" span="149 7" str="produce "/>
<Mention id="M82" type="Trigger" span="157 8;177 7" str=" additive | effects"/>
<Mention id="M63" type="Precipitant" span="136 7" str="alcohol" code="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M"/>
<Mention id="M84" type="SpecificInteraction" span="157 27" str="additive depressant effects" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M67" type="Precipitant" span="102 14" str="antihistamines" code="N0000175750 | N0000029071"/>
<Mention id="M71" type="Precipitant" span="0 15" str="CNS depressants" code="N0000175758"/>
<Mention id="M75" type="Precipitant" span="91 9" str="hypnotics" code="N0000029424 | N0000193842"/>
<Mention id="M79" type="Precipitant" span="78 9" str="sedatives" code="N0000029143 | N0000193842"/>
<Mention id="M83" type="Precipitant" span="118 13" str="tranquilizers" code="N0000029143 | N0000193842"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M81;M82" precipitant="M63" effect="M84" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M81;M82" precipitant="M67" effect="M84" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M81;M82" precipitant="M71" effect="M84" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M81;M82" precipitant="M75" effect="M84" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M81;M82" precipitant="M79" effect="M84" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M81;M82" precipitant="M83" effect="M84" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5875" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Monoamine Oxidase Inhibitors (MAOIs) MAOIs prolong the effects of barbiturates, probably because metabolism of the barbiturate is inhibited.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M88" type="Trigger" span="43 19" str="prolong the effects"/>
<Mention id="M92" type="Precipitant" span="30 5" str="MAOIs" code="N0000000184"/>
<Mention id="M90" type="SpecificInteraction" span="43 35" str="prolong the effects of barbiturates" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M94" type="Precipitant" span="0 28" str="Monoamine Oxidase Inhibitors" code="N0000000184 | N0000175744"/>
<Mention id="M93" type="Trigger" span="97 10;130 9" str="metabolism | inhibited"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M88" precipitant="M92" effect="M90" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I29" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M88" precipitant="M94" effect="M90" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I30" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M93" precipitant="M92" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I31" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M93" precipitant="M94" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5876" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Estradiol, Estrone, Progesterone, and Other Steroidal Hormones Pretreatment with or concurrent administration of phenobarbital may decrease the effect of estradiol by increasing its metabolism.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M95" type="Trigger" span="131 19" str="decrease the effect "/>
<Mention id="M96" type="Trigger" span="167 25" str=" increasing its metabolism"/>
<Mention id="M97" type="Precipitant" span="0 9" str="estradiol" code="4TI98Z838E"/>
<Interaction id="I32" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M95;M96" precipitant="M97" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5877" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>There have been reports of patients treated with antiepileptic drugs (eg, phenobarbital) who become pregnant while taking oral contraceptives.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M100" type="SpecificInteraction" span="93 15" str="become pregnant" code="77386006: Pregnant (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M99" type="Precipitant" span="122 19" str="oral contraceptives" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I33" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M100" precipitant="M99" effect="M100" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5878" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>An alternate contraceptive method might be suggested to women taking barbiturates.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5879" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>General Barbiturates may be habit-forming.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5880" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Tolerance and psychological and physical dependence may occur with continuing use.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5881" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Barbiturates should be administered with caution, if at all, to patients who are mentally depressed, have suicidal tendencies, or have a history of drug abuse.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5882" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Elderly or debilitated patients may react to barbiturates with marked excitement, depression, or confusion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5883" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In some persons, especially pediatric patients, barbiturates repeatedly produce excitement rather than depression.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5884" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In patients with hepatic damage, barbiturates should be administered with caution and initially in reduced doses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5885" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Barbiturates should not be administered to patients showing the premonitory signs of hepatic coma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5886" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Information for Patients Sleep-Driving and Other Complex Behaviors There have been reports of people getting out of bed after taking a sedative-hypnotic and driving their cars while not fully awake, often with no memory of the event.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5887" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>If a patient experiences such an episode, it should be reported to his or her doctor immediately, since sleep-driving can be dangerous.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5888" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>This behavior is more likely to occur when sedative-hypnotics are taken with alcohol or other central nervous system depressants.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M103" type="Trigger" span="17 20" str="more likely to occur"/>
<Mention id="M102" type="Precipitant" span="77 7" str="alcohol" code="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M"/>
<Mention id="M104" type="Precipitant" span="94 34" str="central nervous system depressants" code="N0000175758"/>
<Interaction id="I34" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M103" precipitant="M102"/>
<Interaction id="I35" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M103" precipitant="M104"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5889" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Other complex behaviors (e.g., preparing and eating food, making phone calls, or having sex) have been reported in patients who are not fully awake after taking a sedative-hypnotic.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5890" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>As with “sleep-driving”, patients usually do not remember these events.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5891" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The following information should be given to patients receiving Seconal Sodium: 1.The use of Seconal Sodium carries with it an associated risk of psychological and/or physical dependence.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5892" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The patient should be warned against increasing the dose of the drug without consulting a physician.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5893" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>2.Seconal Sodium may impair the mental and/or physical abilities required for the performance of potentially hazardous tasks, such as driving a car or operating machinery.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5894" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The patient should be cautioned accordingly.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5895" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>3.Alcohol should not be consumed while taking Seconal Sodium.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M105" type="Trigger" span="10 22" str="should not be consumed"/>
<Mention id="M106" type="Precipitant" span="2 7" str="Alcohol" code="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M"/>
<Interaction id="I36" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M105" precipitant="M106"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5896" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The concurrent use of Seconal Sodium with other CNS depressants (e.g., alcohol, narcotics, tranquilizers, and antihistamines) may result in additional CNS-depressant effects.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M123" type="Trigger" span="130 9" str="result in "/>
<Mention id="M124" type="Trigger" span="140 10;166 7" str=" additional | effects"/>
<Mention id="M109" type="Precipitant" span="71 7" str="alcohol" code="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M"/>
<Mention id="M126" type="SpecificInteraction" span="140 33" str="additional CNS-depressant effects" code="418072004: Central nervous system depression (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M113" type="Precipitant" span="110 14" str="antihistamines" code="N0000175750 | N0000029071"/>
<Mention id="M117" type="Precipitant" span="48 15" str="CNS depressants" code="N0000175758"/>
<Mention id="M121" type="Precipitant" span="80 9" str="narcotics" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M125" type="Precipitant" span="91 13" str="tranquilizers" code="N0000029143 | N0000193842"/>
<Interaction id="I37" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M123;M124" precipitant="M109" effect="M126" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I38" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M123;M124" precipitant="M113" effect="M126" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I39" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M123;M124" precipitant="M117" effect="M126" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I40" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M123;M124" precipitant="M121" effect="M126" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I41" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M123;M124" precipitant="M125" effect="M126" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5897" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Laboratory Tests Prolonged therapy with barbiturates should be accompanied by periodic laboratory evaluation of organic systems, including hematopoietic, renal, and hepatic systems.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5898" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Carcinogenesis Animal Data Phenobarbital sodium is carcinogenic in mice and rats after lifetime administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5899" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In mice, it produced benign and malignant liver cell tumors.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5900" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In rats, benign liver cell tumors were observed very late in life.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5901" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Human Data In a 29-year epidemiologic study of 9,136 patients who were treated on an anticonvulsant protocol that included phenobarbital, results indicated a higher than normal incidence of hepatic carcinoma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5902" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Previously, some of these patients had been treated with thorotrast, a drug that is known to produce hepatic carcinomas.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5903" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Thus, this study did not provide sufficient evidence that phenobarbital sodium is carcinogenic in humans.A retrospective study of 84 pediatric patients with brain tumors matched to 73 normal controls and 78 cancer controls (malignant disease other than brain tumors) suggested an association between exposure to barbiturates prenatally and an increased incidence of brain tumors.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5904" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Pregnancy Teratogenic Effects See WARNINGS, Usage in Pregnancy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5905" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Nonteratogenic Effects Reports of infants suffering from long-term barbiturate exposure in utero included the acute withdrawal syndrome of seizures and hyperirritability from birth to a delayed onset of up to 14 days.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5906" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Labor and Delivery Hypnotic doses of barbiturates do not appear to impair uterine activity significantly during labor.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5907" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Full anesthetic doses of barbiturates decrease the force and frequency of uterine contractions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5908" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Administration of sedative-hypnotic barbiturates to the mother during labor may result in respiratory depression in the newborn.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5909" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Premature infants are particularly susceptible to the depressant effects of barbiturates.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5910" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>If barbiturates are used during labor and delivery, resuscitation equipment should be available.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5911" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Data are not available to evaluate the effect of barbiturates when forceps delivery or other intervention is necessary or to determine the effect of barbiturates on the later growth, development, and functional maturity of the pediatric patient.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5912" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Nursing Mothers Caution should be exercised when Seconal Sodium is administered to a nursing woman, because small amounts of barbiturates are excreted in the milk.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5913" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Because sleep disturbances may be the presenting manifestation of a physical and/or psychiatric disorder, symptomatic treatment of insomnia should be initiated only after a careful evaluation of the patient.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5914" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The failure of insomnia to remit after 7 to 10 days of treatment may indicate the presence of a primary psychiatric and/or medical illness that should be evaluated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5915" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Worsening of insomnia or the emergence of new thinking or behavior abnormalities may be the consequence of an unrecognized psychiatric or physical disorder.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5916" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Such findings have emerged during the course of treatment with sedative-hypnotic drugs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5917" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Because some of the important adverse effects of sedative-hypnotics appear to be dose related, it is important to use the smallest possible effective dose, especially in the elderly.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5918" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Complex behaviors such as sleep-driving (i.e., driving while not fully awake after ingestion of a sedative-hypnotic, with amnesia for the event) have been reported.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5919" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>These events can occur in sedative-hypnotic-naÃ¯ve as well as in sedative-hypnotic-experienced persons.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5920" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Although behaviors such as “sleep-driving” may occur with sedative-hypnotics alone at therapeutic doses, the use of alcohol and other CNS depressants with sedative-hypnotics appears to increase the risk of such behaviors, as does the use of sedative-hypnotics at doses exceeding the maximum recommended dose.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M130" type="Trigger" span="185 17" str="increase the risk"/>
<Mention id="M128" type="Precipitant" span="116 7" str="alcohol" code="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M"/>
<Mention id="M132" type="SpecificInteraction" span="9 17;28 13" str="behaviors such as | sleep-driving" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M131" type="Precipitant" span="134 15" str="CNS depressants" code="N0000175758"/>
<Interaction id="I42" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M130" precipitant="M128" effect="M132" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I43" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M130" precipitant="M131" effect="M132" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5921" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Due to the risk to the patient and the community, discontinuation of sedative-hypnotics should be strongly considered for patients who report a sleep-driving episode.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5922" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>As with “sleep-driving” patients usually do not remember these events.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5923" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Habit-Forming Seconal Sodium may be habit-forming.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5924" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Tolerance and psychological and physical dependence may occur with continued use.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5925" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Patients who have psychological dependence on barbiturates may increase the dosage or decrease the dosage interval without consulting a physician and subsequently may develop a physical dependence on barbiturates.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5926" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>To minimize the possibility of overdosage or development of dependence, the prescribing and dispensing of sedative-hypnotic barbiturates should be limited to the amount required for the interval until the next appointment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5927" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The abrupt cessation after prolonged use in a person who is dependent on the drug may result in withdrawal symptoms, including delirium, convulsions, and possibly death.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5928" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Barbiturates should be withdrawn gradually from any patient known to be taking excessive doses over long periods of time.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5929" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Acute or Chronic Pain Caution should be exercised when barbiturates are administered to patients with acute or chronic pain, because paradoxical excitement could be induced or important symptoms could be masked.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5930" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Usage in Pregnancy Barbiturates can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5931" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Retrospective, case-controlled studies have suggested that there may be a connection between the maternal consumption of barbiturates and a higher than expected incidence of fetal abnormalities.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5932" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Barbiturates readily cross the placental barrier and are distributed throughout fetal tissues; the highest concentrations are found in the placenta, fetal liver, and brain.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5933" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Fetal blood levels approach maternal blood levels following parenteral administration.Withdrawal symptoms occur in infants born to women who receive barbiturates throughout the last trimester of pregnancy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5934" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>If Seconal Sodium is used during pregnancy or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking this drug, the patient should be apprised of the potential hazard to the fetus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5935" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Synergistic Effects The concomitant use of alcohol or other CNS depressants may produce additive CNS-depressant effects.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M138" type="Trigger" span="0 19" str="Synergistic Effects "/>
<Mention id="M139" type="Trigger" span="80 7" str=" produce "/>
<Mention id="M140" type="Trigger" span="88 8;12 7" str=" additive | effects"/>
<Mention id="M136" type="Precipitant" span="43 7" str="alcohol" code="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M"/>
<Mention id="M142" type="SpecificInteraction" span="88 31" str="additive CNS-depressant effects" code="418072004: Central nervous system depression (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M141" type="Precipitant" span="60 15" str="CNS depressants" code="N0000175758"/>
<Interaction id="I44" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M138;M139;M140" precipitant="M136" effect="M142" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I45" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M138;M139;M140" precipitant="M141" effect="M142" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5936" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Barbiturates are capable of producing all levels of CNS mood alteration, from excitation to mild sedation, hypnosis, and deep coma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5937" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In high enough therapeutic doses, barbiturates induce anesthesia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5938" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Barbiturates depress the sensory cortex, decrease motor activity, alter cerebellar function, and produce drowsiness, sedation, and hypnosis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5939" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Barbiturate-induced sleep differs from physiologic sleep.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5940" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Sleep laboratory studies have demonstrated that barbiturates reduce the amount of time spent in the rapid eye movement (REM) phase, or dreaming stage of sleep.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5941" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Also, Stages III and IV sleep are decreased.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5942" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following abrupt cessation of regularly used barbiturates, patients may experience markedly increased dreaming, nightmares, and/or insomnia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5943" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Therefore, withdrawal of a single therapeutic dose over 5 or 6 days has been recommended to lessen the REM rebound and disturbed sleep that contribute to drug withdrawal syndrome (for example, decreasing the dose from 3 to 2 doses a day for 1 week).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5944" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In studies, secobarbital sodium and pentobarbital sodium have been found to lose most of their effectiveness for both inducing and maintaining sleep by the end of 2 weeks of continued drug administration, even with the use of multiple doses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5945" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>As with secobarbital sodium and pentobarbital sodium, other barbiturates (including amobarbital) might be expected to lose their effectiveness for inducing and maintaining sleep after about 2 weeks.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5946" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The short-, intermediate-, and to a lesser degree, long-acting barbiturates have been widely prescribed for treating insomnia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5947" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Although the clinical literature abounds with claims that the short-acting barbiturates are superior for producing sleep whereas the intermediate-acting compounds are more effective in maintaining sleep, controlled studies have failed to demonstrate these differential effects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5948" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Therefore, as sleep medications, the barbiturates are of limited value beyond short-term use.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5949" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Barbiturates have little analgesic action at subanesthetic doses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5950" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Rather, in subanesthetic doses, these drugs may increase the reaction to painful stimuli.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5951" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>All barbiturates exhibit anticonvulsant activity in anesthetic doses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5952" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>However, of the drugs in this class, only phenobarbital, mephobarbital, and metharbital are effective as oral anticonvulsants in subhypnotic doses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5953" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Barbiturates are respiratory depressants, and the degree of depression is dependent on the dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5954" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>With hypnotic doses, respiratory depression is similar to that which occurs during physiologic sleep accompanied by a slight decrease in blood pressure and heart rate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5955" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Studies in laboratory animals have shown that barbiturates cause reduction in the tone and contractility of the uterus, ureters, and urinary bladder.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5956" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>However, concentrations of the drugs required to produce this effect in humans are not reached with sedative-hypnotic doses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5957" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Barbiturates do not impair normal hepatic function, but have been shown to induce liver microsomal enzymes, thus increasing and/or altering the metabolism of barbiturates and other drugs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5958" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Pharmacokinetics Barbiturates are absorbed in varying degrees following oral or parenteral administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5959" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The salts are more rapidly absorbed than are the acids.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5960" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The rate of absorption is increased if the sodium salt is ingested as a dilute solution or taken on an empty stomach.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5961" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Duration of action, which is related to the rate at which the barbiturates are redistributed throughout the body, varies among persons and in the same person from time to time.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5962" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Seconal Sodium is classified as a short-acting barbiturate when taken orally.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5963" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Its onset of action is 10 to 15 minutes and its duration of action ranges from 3 to 4 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5964" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Barbiturates are weak acids that are absorbed and rapidly distributed to all tissues and fluids, with high concentrations in the brain, liver, and kidneys.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5965" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Lipid solubility of the barbiturates is the dominant factor in their distribution within the body.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5966" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The more lipid soluble the barbiturate, the more rapidly it penetrates all tissues of the body.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5967" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Barbiturates are bound to plasma and tissue proteins to a varying degree, with the degree of binding increasing directly as a function of lipid solubility.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5968" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Phenobarbital has the lowest lipid solubility, lowest plasma binding, lowest brain protein binding, the longest delay in onset of activity, and the longest duration of action.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5969" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>At the opposite extreme is secobarbital, which has the highest lipid solubility, highest plasma protein binding, highest brain protein binding, the shortest delay in onset of activity, and the shortest duration of action.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5970" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The plasma half-life for secobarbital sodium in adults ranges between 15 to 40 hours, with a mean of 28 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5971" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No data are available for pediatric patients and newborns.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5972" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Barbiturates are metabolized primarily by the hepatic microsomal enzyme system, and the metabolic products are excreted in the urine and, less commonly, in the feces.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5973" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The excretion of unmetabolized barbiturate is 1 feature that distinguishes the long-acting category from those belonging to other categories, which are almost entirely metabolized.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5974" LabelDrug="Seconal Sodium" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The inactive metabolites of the barbiturates are excreted as conjugates of glucuronic acid.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="anticoagulant" precipitantCode="N0000175980" effect="165569003: Prothrombin time low (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="anticoagulant" precipitantCode="N0000175980" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="anticoagulant" precipitantCode="N0000175980"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="dicumarol" precipitantCode="7QID3E7BG7" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="acenocoumarol" precipitantCode="I6WP63U32H" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="oral anticoagulants" precipitantCode="N0000175980" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="phenprocoumon" precipitantCode="Q08SIO485D" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="warfarin" precipitantCode="5Q7ZVV76EI | N0000006403" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="exogenous corticosteroids" precipitantCode="N0000175576" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="corticosteroid" precipitantCode="N0000175576"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="oral | griseofulvin" precipitantCode="32HRV3E3D5" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="griseofulvin" precipitantCode="32HRV3E3D5" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="doxycycline" precipitantCode="N12000U13O" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="doxycycline" precipitantCode="N12000U13O" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="doxycycline" precipitantCode="N12000U13O" effect="C54616"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="phenytoin" precipitantCode="6158TKW0C5 | N0000006023" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="sodium valproate" precipitantCode="5VOM6GYJ0D" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="valproic acid" precipitantCode="614OI1Z5WI" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="alcohol" precipitantCode="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M" effect="418072004: Central nervous system depression (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="alcohol" precipitantCode="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="alcohol" precipitantCode="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="antihistamines" precipitantCode="N0000175750 | N0000029071" effect="418072004: Central nervous system depression (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="antihistamines" precipitantCode="N0000175750 | N0000029071" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cns depressants" precipitantCode="N0000175758" effect="418072004: Central nervous system depression (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cns depressants" precipitantCode="N0000175758" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="hypnotics" precipitantCode="N0000029424 | N0000193842" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sedatives" precipitantCode="N0000029143 | N0000193842" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="tranquilizers" precipitantCode="N0000029143 | N0000193842" effect="418072004: Central nervous system depression (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="tranquilizers" precipitantCode="N0000029143 | N0000193842" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="maois" precipitantCode="N0000000184" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="maois" precipitantCode="N0000000184" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="monoamine oxidase inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000000184 | N0000175744" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="monoamine oxidase inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000000184 | N0000175744" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="estradiol" precipitantCode="4TI98Z838E" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="oral contraceptives" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="77386006: Pregnant (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="central nervous system depressants" precipitantCode="N0000175758"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="narcotics" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="418072004: Central nervous system depression (disorder)"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>