<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="ALBENZA" setid="e8941166-b77d-45aa-a6e8-04f1c0afd845">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
ALBENZA is contraindicated in patients with known hypersensitivity to the benzimidazole class of compounds or any components of ALBENZA. Patients with known hypersensitivity to the benzimidazole class of compounds or any components of ALBENZA.</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
Patients weighing 60 kg or greater, 400 mg twice daily; less than 60 kg, 15 mg/kg/day in divided doses twice daily (maximum total daily dose 800 mg). ALBENZA tablets should be taken with food. ( 2 ) Hydatid disease: 28-day cycle followed by 14-day albendazole-free interval for a total of 3 cycles. ( 2 ) Neurocysticercosis: 8 to 30 days. ( 2 ) See additional important information in the Full Prescribing Information. ( 2 ) Dosing of ALBENZA will vary depending upon the indication. ALBENZA tablets may be crushed or chewed and swallowed with a drink of water. ALBENZA tablets should be taken with food [ see Clinical Pharmacology ( 12.3 ) ]. Table 1: ALBENZA Dosage Indication Patient Weight Dose Duration Hydatid Disease 60 kg or greater 400 mg twice daily, with meals 28-day cycle followed by a 14-day albendazole-free interval, for a total of 3 cycles Less than 60 kg 15 mg/kg/day given in divided doses twice daily with meals (maximum total daily dose 800 mg) Neurocysticercosis 60 kg or greater 400 mg twice daily, with meals 8 to 30 days Less than 60 kg 15 mg/kg/day given in divided doses twice daily with meals (maximum total daily dose 800 mg) Patients being treated for neurocysticercosis should receive appropriate steroid and anticonvulsant therapy as required. Oral or intravenous corticosteroids should be considered to prevent cerebral hypertensive episodes during the first week of treatment [ see Warnings and Precautions ( 5.3 ) ]. Monitor blood counts at the beginning of each 28-day cycle of therapy, and every 2 weeks while on therapy with ALBENZA in all patients [ see Warnings and Precautions ( 5.1 ) ]. Monitor liver enzymes (transaminases) at the beginning of each 28-day cycle of therapy, and at least every 2 weeks during treatment with ALBENZA in all patients [ see Warnings and Precautions ( 5.5 ) ]. Obtain a pregnancy test in women of reproductive potential prior to therapy [ see Warnings and Precautions ( 5.2 ) ].</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
Dexamethasone: Steady-state trough concentrations of albendazole sulfoxide were about 56% higher when dexamethasone was coadministered with each dose of albendazole. ( 7.1 ) Praziquantel: In the fed state increased mean maximum plasma concentration and area under the curve of albendazole sulfoxide by about 50% in healthy subjects. ( 7.2 ) Cimetidine: Increased albendazole sulfoxide concentrations in bile and cystic fluid by about 2-fold in hydatid cyst patients. ( 7.3 ) Theophylline: Albendazole induces cytochrome P450 1A in human hepatoma cells; therefore, it is recommended that plasma concentrations of theophylline be monitored during and after treatment. ( 5.5 , 7.4 ) Steady-state trough concentrations of albendazole sulfoxide were about 56% higher when 8 mg dexamethasone was co-administered with each dose of albendazole (15 mg/kg/day) in 8 neurocysticercosis patients. In the fed state, praziquantel (40 mg/kg) increased mean maximum plasma concentration and area under the curve of albendazole sulfoxide by about 50% in healthy subjects (n = 10) compared with a separate group of subjects (n = 6) given albendazole alone. Mean T max and mean plasma elimination half-life of albendazole sulfoxide were unchanged. The pharmacokinetics of praziquantel were unchanged following co-administration with albendazole (400 mg). Albendazole sulfoxide concentrations in bile and cystic fluid were increased (about 2-fold) in hydatid cyst patients treated with cimetidine (10 mg/kg/day) (n = 7) compared with albendazole (20 mg/kg/day) alone (n = 12). Albendazole sulfoxide plasma concentrations were unchanged 4 hours after dosing. Following a single dose of albendazole (400 mg), the pharmacokinetics of theophylline (aminophylline 5.8 mg/kg infused over 20 minutes) were unchanged. Albendazole induces cytochrome P450 1A in human hepatoma cells; therefore, it is recommended that plasma concentrations of theophylline be monitored during and after treatment.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
Bone Marrow Suppression: Fatalities have been reported due to bone marrow suppression; monitor blood counts in all patients at the beginning of each 28-day cycle of therapy, and every 2 weeks while on therapy. Discontinue ALBENZA if clinically significant changes in blood counts occur. ( 5.1 , 5.4 ) Teratogenic Effects: Obtain pregnancy test in women of reproductive potential prior to therapy and avoid usage in pregnant women except in clinical circumstances where no alternative management is appropriate. Discontinue therapy if pregnancy occurs and apprise patient of potential hazard to the fetus. ( 5.2 ) Risk of Neurologic Symptoms: Neurocysticercosis patients may experience cerebral hypertensive episodes, seizures or focal neurologic deficits after initiation of therapy; begin appropriate steroid and anticonvulsant therapy. ( 5.3 ) Risk of Retinal Damage in Retinal Cysticercosis: Cases of retinal involvement have been reported; examine the patient for the presence of retinal lesions before initiating therapy for neurocysticercosis. ( 5.4 ) Hepatic Effects. Elevations of liver enzymes may occur. Monitor liver enzymes before the start of each treatment cycle and at least every 2 weeks while on ALBENZA therapy and discontinue if clinically significant elevations occur. ( 5.5 ) Fatalities associated with the use of ALBENZA have been reported due to granulocytopenia or pancytopenia ALBENZA may cause bone marrow suppression, aplastic anemia, and agranulocytosis. Monitor blood counts at the beginning of each 28-day cycle of therapy, and every 2 weeks while on therapy with ALBENZA in all patients. Patients with liver disease and patients with hepatic echinococcosis are at increased risk for bone marrow suppression and warrant more frequent monitoring of blood counts. Discontinue ALBENZA if clinically significant decreases in blood cell counts occur. ALBENZA may cause fetal harm and should not be used in pregnant women except in clinical circumstances where no alternative management is appropriate. Obtain pregnancy test prior to prescribing ALBENZA to women of reproductive potential. Advise women of reproductive potential to use effective birth control for the duration of ALBENZA therapy and for one month after end of therapy. Immediately discontinue ALBENZA if a patient becomes pregnant and apprise the patient of the potential hazard to the fetus [ see Use in Specific Populations ( 8.1 ) ]. Patients being treated for neurocysticercosis should receive steroid and anticonvulsant therapy to prevent neurological symptoms (e.g. seizures, increased intracranial pressure and focal signs) as a result of an inflammatory reaction caused by death of the parasite within the brain. Cysticercosis may involve the retina. Before initiating therapy for neurocysticercosis, examine the patient for the presence of retinal lesions. If such lesions are visualized, weigh the need for anticysticeral therapy against the possibility of retinal damage resulting from inflammatory damage caused by ALBENZA-induced death of the parasite. In clinical trials, treatment with ALBENZA has been associated with mild to moderate elevations of hepatic enzymes in approximately 16% of patients. These elevations have generally returned to normal upon discontinuation of therapy. There have also been case reports of acute liver failure of uncertain causality and hepatitis [ see Adverse Reactions ( 6 ) ]. Monitor liver enzymes (transaminases) before the start of each treatment cycle and at least every 2 weeks during treatment. If hepatic enzymes exceed twice the upper limit of normal, consideration should be given to discontinuing ALBENZA therapy based on individual patient circumstances. Restarting ALBENZA treatment in patients whose hepatic enzymes have normalized off treatment is an individual decision that should take into account the risk/benefit of further ALBENZA usage. Perform laboratory tests frequently if ALBENZA treatment is restarted. Patients with elevated liver enzyme test results are at increased risk for hepatotoxicity and bone marrow suppression [ see Warnings and Precautions ( 5.1 ) ]. Discontinue therapy if liver enzymes are significantly increased or if clinically significant decreases in blood cell counts occur. Undiagnosed neurocysticercosis may be uncovered in patients treated with ALBENZA for other conditions. Patients with epidemiologic factors who are at risk for neurocysticercosis should be evaluated prior to initiation of therapy.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
ALBENZA (albendazole) is a synthetic, antihelminthic drug of the class benzimidazole [ see Clinical Pharmacology ( 12.4 ) ]. Absorption Albendazole is poorly absorbed from the gastrointestinal tract due to its low aqueous solubility. Albendazole concentrations are negligible or undetectable in plasma as it is rapidly converted to the sulfoxide metabolite prior to reaching the systemic circulation. The systemic anthelmintic activity has been attributed to the primary metabolite, albendazole sulfoxide. Oral bioavailability appears to be enhanced when albendazole is coadministered with a fatty meal (estimated fat content 40 grams) as evidenced by higher (up to 5-fold on average) plasma concentrations of albendazole sulfoxide as compared to the fasted state. Maximal plasma concentrations of albendazole sulfoxide were achieved 2 hours to 5 hours after dosing and were on average 1310 ng/mL (range 460 ng/mL to 1580 ng/mL) following oral doses of albendazole (400 mg) in 6 hydatid disease patients, when administered with a fatty meal. Plasma concentrations of albendazole sulfoxide increased in a dose-proportional manner over the therapeutic dose range following ingestion of a high-fat meal (fat content 43.1 grams). The mean apparent terminal elimination half-life of albendazole sulfoxide ranged from 8 hours to 12 hours in 25 healthy subjects, as well as in 14 hydatid and 8 neurocysticercosis patients. Following 4 weeks of treatment with albendazole (200 mg three times daily), 12 patients’ plasma concentrations of albendazole sulfoxide were approximately 20% lower than those observed during the first half of the treatment period, suggesting that albendazole may induce its own metabolism. Distribution Albendazole sulfoxide is 70% bound to plasma protein and is widely distributed throughout the body; it has been detected in urine, bile, liver, cyst wall, cyst fluid, and cerebrospinal fluid (CSF). Concentrations in plasma were 3-fold to 10-fold and 2-fold to 4-fold higher than those simultaneously determined in cyst fluid and CSF, respectively. Metabolism and Excretion Albendazole is rapidly converted in the liver to the primary metabolite, albendazole sulfoxide, which is further metabolized to albendazole sulfone and other primary oxidative metabolites that have been identified in human urine. Following oral administration, albendazole has not been detected in human urine. Urinary excretion of albendazole sulfoxide is a minor elimination pathway with less than 1% of the dose recovered in the urine. Biliary elimination presumably accounts for a portion of the elimination as evidenced by biliary concentrations of albendazole sulfoxide similar to those achieved in plasma. Specific Populations Pediatrics Following single-dose administration of 200 mg to 300 mg (approximately 10 mg/kg) ALBENZA to 3 fasted and 2 fed pediatric patients with hydatid cyst disease (age range 6 to 13 years), albendazole sulfoxide pharmacokinetics were similar to those observed in fed adults. Geriatrics Although no studies have investigated the effect of age on albendazole sulfoxide pharmacokinetics, data in 26 hydatid cyst patients (up to 79 years) suggest pharmacokinetics similar to those in young healthy subjects. Mechanism of Action ALBENZA binds to the colchicine-sensitive site of β-tubulin inhibiting their polymerization into microtubules. The decrease in microtubules in the intestinal cells of the parasites decreases their absorptive function, especially the uptake of glucose by the adult and larval forms of the parasites, and also depletes glycogen storage. Insufficient glucose results in insufficient energy for the production of adenosine trisphosphate (ATP) and the parasite eventually dies. Mechanism of Resistance Parasitic resistance to albendazole is caused by changes in amino acids that result in changes in the β-tubulin protein. This causes reduced binding of the drug to β-tubulin. In the specified treatment indications albendazole appears to be active against the larval forms of the following organisms: Echinococcus granulosus Taenia solium</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="5207" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>ALBENZA is contraindicated in patients with known hypersensitivity to the benzimidazole class of compounds or any components of ALBENZA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5208" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Patients with known hypersensitivity to the benzimidazole class of compounds or any components of ALBENZA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5209" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Patients weighing 60 kg or greater, 400 mg twice daily; less than 60 kg, 15 mg/kg/day in divided doses twice daily (maximum total daily dose 800 mg).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5210" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>ALBENZA tablets should be taken with food.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5211" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Hydatid disease: 28-day cycle followed by 14-day albendazole-free interval for a total of 3 cycles.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5212" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>See additional important information in the Full Prescribing Information.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5213" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dosing of ALBENZA will vary depending upon the indication.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5214" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>ALBENZA tablets may be crushed or chewed and swallowed with a drink of water.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5215" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Table 1: ALBENZA Dosage Indication Patient Weight Dose Duration Hydatid Disease 60 kg or greater 400 mg twice daily, with meals 28-day cycle followed by a 14-day albendazole-free interval, for a total of 3 cycles Less than 60 kg 15 mg/kg/day given in divided doses twice daily with meals (maximum total daily dose 800 mg) Neurocysticercosis 60 kg or greater 400 mg twice daily, with meals 8 to 30 days Less than 60 kg 15 mg/kg/day given in divided doses twice daily with meals (maximum total daily dose 800 mg) Patients being treated for neurocysticercosis should receive appropriate steroid and anticonvulsant therapy as required.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5216" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Oral or intravenous corticosteroids should be considered to prevent cerebral hypertensive episodes during the first week of treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5217" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor blood counts at the beginning of each 28-day cycle of therapy, and every 2 weeks while on therapy with ALBENZA in all patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5218" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor liver enzymes (transaminases) at the beginning of each 28-day cycle of therapy, and at least every 2 weeks during treatment with ALBENZA in all patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5219" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Obtain a pregnancy test in women of reproductive potential prior to therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5220" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Dexamethasone: Steady-state trough concentrations of albendazole sulfoxide were about 56% higher when dexamethasone was coadministered with each dose of albendazole.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M1" type="Trigger" span="28 21;90 6" str="trough concentrations | higher"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="0 13" str="dexamethasone" code="7S5I7G3JQL"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M1" precipitant="M2" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5221" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Praziquantel: In the fed state increased mean maximum plasma concentration and area under the curve of albendazole sulfoxide by about 50% in healthy subjects.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M3" type="Trigger" span="31 9;79 20" str="increased | area under the curve"/>
<Mention id="M6" type="Precipitant" span="0 12" str="Praziquantel" code="6490C9U457"/>
<Mention id="M5" type="Trigger" span="31 43" str="increased mean maximum plasma concentration"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M3" precipitant="M6" effect="C54605"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M5" precipitant="M6" effect="C54602"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5222" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Cimetidine: Increased albendazole sulfoxide concentrations in bile and cystic fluid by about 2-fold in hydatid cyst patients.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M7" type="Trigger" span="12 9;44 13" str="Increased | concentration"/>
<Mention id="M8" type="Precipitant" span="0 10" str="Cimetidine" code="80061L1WGD"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M7" precipitant="M8" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5223" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Theophylline: Albendazole induces cytochrome P450 1A in human hepatoma cells; therefore, it is recommended that plasma concentrations of theophylline be monitored during and after treatment.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M9" type="Trigger" span="112 21;153 9" str="plasma concentrations | monitored"/>
<Mention id="M10" type="Precipitant" span="0 12" str="theophylline" code="N0000007076 | C137DTR5RG"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M9" precipitant="M10"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5224" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Steady-state trough concentrations of albendazole sulfoxide were about 56% higher when 8 mg dexamethasone was co-administered with each dose of albendazole (15 mg/kg/day) in 8 neurocysticercosis patients.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M11" type="Trigger" span="13 21;75 6" str="trough concentrations | higher"/>
<Mention id="M12" type="Precipitant" span="92 13" str="dexamethasone" code="7S5I7G3JQL"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M11" precipitant="M12" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5225" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>In the fed state, praziquantel (40 mg/kg) increased mean maximum plasma concentration and area under the curve of albendazole sulfoxide by about 50% in healthy subjects (n = 10) compared with a separate group of subjects (n = 6) given albendazole alone.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M13" type="Trigger" span="42 9;90 20" str="increased | area under the curve"/>
<Mention id="M16" type="Precipitant" span="18 12" str="praziquantel" code="6490C9U457"/>
<Mention id="M15" type="Trigger" span="42 43" str="increased mean maximum plasma concentration"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M13" precipitant="M16" effect="C54605"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M15" precipitant="M16" effect="C54602"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5226" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Mean Tmax and mean plasma elimination half-life of albendazole sulfoxide were unchanged.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5227" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The pharmacokinetics of praziquantel were unchanged following co-administration with albendazole (400 mg).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5228" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Albendazole sulfoxide concentrations in bile and cystic fluid were increased (about 2-fold) in hydatid cyst patients treated with cimetidine (10 mg/kg/day) (n = 7) compared with albendazole (20 mg/kg/day) alone (n = 12).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M17" type="Trigger" span="22 14;67 9" str="concentrations | increased"/>
<Mention id="M18" type="Precipitant" span="130 10" str="cimetidine" code="80061L1WGD"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M17" precipitant="M18" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5229" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Albendazole sulfoxide plasma concentrations were unchanged 4 hours after dosing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5230" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Following a single dose of albendazole (400 mg), the pharmacokinetics of theophylline (aminophylline 5.8 mg/kg infused over 20 minutes) were unchanged.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5231" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Albendazole induces cytochrome P450 1A in human hepatoma cells; therefore, it is recommended that plasma concentrations of theophylline be monitored during and after treatment.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M19" type="Trigger" span="98 21;139 9" str="plasma concentrations | monitored"/>
<Mention id="M20" type="Precipitant" span="123 12" str="theophylline" code="N0000007076 | C137DTR5RG"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M19" precipitant="M20"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5232" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Bone Marrow Suppression: Fatalities have been reported due to bone marrow suppression; monitor blood counts in all patients at the beginning of each 28-day cycle of therapy, and every 2 weeks while on therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5233" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Discontinue ALBENZA if clinically significant changes in blood counts occur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5234" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Teratogenic Effects: Obtain pregnancy test in women of reproductive potential prior to therapy and avoid usage in pregnant women except in clinical circumstances where no alternative management is appropriate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5235" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Discontinue therapy if pregnancy occurs and apprise patient of potential hazard to the fetus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5236" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Risk of Neurologic Symptoms: Neurocysticercosis patients may experience cerebral hypertensive episodes, seizures or focal neurologic deficits after initiation of therapy; begin appropriate steroid and anticonvulsant therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5237" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Risk of Retinal Damage in Retinal Cysticercosis: Cases of retinal involvement have been reported; examine the patient for the presence of retinal lesions before initiating therapy for neurocysticercosis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5238" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor liver enzymes before the start of each treatment cycle and at least every 2 weeks while on ALBENZA therapy and discontinue if clinically significant elevations occur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5239" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Fatalities associated with the use of ALBENZA have been reported due to granulocytopenia or pancytopenia ALBENZA may cause bone marrow suppression, aplastic anemia, and agranulocytosis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5240" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients with liver disease and patients with hepatic echinococcosis are at increased risk for bone marrow suppression and warrant more frequent monitoring of blood counts.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5241" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Discontinue ALBENZA if clinically significant decreases in blood cell counts occur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5242" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>ALBENZA may cause fetal harm and should not be used in pregnant women except in clinical circumstances where no alternative management is appropriate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5243" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Obtain pregnancy test prior to prescribing ALBENZA to women of reproductive potential.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5244" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Advise women of reproductive potential to use effective birth control for the duration of ALBENZA therapy and for one month after end of therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5245" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Immediately discontinue ALBENZA if a patient becomes pregnant and apprise the patient of the potential hazard to the fetus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5246" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients being treated for neurocysticercosis should receive steroid and anticonvulsant therapy to prevent neurological symptoms (e.g. seizures, increased intracranial pressure and focal signs) as a result of an inflammatory reaction caused by death of the parasite within the brain.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5247" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Before initiating therapy for neurocysticercosis, examine the patient for the presence of retinal lesions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5248" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If such lesions are visualized, weigh the need for anticysticeral therapy against the possibility of retinal damage resulting from inflammatory damage caused by ALBENZA-induced death of the parasite.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M21" type="Trigger" span="42 8" str="need for "/>
<Mention id="M22" type="Trigger" span="86 14" str=" possibility of"/>
<Mention id="M23" type="Precipitant" span="51 22" str="anticysticeral therapy" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M24" type="SpecificInteraction" span="101 14" str="retinal damage" code="41445001: Retinal damage (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M21;M22" precipitant="M23" effect="M24" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5249" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In clinical trials, treatment with ALBENZA has been associated with mild to moderate elevations of hepatic enzymes in approximately 16% of patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5250" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>These elevations have generally returned to normal upon discontinuation of therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5251" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There have also been case reports of acute liver failure of uncertain causality and hepatitis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5252" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Monitor liver enzymes (transaminases) before the start of each treatment cycle and at least every 2 weeks during treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5253" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If hepatic enzymes exceed twice the upper limit of normal, consideration should be given to discontinuing ALBENZA therapy based on individual patient circumstances.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5254" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Restarting ALBENZA treatment in patients whose hepatic enzymes have normalized off treatment is an individual decision that should take into account the risk/benefit of further ALBENZA usage.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5255" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Perform laboratory tests frequently if ALBENZA treatment is restarted.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5256" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients with elevated liver enzyme test results are at increased risk for hepatotoxicity and bone marrow suppression.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5257" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Discontinue therapy if liver enzymes are significantly increased or if clinically significant decreases in blood cell counts occur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5258" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Undiagnosed neurocysticercosis may be uncovered in patients treated with ALBENZA for other conditions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5259" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients with epidemiologic factors who are at risk for neurocysticercosis should be evaluated prior to initiation of therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5260" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>ALBENZA (albendazole) is a synthetic, antihelminthic drug of the class benzimidazole.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5261" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Absorption Albendazole is poorly absorbed from the gastrointestinal tract due to its low aqueous solubility.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5262" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Albendazole concentrations are negligible or undetectable in plasma as it is rapidly converted to the sulfoxide metabolite prior to reaching the systemic circulation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5263" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The systemic anthelmintic activity has been attributed to the primary metabolite, albendazole sulfoxide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5264" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Oral bioavailability appears to be enhanced when albendazole is coadministered with a fatty meal (estimated fat content 40 grams) as evidenced by higher (up to 5-fold on average) plasma concentrations of albendazole sulfoxide as compared to the fasted state.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M25" type="Trigger" span="5 15;35 8" str="bioavailability | enhanced "/>
<Mention id="M26" type="Trigger" span="146 6;179 21" str=" higher | plasma concentrations"/>
<Mention id="M27" type="Precipitant" span="86 10" str="fatty meal" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M25;M26" precipitant="M27" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5265" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Maximal plasma concentrations of albendazole sulfoxide were achieved 2 hours to 5 hours after dosing and were on average 1310 ng/mL (range 460 ng/mL to 1580 ng/mL) following oral doses of albendazole (400 mg) in 6 hydatid disease patients, when administered with a fatty meal.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5266" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Plasma concentrations of albendazole sulfoxide increased in a dose-proportional manner over the therapeutic dose range following ingestion of a high-fat meal (fat content 43.1 grams).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5267" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mean apparent terminal elimination half-life of albendazole sulfoxide ranged from 8 hours to 12 hours in 25 healthy subjects, as well as in 14 hydatid and 8 neurocysticercosis patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5268" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following 4 weeks of treatment with albendazole (200 mg three times daily), 12 patients’ plasma concentrations of albendazole sulfoxide were approximately 20% lower than those observed during the first half of the treatment period, suggesting that albendazole may induce its own metabolism.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5269" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Distribution Albendazole sulfoxide is 70% bound to plasma protein and is widely distributed throughout the body; it has been detected in urine, bile, liver, cyst wall, cyst fluid, and cerebrospinal fluid (CSF).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5270" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Concentrations in plasma were 3-fold to 10-fold and 2-fold to 4-fold higher than those simultaneously determined in cyst fluid and CSF, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5271" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Metabolism and Excretion Albendazole is rapidly converted in the liver to the primary metabolite, albendazole sulfoxide, which is further metabolized to albendazole sulfone and other primary oxidative metabolites that have been identified in human urine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5272" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following oral administration, albendazole has not been detected in human urine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5273" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Urinary excretion of albendazole sulfoxide is a minor elimination pathway with less than 1% of the dose recovered in the urine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5274" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Biliary elimination presumably accounts for a portion of the elimination as evidenced by biliary concentrations of albendazole sulfoxide similar to those achieved in plasma.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5275" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Specific Populations Pediatrics Following single-dose administration of 200 mg to 300 mg (approximately 10 mg/kg) ALBENZA to 3 fasted and 2 fed pediatric patients with hydatid cyst disease (age range 6 to 13 years), albendazole sulfoxide pharmacokinetics were similar to those observed in fed adults.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5276" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Geriatrics Although no studies have investigated the effect of age on albendazole sulfoxide pharmacokinetics, data in 26 hydatid cyst patients (up to 79 years) suggest pharmacokinetics similar to those in young healthy subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5277" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Mechanism of Action ALBENZA binds to the colchicine-sensitive site of β-tubulin inhibiting their polymerization into microtubules.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5278" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The decrease in microtubules in the intestinal cells of the parasites decreases their absorptive function, especially the uptake of glucose by the adult and larval forms of the parasites, and also depletes glycogen storage.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5279" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Insufficient glucose results in insufficient energy for the production of adenosine trisphosphate (ATP) and the parasite eventually dies.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5280" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Mechanism of Resistance Parasitic resistance to albendazole is caused by changes in amino acids that result in changes in the β-tubulin protein.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5281" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This causes reduced binding of the drug to β-tubulin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="5282" LabelDrug="ALBENZA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In the specified treatment indications albendazole appears to be active against the larval forms of the following organisms: Echinococcus granulosus Taenia solium</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="dexamethasone" precipitantCode="7S5I7G3JQL" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="praziquantel" precipitantCode="6490C9U457" effect="C54602"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="praziquantel" precipitantCode="6490C9U457" effect="C54605"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cimetidine" precipitantCode="80061L1WGD" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="theophylline" precipitantCode="N0000007076 | C137DTR5RG"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="anticysticeral therapy" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="41445001: Retinal damage (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="fatty meal" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54355"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>