<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="CONTRAVE" setid="ed2da3a6-0614-4bea-8e82-962cbaae6428">
<Text><Section name="Boxed Warning section" id="34066-1">
SUICIDALITY AND ANTIDEPRESSANT DRUGS CONTRAVE ® is not approved for use in the treatment of major depressive disorder or other psychiatric disorders. CONTRAVE contains bupropion, the same active ingredient as some other antidepressant medications (including, but not limited to, WELLBUTRIN, WELLBUTRIN SR, WELLBUTRIN XL and APLENZIN). Antidepressants increased the risk of suicidal thoughts and behavior in children, adolescents, and young adults in short-term trials. These trials did not show an increase in the risk of suicidal thoughts and behavior with antidepressant use in subjects over age 24; there was a reduction in risk with antidepressant use in subjects aged 65 and older. In patients of all ages who are started on CONTRAVE, monitor closely for worsening, and for the emergence of suicidal thoughts and behaviors. Advise families and caregivers of the need for close observation and communication with the prescriber. CONTRAVE is not approved for use in pediatric patients [see Warnings and Precautions ( 5.1 ), Use in Specific Populations ( 8.4 )] . NEUROPSYCHIATRIC REACTIONS IN PATIENTS TAKING BUPROPION FOR SMOKING CESSATION Serious neuropsychiatric reactions have occurred in patients taking bupropion for smoking cessation [see Warnings and Precautions ( 5.2 )]. The majority of these reactions occurred during bupropion treatment, but some occurred in the context of discontinuing treatment. In many cases, a causal relationship to bupropion treatment is not certain, because depressed mood may be a symptom of nicotine withdrawal. However, some of the cases occurred in patients taking bupropion who continued to smoke. Although CONTRAVE is not approved for smoking cessation, observe all patients for neuropsychiatric reactions. Instruct the patient to contact a healthcare provider if such reactions occur [ see Warnings and Precautions ( 5.2 )] . WARNING: SUICIDAL THOUGHTS AND BEHAVIORS; AND NEUROPSYCHIATRIC REACTIONS See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning • Increased risk of suicidal thinking and behavior in children, adolescents, and young adults taking antidepressants for major depressive disorder and other psychiatric disorders. ( 5.1 ) • Monitor for worsening and emergence of suicidal thoughts and behaviors. ( 5.1 ) • Serious neuropsychiatric events have been reported in patients taking bupropion for smoking cessation. ( 5.2 ) • CONTRAVE has not been studied in pediatric patients. ( 5.1 )</Section>
<Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
CONTRAVE is contraindicated in • Uncontrolled hypertension [see Warnings and Precautions ( 5.5 )] • Seizure disorder or a history of seizures [see Warnings and Precautions ( 5.3 )] • Use of other bupropion-containing products (including, but not limited to, WELLBUTRIN, WELLBUTRIN SR, WELLBUTRIN XL, and APLENZIN) • Bulimia or anorexia nervosa, which increase the risk for seizure [see Warnings and Precautions ( 5.3 )] • Chronic opioid or opiate agonist (e.g., methadone) or partial agonists (e.g., buprenorphine) use, or acute opiate withdrawal [see Warnings and Precautions ( 5.4 ) and Drug Interactions ( 7.2 )] • Patients undergoing an abrupt discontinuation of alcohol, benzodiazepines, barbiturates, and antiepileptic drugs [see Warnings and Precautions ( 5.3 ) and Drug Interactions ( 7.7 )] • Concomitant administration of monoamine oxidase inhibitors (MAOI). At least 14 days should elapse between discontinuation of MAOI and initiation of treatment with CONTRAVE. There is an increased risk of hypertensive reactions when CONTRAVE is used concomitantly with MAOIs. Starting CONTRAVE in a patient treated with reversible MAOIs such as linezolid or intravenous methylene blue is also contraindicated [see Dosage and Administration ( 2.4 ), Drug Interactions ( 7.1 )] • Known allergy to bupropion, naltrexone or any other component of CONTRAVE. Anaphylactoid/anaphylactic reactions and Stevens-Johnson syndrome have been reported with bupropion [see Warnings and Precautions ( 5.6 )] • Pregnancy [see Use in Specific Populations ( 8.1 )] • Uncontrolled hypertension ( 4 ) • Seizure disorders, anorexia nervosa or bulimia, or undergoing abrupt discontinuation of alcohol, benzodiazepines, barbiturates, and antiepileptic drugs ( 4 ) • Use of other bupropion-containing products ( 4 ) • Chronic opioid use ( 4 ) • During or within 14 days of taking monoamine oxidase inhibitors (MAOI) ( 4 ) • Known allergy to any of the ingredients in CONTRAVE ( 4 ) • Pregnancy ( 4 )</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
CONTRAVE dose escalation schedule ( 2.1 ): Morning Dose Evening Dose Week 1 1 tablet None Week 2 1 tablet 1 tablet Week 3 2 tablets 1 tablet Week 4 – Onward 2 tablets 2 tablets CONTRAVE dosing should be escalated according to the following schedule: Morning Dose Evening Dose Week 1 1 tablet None Week 2 1 tablet 1 tablet Week 3 2 tablets 1 tablet Week 4 – Onward 2 tablets 2 tablets A total daily dosage of two CONTRAVE 8 mg/90 mg tablets twice daily (32 mg/360 mg) is reached at the start of Week 4. CONTRAVE should be taken by mouth in the morning and in the evening. The tablets should not be cut, chewed, or crushed. Total daily doses greater than 32 mg/360 mg per day (two tablets twice daily) are not recommended. In clinical trials, CONTRAVE was administered with meals. However, CONTRAVE should not be taken with a high-fat meal because of a resulting significant increase in bupropion and naltrexone systemic exposure [see Warnings and Precautions ( 5.3 ) and Clinical Pharmacology ( 12.3 )] . Patients may develop elevated blood pressure or heart rate during CONTRAVE treatment; the risk may be greater during the initial three months of therapy [see Warnings and Precautions ( 5. 6 )] . Because patients with hypertension may be at increased risk for developing blood pressure elevations, such patients should be monitored for this potential effect when initiating treatment with CONTRAVE. Response to therapy should be evaluated after 12 weeks at the maintenance dosage. If a patient has not lost at least 5% of baseline body weight, discontinue CONTRAVE, as it is unlikely that the patient will achieve and sustain clinically meaningful weight loss with continued treatment. BMI is calculated by dividing weight (in kg) by height (in meters) squared. A BMI chart for determining BMI based on height and weight is provided in Table 1 . Table 1. BMI Conversion Chart Weight (lb) 125 130 135 140 145 150 155 160 165 170 175 180 185 190 195 200 205 210 215 220 225 (kg) 56.8 59.1 61.4 63.6 65.9 68.2 70.5 72.7 75.0 77.3 79.5 81.8 84.1 86.4 88.6 90.9 93.2 95.5 97.7 100. 0 102. 3 Height (in) (cm) 58 147.3 26 27 28 29 30 31 32 34 35 36 37 38 39 40 41 42 43 44 45 46 47 59 149.9 25 26 27 28 29 30 31 32 33 34 35 36 37 38 39 40 41 43 44 45 46 60 152.4 24 25 26 27 28 29 30 31 32 33 34 35 36 37 38 39 40 41 42 43 44 61 154.9 24 25 26 27 27 28 29 30 31 32 33 34 35 36 37 38 39 40 41 42 43 62 157.5 23 24 25 26 27 27 28 29 30 31 32 33 34 35 36 37 38 38 39 40 41 63 160.0 22 23 24 25 26 27 28 28 29 30 31 32 33 34 35 36 36 37 38 39 40 64 162.6 22 22 23 24 25 26 27 28 28 29 30 31 32 33 34 34 35 36 37 38 39 65 165.1 21 22 23 23 24 25 26 27 28 28 29 30 31 32 33 33 34 35 36 37 38 66 167.6 20 21 22 23 23 24 25 26 27 27 28 29 30 31 32 32 33 34 35 36 36 67 170.2 20 20 21 22 23 24 24 25 26 27 27 28 29 30 31 31 32 33 34 35 35 68 172.7 19 20 21 21 22 23 24 24 25 26 27 27 28 29 30 30 31 32 33 34 34 69 175.3 18 19 20 21 21 22 23 24 24 25 26 27 27 28 29 30 30 31 32 33 33 70 177.8 18 19 19 20 21 22 22 23 24 24 25 26 27 27 28 29 29 30 31 32 32 71 180.3 17 18 19 20 20 21 22 22 23 24 24 25 26 27 27 28 29 29 30 31 31 72 182.9 17 18 18 19 20 20 21 22 22 23 24 24 25 26 27 27 28 29 29 30 31 73 185.4 17 17 18 19 19 20 20 21 22 22 23 24 24 25 26 26 27 28 28 29 30 74 188.0 16 17 17 18 19 19 20 21 21 22 23 23 24 24 25 26 26 27 28 28 29 75 190.5 16 16 17 18 18 19 19 20 21 21 22 23 23 24 24 25 26 26 27 28 28 76 193.0 15 16 16 17 18 18 19 20 20 21 21 22 23 23 24 24 25 26 26 27 27 In patients with moderate or severe renal impairment, the maximum recommended daily dose for CONTRAVE is two tablets (one tablet each morning and evening). CONTRAVE is not recommended for use in patients with end-stage renal disease. There is a lack of adequate information to guide dosing in patients with mild renal impairment [see Use in Specific Population ( 8.6 ) and Clinical Pharmacology ( 12.3 )] . In patients with hepatic impairment, the maximum recommended daily dose of CONTRAVE is one tablet in the morning [see Use in Specific Population ( 8.7 ) and Clinical Pharmacology ( 12.3 )]. At least 14 days should elapse between discontinuation of an MAOI intended to treat depression and initiation of therapy with CONTRAVE. Conversely, at least 14 days should be allowed after stopping CONTRAVE before starting an MAOI antidepressant [see Contraindications ( 4 ) and Drug Interactions ( 7.1 )] . During concomitant use with CYP2B6 inhibitors (e.g., ticlopidine or clopidogrel), the maximum recommended daily dose of CONTRAVE is two tablets (one tablet each morning and evening) [see Drug Interactions ( 7.4 ) and Clinical Pharmacology ( 12.3 )] .</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
• MAOIs: Increased risk of hypertensive reactions can occur when used concomitantly. ( 7.1 ) • Drugs Metabolized by CYP2D6: Bupropion inhibits CYP2D6 and can increase concentrations of: antidepressants, (e.g., selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors and many tricyclics), antipsychotics (e.g., haloperidol, risperidone and thioridazine), beta-blockers (e.g., metoprolol) and Type 1C antiarrhythmics (e.g., propafenone and flecainide): Consider dose reduction when using with CONTRAVE. ( 7.3 ) • Concomitant Treatment with CYP2B6 Inhibitors (e.g., ticlopidine or clopidogrel) can increase bupropion exposure. Do not exceed one tablet twice daily when taken with CYP2B6 inhibitors. ( 2.5 , 7.4 ) • CYP2B6 Inducers (e.g., ritonavir, lopinavir, efavirenz, carbamazepine, phenobarbital, and phenytoin) may reduce efficacy by reducing bupropion exposure, avoid concomitant use. ( 7.4 ) • Drugs that Lower Seizure Threshold: Dose CONTRAVE with caution. ( 5.3 , 7.5 ) • Dopaminergic Drugs (levodopa and amantadine): CNS toxicity can occur when used concomitantly with CONTRAVE. ( 7.6 ) • Drug-Laboratory Test Interactions: CONTRAVE can cause false-positive urine test results for amphetamines. ( 7.8 ) Concomitant use of MAOIs and bupropion is contraindicated. Bupropion inhibits the re-uptake of dopamine and norepinephrine and can increase the risk for hypertensive reactions when used concomitantly with drugs that also inhibit the re-uptake of dopamine or norepinephrine, including MAOIs. Studies in animals demonstrate that the acute toxicity of bupropion is enhanced by the MAOI phenelzine. At least 14 days should elapse between discontinuation of an MAOI and initiation of treatment with CONTRAVE. Conversely, at least 14 days should be allowed after stopping CONTRAVE before starting an MAOI [see Contraindications ( 4 )] . Patients taking CONTRAVE may not fully benefit from treatment with opioid-containing medicines, such as cough and cold remedies, antidiarrheal preparations, and opioid analgesics. In patients requiring intermittent opiate treatment, CONTRAVE therapy should be temporarily discontinued and opiate dose should not be increased above the standard dose. CONTRAVE may be used with caution after chronic opioid use has been stopped for 7 to 10 days in order to prevent precipitation of withdrawal [see Contraindications ( 4 ) and Warnings and Precautions ( 5.4 )] . During CONTRAVE clinical studies, the use of concomitant opioid or opioid-like medications, including analgesics or antitussives, were excluded.  Metabolized by CYP2D6 In a clinical study, CONTRAVE (32 mg naltrexone/360 mg bupropion) daily was coadministered with a 50 mg dose of metoprolol (a CYP2D6 substrate). CONTRAVE increased metoprolol AUC and C max by approximately 4- and 2-fold, respectively, relative to metoprolol alone. Similar clinical drug interactions resulting in increased pharmacokinetic exposure of CYP2D6 substrates have also been observed with bupropion as a single agent with desipramine or venlafaxine. Coadministration of CONTRAVE with drugs that are metabolized by CYP2D6 isozyme including certain antidepressants (SSRIs and many tricyclics), antipsychotics (e.g., haloperidol, risperidone and thioridazine), beta-blockers (e.g., metoprolol) and Type 1C antiarrhythmics (e.g., propafenone and flecainide), should be approached with caution and should be initiated at the lower end of the dose range of the concomitant medication. If CONTRAVE is added to the treatment regimen of a patient already receiving a drug metabolized by CYP2D6, the need to decrease the dose of the original medication should be considered, particularly for those concomitant medications with a narrow therapeutic index [see Clinical Pharmacology ( 12.3 )] . Bupropion is primarily metabolized to hydroxybupropion by CYP2B6. Therefore, the potential exists for drug interactions between CONTRAVE and drugs that are inhibitors or inducers of CYP2B6. Inhibitors of CYP2B6: Ticlopidine and Clopidogrel: Concomitant treatment with these drugs can increase bupropion exposure but decrease hydroxybupropion exposure. During concomitant use with CYP2B6 inhibitors (e.g., ticlopidine or clopidogrel), the CONTRAVE daily dose should not exceed two tablets (one tablet each morning and evening) [see Dosage and Administration ( 2.5 ) and Clinical Pharmacology ( 12.3 )] . Inducers of CYP2B6: Ritonavir, Lopinavir, and Efavirenz: Concomitant treatment with these drugs can decrease bupropion and hydroxybupropion exposure and may reduce efficacy. Avoiding concomitant use with ritonavir, lopinavir, or efavirenz is recommended [see Clinical Pharmacology ( 12.3 )] . Use extreme caution when coadministering CONTRAVE with other drugs that lower seizure threshold (e.g., antipsychotics, antidepressants, theophylline, or systemic corticosteroids). Use low initial doses and increase the dose gradually. Concomitant use of other bupropion-containing products is contraindicated [see Contraindications ( 4 ) and Warnings and Precautions ( 5.3 ) ]. Bupropion, levodopa, and amantadine have dopamine agonist effects. CNS toxicity has been reported when bupropion was coadministered with levodopa or amantadine. Adverse reactions have included restlessness, agitation, tremor, ataxia, gait disturbance, vertigo, and dizziness. It is presumed that the toxicity results from cumulative dopamine agonist effects. Use caution and monitor for such adverse reactions when administering CONTRAVE concomitantly with these drugs. In postmarketing experience, there have been rare reports of adverse neuropsychiatric events or reduced alcohol tolerance in patients who were drinking alcohol during treatment with bupropion. The consumption of alcohol during treatment with CONTRAVE should be minimized or avoided. False-positive urine immunoassay screening tests for amphetamines have been reported in patients taking bupropion. This is due to lack of specificity of some screening tests. False-positive test results may result even following discontinuation of bupropion therapy. Confirmatory tests, such as gas chromatography/mass spectrometry, will distinguish bupropion from amphetamines. In vitro , CONTRAVE constituents inhibited the renal organic cation transporter OCT2 to a clinically relevant level. The systemic concentrations of substrate drugs transported by OCT2 (such as amantadine, amiloride, cimetidine, dopamine, famotidine, memantine, metformin, pindolol, procainamide, ranitidine, varenicline, oxaliplatin) are likely to increase as a result of reduced renal clearance when coadministered with CONTRAVE. Coadministration of CONTRAVE with such drugs should be approached with caution and patients should be monitored for adverse effects.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
• Suicidal Behavior and Ideation: Monitor for depression or suicidal thoughts. Discontinue CONTRAVE if symptoms develop. ( 5.1 ) • Risk of seizure may be minimized by adhering to the recommended dosing schedule and avoiding coadministration with high-fat meal. ( 5.3 ) • Increase in Blood Pressure and Heart Rate: Monitor blood pressure and heart rate in all patients, especially those with cardiac or cerebrovascular disease. ( 5.5 ) • Hepatotoxicity: Cases of hepatitis and clinically significant liver dysfunction observed with naltrexone exposure. ( 5.7 ) • Angle-closure glaucoma: Angle-closure glaucoma has occurred in patients with untreated anatomically narrow angles treated with antidepressants. ( 5.9 ) • Use of Antidiabetic Medications: Weight loss may cause hypoglycemia. Monitor blood glucose. ( 5.10 ) CONTRAVE contains bupropion, a dopamine and norepinephrine re-uptake inhibitor that is similar to some drugs used for the treatment of depression; therefore, the following precautions pertaining to these products should be considered when treating patients with CONTRAVE. Patients with major depressive disorder, both adult and pediatric, may experience worsening of their depression and/or the emergence of suicidal ideation and behavior (suicidality) or unusual changes in behavior, whether or not they are taking antidepressant medications, and this risk may persist until significant remission occurs. Suicide is a known risk of depression and certain other psychiatric disorders, and these disorders themselves are the strongest predictors of suicide. There has been a long-standing concern that antidepressants may have a role in inducing worsening of depression and the emergence of suicidality in certain patients during the early phases of treatment. In placebo-controlled clinical trials with CONTRAVE for the treatment of obesity in adult patients, no suicides or suicide attempts were reported in studies up to 56 weeks duration with CONTRAVE (equivalent to bupropion doses of 360 mg/day). In these same studies, suicidal ideation was reported by 3 (0.20%) of 1,515 patients treated with placebo compared with 1 (0.03%) of 3,239 treated with CONTRAVE. Pooled analyses of short-term placebo-controlled trials of antidepressant drugs (selective serotonin re-uptake inhibitors [SSRIs] and others) show that these drugs increase the risk of suicidal thinking and behavior (suicidality) in children, adolescents, and young adults (ages 18 to 24) with major depressive disorder (MDD) and other psychiatric disorders. Short-term clinical trials did not show an increase in the risk of suicidality with antidepressants compared with placebo in adults beyond age 24; there was a reduction with antidepressants compared with placebo in adults aged 65 and older. The pooled analyses of placebo-controlled trials of antidepressant drugs in children and adolescents with MDD, obsessive compulsive disorder (OCD), or other psychiatric disorders included a total of 24 short-term trials of nine antidepressant drugs in over 4,400 patients. The pooled analyses of placebo-controlled trials in adults with MDD or other psychiatric disorders included a total of 295 short-term trials (median duration of two months) of 11 antidepressant drugs in over 77,000 patients. There was considerable variation in risk of suicidality among drugs, but a tendency toward an increase in the younger patients for almost all drugs studied. There were differences in absolute risk of suicidality across the different indications, with the highest incidence in MDD. The risk differences (drug vs placebo), however, were relatively stable within age strata and across indications. These risk differences (drug-placebo difference in the number of cases of suicidality per 1,000 patients treated) are provided in Table 2 . Table 2. Risk Differences in the Number of Suicidality Cases by Age Group in the Pooled Placebo-Controlled Trials of Antidepressants in Pediatric and Adult Subjects Age Range Drug-Placebo Difference in Number of Cases of Suicidality per 1,000 Patients Treated Increases Compared to Placebo &amp;lt;18 14 additional cases 18 to 24 5 additional cases Decreases Compared to Placebo 25 to 64 1 fewer case ≥65 6 fewer cases No suicides occurred in any of the antidepressant pediatric trials. There were suicides in the adult antidepressant trials, but the number was not sufficient to reach any conclusion about drug effect on suicide. It is unknown whether the suicidality risk extends to longer-term use, i.e., beyond several months. However, there is substantial evidence from placebo-controlled trials in adults with depression that the use of antidepressants can delay the recurrence of depression. All patients being treated with antidepressants for any indication should be monitored appropriately and observed closely for clinical worsening, suicidality, and unusual changes in behavior, especially during the initial few months of a course of drug therapy, or at times of dose changes, either increases or decreases. This warning applies to CONTRAVE because one of its components, bupropion, is a member of an antidepressant class. The following symptoms, anxiety, agitation, panic attacks, insomnia, irritability, hostility, aggressiveness, impulsivity, akathisia (psychomotor restlessness), hypomania, and mania, have been reported in adult and pediatric patients being treated with antidepressants for major depressive disorder as well as for other indications, both psychiatric and nonpsychiatric. Although a causal link between the emergence of such symptoms and either the worsening of depression and/or the emergence of suicidal impulses has not been established, there is concern that such symptoms may represent precursors to emerging suicidality. Consideration should be given to changing the therapeutic regimen, including possibly discontinuing the medication, in patients whose depression is persistently worse, or who are experiencing emergent suicidality or symptoms that might be precursors to worsening depression or suicidality, especially if these symptoms are severe, abrupt in onset, or were not part of the patient’s presenting symptoms. Families and caregivers of patients being treated with antidepressants for major depressive disorder or other indications, both psychiatric and nonpsychiatric, should be alerted about the need to monitor patients for the emergence of anxiety, agitation, irritability, unusual changes in behavior, and the other symptoms described above, as well as the emergence of suicidality, and to report such symptoms immediately to healthcare providers. Such monitoring should include daily observation by families and caregivers. Prescriptions for CONTRAVE should be written for the smallest quantity of tablets consistent with good patient management, in order to reduce the risk of overdose. CONTRAVE is not approved for smoking cessation treatment, but serious neuropsychiatric symptoms have been reported in patients taking bupropion for smoking cessation. These have included changes in mood (including depression and mania), psychosis, hallucinations, paranoia, delusions, homicidal ideation, hostility, agitation, aggression, anxiety, and panic, as well as suicidal ideation, suicide attempt, and completed suicide [see Warnings and Precautions ( 5.1 )] . Observe patients for the occurrence of neuropsychiatric reactions. Instruct patients to contact a healthcare professional if such reactions occur. In many of these cases, a causal relationship to bupropion treatment is not certain, because depressed mood can be a symptom of nicotine withdrawal. However, some of the cases occurred in patients taking bupropion who continued to smoke. Depression, suicide, attempted suicide and suicidal ideation have been reported in the postmarketing experience with naltrexone used in the treatment of opioid dependence. No causal relationship has been demonstrated. Bupropion, a component of CONTRAVE, can cause seizures. The risk of seizure is dose-related. The incidence of seizure in patients receiving CONTRAVE in clinical trials was approximately 0.1% vs 0% on placebo. CONTRAVE should be discontinued and not restarted in patients who experience a seizure while being treated with CONTRAVE. The risk of seizures is also related to patient factors, clinical situations, and concomitant medications that lower the seizure threshold. Consider these risks before initiating treatment with CONTRAVE. CONTRAVE is contraindicated in patients with a seizure disorder, current or prior diagnosis of anorexia nervosa or bulimia, or undergoing abrupt discontinuation of alcohol, benzodiazepines, barbiturates, and antiepileptic drugs. Caution should be used when prescribing CONTRAVE to patients with predisposing factors that may increase the risk of seizure including: • history of head trauma or prior seizure, severe stroke, arteriovenous malformation, central nervous system tumor or infection, or metabolic disorders (e.g., hypoglycemia, hyponatremia, severe hepatic impairment, and hypoxia) • excessive use of alcohol or sedatives, addiction to cocaine or stimulants, or withdrawal from sedatives • patients with diabetes treated with insulin and/or oral diabetic medications (sulfonylureas and meglitinides) that may cause hypoglycemia • concomitant administration of medications that may lower the seizure threshold, including other bupropion products, antipsychotics, tricyclic antidepressants, theophylline, systemic steroids Recommendations for Reducing the Risk of Seizure: Clinical experience with bupropion suggests that the risk of seizure may be minimized by adhering to the recommended dosing recommendations [see Dosage and Administration ( 2 )] , in particular: • the total daily dose of CONTRAVE does not exceed 360 mg of the bupropion component (i.e., four tablets per day) • the daily dose is administered in divided doses (twice daily) • the dose is escalated gradually • no more than two tablets are taken at one time • coadministration of CONTRAVE with high-fat meals is avoided [see Dosage and Administration ( 2.1 ) and Clinical Pharmacology ( 12.3 )] • if a dose is missed, a patient should wait until the next scheduled dose to resume the regular dosing schedule Vulnerability to Opioid Overdose: CONTRAVE should not be administered to patients receiving chronic opioids, due to the naltrexone component, which is an opioid receptor antagonist [ see Contraindications ( 4 )] . If chronic opiate therapy is required, CONTRAVE treatment should be stopped. In patients requiring intermittent opiate treatment, CONTRAVE therapy should be temporarily discontinued and lower doses of opioids may be needed. Patients should be alerted that they may be more sensitive to opioids, even at lower doses, after CONTRAVE treatment is discontinued. An attempt by a patient to overcome any naltrexone opioid blockade by administering large amounts of exogenous opioids is especially dangerous and may lead to a fatal overdose or life-threatening opioid intoxication (e.g., respiratory arrest, circulatory collapse). Patients should be told of the serious consequences of trying to overcome the opioid blockade. Precipitated Opioid Withdrawal: The symptoms of spontaneous opioid withdrawal, which are associated with the discontinuation of opioid in a dependent individual, are uncomfortable, but they are not generally believed to be severe or necessitate hospitalization. However, when withdrawal is precipitated abruptly, the resulting withdrawal syndrome can be severe enough to require hospitalization. To prevent occurrence of either precipitated withdrawal in patients dependent on opioids or exacerbation of a pre-existing subclinical withdrawal symptoms, opioid-dependent patients, including those being treated for alcohol dependence, should be opioid-free (including tramadol) before starting CONTRAVE treatment. An opioid-free interval of a minimum of 7 to 10 days is recommended for patients previously dependent on short-acting opioids, and those patients transitioning from buprenorphine or methadone may need as long as two weeks. Patients should be made aware of the risks associated with precipitated withdrawal and encouraged to give an accurate account of last opioid use. CONTRAVE can cause an increase in systolic and/or diastolic blood pressure as well as an increase in resting heart rate. In clinical practice with other bupropion-containing products, hypertension, in some cases severe and requiring acute treatment, has been reported. The clinical significance of the increases in blood pressure and heart rate observed with CONTRAVE treatment is unclear, especially for patients with cardiac and cerebrovascular disease, since patients with a history of myocardial infarction or stroke in the previous 6 months, life-threatening arrhythmias, or congestive heart failure were excluded from CONTRAVE clinical trials. Blood pressure and pulse should be measured prior to starting therapy with CONTRAVE and should be monitored at regular intervals consistent with usual clinical practice, particularly among patients with controlled hypertension prior to treatment [see Dosage and Administration ( 2.1 )] . CONTRAVE should not be given to patients with uncontrolled hypertension [see Contraindications ( 4 )] . Among patients treated with CONTRAVE in placebo-controlled clinical trials, mean systolic and diastolic blood pressure was approximately 1 mmHg higher than baseline at Weeks 4 and 8, similar to baseline at Week 12, and approximately 1 mmHg below baseline between Weeks 24 and 56. In contrast, among patients treated with placebo, mean blood pressure was approximately 2 to 3 mmHg below baseline throughout the same time points, yielding statistically significant differences between the groups at every assessment during this period. The largest mean differences between the groups were observed during the first 12 weeks (treatment difference +1.8 to +2.4 mmHg systolic, all p&amp;lt;0.001; +1.7 to +2.1 mmHg diastolic, all p&amp;lt;0.001). For heart rate, at both Weeks 4 and 8, mean heart rate was statistically significantly higher (2.1 bpm) in the CONTRAVE group compared with the placebo group; at Week 52, the difference between groups was +1.7 bpm (p&amp;lt;0.001). In an ambulatory blood pressure monitoring substudy of 182 patients, the mean change from baseline in systolic blood pressure after 52 weeks of treatment was -0.2 mmHg for the CONTRAVE group and -2.8 mmHg for the placebo group (treatment difference, +2.6 mmHg, p=0.08); the mean change in diastolic blood pressure was +0.8 mmHg for the CONTRAVE group and -2.1 mmHg for the placebo group (treatment difference, +2.9 mmHg, p=0.004). A greater percentage of subjects had adverse reactions related to blood pressure or heart rate in the CONTRAVE group compared to the placebo group (6.3% vs 4.2%, respectively), primarily attributable to adverse reactions of Hypertension/Blood Pressure Increased (5.9% vs 4.0%, respectively). These events were observed in both patients with and without evidence of preexisting hypertension. In a trial that enrolled individuals with diabetes, 12.0% of patients in the CONTRAVE group and 6.5% in the placebo group had a blood pressure-related adverse reaction. Anaphylactoid/anaphylactic reactions characterized by symptoms such as pruritus, urticaria, angioedema, and dyspnea requiring medical treatment have been reported in clinical trials with bupropion. In addition, there have been rare spontaneous postmarketing reports of erythema multiforme, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, and anaphylactic shock associated with bupropion. Instruct patients to discontinue CONTRAVE and consult a healthcare provider if they develop an allergic or anaphylactoid/anaphylactic reaction (e.g., skin rash, pruritus, hives, chest pain, edema, or shortness of breath) during treatment. Arthralgia, myalgia, fever with rash, and other symptoms suggestive of delayed hypersensitivity have been reported in association with bupropion. These symptoms may resemble serum sickness. Cases of hepatitis and clinically significant liver dysfunction were observed in association with naltrexone exposure during naltrexone clinical trials and in postmarketing reports for patients using naltrexone. Transient, asymptomatic hepatic transaminase elevations were also observed. When patients presented with elevated transaminases, there were often other potential causative or contributory etiologies identified, including pre-existing alcoholic liver disease, hepatitis B and/or C infection, and concomitant usage of other potentially hepatotoxic drugs. Although clinically significant liver dysfunction is not typically recognized as a manifestation of opioid withdrawal, opioid withdrawal that is precipitated abruptly may lead to systemic sequelae, including acute liver injury. Patients should be warned of the risk of hepatic injury and advised to seek medical attention if they experience symptoms of acute hepatitis. Use of CONTRAVE should be discontinued in the event of symptoms and/or signs of acute hepatitis. In CONTRAVE clinical trials, there were no cases of elevated transaminases greater than three times the upper limit of normal (ULN) in conjunction with an increase in bilirubin greater than two times ULN. Bupropion, a component of CONTRAVE, is a drug used for the treatment of depression. Antidepressant treatment can precipitate a manic, mixed, or hypomanic episode. The risk appears to be increased in patients with bipolar disorder or who have risk factors for bipolar disorder. Prior to initiating CONTRAVE, screen patients for a history of bipolar disorder and the presence of risk factors for bipolar disorder (e.g., family history of bipolar disorder, suicide, or depression). CONTRAVE is not approved for use in treating bipolar depression. No activation of mania or hypomania was reported in the clinical trials evaluating effects of CONTRAVE in obese patients; however, patients receiving antidepressant medications and patients with a history of bipolar disorder or recent hospitalization because of psychiatric illness were excluded from CONTRAVE clinical trials. The pupillary dilation that occurs following use of many antidepressant drugs including bupropion, a component of CONTRAVE, may trigger an angle-closure attack in a patient with anatomically narrow angles who does not have a patent iridectomy. Weight loss may increase the risk of hypoglycemia in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus treated with insulin and/or insulin secretagogues (e.g., sulfonylureas). Measurement of blood glucose levels prior to starting CONTRAVE and during CONTRAVE treatment is recommended in patients with type 2 diabetes. Decreases in medication doses for antidiabetic medications which are non-glucose-dependent should be considered to mitigate the risk of hypoglycemia. If a patient develops hypoglycemia after starting CONTRAVE, appropriate changes should be made to the antidiabetic drug regimen.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
CONTRAVE has two components: naltrexone, an opioid antagonist, and bupropion, a relatively weak inhibitor of the neuronal reuptake of dopamine and norepinephrine. Nonclinical studies suggest that naltrexone and bupropion have effects on two separate areas of the brain involved in the regulation of food intake: the hypothalamus (appetite regulatory center) and the mesolimbic dopamine circuit (reward system). The exact neurochemical effects of CONTRAVE leading to weight loss are not fully understood. Combined, bupropion and naltrexone increased the firing rate of hypothalamic pro-opiomelanocortin (POMC) neurons in vitro , which are associated with regulation of appetite. The combination of bupropion and naltrexone also reduced food intake when injected directly into the ventral tegmental area of the mesolimbic circuit in mice, an area associated with regulation of reward pathways. Absorption Naltrexone Following single oral administration of CONTRAVE (two 8 mg naltrexone/90 mg bupropion tablets) to healthy subjects, mean peak naltrexone concentration (C max ) was 1.4 ng/mL, time to peak concentration (T max ) was 2 hours, and extent of exposure (AUC 0-inf ) was 8.4 ng∙hr/mL. Bupropion Following single oral administration of CONTRAVE (two 8 mg naltrexone/90 mg bupropion tablets) to healthy subjects, mean peak bupropion concentration (C max ) was 168 ng/mL, time to peak concentration (T max ) was three hours, and extent of exposure (AUC 0-inf ) was 1,607 ng∙hr/mL. Food Effect on Absorption When CONTRAVE was administered with a high-fat meal, the AUC and C max for naltrexone increased 2.1-fold and 3.7-fold, respectively, and the AUC and C max for bupropion increased 1.4-fold and 1.8-fold, respectively. At steady state, the food effect increased AUC and C max for naltrexone by 1.7-fold and 1.9-fold, respectively, and increased AUC and C max for bupropion by 1.1-fold and 1.3-fold, respectively. Thus, CONTRAVE should not be taken with high-fat meals because of the resulting significant increases in bupropion and naltrexone systemic exposure. Distribution Naltrexone Naltrexone is 21% plasma protein bound. The mean apparent volume of distribution at steady state for naltrexone (V ss /F) is 5,697 liters. Bupropion Bupropion is 84% plasma protein bound. The mean apparent volume of distribution at steady state for bupropion (V ss /F) is 880 liters. Metabolism and Excretion Naltrexone The major metabolite of naltrexone is 6-beta-naltrexol. The activity of naltrexone is believed to be the result of both the parent and the 6-beta-naltrexol metabolite. Though less potent, 6-beta-naltrexol is eliminated more slowly and thus circulates at much higher concentrations than naltrexone. Naltrexone and 6-beta-naltrexol are not metabolized by cytochrome P450 enzymes and in vitro studies indicate that there is no potential for inhibition or induction of important isozymes. Naltrexone and its metabolites are excreted primarily by the kidney (53% to 79% of the dose). Urinary excretion of unchanged naltrexone accounts for less than 2% of an oral dose. Urinary excretion of unchanged and conjugated 6-beta-naltrexol accounts for 43% of an oral dose. The renal clearance for naltrexone ranges from 30 to 127 mL/min, suggesting that renal elimination is primarily by glomerular filtration. The renal clearance for 6-beta-naltrexol ranges from 230 to 369 mL/min suggesting an additional renal tubular secretory mechanism. Fecal excretion is a minor elimination pathway. Following single oral administration of CONTRAVE tablets to healthy subjects, mean elimination half-life (T 1/2 ) was approximately 5 hours for naltrexone. Following twice daily administration of CONTRAVE, naltrexone did not accumulate and its kinetics appeared linear. However, in comparison to naltrexone, 6-beta-naltrexol accumulates to a larger extent (accumulation ratio ~3). Bupropion Bupropion is extensively metabolized with three active metabolites: hydroxybupropion, threohydrobupropion and erythrohydrobupropion. The metabolites have longer elimination half-lives than bupropion and accumulate to a greater extent. Following bupropion administration, more than 90% of the exposure is a result of metabolites. In vitro findings suggest that CYP2B6 is the principal isozyme involved in the formation of hydroxybupropion whereas cytochrome P450 isozymes are not involved in the formation of the other active metabolites. Bupropion and its metabolites inhibit CYP2D6. Plasma protein binding of hydroxybupropion is similar to that of bupropion (84%) whereas the other two metabolites have approximately half the binding. Following oral administration of 200 mg of 14 C-bupropion in humans, 87% and 10% of the radioactive dose were recovered in the urine and feces, respectively. The fraction of the oral dose of bupropion excreted unchanged was 0.5%, a finding consistent with the extensive metabolism of bupropion. Following single oral administration of CONTRAVE tablets to healthy subjects, mean elimination half-life (T ½ ) was approximately 21 hours for bupropion. Following twice daily administration of CONTRAVE, metabolites of bupropion, and to a lesser extent unchanged bupropion, accumulate and reach steady-state concentrations in approximately one week. Specific Populations Gender Pooled analysis of CONTRAVE data suggested no clinically meaningful differences in the pharmacokinetic parameters of bupropion or naltrexone based on gender. Race Pooled analysis of CONTRAVE data suggested no clinically meaningful differences in the pharmacokinetic parameters of bupropion or naltrexone based on race. Elderly The pharmacokinetics of CONTRAVE have not been evaluated in the geriatric population. The effects of age on the pharmacokinetics of naltrexone or bupropion and their metabolites have not been fully characterized. An exploration of steady-state bupropion concentrations from several depression efficacy studies involving patients dosed in a range of 300 to 750 mg/day, on a three times daily schedule, revealed no relationship between age (18 to 83 years) and plasma concentration of bupropion. A single-dose pharmacokinetic study demonstrated that the disposition of bupropion and its metabolites in elderly subjects was similar to that of younger subjects. These data suggest there is no prominent effect of age on bupropion concentration; however, another pharmacokinetic study, single and multiple dose, has suggested that the elderly are at increased risk for accumulation of bupropion and its metabolites [see Use in Specific Populations ( 8.5 )] . Smokers Pooled analysis of CONTRAVE data revealed no meaningful differences in the plasma concentrations of bupropion or naltrexone in smokers compared with nonsmokers. The effects of cigarette smoking on the pharmacokinetics of bupropion were studied in 34 healthy male and female volunteers; 17 were chronic cigarette smokers and 17 were nonsmokers. Following oral administration of a single 150 mg dose of bupropion, there was no statistically significant difference in C max , half-life, T max , AUC, or clearance of bupropion or its active metabolites between smokers and nonsmokers. Hepatic Impairment Pharmacokinetic data are not available with CONTRAVE in patients with hepatic impairment. The following information is available for individual constituents: Naltrexone An increase in naltrexone AUC of approximately 5- and 10-fold in patients with compensated and decompensated liver cirrhosis, respectively, compared with subjects with normal liver function, has been reported. These data also suggest that alterations in naltrexone bioavailability are related to liver disease severity. Bupropion The effect of hepatic impairment on the pharmacokinetics of bupropion was characterized in two single-dose trials, one trial in patients with alcoholic liver disease and a second trial in patients with mild-to-severe cirrhosis. The first trial showed that the half-life of hydroxybupropion was significantly longer in eight patients with alcoholic liver disease than in eight healthy volunteers (32±14 hours vs 21±5 hours, respectively). Although not statistically significant, the AUCs for bupropion and hydroxybupropion were more variable and tended to be greater (by 53% to 57%) in patients with alcoholic liver disease. The differences in half-life for bupropion and the other metabolites in the two patient groups were minimal. The second trial demonstrated no statistically significant differences in the pharmacokinetics of bupropion and its active metabolites in nine subjects with mild-to-moderate hepatic cirrhosis compared with eight healthy volunteers. However, more variability was observed in some of the pharmacokinetic parameters for bupropion (AUC, C max , and T max ) and its active metabolites (t ½ ) in subjects with mild-to-moderate hepatic cirrhosis. In subjects with severe hepatic cirrhosis, significant alterations in the pharmacokinetics of bupropion and its metabolites were seen (Table 4) . Table 4. Pharmacokinetics of Bupropion and Metabolites in Patients With Severe Hepatic Cirrhosis: Ratio Relative to Healthy Matched Controls C max AUC t½ T max = Difference Bupropion 1.69 3.12 1.43 0.5 h Hydroxybupropion 0.31 1.28 3.88 19 h Threo/erythrohydrobupropion amino alcohol 0.69 2.48 1.96 20 h The dose of CONTRAVE should be reduced in patients with hepatic impairment [see Dosage and Administration ( 2.3 ) and Use in Specific Populations ( 8.7 )] . Renal Impairment A dedicated pharmacokinetic study has not been conducted for CONTRAVE in subjects with renal impairment. The following information is available for the individual constituents: Naltrexone Limited information is available for naltrexone in patients with moderate to severe renal impairment. In a study of seven patients with end-stage renal disease requiring dialysis, peak plasma concentrations of naltrexone were elevated at least 6-fold compared to healthy subjects. Bupropion Limited information is available for bupropion in patients with moderate to severe renal impairment. An inter-trial comparison between normal subjects and patients with end-stage renal failure demonstrated that the bupropion C max and AUC values were comparable in the two groups, whereas the hydroxybupropion and threohydrobupropion metabolites had a 2.3- and 2.8-fold increase, respectively, in AUC for patients with end-stage renal failure. A second trial, comparing normal subjects and patients with moderate-to-severe renal impairment (GFR 30.9 ± 10.8 mL/min) showed that exposure after a single 150 mg dose of sustained-release bupropion was approximately 2-fold higher in patients with impaired renal function while levels of the hydroxybupropion and threo/erythrohydrobupropion (combined) metabolites were similar in the two groups. The elimination of bupropion and/or the major metabolites of bupropion may be reduced by impaired renal function. The dose of CONTRAVE should be reduced in patients with moderate or severe renal impairment. CONTRAVE is not recommended for use in patients with end-stage renal disease [see Dosage and Administration ( 2.2 ) and Use in Specific Populations ( 8.6 )] . Drug Interactions In Vitro Assessment of Drug Interactions At therapeutically relevant concentrations, naltrexone and 6-beta-naltrexol are not major inhibitors of CYP isoforms CYP1A2, CYP2B6, CYP2C8, CYP2E1, CYP2C9, CYP2C19, CYP2D6 or CYP3A4. Both naltrexone and 6-beta-naltrexol are not major inducers of CYP isoforms CYP1A2, CYP2B6, or CYP3A4. Bupropion and its metabolites (hydroxybupropion, erythrohydrobupropion, threohydrobupropion) are inhibitors of CYP2D6. In vitro studies suggest that paroxetine, sertraline, norfluoxetine, fluvoxamine, and nelfinavir inhibit the hydroxylation of bupropion. Bupropion (IC 50 9.3 mcM) and its metabolites, hydroxybupropion (IC 50 82 mcM) and threohydrobupropion and erythrohydrobupropion (1:1 mixture; IC 50 7.8 mcM), inhibited the renal organic transporter OCT2 to a clinically relevant level. The systemic concentrations of substrate drugs transported by OCT2 are likely to increase as a result of reduced renal clearance when coadministered with CONTRAVE. Effects of Naltrexone/Bupropion on the Pharmacokinetics of Other Drugs Drug interaction between CONTRAVE and CYP2D6 substrates (metoprolol) or other drugs (atorvastatin, glyburide, lisinopril, nifedipine, valsartan) has been evaluated. In addition, drug interaction between bupropion, a component of CONTRAVE, and CYP2D6 substrates (desipramine) or other drugs (citalopram, lamotrigine) has also been evaluated. Table 5. Effect of Naltrexone/Bupropion Coadministration on Systemic Exposure of Other Drugs Naltrexone/Bupropion Dosage Coadministered Drug Name and Dose Regimens Change in Systemic Exposure Initiate the following drugs at the lower end of the dose range during concomitant use with CONTRAVE [see Drug Interactions 7 ] : Bupropion 150 mg twice daily for 10 days Desipramine 50 mg single dose ↑5-fold AUC, ↑2-fold C max Bupropion 300 mg (as XL) once daily for 14 days Citalopram 40 mg once daily for 14 days ↑40% AUC, ↑30% C max Naltrexone/Bupropion 16 mg/180 mg twice daily for 7 days Metoprolol 50 mg single dose ↑4-fold AUC, ↑2-fold C max No dose adjustment needed for the following drugs during concomitant use with CONTRAVE: Naltrexone/Bupropion 16 mg/180 mg single dose Atorvastatin 80 mg single dose No Effect Naltrexone/Bupropion 16 mg/180 mg single dose Glyburide 6 mg single dose No Effect Naltrexone/Bupropion 16 mg/180 mg single dose Lisinopril 40 mg single dose No Effect Naltrexone/Bupropion 16 mg/180 mg single dose Nifedipine 90 mg single dose No Effect Naltrexone/Bupropion 16 mg/180 mg single dose Valsartan 320 mg single dose No Effect Bupropion 150 mg twice daily for 12 days Lamotrigine 100 mg single dose No Effect Effects of Other Drugs on the Pharmacokinetics of Naltrexone/Bupropion Drug interactions between CYP2B6 inhibitors (ticlopidine, clopidogrel, prasugrel), CYP2B6 inducers (ritonavir, lopinavir) and bupropion (one of the CONTRAVE components), or between other drugs (atorvastatin, glyburide, metoprolol, lisinopril, nifedipine, valsartan) and CONTRAVE have been evaluated. While not systematically studied, carbamazepine, phenobarbital, or phenytoin may induce the metabolism of bupropion. Table 6. Effect of Coadministered Drugs on Systemic Exposure of Naltrexone/Bupropion Name and Dose Regimens Coadministered Drug CONTRAVE Components Change in Systemic Exposure Do not exceed one tablet twice daily dose of CONTRAVE with the following drugs: Ticlopidine 250 mg twice daily for 4 days Bupropion Hydroxybupropion ↑85% AUC, ↑38% C max ↓84% AUC, ↓78% C max Clopidogrel 75 mg once daily for 4 days Bupropion Hydroxybupropion ↑60% AUC, ↑40% C max ↓52% AUC, ↓50% C max No dose adjustment needed for CONTRAVE with the following drugs: Atorvastatin 80 mg single dose Naltrexone 6-beta naltrexol Bupropion Hydroxybupropion Threohydrobupropion Erythrohydrobupropion No Effect No Effect No Effect No Effect No Effect No Effect Lisinopril 40 mg single dose Naltrexone 6-beta naltrexol Bupropion Hydroxybupropion Threohydrobupropion Erythrohydrobupropion No Effect No Effect No Effect No Effect No Effect No Effect Valsartan 320 mg single dose Naltrexone 6-beta naltrexol Bupropion Hydroxybupropion Threohydrobupropion Erythrohydrobupropion No Effect No Effect No Effect ↓14% AUC, No Effect on C max No Effect No Effect Cimetidine 800 mg single dose Bupropion Hydroxybupropion Threo/Erythrohydrobupropion No Effect No Effect ↑16% AUC, ↑32% C max Citalopram 40 mg once daily for 14 days Bupropion Hydroxybupropion Threohydrobupropion Erythrohydrobupropion No Effect No Effect No Effect No Effect Metoprolol 50 mg single dose Naltrexone 6-beta naltrexol Bupropion Hydroxybupropion Threohydrobupropion Erythrohydrobupropion ↓25% AUC, ↓29% C max No Effect No Effect No Effect No Effect No Effect Nifedipine 90 mg single dose Naltrexone 6-beta naltrexol Bupropion Hydroxybupropion Threohydrobupropion Erythrohydrobupropion ↑24% AUC, ↑58% C max No Effect No Effect on AUC, ↑22% C max No Effect No Effect No Effect Prasugrel 10 mg once daily for 6 days Bupropion Hydroxybupropion ↑18% AUC, ↑14% C max ↓24%AUC, ↓32% C max Use CONTRAVE with caution with the following drugs: Glyburide 6 mg single dose Results were confounded by the food-effect due to oral glucose coadministered with the treatment. Naltrexone 6-beta naltrexol Bupropion Hydroxybupropion Threohydrobupropion Erythrohydrobupropion ↑2-fold AUC, ↑2-fold C max No Effect ↑36% AUC, ↑18% C max ↑22% AUC, ↑21% C max No Effect on AUC, ↑15% C max No Effect Avoid concomitant use of CONTRAVE with following drugs: Ritonavir 100 mg twice daily for 17 days Bupropion Hydroxybupropion Threohydrobupropion Erythrohydrobupropion ↓22% AUC, ↓21 % C max ↓23% AUC, No Effect on C max ↓38% AUC, ↓39 % C max ↓48% AUC, ↓28 % C max 600 mg twice daily for 8 days Bupropion Hydroxybupropion Threohydrobupropion Erythrohydrobupropion ↓66% AUC, ↓62% C max ↓78% AUC, ↓42 % C max ↓50% AUC, ↓58% C max ↓68% AUC, ↓48 % C max Lopinavir/Ritonavir 400 mg/100 mg twice daily for 14 days Bupropion Hydroxybupropion ↓57% AUC, ↓57% C max ↓50% AUC, ↓31% C max Efavirenz 600 mg once daily for 2 weeks Bupropion Hydroxybupropion ↓55% AUC, ↓34% C max No Effect on AUC, ↑50% C max</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="10047" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>SUICIDALITY AND ANTIDEPRESSANT DRUGS CONTRAVE® is not approved for use in the treatment of major depressive disorder or other psychiatric disorders.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10048" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>CONTRAVE contains bupropion, the same active ingredient as some other antidepressant medications (including, but not limited to, WELLBUTRIN, WELLBUTRIN SR, WELLBUTRIN XL and APLENZIN).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10049" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Antidepressants increased the risk of suicidal thoughts and behavior in children, adolescents, and young adults in short-term trials.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10050" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>These trials did not show an increase in the risk of suicidal thoughts and behavior with antidepressant use in subjects over age 24; there was a reduction in risk with antidepressant use in subjects aged 65 and older.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10051" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>In patients of all ages who are started on CONTRAVE, monitor closely for worsening, and for the emergence of suicidal thoughts and behaviors.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10052" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Advise families and caregivers of the need for close observation and communication with the prescriber.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10053" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>CONTRAVE is not approved for use in pediatric patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10054" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>NEUROPSYCHIATRIC REACTIONS IN PATIENTS TAKING BUPROPION FOR SMOKING CESSATION Serious neuropsychiatric reactions have occurred in patients taking bupropion for smoking cessation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10055" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>The majority of these reactions occurred during bupropion treatment, but some occurred in the context of discontinuing treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10056" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>In many cases, a causal relationship to bupropion treatment is not certain, because depressed mood may be a symptom of nicotine withdrawal.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10057" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>However, some of the cases occurred in patients taking bupropion who continued to smoke.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10058" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Although CONTRAVE is not approved for smoking cessation, observe all patients for neuropsychiatric reactions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10059" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Instruct the patient to contact a healthcare provider if such reactions occur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10060" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>WARNING: SUICIDAL THOUGHTS AND BEHAVIORS; AND NEUROPSYCHIATRIC REACTIONS See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning Increased risk of suicidal thinking and behavior in children, adolescents, and young adults taking antidepressants for major depressive disorder and other psychiatric disorders.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10061" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Monitor for worsening and emergence of suicidal thoughts and behaviors.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10062" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>Serious neuropsychiatric events have been reported in patients taking bupropion for smoking cessation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10063" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34066-1">
<SentenceText>CONTRAVE has not been studied in pediatric patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10064" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>CONTRAVE is contraindicated in Uncontrolled hypertension Seizure disorder or a history of seizures Use of other bupropion-containing products (including, but not limited to, WELLBUTRIN, WELLBUTRIN SR, WELLBUTRIN XL, and APLENZIN) Bulimia or anorexia nervosa, which increase the risk for seizure Chronic opioid or opiate agonist (e.g., methadone) or partial agonists (e.g., buprenorphine) use, or acute opiate withdrawal Patients undergoing an abrupt discontinuation of alcohol, benzodiazepines, barbiturates, and antiepileptic drugs Concomitant administration of monoamine oxidase inhibitors (MAOI).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M9" type="Trigger" span="12 15;450 15" str="contraindicated | discontinuation"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="469 7" str="alcohol" code="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M"/>
<Mention id="M4" type="Precipitant" span="513 19" str="antiepileptic drugs" code="N0000175753"/>
<Mention id="M35" type="Trigger" span="12 15" str="contraindicated"/>
<Mention id="M6" type="Precipitant" span="220 8" str="APLENZIN" code="E70G3G5863"/>
<Mention id="M8" type="Precipitant" span="495 12" str="barbiturates" code="N0000175693 | N0000008016"/>
<Mention id="M10" type="Precipitant" span="478 15" str="benzodiazepines" code="N0000007542 | N0000175694"/>
<Mention id="M12" type="Precipitant" span="373 13" str="buprenorphine" code="40D3SCR4GZ"/>
<Mention id="M14" type="Precipitant" span="112 9" str="bupropion" code="01ZG3TPX31"/>
<Mention id="M16" type="Precipitant" span="112 29" str="bupropion-containing products" code="01ZG3TPX31"/>
<Mention id="M18" type="Precipitant" span="295 14" str="Chronic opioid" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M20" type="Precipitant" span="593 4" str="MAOI" code="N0000000184"/>
<Mention id="M22" type="Precipitant" span="335 9" str="methadone" code="UC6VBE7V1Z"/>
<Mention id="M24" type="Precipitant" span="563 28" str="monoamine oxidase inhibitors" code="N0000000184 | N0000175744"/>
<Mention id="M25" type="Trigger" span="12 15;409 10" str="contraindicated | withdrawal"/>
<Mention id="M26" type="Precipitant" span="313 6" str="opiate" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M28" type="Precipitant" span="313 14" str="opiate agonist" code="N0000000174"/>
<Mention id="M30" type="Precipitant" span="349 16" str="partial agonists" code="N0000175685"/>
<Mention id="M32" type="Precipitant" span="174 10" str="WELLBUTRIN" code="ZG7E5POY8O"/>
<Mention id="M34" type="Precipitant" span="186 13" str="WELLBUTRIN SR" code="ZG7E5POY8O"/>
<Mention id="M36" type="Precipitant" span="201 13" str="WELLBUTRIN XL" code="ZG7E5POY8O"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M9" precipitant="M2"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M9" precipitant="M4"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M6"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M9" precipitant="M8"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M9" precipitant="M10"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M12"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M14"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M16"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M18"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M20"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M22"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M24"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M25" precipitant="M26"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M28"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M30"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M32"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M34"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M36"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10065" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>At least 14 days should elapse between discontinuation of MAOI and initiation of treatment with CONTRAVE.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M37" type="Trigger" span="39 15" str="discontinuation"/>
<Mention id="M38" type="Precipitant" span="58 4" str="MAOI" code="N0000000184"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M37" precipitant="M38"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10066" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>There is an increased risk of hypertensive reactions when CONTRAVE is used concomitantly with MAOIs.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M39" type="Trigger" span="12 14" str="increased risk"/>
<Mention id="M40" type="Precipitant" span="94 5" str="MAOIs" code="N0000000184"/>
<Mention id="M41" type="SpecificInteraction" span="30 22" str="hypertensive reactions" code="24184005: Finding of increased blood pressure (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M39" precipitant="M40" effect="M41" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10067" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Starting CONTRAVE in a patient treated with reversible MAOIs such as linezolid or intravenous methylene blue is also contraindicated Known allergy to bupropion, naltrexone or any other component of CONTRAVE.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M46" type="Trigger" span="117 15" str="contraindicated"/>
<Mention id="M43" type="Precipitant" span="82 26" str="intravenous methylene blue" code="N0000007449 | T42P99266K"/>
<Mention id="M45" type="Precipitant" span="69 9" str="linezolid" code="ISQ9I6J12J"/>
<Mention id="M47" type="Precipitant" span="44 16" str="reversible MAOIs" code="N0000000184"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M46" precipitant="M43"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M46" precipitant="M45"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M46" precipitant="M47"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10068" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Anaphylactoid/anaphylactic reactions and Stevens-Johnson syndrome have been reported with bupropion Pregnancy Uncontrolled hypertension (4) Seizure disorders, anorexia nervosa or bulimia, or undergoing abrupt discontinuation of alcohol, benzodiazepines, barbiturates, and antiepileptic drugs (4) Use of other bupropion-containing products (4) Chronic opioid use (4) During or within 14 days of taking monoamine oxidase inhibitors (MAOI) (4) Known allergy to any of the ingredients in CONTRAVE (4) Pregnancy (4)</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10069" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>CONTRAVE dose escalation schedule (2.1): Morning Dose Evening Dose Week 1 1 tablet None Week 2 1 tablet 1 tablet Week 3 2 tablets 1 tablet Week 4 – Onward 2 tablets 2 tablets CONTRAVE dosing should be escalated according to the following schedule: Morning Dose Evening Dose Week 1 1 tablet None Week 2 1 tablet 1 tablet Week 3 2 tablets 1 tablet Week 4 – Onward 2 tablets 2 tablets A total daily dosage of two CONTRAVE 8 mg/90 mg tablets twice daily (32 mg/360 mg) is reached at the start of Week 4.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10070" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>CONTRAVE should be taken by mouth in the morning and in the evening.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10071" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The tablets should not be cut, chewed, or crushed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10072" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Total daily doses greater than 32 mg/360 mg per day (two tablets twice daily) are not recommended.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10073" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In clinical trials, CONTRAVE was administered with meals.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10074" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>However, CONTRAVE should not be taken with a high-fat meal because of a resulting significant increase in bupropion and naltrexone systemic exposure.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M48" type="Trigger" span="94 8;131 17" str="increase | systemic exposure"/>
<Mention id="M49" type="Precipitant" span="45 13" str="high-fat meal" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M48" precipitant="M49" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10075" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Patients may develop elevated blood pressure or heart rate during CONTRAVE treatment; the risk may be greater during the initial three months of therapy [see Warnings and Precautions (5.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10076" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Because patients with hypertension may be at increased risk for developing blood pressure elevations, such patients should be monitored for this potential effect when initiating treatment with CONTRAVE.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10077" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Response to therapy should be evaluated after 12 weeks at the maintenance dosage.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10078" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>If a patient has not lost at least 5% of baseline body weight, discontinue CONTRAVE, as it is unlikely that the patient will achieve and sustain clinically meaningful weight loss with continued treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10079" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>BMI is calculated by dividing weight (in kg) by height (in meters) squared.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10080" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>A BMI chart for determining BMI based on height and weight is provided in Table 1.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10081" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>BMI Conversion Chart Weight (lb) 125 130 135 140 145 150 155 160 165 170 175 180 185 190 195 200 205 210 215 220 225 (kg) 56.8 59.1 61.4 63.6 65.9 68.2 70.5 72.7 75.0 77.3 79.5 81.8 84.1 86.4 88.6 90.9 93.2 95.5 97.7 100.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10082" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>3 Height (in) (cm) 58 147.3 26 27 28 29 30 31 32 34 35 36 37 38 39 40 41 42 43 44 45 46 47 59 149.9 25 26 27 28 29 30 31 32 33 34 35 36 37 38 39 40 41 43 44 45 46 60 152.4 24 25 26 27 28 29 30 31 32 33 34 35 36 37 38 39 40 41 42 43 44 61 154.9 24 25 26 27 27 28 29 30 31 32 33 34 35 36 37 38 39 40 41 42 43 62 157.5 23 24 25 26 27 27 28 29 30 31 32 33 34 35 36 37 38 38 39 40 41 63 160.0 22 23 24 25 26 27 28 28 29 30 31 32 33 34 35 36 36 37 38 39 40 64 162.6 22 22 23 24 25 26 27 28 28 29 30 31 32 33 34 34 35 36 37 38 39 65 165.1 21 22 23 23 24 25 26 27 28 28 29 30 31 32 33 33 34 35 36 37 38 66 167.6 20 21 22 23 23 24 25 26 27 27 28 29 30 31 32 32 33 34 35 36 36 67 170.2 20 20 21 22 23 24 24 25 26 27 27 28 29 30 31 31 32 33 34 35 35 68 172.7 19 20 21 21 22 23 24 24 25 26 27 27 28 29 30 30 31 32 33 34 34 69 175.3 18 19 20 21 21 22 23 24 24 25 26 27 27 28 29 30 30 31 32 33 33 70 177.8 18 19 19 20 21 22 22 23 24 24 25 26 27 27 28 29 29 30 31 32 32 71 180.3 17 18 19 20 20 21 22 22 23 24 24 25 26 27 27 28 29 29 30 31 31 72 182.9 17 18 18 19 20 20 21 22 22 23 24 24 25 26 27 27 28 29 29 30 31 73 185.4 17 17 18 19 19 20 20 21 22 22 23 24 24 25 26 26 27 28 28 29 30 74 188.0 16 17 17 18 19 19 20 21 21 22 23 23 24 24 25 26 26 27 28 28 29 75 190.5 16 16 17 18 18 19 19 20 21 21 22 23 23 24 24 25 26 26 27 28 28 76 193.0 15 16 16 17 18 18 19 20 20 21 21 22 23 23 24 24 25 26 26 27 27 In patients with moderate or severe renal impairment, the maximum recommended daily dose for CONTRAVE is two tablets (one tablet each morning and evening).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10083" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>CONTRAVE is not recommended for use in patients with end-stage renal disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10084" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>There is a lack of adequate information to guide dosing in patients with mild renal impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10085" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In patients with hepatic impairment, the maximum recommended daily dose of CONTRAVE is one tablet in the morning.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10086" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>At least 14 days should elapse between discontinuation of an MAOI intended to treat depression and initiation of therapy with CONTRAVE.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M50" type="Trigger" span="39 15" str="discontinuation"/>
<Mention id="M51" type="Precipitant" span="61 4" str="MAOI" code="N0000000184"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M50" precipitant="M51"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10087" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Conversely, at least 14 days should be allowed after stopping CONTRAVE before starting an MAOI antidepressant.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M52" type="Trigger" span="53 8;71 15" str="stopping | before starting"/>
<Mention id="M53" type="Precipitant" span="90 4" str="MAOI" code="N0000000184"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M52" precipitant="M53"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10088" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>During concomitant use with CYP2B6 inhibitors (e.g., ticlopidine or clopidogrel), the maximum recommended daily dose of CONTRAVE is two tablets (one tablet each morning and evening).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M58" type="Trigger" span="86 7;112 4" str="maximum | dose"/>
<Mention id="M55" type="Precipitant" span="68 11" str="clopidogrel" code="A74586SNO7 | N0000007277"/>
<Mention id="M57" type="Precipitant" span="28 17" str="CYP2B6 inhibitors" code="N0000182139"/>
<Mention id="M59" type="Precipitant" span="53 11" str="ticlopidine" code="OM90ZUW7M1"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M58" precipitant="M55" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M58" precipitant="M57" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I29" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M58" precipitant="M59" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10089" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>MAOIs: Increased risk of hypertensive reactions can occur when used concomitantly.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M60" type="Trigger" span="7 14" str="Increased risk"/>
<Mention id="M61" type="Precipitant" span="0 5" str="MAOIs" code="N0000000184"/>
<Mention id="M62" type="SpecificInteraction" span="25 22" str="hypertensive reactions" code="24184005: Finding of increased blood pressure (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I30" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M60" precipitant="M61" effect="M62" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10090" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Drugs Metabolized by CYP2D6: Bupropion inhibits CYP2D6 and can increase concentrations of: antidepressants, (e.g., selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors and many tricyclics), antipsychotics (e.g., haloperidol, risperidone and thioridazine), beta-blockers (e.g., metoprolol) and Type 1C antiarrhythmics (e.g., propafenone and flecainide): Consider dose reduction when using with CONTRAVE.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M99" type="Trigger" span="63 23" str="increase concentrations "/>
<Mention id="M100" type="Trigger" span="349 14" str=" dose reduction"/>
<Mention id="M65" type="Precipitant" span="91 15" str="antidepressants" code="N0000029147 | N0000178314"/>
<Mention id="M68" type="Precipitant" span="177 14" str="antipsychotics" code="N0000029150 | N0000178316"/>
<Mention id="M71" type="Precipitant" span="243 13" str="beta-blockers" code="N0000000161 | N0000175556"/>
<Mention id="M74" type="Precipitant" span="0 27" str="Drugs Metabolized by CYP2D6" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M77" type="Precipitant" span="327 10" str="flecainide" code="N0000006966 | K94FTS1806"/>
<Mention id="M80" type="Precipitant" span="199 11" str="haloperidol" code="J6292F8L3D | N0000006048"/>
<Mention id="M83" type="Precipitant" span="264 10" str="metoprolol" code="GEB06NHM23"/>
<Mention id="M86" type="Precipitant" span="311 11" str="propafenone" code="68IQX3T69U"/>
<Mention id="M89" type="Precipitant" span="212 11" str="risperidone" code="L6UH7ZF8HC"/>
<Mention id="M92" type="Precipitant" span="115 39" str="selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors" code="N0000175696"/>
<Mention id="M95" type="Precipitant" span="228 12" str="thioridazine" code="N3D6TG58NI"/>
<Mention id="M98" type="Precipitant" span="164 10" str="tricyclics" code="N0000029148 | N0000175752"/>
<Mention id="M101" type="Precipitant" span="280 23" str="Type 1C antiarrhythmics" code="N0000029121 | N0000175426"/>
<Interaction id="I31" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M99;M100" precipitant="M65" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I32" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M99;M100" precipitant="M68" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I33" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M99;M100" precipitant="M71" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I34" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M99;M100" precipitant="M74" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I35" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M99;M100" precipitant="M77" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I36" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M99;M100" precipitant="M80" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I37" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M99;M100" precipitant="M83" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I38" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M99;M100" precipitant="M86" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I39" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M99;M100" precipitant="M89" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I40" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M99;M100" precipitant="M92" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I41" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M99;M100" precipitant="M95" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I42" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M99;M100" precipitant="M98" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I43" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M99;M100" precipitant="M101" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10091" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant Treatment with CYP2B6 Inhibitors (e.g., ticlopidine or clopidogrel) can increase bupropion exposure.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M106" type="Trigger" span="84 8;103 8" str="increase | exposure"/>
<Mention id="M103" type="Precipitant" span="67 11" str="clopidogrel" code="A74586SNO7 | N0000007277"/>
<Mention id="M105" type="Precipitant" span="27 17" str="CYP2B6 Inhibitors" code="N0000182139"/>
<Mention id="M107" type="Precipitant" span="52 11" str="ticlopidine" code="OM90ZUW7M1"/>
<Interaction id="I44" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M106" precipitant="M103" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I45" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M106" precipitant="M105" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I46" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M106" precipitant="M107" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10092" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Do not exceed one tablet twice daily when taken with CYP2B6 inhibitors.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M108" type="Trigger" span="0 13" str="Do not exceed"/>
<Mention id="M109" type="Precipitant" span="53 17" str="CYP2B6 inhibitors" code="N0000182139"/>
<Interaction id="I47" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M108" precipitant="M109" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10093" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>CYP2B6 Inducers (e.g., ritonavir, lopinavir, efavirenz, carbamazepine, phenobarbital, and phenytoin) may reduce efficacy by reducing bupropion exposure, avoid concomitant use.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M128" type="Trigger" span="105 15" str="reduce efficacy"/>
<Mention id="M132" type="Precipitant" span="56 13" str="carbamazepine" code="33CM23913M | N0000007470"/>
<Mention id="M130" type="SpecificInteraction" span="105 15;133 9" str="reduce efficacy | bupropion" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M134" type="Precipitant" span="0 15" str="CYP2B6 Inducers" code="N0000187064"/>
<Mention id="M136" type="Precipitant" span="45 9" str="efavirenz" code="JE6H2O27P8"/>
<Mention id="M138" type="Precipitant" span="34 9" str="lopinavir" code="2494G1JF75"/>
<Mention id="M140" type="Precipitant" span="71 13" str="phenobarbital" code="YQE403BP4D | N0000005893"/>
<Mention id="M142" type="Precipitant" span="90 9" str="phenytoin" code="6158TKW0C5 | N0000006023"/>
<Mention id="M144" type="Precipitant" span="23 9" str="ritonavir" code="O3J8G9O825 | N0000007423"/>
<Mention id="M143" type="Trigger" span="124 8;143 8" str="reducing | exposure"/>
<Interaction id="I48" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M128" precipitant="M132" effect="M130" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I49" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M128" precipitant="M134" effect="M130" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I50" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M128" precipitant="M136" effect="M130" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I51" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M128" precipitant="M138" effect="M130" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I52" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M128" precipitant="M140" effect="M130" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I53" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M128" precipitant="M142" effect="M130" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I54" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M128" precipitant="M144" effect="M130" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I55" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M143" precipitant="M132" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I56" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M143" precipitant="M134" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I57" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M143" precipitant="M136" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I58" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M143" precipitant="M138" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I59" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M143" precipitant="M140" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I60" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M143" precipitant="M142" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I61" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M143" precipitant="M144" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10094" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Drugs that Lower Seizure Threshold: Dose CONTRAVE with caution.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M145" type="Trigger" span="55 7" str="caution"/>
<Mention id="M146" type="Precipitant" span="0 34" str="Drugs that Lower Seizure Threshold" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I62" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M145" precipitant="M146"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10095" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Dopaminergic Drugs (levodopa and amantadine): CNS toxicity can occur when used concomitantly with CONTRAVE.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M153" type="Trigger" span="63 5" str="occur"/>
<Mention id="M148" type="Precipitant" span="33 10" str="amantadine" code="BF4C9Z1J53"/>
<Mention id="M155" type="SpecificInteraction" span="46 12" str="CNS toxicity" code="246557006: Central nervous system symptom (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M151" type="Precipitant" span="0 18" str="Dopaminergic Drugs" code="N0000000117"/>
<Mention id="M154" type="Precipitant" span="20 8" str="levodopa" code="46627O600J"/>
<Interaction id="I63" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M153" precipitant="M148" effect="M155" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I64" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M153" precipitant="M151" effect="M155" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I65" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M153" precipitant="M154" effect="M155" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10096" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Drug-Laboratory Test Interactions: CONTRAVE can cause false-positive urine test results for amphetamines.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M156" type="Trigger" span="48 5" str="cause"/>
<Mention id="M157" type="Precipitant" span="92 12" str="amphetamines" code="CK833KGX7E | N0000007883"/>
<Mention id="M158" type="SpecificInteraction" span="54 50" str="false-positive urine test results for amphetamines" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I66" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M156" precipitant="M157" effect="M158" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10097" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant use of MAOIs and bupropion is contraindicated.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M159" type="Trigger" span="42 15" str="contraindicated"/>
<Mention id="M160" type="Precipitant" span="19 5" str="MAOIs" code="N0000000184"/>
<Interaction id="I67" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M159" precipitant="M160"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10098" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Bupropion inhibits the re-uptake of dopamine and norepinephrine and can increase the risk for hypertensive reactions when used concomitantly with drugs that also inhibit the re-uptake of dopamine or norepinephrine, including MAOIs.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M164" type="Trigger" span="72 17" str="increase the risk"/>
<Mention id="M162" type="Precipitant" span="146 67" str="drugs that also inhibit the re-uptake of dopamine or norepinephrine" code="N0000175424"/>
<Mention id="M166" type="SpecificInteraction" span="94 22" str="hypertensive reactions" code="24184005: Finding of increased blood pressure (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M165" type="Precipitant" span="225 5" str="MAOIs" code="N0000000184"/>
<Interaction id="I68" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M164" precipitant="M162" effect="M166" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I69" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M164" precipitant="M165" effect="M166" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10099" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Studies in animals demonstrate that the acute toxicity of bupropion is enhanced by the MAOI phenelzine.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M167" type="Trigger" span="46 8;71 8" str="toxicity | enhanced"/>
<Mention id="M168" type="Precipitant" span="92 10" str="phenelzine" code="O408N561GF"/>
<Interaction id="I70" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M167" precipitant="M168" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10100" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>At least 14 days should elapse between discontinuation of an MAOI and initiation of treatment with CONTRAVE.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M169" type="Trigger" span="39 15" str="discontinuation"/>
<Mention id="M170" type="Precipitant" span="61 4" str="MAOI" code="N0000000184"/>
<Interaction id="I71" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M169" precipitant="M170"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10101" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Conversely, at least 14 days should be allowed after stopping CONTRAVE before starting an MAOI.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M171" type="Trigger" span="53 8;71 15" str="stopping | before starting"/>
<Mention id="M172" type="Precipitant" span="90 4" str="MAOI" code="N0000000184"/>
<Interaction id="I72" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M171" precipitant="M172"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10102" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Patients taking CONTRAVE may not fully benefit from treatment with opioid-containing medicines, such as cough and cold remedies, antidiarrheal preparations, and opioid analgesics.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M181" type="Trigger" span="29 17" str="not fully benefit"/>
<Mention id="M174" type="Precipitant" span="67 6" str="opioid" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M176" type="Precipitant" span="161 17" str="opioid analgesics" code="N0000175440"/>
<Mention id="M178" type="Precipitant" span="67 17;129 26" str="opioid-containing | antidiarrheal preparations" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M180" type="Precipitant" span="67 17;104 23" str="opioid-containing | cough and cold remedies" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M182" type="Precipitant" span="67 27" str="opioid-containing medicines" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I73" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M181" precipitant="M174"/>
<Interaction id="I74" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M181" precipitant="M176"/>
<Interaction id="I75" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M181" precipitant="M178"/>
<Interaction id="I76" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M181" precipitant="M180"/>
<Interaction id="I77" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M181" precipitant="M182"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10103" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>In patients requiring intermittent opiate treatment, CONTRAVE therapy should be temporarily discontinued and opiate dose should not be increased above the standard dose.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M183" type="Trigger" span="92 12" str="discontinued"/>
<Mention id="M184" type="Precipitant" span="35 6" str="opiate" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I78" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M183" precipitant="M184"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10104" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>CONTRAVE may be used with caution after chronic opioid use has been stopped for 7 to 10 days in order to prevent precipitation of withdrawal.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M185" type="Trigger" span="26 7" str="caution"/>
<Mention id="M186" type="Precipitant" span="40 18" str="chronic opioid use" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I79" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M185" precipitant="M186"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10105" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>During CONTRAVE clinical studies, the use of concomitant opioid or opioid-like medications, including analgesics or antitussives, were excluded.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M193" type="Trigger" span="135 8" str="excluded"/>
<Mention id="M188" type="Precipitant" span="57 6" str="opioid" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M190" type="Precipitant" span="57 6;102 10" str="opioid | analgesics" code="N0000175440"/>
<Mention id="M192" type="Precipitant" span="57 6;116 12" str="opioid | antitussives" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M194" type="Precipitant" span="67 23" str="opioid-like medications" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I80" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M193" precipitant="M188"/>
<Interaction id="I81" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M193" precipitant="M190"/>
<Interaction id="I82" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M193" precipitant="M192"/>
<Interaction id="I83" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M193" precipitant="M194"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10106" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Metabolized by CYP2D6 In a clinical study, CONTRAVE (32 mg naltrexone/360 mg bupropion) daily was coadministered with a 50 mg dose of metoprolol (a CYP2D6 substrate).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10107" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>CONTRAVE increased metoprolol AUC and Cmax by approximately 4- and 2-fold, respectively, relative to metoprolol alone.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M195" type="Trigger" span="9 9;30 3" str="increased | AUC"/>
<Mention id="M198" type="Precipitant" span="19 10" str="metoprolol" code="GEB06NHM23"/>
<Mention id="M197" type="Trigger" span="9 9;38 4" str="increased | Cmax"/>
<Interaction id="I84" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M195" precipitant="M198" effect="C54613"/>
<Interaction id="I85" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M197" precipitant="M198" effect="C54610"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10108" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Similar clinical drug interactions resulting in increased pharmacokinetic exposure of CYP2D6 substrates have also been observed with bupropion as a single agent with desipramine or venlafaxine.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M203" type="Trigger" span="48 9;74 8" str="increased | exposure"/>
<Mention id="M200" type="Precipitant" span="86 17" str="CYP2D6 substrates" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M202" type="Precipitant" span="166 11" str="desipramine" code="TG537D343B"/>
<Mention id="M204" type="Precipitant" span="181 11" str="venlafaxine" code="GRZ5RCB1QG"/>
<Interaction id="I86" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M203" precipitant="M200" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I87" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M203" precipitant="M202" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I88" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M203" precipitant="M204" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10109" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Coadministration of CONTRAVE with drugs that are metabolized by CYP2D6 isozyme including certain antidepressants (SSRIs and many tricyclics), antipsychotics (e.g., haloperidol, risperidone and thioridazine), beta-blockers (e.g., metoprolol) and Type 1C antiarrhythmics (e.g., propafenone and flecainide), should be approached with caution and should be initiated at the lower end of the dose range of the concomitant medication.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M229" type="Trigger" span="370 5;387 4" str="lower | dose"/>
<Mention id="M206" type="Precipitant" span="97 15" str="antidepressants" code="N0000029147 | N0000178314"/>
<Mention id="M208" type="Precipitant" span="142 14" str="antipsychotics" code="N0000029150 | N0000178316"/>
<Mention id="M210" type="Precipitant" span="208 13" str="beta-blockers" code="N0000000161 | N0000175556"/>
<Mention id="M212" type="Precipitant" span="34 36" str="drugs that are metabolized by CYP2D6" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M214" type="Precipitant" span="292 10" str="flecainide" code="N0000006966 | K94FTS1806"/>
<Mention id="M216" type="Precipitant" span="164 11" str="haloperidol" code="J6292F8L3D | N0000006048"/>
<Mention id="M218" type="Precipitant" span="229 10" str="metoprolol" code="GEB06NHM23"/>
<Mention id="M220" type="Precipitant" span="276 11" str="propafenone" code="68IQX3T69U"/>
<Mention id="M222" type="Precipitant" span="177 11" str="risperidone" code="L6UH7ZF8HC"/>
<Mention id="M224" type="Precipitant" span="114 5" str="SSRIs" code="N0000175696"/>
<Mention id="M226" type="Precipitant" span="193 12" str="thioridazine" code="N3D6TG58NI"/>
<Mention id="M228" type="Precipitant" span="129 10" str="tricyclics" code="N0000029148 | N0000175752"/>
<Mention id="M230" type="Precipitant" span="245 23" str="Type 1C antiarrhythmics" code="N0000029121 | N0000175426"/>
<Interaction id="I89" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M229" precipitant="M206" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I90" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M229" precipitant="M208" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I91" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M229" precipitant="M210" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I92" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M229" precipitant="M212" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I93" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M229" precipitant="M214" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I94" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M229" precipitant="M216" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I95" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M229" precipitant="M218" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I96" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M229" precipitant="M220" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I97" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M229" precipitant="M222" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I98" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M229" precipitant="M224" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I99" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M229" precipitant="M226" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I100" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M229" precipitant="M228" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I101" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M229" precipitant="M230" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10110" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>If CONTRAVE is added to the treatment regimen of a patient already receiving a drug metabolized by CYP2D6, the need to decrease the dose of the original medication should be considered, particularly for those concomitant medications with a narrow therapeutic index.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M231" type="Trigger" span="119 17" str="decrease the dose"/>
<Mention id="M232" type="Precipitant" span="79 26" str="drug metabolized by CYP2D6" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I102" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M231" precipitant="M232" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10111" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Bupropion is primarily metabolized to hydroxybupropion by CYP2B6.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10112" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Therefore, the potential exists for drug interactions between CONTRAVE and drugs that are inhibitors or inducers of CYP2B6.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M235" type="Trigger" span="41 12" str="interactions"/>
<Mention id="M234" type="Precipitant" span="104 18" str="inducers of CYP2B6" code="N0000187064"/>
<Mention id="M236" type="Precipitant" span="90 10;113 9" str="inhibitors | of CYP2B6" code="N0000182139"/>
<Interaction id="I103" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M235" precipitant="M234"/>
<Interaction id="I104" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M235" precipitant="M236"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10113" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Inhibitors of CYP2B6: Ticlopidine and Clopidogrel: Concomitant treatment with these drugs can increase bupropion exposure but decrease hydroxybupropion exposure.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M241" type="Trigger" span="94 8;113 8" str="increase | exposure"/>
<Mention id="M238" type="Precipitant" span="38 11" str="Clopidogrel" code="A74586SNO7 | N0000007277"/>
<Mention id="M240" type="Precipitant" span="0 20" str="Inhibitors of CYP2B6" code="N0000182139"/>
<Mention id="M242" type="Precipitant" span="22 11" str="Ticlopidine" code="OM90ZUW7M1"/>
<Interaction id="I105" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M241" precipitant="M238" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I106" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M241" precipitant="M240" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I107" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M241" precipitant="M242" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10114" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>During concomitant use with CYP2B6 inhibitors (e.g., ticlopidine or clopidogrel), the CONTRAVE daily dose should not exceed two tablets (one tablet each morning and evening).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M247" type="Trigger" span="101 22" str="dose should not exceed"/>
<Mention id="M244" type="Precipitant" span="68 11" str="clopidogrel" code="A74586SNO7 | N0000007277"/>
<Mention id="M246" type="Precipitant" span="28 17" str="CYP2B6 inhibitors" code="N0000182139"/>
<Mention id="M248" type="Precipitant" span="53 11" str="ticlopidine" code="OM90ZUW7M1"/>
<Interaction id="I108" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M247" precipitant="M244" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I109" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M247" precipitant="M246" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I110" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M247" precipitant="M248" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10115" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Inducers of CYP2B6: Ritonavir, Lopinavir, and Efavirenz: Concomitant treatment with these drugs can decrease bupropion and hydroxybupropion exposure and may reduce efficacy.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M258" type="Trigger" span="157 15" str="reduce efficacy"/>
<Mention id="M262" type="Precipitant" span="46 9" str="Efavirenz" code="JE6H2O27P8"/>
<Mention id="M260" type="SpecificInteraction" span="109 9;157 15" str="bupropion | reduce efficacy" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M264" type="Precipitant" span="0 18" str="Inducers of CYP2B6" code="N0000187064"/>
<Mention id="M266" type="Precipitant" span="31 9" str="Lopinavir" code="2494G1JF75"/>
<Mention id="M268" type="Precipitant" span="20 9" str="Ritonavir" code="O3J8G9O825 | N0000007423"/>
<Mention id="M267" type="Trigger" span="100 8;140 8" str="decrease | exposure"/>
<Interaction id="I111" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M258" precipitant="M262" effect="M260" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I112" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M258" precipitant="M264" effect="M260" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I113" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M258" precipitant="M266" effect="M260" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I114" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M258" precipitant="M268" effect="M260" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I115" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M267" precipitant="M262" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I116" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M267" precipitant="M264" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I117" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M267" precipitant="M266" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I118" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M267" precipitant="M268" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10116" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Avoiding concomitant use with ritonavir, lopinavir, or efavirenz is recommended.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M273" type="Trigger" span="0 5" str="Avoid"/>
<Mention id="M270" type="Precipitant" span="55 9" str="efavirenz" code="JE6H2O27P8"/>
<Mention id="M272" type="Precipitant" span="41 9" str="lopinavir" code="2494G1JF75"/>
<Mention id="M274" type="Precipitant" span="30 9" str="ritonavir" code="O3J8G9O825 | N0000007423"/>
<Interaction id="I119" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M273" precipitant="M270"/>
<Interaction id="I120" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M273" precipitant="M272"/>
<Interaction id="I121" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M273" precipitant="M274"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10117" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Use extreme caution when coadministering CONTRAVE with other drugs that lower seizure threshold (e.g., antipsychotics, antidepressants, theophylline, or systemic corticosteroids).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M283" type="Trigger" span="12 7" str="caution"/>
<Mention id="M276" type="Precipitant" span="119 15" str="antidepressants" code="N0000029147 | N0000178314"/>
<Mention id="M278" type="Precipitant" span="103 14" str="antipsychotics" code="N0000029150 | N0000178316"/>
<Mention id="M280" type="Precipitant" span="61 34" str="drugs that lower seizure threshold" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M282" type="Precipitant" span="153 24" str="systemic corticosteroids" code="N0000175576"/>
<Mention id="M284" type="Precipitant" span="136 12" str="theophylline" code="N0000007076 | C137DTR5RG"/>
<Interaction id="I122" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M283" precipitant="M276"/>
<Interaction id="I123" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M283" precipitant="M278"/>
<Interaction id="I124" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M283" precipitant="M280"/>
<Interaction id="I125" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M283" precipitant="M282"/>
<Interaction id="I126" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M283" precipitant="M284"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10118" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Use low initial doses and increase the dose gradually.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10119" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant use of other bupropion-containing products is contraindicated.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M285" type="Trigger" span="58 15" str="contraindicated"/>
<Mention id="M286" type="Precipitant" span="25 29" str="bupropion-containing products" code="01ZG3TPX31"/>
<Interaction id="I127" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M285" precipitant="M286"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10120" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Bupropion, levodopa, and amantadine have dopamine agonist effects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10121" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>CNS toxicity has been reported when bupropion was coadministered with levodopa or amantadine.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M292" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 12" str="CNS toxicity" code="246557006: Central nervous system symptom (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M288" type="Precipitant" span="82 10" str="amantadine" code="BF4C9Z1J53"/>
<Mention id="M291" type="Precipitant" span="70 8" str="levodopa" code="46627O600J"/>
<Interaction id="I128" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M292" precipitant="M288" effect="M292" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I129" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M292" precipitant="M291" effect="M292" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10122" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Adverse reactions have included restlessness, agitation, tremor, ataxia, gait disturbance, vertigo, and dizziness.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10123" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>It is presumed that the toxicity results from cumulative dopamine agonist effects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10124" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Use caution and monitor for such adverse reactions when administering CONTRAVE concomitantly with these drugs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10125" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>In postmarketing experience, there have been rare reports of adverse neuropsychiatric events or reduced alcohol tolerance in patients who were drinking alcohol during treatment with bupropion.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M296" type="Trigger" span="61 7;86 6" str="adverse | events"/>
<Mention id="M297" type="Precipitant" span="104 7" str="alcohol" code="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M"/>
<Mention id="M295" type="SpecificInteraction" span="61 31" str="adverse neuropsychiatric events" code="10171000132106: Behavioral and psychological symptoms of dementia (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M298" type="SpecificInteraction" span="96 25" str="reduced alcohol tolerance" code="228353006: Reverse tolerance to alcohol (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I130" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M296" precipitant="M297" effect="M295" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I131" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M296" precipitant="M297" effect="M298" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10126" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The consumption of alcohol during treatment with CONTRAVE should be minimized or avoided.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M299" type="Trigger" span="58 19" str="should be minimized "/>
<Mention id="M300" type="Trigger" span="58 9;81 7" str=" should be | avoided"/>
<Mention id="M301" type="Precipitant" span="19 7" str="alcohol" code="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M"/>
<Interaction id="I132" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M299;M300" precipitant="M301"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10127" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>False-positive urine immunoassay screening tests for amphetamines have been reported in patients taking bupropion.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M302" type="Trigger" span="0 5;43 5" str="False | tests"/>
<Mention id="M303" type="Precipitant" span="53 12" str="amphetamines" code="CK833KGX7E | N0000007883"/>
<Mention id="M304" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 65" str="False-positive urine immunoassay screening tests for amphetamines" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I133" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M302" precipitant="M303" effect="M304" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10128" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>This is due to lack of specificity of some screening tests.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10129" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>False-positive test results may result even following discontinuation of bupropion therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10130" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Confirmatory tests, such as gas chromatography/mass spectrometry, will distinguish bupropion from amphetamines.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10131" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>In vitro, CONTRAVE constituents inhibited the renal organic cation transporter OCT2 to a clinically relevant level.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10132" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The systemic concentrations of substrate drugs transported by OCT2 (such as amantadine, amiloride, cimetidine, dopamine, famotidine, memantine, metformin, pindolol, procainamide, ranitidine, varenicline, oxaliplatin) are likely to increase as a result of reduced renal clearance when coadministered with CONTRAVE.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M341" type="Trigger" span="4 23;231 8" str="systemic concentrations | increase "/>
<Mention id="M342" type="Trigger" span="255 23" str=" reduced renal clearance"/>
<Mention id="M307" type="Precipitant" span="76 10" str="amantadine" code="BF4C9Z1J53"/>
<Mention id="M310" type="Precipitant" span="88 9" str="amiloride" code="7DZO8EB0Z3 | N0000006772"/>
<Mention id="M313" type="Precipitant" span="99 10" str="cimetidine" code="80061L1WGD"/>
<Mention id="M316" type="Precipitant" span="111 8" str="dopamine" code="N0000006091 | VTD58H1Z2X"/>
<Mention id="M319" type="Precipitant" span="41 25" str="drugs transported by OCT2" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M322" type="Precipitant" span="121 10" str="famotidine" code="5QZO15J2Z8"/>
<Mention id="M325" type="Precipitant" span="133 9" str="memantine" code="W8O17SJF3T"/>
<Mention id="M328" type="Precipitant" span="144 9" str="metformin" code="9100L32L2N"/>
<Mention id="M331" type="Precipitant" span="204 11" str="oxaliplatin" code="04ZR38536J"/>
<Mention id="M334" type="Precipitant" span="155 8" str="pindolol" code="BJ4HF6IU1D"/>
<Mention id="M337" type="Precipitant" span="165 12" str="procainamide" code="N0000005813 | L39WTC366D"/>
<Mention id="M340" type="Precipitant" span="179 10" str="ranitidine" code="884KT10YB7"/>
<Mention id="M343" type="Precipitant" span="191 11" str="varenicline" code="W6HS99O8ZO"/>
<Interaction id="I134" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M341;M342" precipitant="M307" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I135" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M341;M342" precipitant="M310" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I136" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M341;M342" precipitant="M313" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I137" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M341;M342" precipitant="M316" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I138" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M341;M342" precipitant="M319" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I139" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M341;M342" precipitant="M322" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I140" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M341;M342" precipitant="M325" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I141" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M341;M342" precipitant="M328" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I142" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M341;M342" precipitant="M331" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I143" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M341;M342" precipitant="M334" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I144" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M341;M342" precipitant="M337" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I145" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M341;M342" precipitant="M340" effect="C54357"/>
<Interaction id="I146" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M341;M342" precipitant="M343" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10133" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Coadministration of CONTRAVE with such drugs should be approached with caution and patients should be monitored for adverse effects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10134" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Suicidal Behavior and Ideation: Monitor for depression or suicidal thoughts.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10135" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Discontinue CONTRAVE if symptoms develop.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10136" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Risk of seizure may be minimized by adhering to the recommended dosing schedule and avoiding coadministration with high-fat meal.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M344" type="Trigger" span="0 7" str="Risk of"/>
<Mention id="M345" type="Precipitant" span="115 13" str="high-fat meal" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M346" type="SpecificInteraction" span="8 7" str="seizure" code="91175000: Seizure (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I147" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M344" precipitant="M345" effect="M346" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10137" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Increase in Blood Pressure and Heart Rate: Monitor blood pressure and heart rate in all patients, especially those with cardiac or cerebrovascular disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10138" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Hepatotoxicity: Cases of hepatitis and clinically significant liver dysfunction observed with naltrexone exposure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10139" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Angle-closure glaucoma: Angle-closure glaucoma has occurred in patients with untreated anatomically narrow angles treated with antidepressants.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M347" type="Trigger" span="51 8" str="occurred"/>
<Mention id="M348" type="Precipitant" span="127 15" str="antidepressants" code="N0000029147 | N0000178314"/>
<Mention id="M349" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 22" str="Angle-closure glaucoma" code="392291006: Angle-closure glaucoma (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I148" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M347" precipitant="M348" effect="M349" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10140" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Use of Antidiabetic Medications: Weight loss may cause hypoglycemia.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M350" type="Trigger" span="49 5" str="cause"/>
<Mention id="M351" type="Precipitant" span="7 24" str="Antidiabetic Medications" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M352" type="SpecificInteraction" span="55 12" str="hypoglycemia" code="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I149" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M350" precipitant="M351" effect="M352" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10141" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>CONTRAVE contains bupropion, a dopamine and norepinephrine re-uptake inhibitor that is similar to some drugs used for the treatment of depression; therefore, the following precautions pertaining to these products should be considered when treating patients with CONTRAVE.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10142" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients with major depressive disorder, both adult and pediatric, may experience worsening of their depression and/or the emergence of suicidal ideation and behavior (suicidality) or unusual changes in behavior, whether or not they are taking antidepressant medications, and this risk may persist until significant remission occurs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10143" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Suicide is a known risk of depression and certain other psychiatric disorders, and these disorders themselves are the strongest predictors of suicide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10144" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There has been a long-standing concern that antidepressants may have a role in inducing worsening of depression and the emergence of suicidality in certain patients during the early phases of treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10145" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In placebo-controlled clinical trials with CONTRAVE for the treatment of obesity in adult patients, no suicides or suicide attempts were reported in studies up to 56 weeks duration with CONTRAVE (equivalent to bupropion doses of 360 mg/day).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10146" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In these same studies, suicidal ideation was reported by 3 (0.20%) of 1,515 patients treated with placebo compared with 1 (0.03%) of 3,239 treated with CONTRAVE.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10147" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Pooled analyses of short-term placebo-controlled trials of antidepressant drugs (selective serotonin re-uptake inhibitors [SSRIs] and others) show that these drugs increase the risk of suicidal thinking and behavior (suicidality) in children, adolescents, and young adults (ages 18 to 24) with major depressive disorder (MDD) and other psychiatric disorders.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10148" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Short-term clinical trials did not show an increase in the risk of suicidality with antidepressants compared with placebo in adults beyond age 24; there was a reduction with antidepressants compared with placebo in adults aged 65 and older.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10149" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The pooled analyses of placebo-controlled trials of antidepressant drugs in children and adolescents with MDD, obsessive compulsive disorder (OCD), or other psychiatric disorders included a total of 24 short-term trials of nine antidepressant drugs in over 4,400 patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10150" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The pooled analyses of placebo-controlled trials in adults with MDD or other psychiatric disorders included a total of 295 short-term trials (median duration of two months) of 11 antidepressant drugs in over 77,000 patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10151" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There was considerable variation in risk of suicidality among drugs, but a tendency toward an increase in the younger patients for almost all drugs studied.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10152" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There were differences in absolute risk of suicidality across the different indications, with the highest incidence in MDD.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10153" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The risk differences (drug vs placebo), however, were relatively stable within age strata and across indications.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10154" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>These risk differences (drug-placebo difference in the number of cases of suicidality per 1,000 patients treated) are provided in Table 2.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10155" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Risk Differences in the Number of Suicidality Cases by Age Group in the Pooled Placebo-Controlled Trials of Antidepressants in Pediatric and Adult Subjects Age Range Drug-Placebo Difference in Number of Cases of Suicidality per 1,000 Patients Treated Increases Compared to Placebo &lt;18 14 additional cases 18 to 24 5 additional cases Decreases Compared to Placebo 25 to 64 1 fewer case ≥65 6 fewer cases No suicides occurred in any of the antidepressant pediatric trials.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10156" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There were suicides in the adult antidepressant trials, but the number was not sufficient to reach any conclusion about drug effect on suicide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10157" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>It is unknown whether the suicidality risk extends to longer-term use, i.e., beyond several months.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10158" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>However, there is substantial evidence from placebo-controlled trials in adults with depression that the use of antidepressants can delay the recurrence of depression.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10159" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>All patients being treated with antidepressants for any indication should be monitored appropriately and observed closely for clinical worsening, suicidality, and unusual changes in behavior, especially during the initial few months of a course of drug therapy, or at times of dose changes, either increases or decreases.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10160" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>This warning applies to CONTRAVE because one of its components, bupropion, is a member of an antidepressant class.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10161" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The following symptoms, anxiety, agitation, panic attacks, insomnia, irritability, hostility, aggressiveness, impulsivity, akathisia (psychomotor restlessness), hypomania, and mania, have been reported in adult and pediatric patients being treated with antidepressants for major depressive disorder as well as for other indications, both psychiatric and nonpsychiatric.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10162" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Although a causal link between the emergence of such symptoms and either the worsening of depression and/or the emergence of suicidal impulses has not been established, there is concern that such symptoms may represent precursors to emerging suicidality.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10163" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Consideration should be given to changing the therapeutic regimen, including possibly discontinuing the medication, in patients whose depression is persistently worse, or who are experiencing emergent suicidality or symptoms that might be precursors to worsening depression or suicidality, especially if these symptoms are severe, abrupt in onset, or were not part of the patient’s presenting symptoms.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10164" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Families and caregivers of patients being treated with antidepressants for major depressive disorder or other indications, both psychiatric and nonpsychiatric, should be alerted about the need to monitor patients for the emergence of anxiety, agitation, irritability, unusual changes in behavior, and the other symptoms described above, as well as the emergence of suicidality, and to report such symptoms immediately to healthcare providers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10165" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Such monitoring should include daily observation by families and caregivers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10166" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Prescriptions for CONTRAVE should be written for the smallest quantity of tablets consistent with good patient management, in order to reduce the risk of overdose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10167" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>CONTRAVE is not approved for smoking cessation treatment, but serious neuropsychiatric symptoms have been reported in patients taking bupropion for smoking cessation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10168" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>These have included changes in mood (including depression and mania), psychosis, hallucinations, paranoia, delusions, homicidal ideation, hostility, agitation, aggression, anxiety, and panic, as well as suicidal ideation, suicide attempt, and completed suicide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10169" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Observe patients for the occurrence of neuropsychiatric reactions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10170" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Instruct patients to contact a healthcare professional if such reactions occur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10171" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In many of these cases, a causal relationship to bupropion treatment is not certain, because depressed mood can be a symptom of nicotine withdrawal.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10172" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Depression, suicide, attempted suicide and suicidal ideation have been reported in the postmarketing experience with naltrexone used in the treatment of opioid dependence.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10173" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>No causal relationship has been demonstrated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10174" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Bupropion, a component of CONTRAVE, can cause seizures.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10175" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The incidence of seizure in patients receiving CONTRAVE in clinical trials was approximately 0.1% vs 0% on placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10176" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>CONTRAVE should be discontinued and not restarted in patients who experience a seizure while being treated with CONTRAVE.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10177" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The risk of seizures is also related to patient factors, clinical situations, and concomitant medications that lower the seizure threshold.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10178" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Consider these risks before initiating treatment with CONTRAVE.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10179" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>CONTRAVE is contraindicated in patients with a seizure disorder, current or prior diagnosis of anorexia nervosa or bulimia, or undergoing abrupt discontinuation of alcohol, benzodiazepines, barbiturates, and antiepileptic drugs.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M359" type="Trigger" span="12 15;145 15" str="contraindicated | discontinuation"/>
<Mention id="M354" type="Precipitant" span="164 7" str="alcohol" code="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M"/>
<Mention id="M356" type="Precipitant" span="208 19" str="antiepileptic drugs" code="N0000175753"/>
<Mention id="M358" type="Precipitant" span="190 12" str="barbiturates" code="N0000175693 | N0000008016"/>
<Mention id="M360" type="Precipitant" span="173 15" str="benzodiazepines" code="N0000007542 | N0000175694"/>
<Interaction id="I150" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M359" precipitant="M354"/>
<Interaction id="I151" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M359" precipitant="M356"/>
<Interaction id="I152" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M359" precipitant="M358"/>
<Interaction id="I153" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M359" precipitant="M360"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10180" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Caution should be used when prescribing CONTRAVE to patients with predisposing factors that may increase the risk of seizure including: history of head trauma or prior seizure, severe stroke, arteriovenous malformation, central nervous system tumor or infection, or metabolic disorders (e.g., hypoglycemia, hyponatremia, severe hepatic impairment, and hypoxia) excessive use of alcohol or sedatives, addiction to cocaine or stimulants, or withdrawal from sedatives patients with diabetes treated with insulin and/or oral diabetic medications (sulfonylureas and meglitinides) that may cause hypoglycemia concomitant administration of medications that may lower the seizure threshold, including other bupropion products, antipsychotics, tricyclic antidepressants, theophylline, systemic steroids Recommendations for Reducing the Risk of Seizure: Clinical experience with bupropion suggests that the risk of seizure may be minimized by adhering to the recommended dosing recommendations, in particular: the total daily dose of CONTRAVE does not exceed 360 mg of the bupropion component (i.e., four tablets per day) the daily dose is administered in divided doses (twice daily) the dose is escalated gradually no more than two tablets are taken at one time coadministration of CONTRAVE with high-fat meals is avoided if a dose is missed, a patient should wait until the next scheduled dose to resume the regular dosing schedule Vulnerability to Opioid Overdose: CONTRAVE should not be administered to patients receiving chronic opioids, due to the naltrexone component, which is an opioid receptor antagonist.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M388" type="Trigger" span="654 5" str="lower"/>
<Mention id="M362" type="Precipitant" span="719 14" str="antipsychotics" code="N0000029150 | N0000178316"/>
<Mention id="M390" type="SpecificInteraction" span="654 27" str="lower the seizure threshold" code="91175000: Seizure (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M365" type="Precipitant" span="699 18" str="bupropion products" code="01ZG3TPX31"/>
<Mention id="M379" type="Trigger" span="584 5" str="cause"/>
<Mention id="M368" type="Precipitant" span="501 7" str="insulin" code="N0000004931 | N0000175944"/>
<Mention id="M381" type="SpecificInteraction" span="293 12" str="hypoglycemia" code="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M371" type="Precipitant" span="633 48" str="medications that may lower the seizure threshold" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M374" type="Precipitant" span="561 12" str="meglitinides" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M377" type="Precipitant" span="516 25" str="oral diabetic medications" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M380" type="Precipitant" span="543 13" str="sulfonylureas" code="N0000175608 | N0000008054"/>
<Mention id="M383" type="Precipitant" span="776 17" str="systemic steroids" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M386" type="Precipitant" span="762 12" str="theophylline" code="N0000007076 | C137DTR5RG"/>
<Mention id="M389" type="Precipitant" span="735 25" str="tricyclic antidepressants" code="N0000029148 | N0000175752"/>
<Mention id="M401" type="Trigger" span="0 7" str="Caution"/>
<Mention id="M392" type="Precipitant" span="378 7" str="alcohol" code="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M"/>
<Mention id="M393" type="Trigger" span="1467 26" str="should not be administered"/>
<Mention id="M394" type="Precipitant" span="1516 15" str="chronic opioids" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M396" type="Precipitant" span="413 7" str="cocaine" code="I5Y540LHVR"/>
<Mention id="M397" type="Trigger" span="1305 5" str="avoid"/>
<Mention id="M398" type="Precipitant" span="1287 14" str="high-fat meals" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M400" type="Precipitant" span="389 9" str="sedatives" code="N0000029143 | N0000193842"/>
<Mention id="M402" type="Precipitant" span="424 10" str="stimulants" code="N0000175739"/>
<Interaction id="I154" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M388" precipitant="M362" effect="M390" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I155" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M388" precipitant="M365" effect="M390" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I156" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M379" precipitant="M368" effect="M381" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I157" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M388" precipitant="M371" effect="M390" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I158" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M379" precipitant="M374" effect="M381" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I159" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M379" precipitant="M377" effect="M381" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I160" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M379" precipitant="M380" effect="M381" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I161" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M388" precipitant="M383" effect="M390" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I162" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M388" precipitant="M386" effect="M390" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I163" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M388" precipitant="M389" effect="M390" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I164" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M401" precipitant="M392"/>
<Interaction id="I165" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M393" precipitant="M394"/>
<Interaction id="I166" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M401" precipitant="M396"/>
<Interaction id="I167" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M397" precipitant="M398"/>
<Interaction id="I168" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M401" precipitant="M400"/>
<Interaction id="I169" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M401" precipitant="M402"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10181" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If chronic opiate therapy is required, CONTRAVE treatment should be stopped.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M403" type="Trigger" span="58 17" str="should be stopped"/>
<Mention id="M404" type="Precipitant" span="3 22" str="chronic opiate therapy" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I170" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M403" precipitant="M404"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10182" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In patients requiring intermittent opiate treatment, CONTRAVE therapy should be temporarily discontinued and lower doses of opioids may be needed.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M405" type="Trigger" span="92 12" str="discontinued "/>
<Mention id="M406" type="Trigger" span="109 11" str=" lower doses"/>
<Mention id="M407" type="Precipitant" span="22 29" str="intermittent opiate treatment" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I171" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M405;M406" precipitant="M407"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10183" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients should be alerted that they may be more sensitive to opioids, even at lower doses, after CONTRAVE treatment is discontinued.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M408" type="Trigger" span="44 14" str="more sensitive"/>
<Mention id="M409" type="Precipitant" span="62 7" str="opioids" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M410" type="SpecificInteraction" span="44 25" str="more sensitive to opioids" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I172" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M408" precipitant="M409" effect="M410" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10184" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>An attempt by a patient to overcome any naltrexone opioid blockade by administering large amounts of exogenous opioids is especially dangerous and may lead to a fatal overdose or life-threatening opioid intoxication (e.g., respiratory arrest, circulatory collapse).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M420" type="Trigger" span="151 7" str="lead to"/>
<Mention id="M421" type="Precipitant" span="101 17" str="exogenous opioids" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M413" type="SpecificInteraction" span="243 20" str="circulatory collapse" code="27942005: Shock (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M416" type="SpecificInteraction" span="161 14" str="fatal overdose" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M419" type="SpecificInteraction" span="179 36" str="life-threatening opioid intoxication" code="77721001: Opioid intoxication (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M422" type="SpecificInteraction" span="223 18" str="respiratory arrest" code="87317003: Respiratory arrest (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I173" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M420" precipitant="M421" effect="M413" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I174" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M420" precipitant="M421" effect="M416" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I175" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M420" precipitant="M421" effect="M419" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I176" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M420" precipitant="M421" effect="M422" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10185" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients should be told of the serious consequences of trying to overcome the opioid blockade.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10186" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Precipitated Opioid Withdrawal: The symptoms of spontaneous opioid withdrawal, which are associated with the discontinuation of opioid in a dependent individual, are uncomfortable, but they are not generally believed to be severe or necessitate hospitalization.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M426" type="Trigger" span="89 35" str="associated with the discontinuation"/>
<Mention id="M427" type="Precipitant" span="13 6" str="opioid" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M425" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 30" str="Precipitated Opioid Withdrawal" code="87132004: Opioid withdrawal (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M428" type="SpecificInteraction" span="36 41" str="symptoms of spontaneous opioid withdrawal" code="87132004: Opioid withdrawal (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I177" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M426" precipitant="M427" effect="M425" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I178" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M426" precipitant="M427" effect="M428" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10187" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>However, when withdrawal is precipitated abruptly, the resulting withdrawal syndrome can be severe enough to require hospitalization.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10188" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>To prevent occurrence of either precipitated withdrawal in patients dependent on opioids or exacerbation of a pre-existing subclinical withdrawal symptoms, opioid-dependent patients, including those being treated for alcohol dependence, should be opioid-free (including tramadol) before starting CONTRAVE treatment.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M444" type="Trigger" span="45 10" str="withdrawal"/>
<Mention id="M433" type="Precipitant" span="217 7" str="alcohol" code="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M"/>
<Mention id="M443" type="SpecificInteraction" span="92 15;135 19" str="exacerbation of | withdrawal symptoms" code="363101005: Drug withdrawal (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M446" type="SpecificInteraction" span="32 23;81 7" str="precipitated withdrawal | opioids" code="87132004: Opioid withdrawal (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M439" type="Precipitant" span="81 6" str="opioid" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M445" type="Precipitant" span="270 8" str="tramadol" code="39J1LGJ30J"/>
<Interaction id="I179" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M444" precipitant="M433" effect="M443" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I180" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M444" precipitant="M433" effect="M446" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I181" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M444" precipitant="M439" effect="M443" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I182" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M444" precipitant="M439" effect="M446" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I183" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M444" precipitant="M445" effect="M443" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I184" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M444" precipitant="M445" effect="M446" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10189" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>An opioid-free interval of a minimum of 7 to 10 days is recommended for patients previously dependent on short-acting opioids, and those patients transitioning from buprenorphine or methadone may need as long as two weeks.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M453" type="Trigger" span="10 13" str="free interval"/>
<Mention id="M448" type="Precipitant" span="165 13" str="buprenorphine" code="40D3SCR4GZ"/>
<Mention id="M450" type="Precipitant" span="182 9" str="methadone" code="UC6VBE7V1Z"/>
<Mention id="M452" type="Precipitant" span="3 6" str="opioid" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M454" type="Precipitant" span="105 20" str="short-acting opioids" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I185" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M453" precipitant="M448"/>
<Interaction id="I186" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M453" precipitant="M450"/>
<Interaction id="I187" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M453" precipitant="M452"/>
<Interaction id="I188" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M453" precipitant="M454"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10190" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients should be made aware of the risks associated with precipitated withdrawal and encouraged to give an accurate account of last opioid use.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M455" type="Trigger" span="37 5" str="risks "/>
<Mention id="M456" type="Trigger" span="43 15" str=" associated with"/>
<Mention id="M457" type="Precipitant" span="134 6" str="opioid" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M458" type="SpecificInteraction" span="59 23" str="precipitated withdrawal" code="363101005: Drug withdrawal (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I189" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M455;M456" precipitant="M457" effect="M458" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10191" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>CONTRAVE can cause an increase in systolic and/or diastolic blood pressure as well as an increase in resting heart rate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10192" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In clinical practice with other bupropion-containing products, hypertension, in some cases severe and requiring acute treatment, has been reported.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10193" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The clinical significance of the increases in blood pressure and heart rate observed with CONTRAVE treatment is unclear, especially for patients with cardiac and cerebrovascular disease, since patients with a history of myocardial infarction or stroke in the previous 6 months, life-threatening arrhythmias, or congestive heart failure were excluded from CONTRAVE clinical trials.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10194" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Blood pressure and pulse should be measured prior to starting therapy with CONTRAVE and should be monitored at regular intervals consistent with usual clinical practice, particularly among patients with controlled hypertension prior to treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10195" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>CONTRAVE should not be given to patients with uncontrolled hypertension.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10196" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Among patients treated with CONTRAVE in placebo-controlled clinical trials, mean systolic and diastolic blood pressure was approximately 1 mmHg higher than baseline at Weeks 4 and 8, similar to baseline at Week 12, and approximately 1 mmHg below baseline between Weeks 24 and 56.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10197" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In contrast, among patients treated with placebo, mean blood pressure was approximately 2 to 3 mmHg below baseline throughout the same time points, yielding statistically significant differences between the groups at every assessment during this period.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10198" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The largest mean differences between the groups were observed during the first 12 weeks (treatment difference +1.8 to +2.4 mmHg systolic, all p&lt;0.001; +1.7 to +2.1 mmHg diastolic, all p&lt;0.001).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10199" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>For heart rate, at both Weeks 4 and 8, mean heart rate was statistically significantly higher (2.1 bpm) in the CONTRAVE group compared with the placebo group; at Week 52, the difference between groups was +1.7 bpm (p&lt;0.001).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10200" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In an ambulatory blood pressure monitoring substudy of 182 patients, the mean change from baseline in systolic blood pressure after 52 weeks of treatment was -0.2 mmHg for the CONTRAVE group and -2.8 mmHg for the placebo group (treatment difference, +2.6 mmHg, p=0.08); the mean change in diastolic blood pressure was +0.8 mmHg for the CONTRAVE group and -2.1 mmHg for the placebo group (treatment difference, +2.9 mmHg, p=0.004).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10201" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>A greater percentage of subjects had adverse reactions related to blood pressure or heart rate in the CONTRAVE group compared to the placebo group (6.3% vs 4.2%, respectively), primarily attributable to adverse reactions of Hypertension/Blood Pressure Increased (5.9% vs 4.0%, respectively).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10202" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>These events were observed in both patients with and without evidence of preexisting hypertension.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10203" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In a trial that enrolled individuals with diabetes, 12.0% of patients in the CONTRAVE group and 6.5% in the placebo group had a blood pressure-related adverse reaction.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10204" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Anaphylactoid/anaphylactic reactions characterized by symptoms such as pruritus, urticaria, angioedema, and dyspnea requiring medical treatment have been reported in clinical trials with bupropion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10205" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In addition, there have been rare spontaneous postmarketing reports of erythema multiforme, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, and anaphylactic shock associated with bupropion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10206" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Instruct patients to discontinue CONTRAVE and consult a healthcare provider if they develop an allergic or anaphylactoid/anaphylactic reaction (e.g., skin rash, pruritus, hives, chest pain, edema, or shortness of breath) during treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10207" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Arthralgia, myalgia, fever with rash, and other symptoms suggestive of delayed hypersensitivity have been reported in association with bupropion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10208" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>These symptoms may resemble serum sickness.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10209" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Cases of hepatitis and clinically significant liver dysfunction were observed in association with naltrexone exposure during naltrexone clinical trials and in postmarketing reports for patients using naltrexone.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10210" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Transient, asymptomatic hepatic transaminase elevations were also observed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10211" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>When patients presented with elevated transaminases, there were often other potential causative or contributory etiologies identified, including pre-existing alcoholic liver disease, hepatitis B and/or C infection, and concomitant usage of other potentially hepatotoxic drugs.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M459" type="Trigger" span="14 14" str="presented with"/>
<Mention id="M460" type="Precipitant" span="246 29" str="potentially hepatotoxic drugs" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M461" type="SpecificInteraction" span="29 22" str="elevated transaminases" code="160931000119108: Increased aspartate transaminase level (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I190" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M459" precipitant="M460" effect="M461" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10212" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Although clinically significant liver dysfunction is not typically recognized as a manifestation of opioid withdrawal, opioid withdrawal that is precipitated abruptly may lead to systemic sequelae, including acute liver injury.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10213" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients should be warned of the risk of hepatic injury and advised to seek medical attention if they experience symptoms of acute hepatitis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10214" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Use of CONTRAVE should be discontinued in the event of symptoms and/or signs of acute hepatitis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10215" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In CONTRAVE clinical trials, there were no cases of elevated transaminases greater than three times the upper limit of normal (ULN) in conjunction with an increase in bilirubin greater than two times ULN.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10216" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Bupropion, a component of CONTRAVE, is a drug used for the treatment of depression.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10217" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Antidepressant treatment can precipitate a manic, mixed, or hypomanic episode.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10218" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The risk appears to be increased in patients with bipolar disorder or who have risk factors for bipolar disorder.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10219" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Prior to initiating CONTRAVE, screen patients for a history of bipolar disorder and the presence of risk factors for bipolar disorder (e.g., family history of bipolar disorder, suicide, or depression).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10220" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>CONTRAVE is not approved for use in treating bipolar depression.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10221" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>No activation of mania or hypomania was reported in the clinical trials evaluating effects of CONTRAVE in obese patients; however, patients receiving antidepressant medications and patients with a history of bipolar disorder or recent hospitalization because of psychiatric illness were excluded from CONTRAVE clinical trials.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10222" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The pupillary dilation that occurs following use of many antidepressant drugs including bupropion, a component of CONTRAVE, may trigger an angle-closure attack in a patient with anatomically narrow angles who does not have a patent iridectomy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10223" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Weight loss may increase the risk of hypoglycemia in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus treated with insulin and/or insulin secretagogues (e.g., sulfonylureas).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M468" type="Trigger" span="16 17" str="increase the risk"/>
<Mention id="M463" type="Precipitant" span="105 7" str="insulin" code="N0000004931 | N0000175944"/>
<Mention id="M470" type="SpecificInteraction" span="37 12" str="hypoglycemia" code="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M466" type="Precipitant" span="120 21" str="insulin secretagogues" code="N0000009360"/>
<Mention id="M469" type="Precipitant" span="149 13" str="sulfonylureas" code="N0000175608 | N0000008054"/>
<Interaction id="I191" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M468" precipitant="M463" effect="M470" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I192" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M468" precipitant="M466" effect="M470" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I193" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M468" precipitant="M469" effect="M470" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10224" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Measurement of blood glucose levels prior to starting CONTRAVE and during CONTRAVE treatment is recommended in patients with type 2 diabetes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10225" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Decreases in medication doses for antidiabetic medications which are non-glucose-dependent should be considered to mitigate the risk of hypoglycemia.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M471" type="Trigger" span="128 7" str="risk of"/>
<Mention id="M472" type="Precipitant" span="34 24" str="antidiabetic medications" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M473" type="SpecificInteraction" span="136 12" str="hypoglycemia" code="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I194" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M471" precipitant="M472" effect="M473" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10226" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If a patient develops hypoglycemia after starting CONTRAVE, appropriate changes should be made to the antidiabetic drug regimen.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M474" type="Trigger" span="0 2;13 8" str="If | develops"/>
<Mention id="M475" type="Precipitant" span="102 17" str="antidiabetic drug" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M476" type="SpecificInteraction" span="22 12" str="hypoglycemia" code="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I195" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M474" precipitant="M475" effect="M476" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10227" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>CONTRAVE has two components: naltrexone, an opioid antagonist, and bupropion, a relatively weak inhibitor of the neuronal reuptake of dopamine and norepinephrine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10228" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Nonclinical studies suggest that naltrexone and bupropion have effects on two separate areas of the brain involved in the regulation of food intake: the hypothalamus (appetite regulatory center) and the mesolimbic dopamine circuit (reward system).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10229" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The exact neurochemical effects of CONTRAVE leading to weight loss are not fully understood.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10230" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Combined, bupropion and naltrexone increased the firing rate of hypothalamic pro-opiomelanocortin (POMC) neurons in vitro, which are associated with regulation of appetite.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10231" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The combination of bupropion and naltrexone also reduced food intake when injected directly into the ventral tegmental area of the mesolimbic circuit in mice, an area associated with regulation of reward pathways.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10232" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Absorption Naltrexone Following single oral administration of CONTRAVE (two 8 mg naltrexone/90 mg bupropion tablets) to healthy subjects, mean peak naltrexone concentration (Cmax) was 1.4 ng/mL, time to peak concentration (Tmax) was 2 hours, and extent of exposure (AUC0-inf) was 8.4 ng∙hr/mL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10233" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Bupropion Following single oral administration of CONTRAVE (two 8 mg naltrexone/90 mg bupropion tablets) to healthy subjects, mean peak bupropion concentration (Cmax) was 168 ng/mL, time to peak concentration (Tmax) was three hours, and extent of exposure (AUC0-inf) was 1,607 ng∙hr/mL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10234" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Food Effect on Absorption When CONTRAVE was administered with a high-fat meal, the AUC and Cmax for naltrexone increased 2.1-fold and 3.7-fold, respectively, and the AUC and Cmax for bupropion increased 1.4-fold and 1.8-fold, respectively.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M483" type="Trigger" span="83 3;111 9" str="AUC | increased"/>
<Mention id="M480" type="Precipitant" span="0 4" str="Food" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M481" type="Trigger" span="91 4;111 9" str="Cmax | increased"/>
<Mention id="M484" type="Precipitant" span="64 13" str="high-fat meal" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I196" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M483" precipitant="M480" effect="C54605"/>
<Interaction id="I197" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M481" precipitant="M480" effect="C54602"/>
<Interaction id="I198" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M481" precipitant="M484" effect="C54602"/>
<Interaction id="I199" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M483" precipitant="M484" effect="C54605"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10235" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>At steady state, the food effect increased AUC and Cmax for naltrexone by 1.7-fold and 1.9-fold, respectively, and increased AUC and Cmax for bupropion by 1.1-fold and 1.3-fold, respectively.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M485" type="Trigger" span="33 9;51 4" str="increased | Cmax"/>
<Mention id="M488" type="Precipitant" span="21 4" str="food" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M487" type="Trigger" span="33 13" str="increased AUC"/>
<Interaction id="I200" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M485" precipitant="M488" effect="C54602"/>
<Interaction id="I201" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M487" precipitant="M488" effect="C54605"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10236" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Thus, CONTRAVE should not be taken with high-fat meals because of the resulting significant increases in bupropion and naltrexone systemic exposure.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M489" type="Trigger" span="92 9;130 17" str="increases | systemic exposure"/>
<Mention id="M490" type="Precipitant" span="40 14" str="high-fat meals" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I202" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M489" precipitant="M490" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10237" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Distribution Naltrexone Naltrexone is 21% plasma protein bound.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10238" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mean apparent volume of distribution at steady state for naltrexone (Vss/F) is 5,697 liters.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10239" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Bupropion Bupropion is 84% plasma protein bound.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10240" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mean apparent volume of distribution at steady state for bupropion (Vss/F) is 880 liters.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10241" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Metabolism and Excretion Naltrexone The major metabolite of naltrexone is 6-beta-naltrexol.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10242" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The activity of naltrexone is believed to be the result of both the parent and the 6-beta-naltrexol metabolite.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10243" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Though less potent, 6-beta-naltrexol is eliminated more slowly and thus circulates at much higher concentrations than naltrexone.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10244" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Naltrexone and 6-beta-naltrexol are not metabolized by cytochrome P450 enzymes and in vitro studies indicate that there is no potential for inhibition or induction of important isozymes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10245" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Naltrexone and its metabolites are excreted primarily by the kidney (53% to 79% of the dose).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10246" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Urinary excretion of unchanged naltrexone accounts for less than 2% of an oral dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10247" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Urinary excretion of unchanged and conjugated 6-beta-naltrexol accounts for 43% of an oral dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10248" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The renal clearance for naltrexone ranges from 30 to 127 mL/min, suggesting that renal elimination is primarily by glomerular filtration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10249" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The renal clearance for 6-beta-naltrexol ranges from 230 to 369 mL/min suggesting an additional renal tubular secretory mechanism.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10250" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Fecal excretion is a minor elimination pathway.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10251" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following single oral administration of CONTRAVE tablets to healthy subjects, mean elimination half-life (T1/2) was approximately 5 hours for naltrexone.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10252" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following twice daily administration of CONTRAVE, naltrexone did not accumulate and its kinetics appeared linear.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10253" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>However, in comparison to naltrexone, 6-beta-naltrexol accumulates to a larger extent (accumulation ratio ~3).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10254" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Bupropion Bupropion is extensively metabolized with three active metabolites: hydroxybupropion, threohydrobupropion and erythrohydrobupropion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10255" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The metabolites have longer elimination half-lives than bupropion and accumulate to a greater extent.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10256" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following bupropion administration, more than 90% of the exposure is a result of metabolites.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10257" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In vitro findings suggest that CYP2B6 is the principal isozyme involved in the formation of hydroxybupropion whereas cytochrome P450 isozymes are not involved in the formation of the other active metabolites.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10258" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Bupropion and its metabolites inhibit CYP2D6.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10259" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Plasma protein binding of hydroxybupropion is similar to that of bupropion (84%) whereas the other two metabolites have approximately half the binding.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10260" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following oral administration of 200 mg of 14C-bupropion in humans, 87% and 10% of the radioactive dose were recovered in the urine and feces, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10261" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The fraction of the oral dose of bupropion excreted unchanged was 0.5%, a finding consistent with the extensive metabolism of bupropion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10262" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following single oral administration of CONTRAVE tablets to healthy subjects, mean elimination half-life (T½) was approximately 21 hours for bupropion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10263" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following twice daily administration of CONTRAVE, metabolites of bupropion, and to a lesser extent unchanged bupropion, accumulate and reach steady-state concentrations in approximately one week.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10264" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Specific Populations Gender Pooled analysis of CONTRAVE data suggested no clinically meaningful differences in the pharmacokinetic parameters of bupropion or naltrexone based on gender.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10265" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Race Pooled analysis of CONTRAVE data suggested no clinically meaningful differences in the pharmacokinetic parameters of bupropion or naltrexone based on race.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10266" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Elderly The pharmacokinetics of CONTRAVE have not been evaluated in the geriatric population.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10267" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The effects of age on the pharmacokinetics of naltrexone or bupropion and their metabolites have not been fully characterized.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10268" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>An exploration of steady-state bupropion concentrations from several depression efficacy studies involving patients dosed in a range of 300 to 750 mg/day, on a three times daily schedule, revealed no relationship between age (18 to 83 years) and plasma concentration of bupropion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10269" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A single-dose pharmacokinetic study demonstrated that the disposition of bupropion and its metabolites in elderly subjects was similar to that of younger subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10270" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>These data suggest there is no prominent effect of age on bupropion concentration; however, another pharmacokinetic study, single and multiple dose, has suggested that the elderly are at increased risk for accumulation of bupropion and its metabolites.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10271" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Smokers Pooled analysis of CONTRAVE data revealed no meaningful differences in the plasma concentrations of bupropion or naltrexone in smokers compared with nonsmokers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10272" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The effects of cigarette smoking on the pharmacokinetics of bupropion were studied in 34 healthy male and female volunteers; 17 were chronic cigarette smokers and 17 were nonsmokers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10273" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following oral administration of a single 150 mg dose of bupropion, there was no statistically significant difference in Cmax, half-life, Tmax, AUC, or clearance of bupropion or its active metabolites between smokers and nonsmokers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10274" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Hepatic Impairment Pharmacokinetic data are not available with CONTRAVE in patients with hepatic impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10275" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The following information is available for individual constituents: Naltrexone An increase in naltrexone AUC of approximately 5- and 10-fold in patients with compensated and decompensated liver cirrhosis, respectively, compared with subjects with normal liver function, has been reported.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10276" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>These data also suggest that alterations in naltrexone bioavailability are related to liver disease severity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10277" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Bupropion The effect of hepatic impairment on the pharmacokinetics of bupropion was characterized in two single-dose trials, one trial in patients with alcoholic liver disease and a second trial in patients with mild-to-severe cirrhosis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10278" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The first trial showed that the half-life of hydroxybupropion was significantly longer in eight patients with alcoholic liver disease than in eight healthy volunteers (32±14 hours vs 21±5 hours, respectively).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10279" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Although not statistically significant, the AUCs for bupropion and hydroxybupropion were more variable and tended to be greater (by 53% to 57%) in patients with alcoholic liver disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10280" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The differences in half-life for bupropion and the other metabolites in the two patient groups were minimal.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10281" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The second trial demonstrated no statistically significant differences in the pharmacokinetics of bupropion and its active metabolites in nine subjects with mild-to-moderate hepatic cirrhosis compared with eight healthy volunteers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10282" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>However, more variability was observed in some of the pharmacokinetic parameters for bupropion (AUC, Cmax, and Tmax) and its active metabolites (t½) in subjects with mild-to-moderate hepatic cirrhosis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10283" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In subjects with severe hepatic cirrhosis, significant alterations in the pharmacokinetics of bupropion and its metabolites were seen (Table 4).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10284" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Pharmacokinetics of Bupropion and Metabolites in Patients With Severe Hepatic Cirrhosis: Ratio Relative to Healthy Matched Controls Cmax AUC t½ Tmax = Difference Bupropion 1.69 3.12 1.43 0.5 h Hydroxybupropion 0.31 1.28 3.88 19 h Threo/erythrohydrobupropion amino alcohol 0.69 2.48 1.96 20 h The dose of CONTRAVE should be reduced in patients with hepatic impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10285" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Renal Impairment A dedicated pharmacokinetic study has not been conducted for CONTRAVE in subjects with renal impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10286" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The following information is available for the individual constituents: Naltrexone Limited information is available for naltrexone in patients with moderate to severe renal impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10287" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In a study of seven patients with end-stage renal disease requiring dialysis, peak plasma concentrations of naltrexone were elevated at least 6-fold compared to healthy subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10288" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Bupropion Limited information is available for bupropion in patients with moderate to severe renal impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10289" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>An inter-trial comparison between normal subjects and patients with end-stage renal failure demonstrated that the bupropion Cmax and AUC values were comparable in the two groups, whereas the hydroxybupropion and threohydrobupropion metabolites had a 2.3- and 2.8-fold increase, respectively, in AUC for patients with end-stage renal failure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10290" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A second trial, comparing normal subjects and patients with moderate-to-severe renal impairment (GFR 30.9 ± 10.8 mL/min) showed that exposure after a single 150 mg dose of sustained-release bupropion was approximately 2-fold higher in patients with impaired renal function while levels of the hydroxybupropion and threo/erythrohydrobupropion (combined) metabolites were similar in the two groups.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10291" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The elimination of bupropion and/or the major metabolites of bupropion may be reduced by impaired renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10292" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The dose of CONTRAVE should be reduced in patients with moderate or severe renal impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10293" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Drug Interactions In Vitro Assessment of Drug Interactions At therapeutically relevant concentrations, naltrexone and 6-beta-naltrexol are not major inhibitors of CYP isoforms CYP1A2, CYP2B6, CYP2C8, CYP2E1, CYP2C9, CYP2C19, CYP2D6 or CYP3A4.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10294" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Both naltrexone and 6-beta-naltrexol are not major inducers of CYP isoforms CYP1A2, CYP2B6, or CYP3A4.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10295" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Bupropion and its metabolites (hydroxybupropion, erythrohydrobupropion, threohydrobupropion) are inhibitors of CYP2D6.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10296" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In vitro studies suggest that paroxetine, sertraline, norfluoxetine, fluvoxamine, and nelfinavir inhibit the hydroxylation of bupropion.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M499" type="Trigger" span="97 25" str="inhibit the hydroxylation"/>
<Mention id="M492" type="Precipitant" span="69 11" str="fluvoxamine" code="O4L1XPO44W"/>
<Mention id="M494" type="Precipitant" span="86 10" str="nelfinavir" code="HO3OGH5D7I | N0000006047"/>
<Mention id="M496" type="Precipitant" span="54 13" str="norfluoxetine" code="K8D70XE2F4"/>
<Mention id="M498" type="Precipitant" span="30 10" str="paroxetine" code="41VRH5220H"/>
<Mention id="M500" type="Precipitant" span="42 10" str="sertraline" code="QUC7NX6WMB"/>
<Interaction id="I203" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M499" precipitant="M492" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I204" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M499" precipitant="M494" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I205" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M499" precipitant="M496" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I206" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M499" precipitant="M498" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I207" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M499" precipitant="M500" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10297" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Bupropion (IC50 9.3 mcM) and its metabolites, hydroxybupropion (IC50 82 mcM) and threohydrobupropion and erythrohydrobupropion (1:1 mixture; IC50 7.8 mcM), inhibited the renal organic transporter OCT2 to a clinically relevant level.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10298" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The systemic concentrations of substrate drugs transported by OCT2 are likely to increase as a result of reduced renal clearance when coadministered with CONTRAVE.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M501" type="Trigger" span="4 23;81 8" str="systemic concentrations | increase "/>
<Mention id="M502" type="Trigger" span="105 23" str=" reduced renal clearance"/>
<Mention id="M503" type="Precipitant" span="41 25" str="drugs transported by OCT2" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I208" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M501;M502" precipitant="M503" effect="C54357"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10299" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Effects of Naltrexone/Bupropion on the Pharmacokinetics of Other Drugs Drug interaction between CONTRAVE and CYP2D6 substrates (metoprolol) or other drugs (atorvastatin, glyburide, lisinopril, nifedipine, valsartan) has been evaluated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10300" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In addition, drug interaction between bupropion, a component of CONTRAVE, and CYP2D6 substrates (desipramine) or other drugs (citalopram, lamotrigine) has also been evaluated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10301" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Effect of Naltrexone/Bupropion Coadministration on Systemic Exposure of Other Drugs Naltrexone/Bupropion Dosage Coadministered Drug Name and Dose Regimens Change in Systemic Exposure Initiate the following drugs at the lower end of the dose range during concomitant use with CONTRAVE : Bupropion 150 mg twice daily for 10 days Desipramine 50 mg single dose ↑5-fold AUC, ↑2-fold Cmax Bupropion 300 mg (as XL) once daily for 14 days Citalopram 40 mg once daily for 14 days ↑40% AUC, ↑30% Cmax Naltrexone/Bupropion 16 mg/180 mg twice daily for 7 days Metoprolol 50 mg single dose ↑4-fold AUC, ↑2-fold Cmax No dose adjustment needed for the following drugs during concomitant use with CONTRAVE: Naltrexone/Bupropion 16 mg/180 mg single dose Atorvastatin 80 mg single dose No Effect Naltrexone/Bupropion 16 mg/180 mg single dose Glyburide 6 mg single dose No Effect Naltrexone/Bupropion 16 mg/180 mg single dose Lisinopril 40 mg single dose No Effect Naltrexone/Bupropion 16 mg/180 mg single dose Nifedipine 90 mg single dose No Effect Naltrexone/Bupropion 16 mg/180 mg single dose Valsartan 320 mg single dose No Effect Bupropion 150 mg twice daily for 12 days Lamotrigine 100 mg single dose No Effect Effects of Other Drugs on the Pharmacokinetics of Naltrexone/Bupropion Drug interactions between CYP2B6 inhibitors (ticlopidine, clopidogrel, prasugrel), CYP2B6 inducers (ritonavir, lopinavir) and bupropion (one of the CONTRAVE components), or between other drugs (atorvastatin, glyburide, metoprolol, lisinopril, nifedipine, valsartan) and CONTRAVE have been evaluated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10302" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>While not systematically studied, carbamazepine, phenobarbital, or phenytoin may induce the metabolism of bupropion.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M508" type="Trigger" span="81 21" str="induce the metabolism"/>
<Mention id="M505" type="Precipitant" span="34 13" str="carbamazepine" code="33CM23913M | N0000007470"/>
<Mention id="M507" type="Precipitant" span="49 13" str="phenobarbital" code="YQE403BP4D | N0000005893"/>
<Mention id="M509" type="Precipitant" span="67 9" str="phenytoin" code="6158TKW0C5 | N0000006023"/>
<Interaction id="I209" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M508" precipitant="M505" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I210" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M508" precipitant="M507" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I211" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M508" precipitant="M509" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10303" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Effect of Coadministered Drugs on Systemic Exposure of Naltrexone/Bupropion Name and Dose Regimens Coadministered Drug CONTRAVE Components Change in Systemic Exposure Do not exceed one tablet twice daily dose of CONTRAVE with the following drugs: Ticlopidine 250 mg twice daily for 4 days Bupropion Hydroxybupropion ↑85% AUC, ↑38% Cmax ↓84% AUC, ↓78% Cmax Clopidogrel 75 mg once daily for 4 days Bupropion Hydroxybupropion ↑60% AUC, ↑40% Cmax ↓52% AUC, ↓50% Cmax No dose adjustment needed for CONTRAVE with the following drugs: Atorvastatin 80 mg single dose Naltrexone 6-beta naltrexol Bupropion Hydroxybupropion Threohydrobupropion Erythrohydrobupropion No Effect No Effect No Effect No Effect No Effect No Effect Lisinopril 40 mg single dose Naltrexone 6-beta naltrexol Bupropion Hydroxybupropion Threohydrobupropion Erythrohydrobupropion No Effect No Effect No Effect No Effect No Effect No Effect Valsartan 320 mg single dose Naltrexone 6-beta naltrexol Bupropion Hydroxybupropion Threohydrobupropion Erythrohydrobupropion No Effect No Effect No Effect ↓14% AUC, No Effect on Cmax No Effect No Effect Cimetidine 800 mg single dose Bupropion Hydroxybupropion Threo/Erythrohydrobupropion No Effect No Effect ↑16% AUC, ↑32% Cmax Citalopram 40 mg once daily for 14 days Bupropion Hydroxybupropion Threohydrobupropion Erythrohydrobupropion No Effect No Effect No Effect No Effect Metoprolol 50 mg single dose Naltrexone 6-beta naltrexol Bupropion Hydroxybupropion Threohydrobupropion Erythrohydrobupropion ↓25% AUC, ↓29% Cmax No Effect No Effect No Effect No Effect No Effect Nifedipine 90 mg single dose Naltrexone 6-beta naltrexol Bupropion Hydroxybupropion Threohydrobupropion Erythrohydrobupropion ↑24% AUC, ↑58% Cmax No Effect No Effect on AUC, ↑22% Cmax No Effect No Effect No Effect Prasugrel 10 mg once daily for 6 days Bupropion Hydroxybupropion ↑18% AUC, ↑14% Cmax ↓24%AUC, ↓32% Cmax Use CONTRAVE with caution with the following drugs: Glyburide 6 mg single doseResults were confounded by the food-effect due to oral glucose coadministered with the treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10304" LabelDrug="CONTRAVE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Naltrexone 6-beta naltrexol Bupropion Hydroxybupropion Threohydrobupropion Erythrohydrobupropion ↑2-fold AUC, ↑2-fold Cmax No Effect ↑36% AUC, ↑18% Cmax ↑22% AUC, ↑21% Cmax No Effect on AUC, ↑15% Cmax No Effect Avoid concomitant use of CONTRAVE with following drugs: Ritonavir 100 mg twice daily for 17 days Bupropion Hydroxybupropion Threohydrobupropion Erythrohydrobupropion ↓22% AUC, ↓21 % Cmax ↓23% AUC, No Effect on Cmax ↓38% AUC, ↓39 % Cmax ↓48% AUC, ↓28 % Cmax 600 mg twice daily for 8 days Bupropion Hydroxybupropion Threohydrobupropion Erythrohydrobupropion ↓66% AUC, ↓62% Cmax ↓78% AUC, ↓42 % Cmax ↓50% AUC, ↓58% Cmax ↓68% AUC, ↓48 % Cmax Lopinavir/Ritonavir 400 mg/100 mg twice daily for 14 days Bupropion Hydroxybupropion ↓57% AUC, ↓57% Cmax ↓50% AUC, ↓31% Cmax Efavirenz 600 mg once daily for 2 weeks Bupropion Hydroxybupropion ↓55% AUC, ↓34% Cmax No Effect on AUC, ↑50% Cmax</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="alcohol" precipitantCode="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M" effect="10171000132106: Behavioral and psychological symptoms of dementia (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="alcohol" precipitantCode="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M" effect="228353006: Reverse tolerance to alcohol (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="alcohol" precipitantCode="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M" effect="363101005: Drug withdrawal (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="alcohol" precipitantCode="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M" effect="87132004: Opioid withdrawal (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="alcohol" precipitantCode="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="antiepileptic drugs" precipitantCode="N0000175753"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="aplenzin" precipitantCode="E70G3G5863"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="barbiturates" precipitantCode="N0000175693 | N0000008016"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="benzodiazepines" precipitantCode="N0000007542 | N0000175694"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="buprenorphine" precipitantCode="40D3SCR4GZ"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="bupropion" precipitantCode="01ZG3TPX31"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="bupropion-containing products" precipitantCode="01ZG3TPX31"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="chronic opioid" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="maoi" precipitantCode="N0000000184"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="methadone" precipitantCode="UC6VBE7V1Z"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="monoamine oxidase inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000000184 | N0000175744"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="opiate" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="opiate agonist" precipitantCode="N0000000174"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="partial agonists" precipitantCode="N0000175685"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="wellbutrin" precipitantCode="ZG7E5POY8O"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="wellbutrin sr" precipitantCode="ZG7E5POY8O"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="wellbutrin xl" precipitantCode="ZG7E5POY8O"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="maois" precipitantCode="N0000000184" effect="24184005: Finding of increased blood pressure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="maois" precipitantCode="N0000000184"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="intravenous methylene blue" precipitantCode="N0000007449 | T42P99266K"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="linezolid" precipitantCode="ISQ9I6J12J"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="reversible maois" precipitantCode="N0000000184"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="high-fat meal" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="91175000: Seizure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="high-fat meal" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="high-fat meal" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54602"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="high-fat meal" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54605"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="clopidogrel" precipitantCode="A74586SNO7 | N0000007277" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cyp2b6 inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000182139" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="ticlopidine" precipitantCode="OM90ZUW7M1" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="antidepressants" precipitantCode="N0000029147 | N0000178314" effect="392291006: Angle-closure glaucoma (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="antidepressants" precipitantCode="N0000029147 | N0000178314" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="antidepressants" precipitantCode="N0000029147 | N0000178314"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="antipsychotics" precipitantCode="N0000029150 | N0000178316" effect="91175000: Seizure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="antipsychotics" precipitantCode="N0000029150 | N0000178316" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="antipsychotics" precipitantCode="N0000029150 | N0000178316"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="beta-blockers" precipitantCode="N0000000161 | N0000175556" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="drugs metabolized by cyp2d6" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="flecainide" precipitantCode="N0000006966 | K94FTS1806" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="haloperidol" precipitantCode="J6292F8L3D | N0000006048" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="metoprolol" precipitantCode="GEB06NHM23" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="metoprolol" precipitantCode="GEB06NHM23" effect="C54610"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="metoprolol" precipitantCode="GEB06NHM23" effect="C54613"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="propafenone" precipitantCode="68IQX3T69U" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="risperidone" precipitantCode="L6UH7ZF8HC" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000175696" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="thioridazine" precipitantCode="N3D6TG58NI" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="tricyclics" precipitantCode="N0000029148 | N0000175752" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="type 1c antiarrhythmics" precipitantCode="N0000029121 | N0000175426" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="carbamazepine" precipitantCode="33CM23913M | N0000007470" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="carbamazepine" precipitantCode="33CM23913M | N0000007470" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cyp2b6 inducers" precipitantCode="N0000187064" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cyp2b6 inducers" precipitantCode="N0000187064" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="efavirenz" precipitantCode="JE6H2O27P8" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="efavirenz" precipitantCode="JE6H2O27P8" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="efavirenz" precipitantCode="JE6H2O27P8"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="lopinavir" precipitantCode="2494G1JF75" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="lopinavir" precipitantCode="2494G1JF75" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="lopinavir" precipitantCode="2494G1JF75"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="phenobarbital" precipitantCode="YQE403BP4D | N0000005893" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="phenobarbital" precipitantCode="YQE403BP4D | N0000005893" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="phenytoin" precipitantCode="6158TKW0C5 | N0000006023" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="phenytoin" precipitantCode="6158TKW0C5 | N0000006023" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="ritonavir" precipitantCode="O3J8G9O825 | N0000007423" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="ritonavir" precipitantCode="O3J8G9O825 | N0000007423" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="ritonavir" precipitantCode="O3J8G9O825 | N0000007423"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="drugs that lower seizure threshold" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="amantadine" precipitantCode="BF4C9Z1J53" effect="246557006: Central nervous system symptom (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="amantadine" precipitantCode="BF4C9Z1J53" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="dopaminergic drugs" precipitantCode="N0000000117" effect="246557006: Central nervous system symptom (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="levodopa" precipitantCode="46627O600J" effect="246557006: Central nervous system symptom (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="amphetamines" precipitantCode="CK833KGX7E | N0000007883" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="drugs that also inhibit the re-uptake of dopamine or norepinephrine" precipitantCode="N0000175424" effect="24184005: Finding of increased blood pressure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="phenelzine" precipitantCode="O408N561GF" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="opioid" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="363101005: Drug withdrawal (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="opioid" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="87132004: Opioid withdrawal (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="opioid" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="opioid analgesics" precipitantCode="N0000175440"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="opioid-containing | antidiarrheal preparations" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="opioid-containing | cough and cold remedies" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="opioid-containing medicines" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="chronic opioid use" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="opioid | analgesics" precipitantCode="N0000175440"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="opioid | antitussives" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="opioid-like medications" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cyp2d6 substrates" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="desipramine" precipitantCode="TG537D343B" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="venlafaxine" precipitantCode="GRZ5RCB1QG" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="drugs that are metabolized by cyp2d6" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="ssris" precipitantCode="N0000175696" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="drug metabolized by cyp2d6" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="inducers of cyp2b6" precipitantCode="N0000187064" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="inducers of cyp2b6" precipitantCode="N0000187064" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="inducers of cyp2b6" precipitantCode="N0000187064"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="inhibitors | of cyp2b6" precipitantCode="N0000182139"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="inhibitors of cyp2b6" precipitantCode="N0000182139" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="systemic corticosteroids" precipitantCode="N0000175576"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="theophylline" precipitantCode="N0000007076 | C137DTR5RG" effect="91175000: Seizure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="theophylline" precipitantCode="N0000007076 | C137DTR5RG"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="amiloride" precipitantCode="7DZO8EB0Z3 | N0000006772" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cimetidine" precipitantCode="80061L1WGD" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="dopamine" precipitantCode="N0000006091 | VTD58H1Z2X" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="drugs transported by oct2" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="famotidine" precipitantCode="5QZO15J2Z8" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="memantine" precipitantCode="W8O17SJF3T" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="metformin" precipitantCode="9100L32L2N" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="oxaliplatin" precipitantCode="04ZR38536J" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="pindolol" precipitantCode="BJ4HF6IU1D" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="procainamide" precipitantCode="N0000005813 | L39WTC366D" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="ranitidine" precipitantCode="884KT10YB7" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="varenicline" precipitantCode="W6HS99O8ZO" effect="C54357"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="antidiabetic medications" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="bupropion products" precipitantCode="01ZG3TPX31" effect="91175000: Seizure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="insulin" precipitantCode="N0000004931 | N0000175944" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="medications that may lower the seizure threshold" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="91175000: Seizure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="meglitinides" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="oral diabetic medications" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sulfonylureas" precipitantCode="N0000175608 | N0000008054" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="systemic steroids" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="91175000: Seizure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="tricyclic antidepressants" precipitantCode="N0000029148 | N0000175752" effect="91175000: Seizure (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="chronic opioids" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="cocaine" precipitantCode="I5Y540LHVR"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="high-fat meals" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="high-fat meals" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="sedatives" precipitantCode="N0000029143 | N0000193842"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="stimulants" precipitantCode="N0000175739"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="chronic opiate therapy" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="intermittent opiate treatment" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="opioids" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="exogenous opioids" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="27942005: Shock (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="exogenous opioids" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="77721001: Opioid intoxication (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="exogenous opioids" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="87317003: Respiratory arrest (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="exogenous opioids" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="tramadol" precipitantCode="39J1LGJ30J" effect="363101005: Drug withdrawal (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="tramadol" precipitantCode="39J1LGJ30J" effect="87132004: Opioid withdrawal (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="short-acting opioids" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="potentially hepatotoxic drugs" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="160931000119108: Increased aspartate transaminase level (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="insulin secretagogues" precipitantCode="N0000009360" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="antidiabetic drug" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="food" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54602"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="food" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54605"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="fluvoxamine" precipitantCode="O4L1XPO44W" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="nelfinavir" precipitantCode="HO3OGH5D7I | N0000006047" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="norfluoxetine" precipitantCode="K8D70XE2F4" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="paroxetine" precipitantCode="41VRH5220H" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="sertraline" precipitantCode="QUC7NX6WMB" effect="C54355"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>