<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="JANUVIA" setid="f85a48d0-0407-4c50-b0fa-7673a160bf01">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
History of a serious hypersensitivity reaction to sitagliptin, such as anaphylaxis or angioedema. [See Warnings and Precautions (5.5) ; Adverse Reactions (6.2) .] History of a serious hypersensitivity reaction to sitagliptin, such as anaphylaxis or angioedema ( 5.5 , 6.2 )</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
The recommended dose of JANUVIA is 100 mg once daily. JANUVIA can be taken with or without food. ( 2.1 ) Dosage adjustment is recommended for patients with eGFR less than 45 mL/min/1.73 m 2 . ( 2.2 ) Dosage Adjustment in Patients with Renal Impairment ( 2.2 ) eGFR greater than or equal to 30 mL/min/1.73 m 2 to less than 45 mL/min/1.73 m 2 eGFR less than 30 mL/min/1.73 m 2 (including patients with end stage renal disease [ESRD] on dialysis) 50 mg once daily 25 mg once daily The recommended dose of JANUVIA is 100 mg once daily. JANUVIA can be taken with or without food. For patients with an estimated glomerular filtration rate [eGFR] greater than or equal to 45 mL/min/1.73 m 2 to less than 90 mL/min/1.73 m 2 , no dosage adjustment for JANUVIA is required. For patients with moderate renal impairment (eGFR greater than or equal to 30 mL/min/1.73 m 2 to less than 45 mL/min/1.73 m 2 ), the dose of JANUVIA is 50 mg once daily. For patients with severe renal impairment (eGFR less than 30 mL/min/1.73 m 2 ) or with end-stage renal disease (ESRD) requiring hemodialysis or peritoneal dialysis, the dose of JANUVIA is 25 mg once daily. JANUVIA may be administered without regard to the timing of dialysis. Because there is a need for dosage adjustment based upon renal function, assessment of renal function is recommended prior to initiation of JANUVIA and periodically thereafter. There have been postmarketing reports of worsening renal function in patients with renal impairment, some of whom were prescribed inappropriate doses of sitagliptin.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
There was a slight increase in the area under the curve (AUC, 11%) and mean peak drug concentration (C max , 18%) of digoxin with the coadministration of 100 mg sitagliptin for 10 days. Patients receiving digoxin should be monitored appropriately. No dosage adjustment of digoxin or JANUVIA is recommended. Coadministration of JANUVIA with an insulin secretagogue (e.g., sulfonylurea) or insulin may require lower doses of the insulin secretagogue or insulin to reduce the risk of hypoglycemia. [See Warnings and Precautions (5.4) .]</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
There have been postmarketing reports of acute pancreatitis, including fatal and non-fatal hemorrhagic or necrotizing pancreatitis. If pancreatitis is suspected, promptly discontinue JANUVIA. ( 5.1 ) Heart failure has been observed with two other members of the DPP-4 inhibitor class. Consider risks and benefits of JANUVIA in patients who have known risk factors for heart failure. Monitor patients for signs and symptoms. ( 5.2 ) There have been postmarketing reports of acute renal failure, sometimes requiring dialysis. Dosage adjustment is recommended in patients with moderate or severe renal impairment and in patients with ESRD. Assessment of renal function is recommended prior to initiating JANUVIA and periodically thereafter. ( 2.2 , 5.3 , 6.2 ) There is an increased risk of hypoglycemia when JANUVIA is added to an insulin secretagogue (e.g., sulfonylurea) or insulin therapy. Consider lowering the dose of the sulfonylurea or insulin to reduce the risk of hypoglycemia. ( 5.4 , 7.2 ) There have been postmarketing reports of serious allergic and hypersensitivity reactions in patients treated with JANUVIA such as anaphylaxis, angioedema, and exfoliative skin conditions including Stevens-Johnson syndrome. In such cases, promptly stop JANUVIA, assess for other potential causes, institute appropriate monitoring and treatment, and initiate alternative treatment for diabetes. ( 5.5 , 6.2 ) Severe and disabling arthralgia has been reported in patients taking DPP-4 inhibitors. Consider as a possible cause for severe joint pain and discontinue drug if appropriate. ( 5.6 ) There have been postmarketing reports of bullous pemphigoid requiring hospitalization in patients taking DPP-4 inhibitors. Tell patients to report development of blisters or erosions. If bullous pemphigoid is suspected, discontinue JANUVIA. ( 5.7 ) There have been no clinical studies establishing conclusive evidence of macrovascular risk reduction with JANUVIA. ( 5.8 ) There have been postmarketing reports of acute pancreatitis, including fatal and non-fatal hemorrhagic or necrotizing pancreatitis, in patients taking JANUVIA. After initiation of JANUVIA, patients should be observed carefully for signs and symptoms of pancreatitis. If pancreatitis is suspected, JANUVIA should promptly be discontinued and appropriate management should be initiated. It is unknown whether patients with a history of pancreatitis are at increased risk for the development of pancreatitis while using JANUVIA. An association between dipeptidyl peptidase-4 (DPP-4) inhibitor treatment and heart failure has been observed in cardiovascular outcomes trials for two other members of the DPP-4 inhibitor class. These trials evaluated patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus and atherosclerotic cardiovascular disease. Consider the risks and benefits of JANUVIA prior to initiating treatment in patients at risk for heart failure, such as those with a prior history of heart failure and a history of renal impairment, and observe these patients for signs and symptoms of heart failure during therapy. Advise patients of the characteristic symptoms of heart failure and to immediately report such symptoms. If heart failure develops, evaluate and manage according to current standards of care and consider discontinuation of JANUVIA. Assessment of renal function is recommended prior to initiating JANUVIA and periodically thereafter. A dosage adjustment is recommended in patients with moderate or severe renal impairment and in patients with ESRD requiring hemodialysis or peritoneal dialysis. [See Dosage and Administration (2.2) ; Clinical Pharmacology (12.3) .] Caution should be used to ensure that the correct dose of JANUVIA is prescribed for patients with moderate (eGFR ≥30 mL/min/1.73 m 2 to &amp;lt;45 mL/min/1.73 m 2 ) or severe (eGFR &amp;lt;30 mL/min/1.73 m 2 ) renal impairment. There have been postmarketing reports of worsening renal function, including acute renal failure, sometimes requiring dialysis. A subset of these reports involved patients with renal impairment, some of whom were prescribed inappropriate doses of sitagliptin. A return to baseline levels of renal impairment has been observed with supportive treatment and discontinuation of potentially causative agents. Consideration can be given to cautiously reinitiating JANUVIA if another etiology is deemed likely to have precipitated the acute worsening of renal function. JANUVIA has not been found to be nephrotoxic in preclinical studies at clinically relevant doses, or in clinical trials. When JANUVIA was used in combination with a sulfonylurea or with insulin, medications known to cause hypoglycemia, the incidence of hypoglycemia was increased over that of placebo used in combination with a sulfonylurea or with insulin. [See Adverse Reactions (6.1) .] Therefore, a lower dose of sulfonylurea or insulin may be required to reduce the risk of hypoglycemia. [See Drug Interactions (7.2) .] There have been postmarketing reports of serious hypersensitivity reactions in patients treated with JANUVIA. These reactions include anaphylaxis, angioedema, and exfoliative skin conditions including Stevens-Johnson syndrome. Onset of these reactions occurred within the first 3 months after initiation of treatment with JANUVIA, with some reports occurring after the first dose. If a hypersensitivity reaction is suspected, discontinue JANUVIA, assess for other potential causes for the event, and institute alternative treatment for diabetes. [See Adverse Reactions (6.2) .] Angioedema has also been reported with other DPP-4 inhibitors. Use caution in a patient with a history of angioedema with another DPP-4 inhibitor because it is unknown whether such patients will be predisposed to angioedema with JANUVIA. There have been postmarketing reports of severe and disabling arthralgia in patients taking DPP-4 inhibitors. The time to onset of symptoms following initiation of drug therapy varied from one day to years. Patients experienced relief of symptoms upon discontinuation of the medication. A subset of patients experienced a recurrence of symptoms when restarting the same drug or a different DPP-4 inhibitor. Consider DPP-4 inhibitors as a possible cause for severe joint pain and discontinue drug if appropriate. Postmarketing cases of bullous pemphigoid requiring hospitalization have been reported with DPP-4 inhibitor use. In reported cases, patients typically recovered with topical or systemic immunosuppressive treatment and discontinuation of the DPP-4 inhibitor. Tell patients to report development of blisters or erosions while receiving JANUVIA. If bullous pemphigoid is suspected, JANUVIA should be discontinued and referral to a dermatologist should be considered for diagnosis and appropriate treatment. There have been no clinical studies establishing conclusive evidence of macrovascular risk reduction with JANUVIA.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Sitagliptin is a DPP-4 inhibitor, which is believed to exert its actions in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus by slowing the inactivation of incretin hormones. Concentrations of the active intact hormones are increased by sitagliptin, thereby increasing and prolonging the action of these hormones. Incretin hormones, including glucagon-like peptide-1 (GLP-1) and glucose-dependent insulinotropic polypeptide (GIP), are released by the intestine throughout the day, and levels are increased in response to a meal. These hormones are rapidly inactivated by the enzyme, DPP-4. The incretins are part of an endogenous system involved in the physiologic regulation of glucose homeostasis. When blood glucose concentrations are normal or elevated, GLP-1 and GIP increase insulin synthesis and release from pancreatic beta cells by intracellular signaling pathways involving cyclic AMP. GLP-1 also lowers glucagon secretion from pancreatic alpha cells, leading to reduced hepatic glucose production. By increasing and prolonging active incretin levels, sitagliptin increases insulin release and decreases glucagon levels in the circulation in a glucose-dependent manner. Sitagliptin demonstrates selectivity for DPP-4 and does not inhibit DPP-8 or DPP-9 activity in vitro at concentrations approximating those from therapeutic doses. General In patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus, administration of sitagliptin led to inhibition of DPP-4 enzyme activity for a 24-hour period. After an oral glucose load or a meal, this DPP-4 inhibition resulted in a 2- to 3-fold increase in circulating levels of active GLP-1 and GIP, decreased glucagon concentrations, and increased responsiveness of insulin release to glucose, resulting in higher C-peptide and insulin concentrations. The rise in insulin with the decrease in glucagon was associated with lower fasting glucose concentrations and reduced glucose excursion following an oral glucose load or a meal. In studies with healthy subjects, sitagliptin did not lower blood glucose or cause hypoglycemia. Sitagliptin and Metformin hydrochloride Coadministration In a two-day study in healthy subjects, sitagliptin alone increased active GLP-1 concentrations, whereas metformin alone increased active and total GLP-1 concentrations to similar extents. Coadministration of sitagliptin and metformin had an additive effect on active GLP-1 concentrations. Sitagliptin, but not metformin, increased active GIP concentrations. It is unclear how these findings relate to changes in glycemic control in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus. Cardiac Electrophysiology In a randomized, placebo-controlled crossover study, 79 healthy subjects were administered a single oral dose of sitagliptin 100 mg, sitagliptin 800 mg (8 times the recommended dose), and placebo. At the recommended dose of 100 mg, there was no effect on the QTc interval obtained at the peak plasma concentration, or at any other time during the study. Following the 800 mg dose, the maximum increase in the placebo-corrected mean change in QTc from baseline was observed at 3 hours postdose and was 8.0 msec. This increase is not considered to be clinically significant. At the 800 mg dose, peak sitagliptin plasma concentrations were approximately 11 times higher than the peak concentrations following a 100-mg dose. In patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus administered sitagliptin 100 mg (N=81) or sitagliptin 200 mg (N=63) daily, there were no meaningful changes in QTc interval based on ECG data obtained at the time of expected peak plasma concentration. The pharmacokinetics of sitagliptin have been extensively characterized in healthy subjects and patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus. Following a single oral 100-mg dose to healthy volunteers, mean plasma AUC of sitagliptin was 8.52 μM•hr, C max was 950 nM, and apparent terminal half-life (t 1/2 ) was 12.4 hours. Plasma AUC of sitagliptin increased in a dose-proportional manner and increased approximately 14% following 100 mg doses at steady-state compared to the first dose. The intra-subject and inter-subject coefficients of variation for sitagliptin AUC were small (5.8% and 15.1%). The pharmacokinetics of sitagliptin was generally similar in healthy subjects and in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus. Absorption After oral administration of a 100 mg dose to healthy subjects, sitagliptin was rapidly absorbed with peak plasma concentrations (median T max ) occurring 1 to 4 hours postdose. The absolute bioavailability of sitagliptin is approximately 87%. Effect of Food Coadministration of a high-fat meal with sitagliptin had no effect on the pharmacokinetics of sitagliptin. Distribution The mean volume of distribution at steady state following a single 100-mg intravenous dose of sitagliptin to healthy subjects is approximately 198 liters. The fraction of sitagliptin reversibly bound to plasma proteins is low (38%). Elimination Approximately 79% of sitagliptin is excreted unchanged in the urine with metabolism being a minor pathway of elimination. The apparent terminal t 1/2 following a 100 mg oral dose of sitagliptin was approximately 12.4 hours and renal clearance was approximately 350 mL/min. Metabolism Following a [ 14 C]sitagliptin oral dose, approximately 16% of the radioactivity was excreted as metabolites of sitagliptin. Six metabolites were detected at trace levels and are not expected to contribute to the plasma DPP-4 inhibitory activity of sitagliptin. In vitro studies indicated that the primary enzyme responsible for the limited metabolism of sitagliptin was CYP3A4, with contribution from CYP2C8. Excretion Following administration of an oral [ 14 C]sitagliptin dose to healthy subjects, approximately 100% of the administered radioactivity was eliminated in feces (13%) or urine (87%) within one week of dosing. Elimination of sitagliptin occurs primarily via renal excretion and involves active tubular secretion. Sitagliptin is a substrate for human organic anion transporter-3 (hOAT-3), which may be involved in the renal elimination of sitagliptin. The clinical relevance of hOAT-3 in sitagliptin transport has not been established. Sitagliptin is also a substrate of P-glycoprotein (P-gp), which may also be involved in mediating the renal elimination of sitagliptin. However, cyclosporine, a P-gp inhibitor, did not reduce the renal clearance of sitagliptin. Specific Populations Patients with Renal Impairment An approximately 2-fold increase in the plasma AUC of sitagliptin was observed in patients with moderate renal impairment with eGFR of 30 to less than 45 mL/min/1.73 m 2 , and an approximately 4-fold increase was observed in patients with severe renal impairment, including patients with ESRD on hemodialysis, as compared to normal healthy control subjects. Patients with Hepatic Impairment In patients with moderate hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh score 7 to 9), mean AUC and C max of sitagliptin increased approximately 21% and 13%, respectively, compared to healthy matched controls following administration of a single 100-mg dose of sitagliptin. These differences are not considered to be clinically meaningful. There is no clinical experience in patients with severe hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh score &amp;gt;9). Effects of Age, Body Mass Index (BMI), Gender, and Race Based on a population pharmacokinetic analysis or a composite analysis of available pharmacokinetic data, BMI, gender, and race do not have a clinically meaningful effect on the pharmacokinetics of sitagliptin. When the effects of age on renal function are taken into account, age alone did not have a clinically meaningful impact on the pharmacokinetics of sitagliptin based on a population pharmacokinetic analysis. Elderly subjects (65 to 80 years) had approximately 19% higher plasma concentrations of sitagliptin compared to younger subjects. Pediatric Patients Studies characterizing the pharmacokinetics of sitagliptin in pediatric patients have not been performed. Drug Interaction Studies In Vitro Assessment of Drug Interactions Sitagliptin is not an inhibitor of CYP isozymes CYP3A4, 2C8, 2C9, 2D6, 1A2, 2C19 or 2B6, and is not an inducer of CYP3A4. Sitagliptin is a P-gp substrate, but does not inhibit P-gp mediated transport of digoxin. Based on these results, sitagliptin is considered unlikely to cause interactions with other drugs that utilize these pathways. Sitagliptin is not extensively bound to plasma proteins. Therefore, the propensity of sitagliptin to be involved in clinically meaningful drug-drug interactions mediated by plasma protein binding displacement is very low. In Vivo Assessment of Drug Interactions Effects of Sitagliptin on Other Drugs In clinical studies, sitagliptin did not meaningfully alter the pharmacokinetics of metformin, glyburide, simvastatin, rosiglitazone, digoxin, warfarin, or an oral contraceptive (ethinyl estradiol and norethindrone) (Table 4), providing in vivo evidence of a low propensity for causing drug interactions with substrates of CYP3A4, CYP2C8, CYP2C9, P-gp, and organic cationic transporter (OCT). Table 4: Effect of Sitagliptin on Systemic Exposure of Coadministered Drugs Coadministered Drug Dose of Coadministered Drug All doses administered as single dose unless otherwise specified. Dose of Sitagliptin Geometric Mean Ratio (ratio with/without sitagliptin) No Effect = 1.00 AUC AUC is reported as AUC 0-∞ unless otherwise specified. C max No dosing adjustments required for the following: Digoxin 0.25 mg Multiple dose. once daily for 10 days 100 mg once daily for 10 days Digoxin 1.11 AUC 0-24hr . 1.18 Glyburide 1.25 mg 200 mg once daily for 6 days Glyburide 1.09 1.01 Simvastatin 20 mg 200 mg once daily for 5 days Simvastatin 0.85 AUC 0-last . 0.80 Simvastatin Acid 1.12 1.06 Rosiglitazone 4 mg 200 mg once daily for 5 days Rosiglitazone 0.98 0.99 Warfarin 30 mg single dose on day 5 200 mg once daily for 11 days S(-) Warfarin 0.95 0.89 R(+) Warfarin 0.99 0.89 Ethinyl estradiol and norethindrone 21 days once daily of 35 µg ethinyl estradiol with norethindrone 0.5 mg × 7 days, 0.75 mg × 7 days, 1.0 mg × 7 days 200 mg once daily for 21 days Ethinyl estradiol 0.99 0.97 Norethindrone 1.03 0.98 Metformin 1000 mg twice daily for 14 days 50 mg twice daily for 7 days Metformin 1.02 AUC 0-12hr . 0.97 Effects of Other Drugs on Sitagliptin Clinical data described below suggest that sitagliptin is not susceptible to clinically meaningful interactions by coadministered medications (Table 5). Table 5: Effect of Coadministered Drugs on Systemic Exposure of Sitagliptin Coadministered Drug Dose of Coadministered Drug All doses administered as single dose unless otherwise specified. Dose of Sitagliptin Geometric Mean Ratio (ratio with/without coadministered drug) No Effect = 1.00 AUC AUC is reported as AUC 0-∞ unless otherwise specified. C max No dosing adjustments required for the following: Cyclosporine 600 mg once daily 100 mg once daily Sitagliptin 1.29 1.68 Metformin 1000 mg Multiple dose. twice daily for 14 days 50 mg twice daily for 7 days Sitagliptin 1.02 AUC 0-12hr . 1.05</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="3520" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>History of a serious hypersensitivity reaction to sitagliptin, such as anaphylaxis or angioedema.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3521" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>History of a serious hypersensitivity reaction to sitagliptin, such as anaphylaxis or angioedema (5.5, 6.2)</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3522" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The recommended dose of JANUVIA is 100 mg once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3523" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>JANUVIA can be taken with or without food.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3524" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dosage adjustment is recommended for patients with eGFR less than 45 mL/min/1.73 m2.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3525" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dosage Adjustment in Patients with Renal Impairment (2.2) eGFR greater than or equal to 30 mL/min/1.73 m2 to less than 45 mL/min/1.73 m2 eGFR less than 30 mL/min/1.73 m2 (including patients with end stage renal disease [ESRD] on dialysis) 50 mg once daily 25 mg once daily The recommended dose of JANUVIA is 100 mg once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3526" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For patients with an estimated glomerular filtration rate [eGFR] greater than or equal to 45 mL/min/1.73 m2 to less than 90 mL/min/1.73 m2, no dosage adjustment for JANUVIA is required.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3527" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For patients with moderate renal impairment (eGFR greater than or equal to 30 mL/min/1.73 m2 to less than 45 mL/min/1.73 m2), the dose of JANUVIA is 50 mg once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3528" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>For patients with severe renal impairment (eGFR less than 30 mL/min/1.73 m2) or with end-stage renal disease (ESRD) requiring hemodialysis or peritoneal dialysis, the dose of JANUVIA is 25 mg once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3529" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>JANUVIA may be administered without regard to the timing of dialysis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3530" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Because there is a need for dosage adjustment based upon renal function, assessment of renal function is recommended prior to initiation of JANUVIA and periodically thereafter.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3531" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>There have been postmarketing reports of worsening renal function in patients with renal impairment, some of whom were prescribed inappropriate doses of sitagliptin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3532" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>There was a slight increase in the area under the curve (AUC, 11%) and mean peak drug concentration (Cmax, 18%) of digoxin with the coadministration of 100 mg sitagliptin for 10 days.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M1" type="Trigger" span="19 8;76 4;86 13" str="increase | peak | concentration "/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Trigger" span="19 8;101 4" str=" increase | Cmax"/>
<Mention id="M6" type="Precipitant" span="115 7" str="digoxin" code="73K4184T59 | N0000005903"/>
<Mention id="M4" type="Trigger" span="19 36" str="increase in the area under the curve "/>
<Mention id="M5" type="Trigger" span="19 8;57 3" str=" increase | AUC"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M1;M2" precipitant="M6" effect="C54610"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M4;M5" precipitant="M6" effect="C54613"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3533" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Patients receiving digoxin should be monitored appropriately.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M7" type="Trigger" span="27 19" str="should be monitored"/>
<Mention id="M8" type="Precipitant" span="19 7" str="digoxin" code="73K4184T59 | N0000005903"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M7" precipitant="M8"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3534" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>No dosage adjustment of digoxin or JANUVIA is recommended.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3535" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Coadministration of JANUVIA with an insulin secretagogue (e.g., sulfonylurea) or insulin may require lower doses of the insulin secretagogue or insulin to reduce the risk of hypoglycemia.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M17" type="Trigger" span="101 10" str="lower dose "/>
<Mention id="M18" type="Trigger" span="166 7" str=" risk of"/>
<Mention id="M11" type="Precipitant" span="36 7" str="insulin" code="N0000004931 | N0000175944"/>
<Mention id="M20" type="SpecificInteraction" span="174 12" str="hypoglycemia" code="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M15" type="Precipitant" span="36 20" str="insulin secretagogue" code="N0000009360"/>
<Mention id="M19" type="Precipitant" span="64 12" str="sulfonylurea" code="N0000175608 | N0000008054"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M17;M18" precipitant="M11" effect="M20" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M17;M18" precipitant="M15" effect="M20" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M17;M18" precipitant="M19" effect="M20" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3536" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There have been postmarketing reports of acute pancreatitis, including fatal and non-fatal hemorrhagic or necrotizing pancreatitis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3537" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If pancreatitis is suspected, promptly discontinue JANUVIA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3538" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Heart failure has been observed with two other members of the DPP-4 inhibitor class.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3539" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Consider risks and benefits of JANUVIA in patients who have known risk factors for heart failure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3540" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There have been postmarketing reports of acute renal failure, sometimes requiring dialysis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3541" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Dosage adjustment is recommended in patients with moderate or severe renal impairment and in patients with ESRD.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3542" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Assessment of renal function is recommended prior to initiating JANUVIA and periodically thereafter.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3543" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There is an increased risk of hypoglycemia when JANUVIA is added to an insulin secretagogue (e.g., sulfonylurea) or insulin therapy.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M27" type="Trigger" span="12 14" str="increased risk"/>
<Mention id="M22" type="Precipitant" span="71 7" str="insulin" code="N0000004931 | N0000175944"/>
<Mention id="M29" type="SpecificInteraction" span="30 12" str="hypoglycemia" code="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M25" type="Precipitant" span="71 20" str="insulin secretagogue" code="N0000009360"/>
<Mention id="M28" type="Precipitant" span="99 12" str="sulfonylurea" code="N0000175608 | N0000008054"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M27" precipitant="M22" effect="M29" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M27" precipitant="M25" effect="M29" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M27" precipitant="M28" effect="M29" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3544" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Consider lowering the dose of the sulfonylurea or insulin to reduce the risk of hypoglycemia.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M34" type="Trigger" span="9 17" str="lowering the dose "/>
<Mention id="M35" type="Trigger" span="72 7" str=" risk of"/>
<Mention id="M32" type="Precipitant" span="50 7" str="insulin" code="N0000004931 | N0000175944"/>
<Mention id="M37" type="SpecificInteraction" span="80 12" str="hypoglycemia" code="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M36" type="Precipitant" span="34 12" str="sulfonylurea" code="N0000175608 | N0000008054"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M34;M35" precipitant="M32" effect="M37" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M34;M35" precipitant="M36" effect="M37" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3545" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There have been postmarketing reports of serious allergic and hypersensitivity reactions in patients treated with JANUVIA such as anaphylaxis, angioedema, and exfoliative skin conditions including Stevens-Johnson syndrome.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3546" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In such cases, promptly stop JANUVIA, assess for other potential causes, institute appropriate monitoring and treatment, and initiate alternative treatment for diabetes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3547" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Severe and disabling arthralgia has been reported in patients taking DPP-4 inhibitors.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3548" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Consider as a possible cause for severe joint pain and discontinue drug if appropriate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3549" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There have been postmarketing reports of bullous pemphigoid requiring hospitalization in patients taking DPP-4 inhibitors.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3550" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Tell patients to report development of blisters or erosions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3551" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If bullous pemphigoid is suspected, discontinue JANUVIA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3552" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There have been no clinical studies establishing conclusive evidence of macrovascular risk reduction with JANUVIA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3553" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There have been postmarketing reports of acute pancreatitis, including fatal and non-fatal hemorrhagic or necrotizing pancreatitis, in patients taking JANUVIA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3554" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>After initiation of JANUVIA, patients should be observed carefully for signs and symptoms of pancreatitis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3555" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If pancreatitis is suspected, JANUVIA should promptly be discontinued and appropriate management should be initiated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3556" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>It is unknown whether patients with a history of pancreatitis are at increased risk for the development of pancreatitis while using JANUVIA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3557" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>An association between dipeptidyl peptidase-4 (DPP-4) inhibitor treatment and heart failure has been observed in cardiovascular outcomes trials for two other members of the DPP-4 inhibitor class.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3558" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>These trials evaluated patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus and atherosclerotic cardiovascular disease.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3559" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Consider the risks and benefits of JANUVIA prior to initiating treatment in patients at risk for heart failure, such as those with a prior history of heart failure and a history of renal impairment, and observe these patients for signs and symptoms of heart failure during therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3560" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Advise patients of the characteristic symptoms of heart failure and to immediately report such symptoms.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3561" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If heart failure develops, evaluate and manage according to current standards of care and consider discontinuation of JANUVIA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3562" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>A dosage adjustment is recommended in patients with moderate or severe renal impairment and in patients with ESRD requiring hemodialysis or peritoneal dialysis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3563" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Caution should be used to ensure that the correct dose of JANUVIA is prescribed for patients with moderate (eGFR ≥30 mL/min/1.73 m2 to &lt;45 mL/min/1.73 m2) or severe (eGFR &lt;30 mL/min/1.73 m2) renal impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3564" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There have been postmarketing reports of worsening renal function, including acute renal failure, sometimes requiring dialysis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3565" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>A subset of these reports involved patients with renal impairment, some of whom were prescribed inappropriate doses of sitagliptin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3566" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>A return to baseline levels of renal impairment has been observed with supportive treatment and discontinuation of potentially causative agents.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3567" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Consideration can be given to cautiously reinitiating JANUVIA if another etiology is deemed likely to have precipitated the acute worsening of renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3568" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>JANUVIA has not been found to be nephrotoxic in preclinical studies at clinically relevant doses, or in clinical trials.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3569" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>When JANUVIA was used in combination with a sulfonylurea or with insulin, medications known to cause hypoglycemia, the incidence of hypoglycemia was increased over that of placebo used in combination with a sulfonylurea or with insulin.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M44" type="Trigger" span="119 9;149 9" str="incidence | increased"/>
<Mention id="M39" type="Precipitant" span="65 7" str="insulin" code="N0000004931 | N0000175944"/>
<Mention id="M46" type="SpecificInteraction" span="101 12" str="hypoglycemia" code="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M42" type="Precipitant" span="74 39" str="medications known to cause hypoglycemia" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M45" type="Precipitant" span="44 12" str="sulfonylurea" code="N0000175608 | N0000008054"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M44" precipitant="M39" effect="M46" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M44" precipitant="M42" effect="M46" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M44" precipitant="M45" effect="M46" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3570" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Therefore, a lower dose of sulfonylurea or insulin may be required to reduce the risk of hypoglycemia.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M51" type="Trigger" span="13 10" str="lower dose "/>
<Mention id="M52" type="Trigger" span="81 7" str=" risk of"/>
<Mention id="M49" type="Precipitant" span="43 7" str="insulin" code="N0000004931 | N0000175944"/>
<Mention id="M54" type="SpecificInteraction" span="89 12" str="hypoglycemia" code="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M53" type="Precipitant" span="27 12" str="sulfonylurea" code="N0000175608 | N0000008054"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M51;M52" precipitant="M49" effect="M54" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M51;M52" precipitant="M53" effect="M54" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3571" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There have been postmarketing reports of serious hypersensitivity reactions in patients treated with JANUVIA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3572" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>These reactions include anaphylaxis, angioedema, and exfoliative skin conditions including Stevens-Johnson syndrome.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3573" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Onset of these reactions occurred within the first 3 months after initiation of treatment with JANUVIA, with some reports occurring after the first dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3574" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If a hypersensitivity reaction is suspected, discontinue JANUVIA, assess for other potential causes for the event, and institute alternative treatment for diabetes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3575" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Angioedema has also been reported with other DPP-4 inhibitors.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3576" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Use caution in a patient with a history of angioedema with another DPP-4 inhibitor because it is unknown whether such patients will be predisposed to angioedema with JANUVIA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3577" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>There have been postmarketing reports of severe and disabling arthralgia in patients taking DPP-4 inhibitors.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3578" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>The time to onset of symptoms following initiation of drug therapy varied from one day to years.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3579" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients experienced relief of symptoms upon discontinuation of the medication.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3580" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>A subset of patients experienced a recurrence of symptoms when restarting the same drug or a different DPP-4 inhibitor.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3581" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Consider DPP-4 inhibitors as a possible cause for severe joint pain and discontinue drug if appropriate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3582" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Postmarketing cases of bullous pemphigoid requiring hospitalization have been reported with DPP-4 inhibitor use.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3583" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In reported cases, patients typically recovered with topical or systemic immunosuppressive treatment and discontinuation of the DPP-4 inhibitor.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3584" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Tell patients to report development of blisters or erosions while receiving JANUVIA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3585" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If bullous pemphigoid is suspected, JANUVIA should be discontinued and referral to a dermatologist should be considered for diagnosis and appropriate treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3586" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Sitagliptin is a DPP-4 inhibitor, which is believed to exert its actions in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus by slowing the inactivation of incretin hormones.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3587" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Concentrations of the active intact hormones are increased by sitagliptin, thereby increasing and prolonging the action of these hormones.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3588" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Incretin hormones, including glucagon-like peptide-1 (GLP-1) and glucose-dependent insulinotropic polypeptide (GIP), are released by the intestine throughout the day, and levels are increased in response to a meal.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3589" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>These hormones are rapidly inactivated by the enzyme, DPP-4.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3590" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The incretins are part of an endogenous system involved in the physiologic regulation of glucose homeostasis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3591" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>When blood glucose concentrations are normal or elevated, GLP-1 and GIP increase insulin synthesis and release from pancreatic beta cells by intracellular signaling pathways involving cyclic AMP.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3592" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>GLP-1 also lowers glucagon secretion from pancreatic alpha cells, leading to reduced hepatic glucose production.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3593" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>By increasing and prolonging active incretin levels, sitagliptin increases insulin release and decreases glucagon levels in the circulation in a glucose-dependent manner.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3594" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Sitagliptin demonstrates selectivity for DPP-4 and does not inhibit DPP-8 or DPP-9 activity in vitro at concentrations approximating those from therapeutic doses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3595" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>General In patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus, administration of sitagliptin led to inhibition of DPP-4 enzyme activity for a 24-hour period.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3596" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>After an oral glucose load or a meal, this DPP-4 inhibition resulted in a 2- to 3-fold increase in circulating levels of active GLP-1 and GIP, decreased glucagon concentrations, and increased responsiveness of insulin release to glucose, resulting in higher C-peptide and insulin concentrations.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3597" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The rise in insulin with the decrease in glucagon was associated with lower fasting glucose concentrations and reduced glucose excursion following an oral glucose load or a meal.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3598" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In studies with healthy subjects, sitagliptin did not lower blood glucose or cause hypoglycemia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3599" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Sitagliptin and Metformin hydrochloride Coadministration In a two-day study in healthy subjects, sitagliptin alone increased active GLP-1 concentrations, whereas metformin alone increased active and total GLP-1 concentrations to similar extents.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3600" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Coadministration of sitagliptin and metformin had an additive effect on active GLP-1 concentrations.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3601" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Sitagliptin, but not metformin, increased active GIP concentrations.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3602" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>It is unclear how these findings relate to changes in glycemic control in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3603" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Cardiac Electrophysiology In a randomized, placebo-controlled crossover study, 79 healthy subjects were administered a single oral dose of sitagliptin 100 mg, sitagliptin 800 mg (8 times the recommended dose), and placebo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3604" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>At the recommended dose of 100 mg, there was no effect on the QTc interval obtained at the peak plasma concentration, or at any other time during the study.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3605" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following the 800 mg dose, the maximum increase in the placebo-corrected mean change in QTc from baseline was observed at 3 hours postdose and was 8.0 msec.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3606" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This increase is not considered to be clinically significant.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3607" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>At the 800 mg dose, peak sitagliptin plasma concentrations were approximately 11 times higher than the peak concentrations following a 100-mg dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3608" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus administered sitagliptin 100 mg (N=81) or sitagliptin 200 mg (N=63) daily, there were no meaningful changes in QTc interval based on ECG data obtained at the time of expected peak plasma concentration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3609" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacokinetics of sitagliptin have been extensively characterized in healthy subjects and patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3610" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following a single oral 100-mg dose to healthy volunteers, mean plasma AUC of sitagliptin was 8.52 μMhr, Cmax was 950 nM, and apparent terminal half-life (t1/2) was 12.4 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3611" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Plasma AUC of sitagliptin increased in a dose-proportional manner and increased approximately 14% following 100 mg doses at steady-state compared to the first dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3612" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The intra-subject and inter-subject coefficients of variation for sitagliptin AUC were small (5.8% and 15.1%).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3613" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacokinetics of sitagliptin was generally similar in healthy subjects and in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3614" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Absorption After oral administration of a 100 mg dose to healthy subjects, sitagliptin was rapidly absorbed with peak plasma concentrations (median Tmax) occurring 1 to 4 hours postdose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3615" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The absolute bioavailability of sitagliptin is approximately 87%.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3616" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Effect of Food Coadministration of a high-fat meal with sitagliptin had no effect on the pharmacokinetics of sitagliptin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3617" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Distribution The mean volume of distribution at steady state following a single 100-mg intravenous dose of sitagliptin to healthy subjects is approximately 198 liters.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3618" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The fraction of sitagliptin reversibly bound to plasma proteins is low (38%).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3619" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Elimination Approximately 79% of sitagliptin is excreted unchanged in the urine with metabolism being a minor pathway of elimination.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3620" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The apparent terminal t1/2 following a 100 mg oral dose of sitagliptin was approximately 12.4 hours and renal clearance was approximately 350 mL/min.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3621" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Metabolism Following a [14C]sitagliptin oral dose, approximately 16% of the radioactivity was excreted as metabolites of sitagliptin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3622" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Six metabolites were detected at trace levels and are not expected to contribute to the plasma DPP-4 inhibitory activity of sitagliptin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3623" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In vitro studies indicated that the primary enzyme responsible for the limited metabolism of sitagliptin was CYP3A4, with contribution from CYP2C8.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3624" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Excretion Following administration of an oral [14C]sitagliptin dose to healthy subjects, approximately 100% of the administered radioactivity was eliminated in feces (13%) or urine (87%) within one week of dosing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3625" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Elimination of sitagliptin occurs primarily via renal excretion and involves active tubular secretion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3626" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Sitagliptin is a substrate for human organic anion transporter-3 (hOAT-3), which may be involved in the renal elimination of sitagliptin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3627" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The clinical relevance of hOAT-3 in sitagliptin transport has not been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3628" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Sitagliptin is also a substrate of P-glycoprotein (P-gp), which may also be involved in mediating the renal elimination of sitagliptin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3629" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>However, cyclosporine, a P-gp inhibitor, did not reduce the renal clearance of sitagliptin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3630" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Specific Populations Patients with Renal Impairment An approximately 2-fold increase in the plasma AUC of sitagliptin was observed in patients with moderate renal impairment with eGFR of 30 to less than 45 mL/min/1.73 m2, and an approximately 4-fold increase was observed in patients with severe renal impairment, including patients with ESRD on hemodialysis, as compared to normal healthy control subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3631" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Patients with Hepatic Impairment In patients with moderate hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh score 7 to 9), mean AUC and Cmax of sitagliptin increased approximately 21% and 13%, respectively, compared to healthy matched controls following administration of a single 100-mg dose of sitagliptin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3632" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>These differences are not considered to be clinically meaningful.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3633" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There is no clinical experience in patients with severe hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh score &gt;9).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3634" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Effects of Age, Body Mass Index (BMI), Gender, and Race Based on a population pharmacokinetic analysis or a composite analysis of available pharmacokinetic data, BMI, gender, and race do not have a clinically meaningful effect on the pharmacokinetics of sitagliptin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3635" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>When the effects of age on renal function are taken into account, age alone did not have a clinically meaningful impact on the pharmacokinetics of sitagliptin based on a population pharmacokinetic analysis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3636" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Elderly subjects (65 to 80 years) had approximately 19% higher plasma concentrations of sitagliptin compared to younger subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3637" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Pediatric Patients Studies characterizing the pharmacokinetics of sitagliptin in pediatric patients have not been performed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3638" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Drug Interaction Studies In Vitro Assessment of Drug Interactions Sitagliptin is not an inhibitor of CYP isozymes CYP3A4, 2C8, 2C9, 2D6, 1A2, 2C19 or 2B6, and is not an inducer of CYP3A4.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3639" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Sitagliptin is a P-gp substrate, but does not inhibit P-gp mediated transport of digoxin.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3640" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Based on these results, sitagliptin is considered unlikely to cause interactions with other drugs that utilize these pathways.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3641" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Sitagliptin is not extensively bound to plasma proteins.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3642" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Therefore, the propensity of sitagliptin to be involved in clinically meaningful drug-drug interactions mediated by plasma protein binding displacement is very low.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3643" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In Vivo Assessment of Drug Interactions Effects of Sitagliptin on Other Drugs In clinical studies, sitagliptin did not meaningfully alter the pharmacokinetics of metformin, glyburide, simvastatin, rosiglitazone, digoxin, warfarin, or an oral contraceptive (ethinyl estradiol and norethindrone) (Table 4), providing in vivo evidence of a low propensity for causing drug interactions with substrates of CYP3A4, CYP2C8, CYP2C9, P-gp, and organic cationic transporter (OCT).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3644" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Table 4: Effect of Sitagliptin on Systemic Exposure of Coadministered Drugs Coadministered Drug Dose of Coadministered DrugAll doses administered as single dose unless otherwise specified.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3645" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Dose of Sitagliptin Geometric Mean Ratio(ratio with/without sitagliptin)No Effect = 1.00 AUCAUC is reported as AUC0-∞ unless otherwise specified.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3646" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Cmax No dosing adjustments required for the following: Digoxin 0.25 mgMultiple dose. once daily for 10 days 100 mg once daily for 10 days Digoxin 1.11AUC0-24hr.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3647" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>1.18 Glyburide 1.25 mg 200 mg once daily for 6 days Glyburide 1.09 1.01 Simvastatin 20 mg 200 mg once daily for 5 days Simvastatin 0.85AUC0-last.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3648" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>0.80 Simvastatin Acid 1.12 1.06 Rosiglitazone 4 mg 200 mg once daily for 5 days Rosiglitazone 0.98 0.99 Warfarin 30 mg single dose on day 5 200 mg once daily for 11 days S(-) Warfarin 0.95 0.89 R(+) Warfarin 0.99 0.89 Ethinyl estradiol and norethindrone 21 days once daily of 35 µg ethinyl estradiol with norethindrone 0.5 mg Ã— 7 days, 0.75 mg Ã— 7 days, 1.0 mg Ã— 7 days 200 mg once daily for 21 days Ethinyl estradiol 0.99 0.97 Norethindrone 1.03 0.98 Metformin 1000 mg twice daily for 14 days 50 mg twice daily for 7 days Metformin 1.02AUC0-12hr.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3649" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>0.97 Effects of Other Drugs on Sitagliptin Clinical data described below suggest that sitagliptin is not susceptible to clinically meaningful interactions by coadministered medications (Table 5).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3650" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Table 5: Effect of Coadministered Drugs on Systemic Exposure of Sitagliptin Coadministered Drug Dose of Coadministered DrugAll doses administered as single dose unless otherwise specified.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3651" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Dose of Sitagliptin Geometric Mean Ratio(ratio with/without coadministered drug)No Effect = 1.00 AUCAUC is reported as AUC0-∞ unless otherwise specified.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="3652" LabelDrug="JANUVIA" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Cmax No dosing adjustments required for the following: Cyclosporine 600 mg once daily 100 mg once daily Sitagliptin 1.29 1.68 Metformin 1000 mgMultiple dose. twice daily for 14 days 50 mg twice daily for 7 days Sitagliptin 1.02AUC0-12hr.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="digoxin" precipitantCode="73K4184T59 | N0000005903" effect="C54610"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="digoxin" precipitantCode="73K4184T59 | N0000005903" effect="C54613"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="digoxin" precipitantCode="73K4184T59 | N0000005903"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="insulin" precipitantCode="N0000004931 | N0000175944" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="insulin secretagogue" precipitantCode="N0000009360" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="sulfonylurea" precipitantCode="N0000175608 | N0000008054" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="medications known to cause hypoglycemia" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="302866003: Hypoglycemia (disorder)"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>