<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="VALTREX" setid="f8e0d8f8-cb73-4206-a484-88f5c4fbd719">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
VALTREX is contraindicated in patients who have had a demonstrated clinically significant hypersensitivity reaction (e.g., anaphylaxis) to valacyclovir, acyclovir, or any component of the formulation [see Adverse Reactions (6.3)] . Hypersensitivity to valacyclovir (e.g., anaphylaxis), acyclovir, or any component of the formulation. ( 4 )</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
• VALTREX may be given without regard to meals. • Valacyclovir oral suspension (25 mg/mL or 50 mg/mL) may be prepared extemporaneously from 500-mg VALTREX Caplets for use in pediatric patients for whom a solid dosage form is not appropriate [see Dosage and Administration (2.3)] . Adult Dosage ( 2.1 ) Cold Sores 2 grams every 12 hours for 1 day Genital Herpes Initial episode 1 gram twice daily for 10 days Recurrent episodes 500 mg twice daily for 3 days Suppressive therapy Immunocompetent patients 1 gram once daily Alternate dose in patients with less than or equal to 9 recurrences/year 500 mg once daily HIV-1─infected patients 500 mg twice daily Reduction of transmission 500 mg once daily Herpes Zoster 1 gram 3 times daily for 7 days Pediatric Dosage ( 2.2 ) Cold Sores (aged greater than or equal to 12 years) 2 grams every 12 hours for 1 day Chickenpox (aged 2 to less than 18 years) 20 mg/kg 3 times daily for 5 days; not to exceed 1 gram 3 times daily Valacyclovir oral suspension (25 mg/mL or 50 mg/mL) can be prepared from the 500 mg VALTREX Caplets. ( 2.3 ) Cold Sores (Herpes Labialis): The recommended dosage of VALTREX for treatment of cold sores is 2 grams twice daily for 1 day taken 12 hours apart. Therapy should be initiated at the earliest symptom of a cold sore (e.g., tingling, itching, or burning). Genital Herpes: Initial Episode: The recommended dosage of VALTREX for treatment of initial genital herpes is 1 gram twice daily for 10 days. Therapy was most effective when administered within 48 hours of the onset of signs and symptoms. Recurrent Episodes: The recommended dosage of VALTREX for treatment of recurrent genital herpes is 500 mg twice daily for 3 days. Initiate treatment at the first sign or symptom of an episode. Suppressive Therapy: The recommended dosage of VALTREX for chronic suppressive therapy of recurrent genital herpes is 1 gram once daily in patients with normal immune function. In patients with a history of 9 or fewer recurrences per year, an alternative dose is 500 mg once daily. In HIV─1─infected patients with a CD4+ cell count greater than or equal to 100 cells/mm 3 , the recommended dosage of VALTREX for chronic suppressive therapy of recurrent genital herpes is 500 mg twice daily. Reduction of Transmission: The recommended dosage of VALTREX for reduction of transmission of genital herpes in patients with a history of 9 or fewer recurrences per year is 500 mg once daily for the source partner. Herpes Zoster: The recommended dosage of VALTREX for treatment of herpes zoster is 1 gram 3 times daily for 7 days. Therapy should be initiated at the earliest sign or symptom of herpes zoster and is most effective when started within 48 hours of the onset of rash. Cold Sores (Herpes Labialis): The recommended dosage of VALTREX for the treatment of cold sores in pediatric patients aged greater than or equal to 12 years is 2 grams twice daily for 1 day taken 12 hours apart. Therapy should be initiated at the earliest symptom of a cold sore (e.g., tingling, itching, or burning). Chickenpox: The recommended dosage of VALTREX for treatment of chickenpox in immunocompetent pediatric patients aged 2 to less than 18 years is 20 mg/kg administered 3 times daily for 5 days. The total dose should not exceed 1 gram 3 times daily. Therapy should be initiated at the earliest sign or symptom [see Use in Specific Populations (8.4), Clinical Pharmacology (12.3), Clinical Studies (14.4)] . Ingredients and Preparation per USP─NF: VALTREX Caplets 500 mg, cherry flavor, and Suspension Structured Vehicle USP─NF (SSV). Valacyclovir oral suspension (25 mg/mL or 50 mg/mL) should be prepared in lots of 100 mL. Prepare Suspension at Time of Dispensing as Follows: • Prepare SSV according to the USP-NF. • Using a pestle and mortar, grind the required number of VALTREX 500 mg Caplets until a fine powder is produced (5 VALTREX Caplets for 25 mg/mL suspension; 10 VALTREX Caplets for 50 mg/mL suspension). • Gradually add approximately 5-mL aliquots of SSV to the mortar and triturate the powder until a paste has been produced. Ensure that the powder has been adequately wetted. • Continue to add approximately 5-mL aliquots of SSV to the mortar, mixing thoroughly between additions, until a concentrated suspension is produced, to a minimum total quantity of 20 mL SSV and a maximum total quantity of 40 mL SSV for both the 25-mg/mL and 50─mg/mL suspensions. • Transfer the mixture to a suitable 100-mL measuring flask. • Transfer the cherry flavor* to the mortar and dissolve in approximately 5 mL of SSV. Once dissolved, add to the measuring flask. • Rinse the mortar at least 3 times with approximately 5-mL aliquots of SSV, transferring the rinsing to the measuring flask between additions. • Make the suspension to volume (100 mL) with SSV and shake thoroughly to mix. • Transfer the suspension to an amber glass medicine bottle with a child─resistant closure. • The prepared suspension should be labeled with the following information “Shake well before using. Store suspension between 2° to 8°C (36° to 46°F) in a refrigerator. Discard after 28 days.” *The amount of cherry flavor added is as instructed by the suppliers of the cherry flavor. Dosage recommendations for adult patients with reduced renal function are provided in Table 1 [see Use in Specific Populations (8.5, 8.6), Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)] . Data are not available for the use of VALTREX in pediatric patients with a creatinine clearance less than 50 mL/min/1.73 m 2 . Table 1. VALTREX Dosage Recommendations for Adults With Renal Impairment Indications Normal Dosage Regimen (Creatinine Clearance ≥50 mL/min) Creatinine Clearance (mL/min) 30-49 10-29 &amp;lt;10 Cold sores (Herpes labialis) Do not exceed 1 day of treatment. Two 2 gram doses taken 12 hours apart Two 1 gram doses taken 12 hours apart Two 500 mg doses taken 12 hours apart 500 mg single dose Genital herpes: Initial episode 1 gram every 12 hours no reduction 1 gram every 24 hours 500 mg every 24 hours Genital herpes: Recurrent episode 500 mg every 12 hours no reduction 500 mg every 24 hours 500 mg every 24 hours Genital herpes: Suppressive therapy Immunocompetent patients 1 gram every 24 hours no reduction 500 mg every 24 hours 500 mg every 24 hours Alternate dose for immunocompetent patients with less than or equal to 9 recurrences/year 500 mg every 24 hours no reduction 500 mg every 48 hours 500 mg every 48 hours HIV─1─infected patients 500 mg every 12 hours no reduction 500 mg every 24 hours 500 mg every 24 hours Herpes zoster 1 gram every 8 hours 1 gram every 12 hours 1 gram every 24 hours 500 mg every 24 hours Hemodialysis: Patients requiring hemodialysis should receive the recommended dose of VALTREX after hemodialysis. During hemodialysis, the half─life of acyclovir after administration of VALTREX is approximately 4 hours. About one-third of acyclovir in the body is removed by dialysis during a 4─hour hemodialysis session. Peritoneal Dialysis: There is no information specific to administration of VALTREX in patients receiving peritoneal dialysis. The effect of chronic ambulatory peritoneal dialysis (CAPD) and continuous arteriovenous hemofiltration/dialysis (CAVHD) on acyclovir pharmacokinetics has been studied. The removal of acyclovir after CAPD and CAVHD is less pronounced than with hemodialysis, and the pharmacokinetic parameters closely resemble those observed in patients with end─stage renal disease (ESRD) not receiving hemodialysis. Therefore, supplemental doses of VALTREX should not be required following CAPD or CAVHD.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
No clinically significant drug-drug or drug-food interactions with VALTREX are known [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)].</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
• Thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura/hemolytic uremic syndrome (TTP/HUS): Has occurred in patients with advanced HIV-1 disease and in allogenic bone marrow transplant and renal transplant patients receiving 8 grams per day of VALTREX in clinical trials. Discontinue treatment if clinical symptoms and laboratory findings consistent with TTP/HUS occur. ( 5.1 ) • Acute renal failure: May occur in elderly patients (with or without reduced renal function), patients with underlying renal disease who receive higher than recommended doses of VALTREX for their level of renal function, patients who receive concomitant nephrotoxic drugs, or inadequately hydrated patients. Use with caution in elderly patients and reduce dosage in patients with renal impairment. ( 2.4 , 5.2 ) • Central nervous system adverse reactions (e.g., agitation, hallucinations, confusion, and encephalopathy): May occur in both adult and pediatric patients (with or without reduced renal function) and in patients with underlying renal disease who receive higher than recommended doses of VALTREX for their level of renal function. Elderly patients are more likely to have central nervous system adverse reactions. Use with caution in elderly patients and reduce dosage in patients with renal impairment. ( 2.4, 5.3 ) TTP/HUS, in some cases resulting in death, has occurred in patients with advanced HIV─1 disease and also in allogeneic bone marrow transplant and renal transplant recipients participating in clinical trials of VALTREX at doses of 8 grams per day. Treatment with VALTREX should be stopped immediately if clinical signs, symptoms, and laboratory abnormalities consistent with TTP/HUS occur. Cases of acute renal failure have been reported in: • Elderly patients with or without reduced renal function. Caution should be exercised when administering VALTREX to geriatric patients, and dosage reduction is recommended for those with impaired renal function [see Dosage and Administration (2.4), Use in Specific Populations (8.5)]. • Patients with underlying renal disease who received higher-than-recommended doses of VALTREX for their level of renal function. Dosage reduction is recommended when administering VALTREX to patients with renal impairment [see Dosage and Administration (2.4), Use in Specific Populations (8.6)]. • Patients receiving other nephrotoxic drugs. Caution should be exercised when administering VALTREX to patients receiving potentially nephrotoxic drugs. • Patients without adequate hydration. Precipitation of acyclovir in renal tubules may occur when the solubility (2.5 mg/mL) is exceeded in the intratubular fluid. Adequate hydration should be maintained for all patients. In the event of acute renal failure and anuria, the patient may benefit from hemodialysis until renal function is restored [see Dosage and Administration (2.4), Adverse Reactions (6.3)] . Central nervous system adverse reactions, including agitation, hallucinations, confusion, delirium, seizures, and encephalopathy, have been reported in both adult and pediatric patients with or without reduced renal function and in patients with underlying renal disease who received higher-than-recommended doses of VALTREX for their level of renal function. Elderly patients are more likely to have central nervous system adverse reactions. VALTREX should be discontinued if central nervous system adverse reactions occur [see Adverse Reactions (6.3), Use in Specific Populations (8.5, 8.6)].</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Valacyclovir is an antiviral drug [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.4)]. The pharmacokinetics of valacyclovir and acyclovir after oral administration of VALTREX have been investigated in 14 volunteer trials involving 283 adults and in 3 trials involving 112 pediatric subjects aged 1 month to less than 12 years. Pharmacokinetics in Adults: Absorption and Bioavailability: After oral administration, valacyclovir hydrochloride is rapidly absorbed from the gastrointestinal tract and nearly completely converted to acyclovir and L─ valine by first-pass intestinal and/or hepatic metabolism. The absolute bioavailability of acyclovir after administration of VALTREX is 54.5% ± 9.1% as determined following a 1─gram oral dose of VALTREX and a 350─mg intravenous acyclovir dose to 12 healthy volunteers. Acyclovir bioavailability from the administration of VALTREX is not altered by administration with food (30 minutes after an 873 Kcal breakfast, which included 51 grams of fat). Acyclovir pharmacokinetic parameter estimates following administration of VALTREX to healthy adult volunteers are presented in Table 3. There was a less than dose─proportional increase in acyclovir maximum concentration (C max ) and area under the acyclovir concentration─time curve (AUC) after single─dose and multiple─dose administration (4 times daily) of VALTREX from doses between 250 mg to 1 gram. There is no accumulation of acyclovir after the administration of valacyclovir at the recommended dosage regimens in adults with normal renal function. Table 3. Mean (±SD) Plasma Acyclovir Pharmacokinetic Parameters Following Administration of VALTREX to Healthy Adult Volunteers Dose Single─Dose Administration (N = 8) Multiple─Dose Administration a (N = 24, 8 per treatment arm) C max (±SD) (mcg/mL) AUC (±SD) (h•mcg/mL) C max (±SD) (mcg/mL) AUC (±SD) (h•mcg/mL) 100 mg 0.83 (±0.14) 2.28 (±0.40) ND ND 250 mg 2.15 (±0.50) 5.76 (±0.60) 2.11 (±0.33) 5.66 (±1.09) 500 mg 3.28 (±0.83) 11.59 (±1.79) 3.69 (±0.87) 9.88 (±2.01) 750 mg 4.17 (±1.14) 14.11 (±3.54) ND ND 1,000 mg 5.65 (±2.37) 19.52 (±6.04) 4.96 (±0.64) 15.70 (±2.27) a Administered 4 times daily for 11 days. ND = not done. Distribution: The binding of valacyclovir to human plasma proteins ranges from 13.5% to 17.9%. The binding of acyclovir to human plasma proteins ranges from 9% to 33%. Metabolism: Valacyclovir is converted to acyclovir and L─valine by first─pass intestinal and/or hepatic metabolism. Acyclovir is converted to a small extent to inactive metabolites by aldehyde oxidase and by alcohol and aldehyde dehydrogenase. Neither valacyclovir nor acyclovir is metabolized by cytochrome P450 enzymes. Plasma concentrations of unconverted valacyclovir are low and transient, generally becoming non-quantifiable by 3 hours after administration. Peak plasma valacyclovir concentrations are generally less than 0.5 mcg/mL at all doses. After single─dose administration of 1 gram of VALTREX, average plasma valacyclovir concentrations observed were 0.5, 0.4, and 0.8 mcg/mL in subjects with hepatic dysfunction, renal insufficiency, and in healthy subjects who received concomitant cimetidine and probenecid, respectively. Elimination: The pharmacokinetic disposition of acyclovir delivered by valacyclovir is consistent with previous experience from intravenous and oral acyclovir. Following the oral administration of a single 1 gram dose of radiolabeled valacyclovir to 4 healthy subjects, 46% and 47% of administered radioactivity was recovered in urine and feces, respectively, over 96 hours. Acyclovir accounted for 89% of the radioactivity excreted in the urine. Renal clearance of acyclovir following the administration of a single 1-gram dose of VALTREX to 12 healthy subjects was approximately 255 ± 86 mL/min which represents 42% of total acyclovir apparent plasma clearance. The plasma elimination half‑life of acyclovir typically averaged 2.5 to 3.3 hours in all trials of VALTREX in subjects with normal renal function. Specific Populations: Renal Impairment: Reduction in dosage is recommended in patients with renal impairment [see Dosage and Administration (2.4), Use in Specific Populations (8.5, 8.6)]. Following administration of VALTREX to subjects with ESRD, the average acyclovir half‑life is approximately 14 hours. During hemodialysis, the acyclovir half‑life is approximately 4 hours. Approximately one‑third of acyclovir in the body is removed by dialysis during a 4‑hour hemodialysis session. Apparent plasma clearance of acyclovir in subjects on dialysis was 86.3 ± 21.3 mL/min/1.73 m 2 compared with 679.16 ± 162.76 mL/min/1.73 m 2 in healthy subjects. Hepatic Impairment: Administration of VALTREX to subjects with moderate (biopsy─proven cirrhosis) or severe (with and without ascites and biopsy─proven cirrhosis) liver disease indicated that the rate but not the extent of conversion of valacyclovir to acyclovir is reduced, and the acyclovir half─life is not affected. Dosage modification is not recommended for patients with cirrhosis. HIV-1 Disease: In 9 subjects with HIV-1 disease and CD4+ cell counts less than 150 cells/mm 3 who received VALTREX at a dosage of 1 gram 4 times daily for 30 days, the pharmacokinetics of valacyclovir and acyclovir were not different from that observed in healthy subjects. Geriatrics: After single-dose administration of 1 gram of VALTREX in healthy geriatric subjects, the half‑life of acyclovir was 3.11 ± 0.51 hours, compared with 2.91 ± 0.63 hours in healthy younger adult subjects. The pharmacokinetics of acyclovir following single- and multiple‑dose oral administration of VALTREX in geriatric subjects varied with renal function. Dose reduction may be required in geriatric patients, depending on the underlying renal status of the patient [see Dosage and Administration (2.4), Use in Specific Populations (8.5. 8.6)] . Pediatrics: Acyclovir pharmacokinetics have been evaluated in a total of 98 pediatric subjects (aged 1 month to less than 12 years) following administration of the first dose of an extemporaneous oral suspension of valacyclovir [see Adverse Reactions (6.2), Use in Specific Populations (8.4)] . Acyclovir pharmacokinetic parameter estimates following a 20─mg/kg dose are provided in Table 4. Table 4. Mean (±SD) Plasma Acyclovir Pharmacokinetic Parameter Estimates Following First-Dose Administration of 20 mg/kg Valacyclovir Oral Suspension to Pediatric Subjects vs. 1─Gram Single Dose of VALTREX to Adults a Historical estimates using pediatric pharmacokinetic sampling schedule. Parameter Pediatric Subjects (20 mg/kg Oral Suspension) Adults 1─gram Solid Dose of VALTREX a (N = 15) 1 -&amp;lt;2 yr (N = 6) 2 -&amp;lt;6 yr (N = 12) 6 -&amp;lt;12 yr (N = 8) AUC (mcg•h/mL) 14.4 (±6.26) 10.1 (±3.35) 13.1 (±3.43) 17.2 (±3.10) C max (mcg/mL) 4.03 (±1.37) 3.75 (±1.14) 4.71 (±1.20) 4.72 (±1.37) Drug Interactions: When VALTREX is coadministered with antacids, cimetidine and/or probenicid, digoxin, or thiazide diuretics in patients with normal renal function, the effects are not considered to be of clinical significance (see below). Therefore, when VALTREX is coadministered with these drugs in patients with normal renal function, no dosage adjustment is recommended. Antacids: The pharmacokinetics of acyclovir after a single dose of VALTREX (1 gram) were unchanged by coadministration of a single dose of antacids (Al 3+ or Mg ++ ). Cimetidine: Acyclovir C max and AUC following a single dose of VALTREX (1 gram) increased by 8% and 32%, respectively, after a single dose of cimetidine (800 mg). Cimetidine Plus Probenecid: Acyclovir C max and AUC following a single dose of VALTREX (1 gram) increased by 30% and 78%, respectively, after a combination of cimetidine and probenecid, primarily due to a reduction in renal clearance of acyclovir. Digoxin: The pharmacokinetics of digoxin were not affected by coadministration of VALTREX 1 gram 3 times daily, and the pharmacokinetics of acyclovir after a single dose of VALTREX (1 gram) was unchanged by coadministration of digoxin (2 doses of 0.75 mg). Probenecid: Acyclovir C max and AUC following a single dose of VALTREX (1 gram) increased by 22% and 49%, respectively, after probenecid (1 gram). Thiazide Diuretics: The pharmacokinetics of acyclovir after a single dose of VALTREX (1 gram) were unchanged by coadministration of multiple doses of thiazide diuretics. Mechanism of Action: Valacyclovir is a nucleoside analogue DNA polymerase inhibitor. Valacyclovir hydrochloride is rapidly converted to acyclovir which has demonstrated antiviral activity against HSV types 1 (HSV─1) and 2 (HSV─2) and VZV both in cell culture and in vivo. The inhibitory activity of acyclovir is highly selective due to its affinity for the enzyme thymidine kinase (TK) encoded by HSV and VZV. This viral enzyme converts acyclovir into acyclovir monophosphate, a nucleotide analogue. The monophosphate is further converted into diphosphate by cellular guanylate kinase and into triphosphate by a number of cellular enzymes. In biochemical assays, acyclovir triphosphate inhibits replication of herpes viral DNA. This is accomplished in 3 ways: 1) competitive inhibition of viral DNA polymerase, 2) incorporation and termination of the growing viral DNA chain, and 3) inactivation of the viral DNA polymerase. The greater antiviral activity of acyclovir against HSV compared with VZV is due to its more efficient phosphorylation by the viral TK. Antiviral Activities: The quantitative relationship between the cell culture susceptibility of herpesviruses to antivirals and the clinical response to therapy has not been established in humans, and virus sensitivity testing has not been standardized. Sensitivity testing results, expressed as the concentration of drug required to inhibit by 50% the growth of virus in cell culture (EC 50 ), vary greatly depending upon a number of factors. Using plaque-reduction assays, the EC 50 values against herpes simplex virus isolates range from 0.09 to 60 μM (0.02 to 13.5 mcg/mL) for HSV─1 and from 0.04 to 44 µM (0.01 to 9.9 mcg/mL) for HSV─2. The EC 50 values for acyclovir against most laboratory strains and clinical isolates of VZV range from 0.53 to 48 µM (0.12 to 10.8 mcg/mL). Acyclovir also demonstrates activity against the Oka vaccine strain of VZV with a mean EC 50 of 6 µM (1.35 mcg/mL). Resistance: Resistance of HSV and VZV to acyclovir can result from qualitative and quantitative changes in the viral TK and/or DNA polymerase. Clinical isolates of VZV with reduced susceptibility to acyclovir have been recovered from patients with AIDS. In these cases, TK-deficient mutants of VZV have been recovered. Resistance of HSV and VZV to acyclovir occurs by the same mechanisms. While most of the acyclovir─resistant mutants isolated thus far from immunocompromised patients have been found to be TK─deficient mutants, other mutants involving the viral TK gene (TK partial and TK altered) and DNA polymerase have also been isolated. TK─negative mutants may cause severe disease in immunocompromised patients. The possibility of viral resistance to valacyclovir (and therefore, to acyclovir) should be considered in patients who show poor clinical response during therapy.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="7040" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>VALTREX is contraindicated in patients who have had a demonstrated clinically significant hypersensitivity reaction (e.g., anaphylaxis) to valacyclovir, acyclovir, or any component of the formulation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7041" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Hypersensitivity to valacyclovir (e.g., anaphylaxis), acyclovir, or any component of the formulation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7042" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>VALTREX may be given without regard to meals.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7043" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Valacyclovir oral suspension (25 mg/mL or 50 mg/mL) may be prepared extemporaneously from 500-mg VALTREX Caplets for use in pediatric patients for whom a solid dosage form is not appropriate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7044" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Adult Dosage (2.1) Cold Sores 2 grams every 12 hours for 1 day Genital Herpes Initial episode 1 gram twice daily for 10 days Recurrent episodes 500 mg twice daily for 3 days Suppressive therapy Immunocompetent patients 1 gram once daily Alternate dose in patients with less than or equal to 9 recurrences/year 500 mg once daily HIV-1─infected patients 500 mg twice daily Reduction of transmission 500 mg once daily Herpes Zoster 1 gram 3 times daily for 7 days Pediatric Dosage (2.2) Cold Sores (aged greater than or equal to 12 years) 2 grams every 12 hours for 1 day Chickenpox (aged 2 to less than 18 years) 20 mg/kg 3 times daily for 5 days; not to exceed 1 gram 3 times daily Valacyclovir oral suspension (25 mg/mL or 50 mg/mL) can be prepared from the 500 mg VALTREX Caplets.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7045" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Cold Sores (Herpes Labialis): The recommended dosage of VALTREX for treatment of cold sores is 2 grams twice daily for 1 day taken 12 hours apart.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7046" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Therapy should be initiated at the earliest symptom of a cold sore (e.g., tingling, itching, or burning).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7047" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Genital Herpes: Initial Episode: The recommended dosage of VALTREX for treatment of initial genital herpes is 1 gram twice daily for 10 days.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7048" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Therapy was most effective when administered within 48 hours of the onset of signs and symptoms.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7049" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Recurrent Episodes: The recommended dosage of VALTREX for treatment of recurrent genital herpes is 500 mg twice daily for 3 days.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7050" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Initiate treatment at the first sign or symptom of an episode.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7051" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Suppressive Therapy: The recommended dosage of VALTREX for chronic suppressive therapy of recurrent genital herpes is 1 gram once daily in patients with normal immune function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7052" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In patients with a history of 9 or fewer recurrences per year, an alternative dose is 500 mg once daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7053" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In HIV─1─infected patients with a CD4+ cell count greater than or equal to 100 cells/mm3, the recommended dosage of VALTREX for chronic suppressive therapy of recurrent genital herpes is 500 mg twice daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7054" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Reduction of Transmission: The recommended dosage of VALTREX for reduction of transmission of genital herpes in patients with a history of 9 or fewer recurrences per year is 500 mg once daily for the source partner.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7055" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Herpes Zoster: The recommended dosage of VALTREX for treatment of herpes zoster is 1 gram 3 times daily for 7 days.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7056" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Therapy should be initiated at the earliest sign or symptom of herpes zoster and is most effective when started within 48 hours of the onset of rash.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7057" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Cold Sores (Herpes Labialis): The recommended dosage of VALTREX for the treatment of cold sores in pediatric patients aged greater than or equal to 12 years is 2 grams twice daily for 1 day taken 12 hours apart.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7058" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Chickenpox: The recommended dosage of VALTREX for treatment of chickenpox in immunocompetent pediatric patients aged 2 to less than 18 years is 20 mg/kg administered 3 times daily for 5 days.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7059" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The total dose should not exceed 1 gram 3 times daily.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7060" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Therapy should be initiated at the earliest sign or symptom.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7061" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Ingredients and Preparation per USP─NF: VALTREX Caplets 500 mg, cherry flavor, and Suspension Structured Vehicle USP─NF (SSV).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7062" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Valacyclovir oral suspension (25 mg/mL or 50 mg/mL) should be prepared in lots of 100 mL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7063" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Prepare Suspension at Time of Dispensing as Follows: Prepare SSV according to the USP-NF.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7064" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Using a pestle and mortar, grind the required number of VALTREX 500 mg Caplets until a fine powder is produced (5 VALTREX Caplets for 25 mg/mL suspension; 10 VALTREX Caplets for 50 mg/mL suspension).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7065" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Gradually add approximately 5-mL aliquots of SSV to the mortar and triturate the powder until a paste has been produced.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7066" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Ensure that the powder has been adequately wetted.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7067" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Continue to add approximately 5-mL aliquots of SSV to the mortar, mixing thoroughly between additions, until a concentrated suspension is produced, to a minimum total quantity of 20 mL SSV and a maximum total quantity of 40 mL SSV for both the 25-mg/mL and 50─mg/mL suspensions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7068" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Transfer the mixture to a suitable 100-mL measuring flask.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7069" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Transfer the cherry flavor* to the mortar and dissolve in approximately 5 mL of SSV.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7070" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Once dissolved, add to the measuring flask.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7071" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Rinse the mortar at least 3 times with approximately 5-mL aliquots of SSV, transferring the rinsing to the measuring flask between additions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7072" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Make the suspension to volume (100 mL) with SSV and shake thoroughly to mix.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7073" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Transfer the suspension to an amber glass medicine bottle with a child─resistant closure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7074" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The prepared suspension should be labeled with the following information “Shake well before using.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7075" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Store suspension between 2° to 8°C (36° to 46°F) in a refrigerator.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7076" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Discard after 28 days.” *The amount of cherry flavor added is as instructed by the suppliers of the cherry flavor.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7077" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dosage recommendations for adult patients with reduced renal function are provided in Table 1.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7078" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Data are not available for the use of VALTREX in pediatric patients with a creatinine clearance less than 50 mL/min/1.73 m2.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7079" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>VALTREX Dosage Recommendations for Adults With Renal Impairment Indications Normal Dosage Regimen (Creatinine Clearance ≥50 mL/min) Creatinine Clearance (mL/min) 30-49 10-29 &lt;10 Cold sores (Herpes labialis) Do not exceed 1 day of treatment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7080" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Two 2 gram doses taken 12 hours apart Two 1 gram doses taken 12 hours apart Two 500 mg doses taken 12 hours apart 500 mg single dose Genital herpes: Initial episode 1 gram every 12 hours no reduction 1 gram every 24 hours 500 mg every 24 hours Genital herpes: Recurrent episode 500 mg every 12 hours no reduction 500 mg every 24 hours 500 mg every 24 hours Genital herpes: Suppressive therapy Immunocompetent patients 1 gram every 24 hours no reduction 500 mg every 24 hours 500 mg every 24 hours Alternate dose for immunocompetent patients with less than or equal to 9 recurrences/year 500 mg every 24 hours no reduction 500 mg every 48 hours 500 mg every 48 hours HIV─1─infected patients 500 mg every 12 hours no reduction 500 mg every 24 hours 500 mg every 24 hours Herpes zoster 1 gram every 8 hours 1 gram every 12 hours 1 gram every 24 hours 500 mg every 24 hours Hemodialysis: Patients requiring hemodialysis should receive the recommended dose of VALTREX after hemodialysis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7081" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>During hemodialysis, the half─life of acyclovir after administration of VALTREX is approximately 4 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7082" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>About one-third of acyclovir in the body is removed by dialysis during a 4─hour hemodialysis session.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7083" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Peritoneal Dialysis: There is no information specific to administration of VALTREX in patients receiving peritoneal dialysis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7084" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The effect of chronic ambulatory peritoneal dialysis (CAPD) and continuous arteriovenous hemofiltration/dialysis (CAVHD) on acyclovir pharmacokinetics has been studied.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7085" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The removal of acyclovir after CAPD and CAVHD is less pronounced than with hemodialysis, and the pharmacokinetic parameters closely resemble those observed in patients with end─stage renal disease (ESRD) not receiving hemodialysis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7086" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Therefore, supplemental doses of VALTREX should not be required following CAPD or CAVHD.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7087" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>No clinically significant drug-drug or drug-food interactions with VALTREX are known.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7088" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura/hemolytic uremic syndrome (TTP/HUS): Has occurred in patients with advanced HIV-1 disease and in allogenic bone marrow transplant and renal transplant patients receiving 8 grams per day of VALTREX in clinical trials.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7089" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Discontinue treatment if clinical symptoms and laboratory findings consistent with TTP/HUS occur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7090" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Acute renal failure: May occur in elderly patients (with or without reduced renal function), patients with underlying renal disease who receive higher than recommended doses of VALTREX for their level of renal function, patients who receive concomitant nephrotoxic drugs, or inadequately hydrated patients.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M1" type="Trigger" span="25 5" str="occur"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="253 17" str="nephrotoxic drugs" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M3" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 19" str="acute renal failure" code="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M1" precipitant="M2" effect="M3" effectCodeMatch="Exact"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7091" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Use with caution in elderly patients and reduce dosage in patients with renal impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7092" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Central nervous system adverse reactions (e.g., agitation, hallucinations, confusion, and encephalopathy): May occur in both adult and pediatric patients (with or without reduced renal function) and in patients with underlying renal disease who receive higher than recommended doses of VALTREX for their level of renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7093" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Elderly patients are more likely to have central nervous system adverse reactions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7094" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>TTP/HUS, in some cases resulting in death, has occurred in patients with advanced HIV─1 disease and also in allogeneic bone marrow transplant and renal transplant recipients participating in clinical trials of VALTREX at doses of 8 grams per day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7095" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Treatment with VALTREX should be stopped immediately if clinical signs, symptoms, and laboratory abnormalities consistent with TTP/HUS occur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7096" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Cases of acute renal failure have been reported in: Elderly patients with or without reduced renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7097" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Caution should be exercised when administering VALTREX to geriatric patients, and dosage reduction is recommended for those with impaired renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7098" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients with underlying renal disease who received higher-than-recommended doses of VALTREX for their level of renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7099" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Dosage reduction is recommended when administering VALTREX to patients with renal impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7100" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients receiving other nephrotoxic drugs.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7101" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Caution should be exercised when administering VALTREX to patients receiving potentially nephrotoxic drugs.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M4" type="Trigger" span="0 7" str="Caution"/>
<Mention id="M5" type="Precipitant" span="89 17" str="nephrotoxic drugs" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M4" precipitant="M5"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7102" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Precipitation of acyclovir in renal tubules may occur when the solubility (2.5 mg/mL) is exceeded in the intratubular fluid.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7103" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Adequate hydration should be maintained for all patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7104" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In the event of acute renal failure and anuria, the patient may benefit from hemodialysis until renal function is restored.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7105" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Central nervous system adverse reactions, including agitation, hallucinations, confusion, delirium, seizures, and encephalopathy, have been reported in both adult and pediatric patients with or without reduced renal function and in patients with underlying renal disease who received higher-than-recommended doses of VALTREX for their level of renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7106" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>VALTREX should be discontinued if central nervous system adverse reactions occur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7107" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Valacyclovir is an antiviral drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7108" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacokinetics of valacyclovir and acyclovir after oral administration of VALTREX have been investigated in 14 volunteer trials involving 283 adults and in 3 trials involving 112 pediatric subjects aged 1 month to less than 12 years.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7109" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Pharmacokinetics in Adults: Absorption and Bioavailability: After oral administration, valacyclovir hydrochloride is rapidly absorbed from the gastrointestinal tract and nearly completely converted to acyclovir and L─valine by first-pass intestinal and/or hepatic metabolism.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7110" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The absolute bioavailability of acyclovir after administration of VALTREX is 54.5% ± 9.1% as determined following a 1─gram oral dose of VALTREX and a 350─mg intravenous acyclovir dose to 12 healthy volunteers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7111" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Acyclovir bioavailability from the administration of VALTREX is not altered by administration with food (30 minutes after an 873 Kcal breakfast, which included 51 grams of fat).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7112" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Acyclovir pharmacokinetic parameter estimates following administration of VALTREX to healthy adult volunteers are presented in Table 3.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7113" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There was a less than dose─proportional increase in acyclovir maximum concentration (Cmax) and area under the acyclovir concentration─time curve (AUC) after single─dose and multiple─dose administration (4 times daily) of VALTREX from doses between 250 mg to 1 gram.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7114" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There is no accumulation of acyclovir after the administration of valacyclovir at the recommended dosage regimens in adults with normal renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7115" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Mean (±SD) Plasma Acyclovir Pharmacokinetic Parameters Following Administration of VALTREX to Healthy Adult Volunteers Dose Single─Dose Administration (N = 8) Multiple─Dose Administrationa (N = 24, 8 per treatment arm) Cmax (±SD) (mcg/mL) AUC (±SD) (hmcg/mL) Cmax (±SD) (mcg/mL) AUC (±SD) (hmcg/mL) 100 mg 0.83 (±0.14) 2.28 (±0.40) ND ND 250 mg 2.15 (±0.50) 5.76 (±0.60) 2.11 (±0.33) 5.66 (±1.09) 500 mg 3.28 (±0.83) 11.59 (±1.79) 3.69 (±0.87) 9.88 (±2.01) 750 mg 4.17 (±1.14) 14.11 (±3.54) ND ND 1,000 mg 5.65 (±2.37) 19.52 (±6.04) 4.96 (±0.64) 15.70 (±2.27) a Administered 4 times daily for 11 days.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7116" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Distribution: The binding of valacyclovir to human plasma proteins ranges from 13.5% to 17.9%.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7117" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The binding of acyclovir to human plasma proteins ranges from 9% to 33%.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7118" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Metabolism: Valacyclovir is converted to acyclovir and L─valine by first─pass intestinal and/or hepatic metabolism.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7119" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Acyclovir is converted to a small extent to inactive metabolites by aldehyde oxidase and by alcohol and aldehyde dehydrogenase.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7120" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Neither valacyclovir nor acyclovir is metabolized by cytochrome P450 enzymes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7121" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Plasma concentrations of unconverted valacyclovir are low and transient, generally becoming non-quantifiable by 3 hours after administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7122" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Peak plasma valacyclovir concentrations are generally less than 0.5 mcg/mL at all doses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7123" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>After single─dose administration of 1 gram of VALTREX, average plasma valacyclovir concentrations observed were 0.5, 0.4, and 0.8 mcg/mL in subjects with hepatic dysfunction, renal insufficiency, and in healthy subjects who received concomitant cimetidine and probenecid, respectively.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7124" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Elimination: The pharmacokinetic disposition of acyclovir delivered by valacyclovir is consistent with previous experience from intravenous and oral acyclovir.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7125" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following the oral administration of a single 1 gram dose of radiolabeled valacyclovir to 4 healthy subjects, 46% and 47% of administered radioactivity was recovered in urine and feces, respectively, over 96 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7126" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Acyclovir accounted for 89% of the radioactivity excreted in the urine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7127" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Renal clearance of acyclovir following the administration of a single 1-gram dose of VALTREX to 12 healthy subjects was approximately 255 ± 86 mL/min which represents 42% of total acyclovir apparent plasma clearance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7128" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The plasma elimination half‑life of acyclovir typically averaged 2.5 to 3.3 hours in all trials of VALTREX in subjects with normal renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7129" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Specific Populations: Renal Impairment: Reduction in dosage is recommended in patients with renal impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7130" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Following administration of VALTREX to subjects with ESRD, the average acyclovir half‑life is approximately 14 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7131" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>During hemodialysis, the acyclovir half‑life is approximately 4 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7132" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Approximately one‑third of acyclovir in the body is removed by dialysis during a 4‑hour hemodialysis session.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7133" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Apparent plasma clearance of acyclovir in subjects on dialysis was 86.3 ± 21.3 mL/min/1.73 m2 compared with 679.16 ± 162.76 mL/min/1.73 m2 in healthy subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7134" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Hepatic Impairment: Administration of VALTREX to subjects with moderate (biopsy─proven cirrhosis) or severe (with and without ascites and biopsy─proven cirrhosis) liver disease indicated that the rate but not the extent of conversion of valacyclovir to acyclovir is reduced, and the acyclovir half─life is not affected.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7135" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Dosage modification is not recommended for patients with cirrhosis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7136" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>HIV-1 Disease: In 9 subjects with HIV-1 disease and CD4+ cell counts less than 150 cells/mm3 who received VALTREX at a dosage of 1 gram 4 times daily for 30 days, the pharmacokinetics of valacyclovir and acyclovir were not different from that observed in healthy subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7137" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Geriatrics: After single-dose administration of 1 gram of VALTREX in healthy geriatric subjects, the half‑life of acyclovir was 3.11 ± 0.51 hours, compared with 2.91 ± 0.63 hours in healthy younger adult subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7138" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacokinetics of acyclovir following single- and multiple‑dose oral administration of VALTREX in geriatric subjects varied with renal function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7139" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Dose reduction may be required in geriatric patients, depending on the underlying renal status of the patient [see Dosage and Administration (2.4), Use in Specific Populations (8.5.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7140" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Pediatrics: Acyclovir pharmacokinetics have been evaluated in a total of 98 pediatric subjects (aged 1 month to less than 12 years) following administration of the first dose of an extemporaneous oral suspension of valacyclovir.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7141" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Acyclovir pharmacokinetic parameter estimates following a 20─mg/kg dose are provided in Table 4.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7142" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Mean (±SD) Plasma Acyclovir Pharmacokinetic Parameter Estimates Following First-Dose Administration of 20 mg/kg Valacyclovir Oral Suspension to Pediatric Subjects vs. 1─Gram Single Dose of VALTREX to Adults a Historical estimates using pediatric pharmacokinetic sampling schedule.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7143" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Parameter Pediatric Subjects (20 mg/kg Oral Suspension) Adults 1─gram Solid Dose of VALTREXa (N = 15) 1 -&lt;2 yr (N = 6) 2 -&lt;6 yr (N = 12) 6 -&lt;12 yr (N = 8) AUC (mcgh/mL) 14.4 (±6.26) 10.1 (±3.35) 13.1 (±3.43) 17.2 (±3.10) Cmax (mcg/mL) 4.03 (±1.37) 3.75 (±1.14) 4.71 (±1.20) 4.72 (±1.37) Drug Interactions: When VALTREX is coadministered with antacids, cimetidine and/or probenicid, digoxin, or thiazide diuretics in patients with normal renal function, the effects are not considered to be of clinical significance.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7144" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Therefore, when VALTREX is coadministered with these drugs in patients with normal renal function, no dosage adjustment is recommended.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7145" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Antacids: The pharmacokinetics of acyclovir after a single dose of VALTREX (1 gram) were unchanged by coadministration of a single dose of antacids (Al3+ or Mg++).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7146" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Cimetidine: Acyclovir Cmax and AUC following a single dose of VALTREX (1 gram) increased by 8% and 32%, respectively, after a single dose of cimetidine (800 mg).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M6" type="Trigger" span="31 3;79 9" str="AUC | increased"/>
<Mention id="M9" type="Precipitant" span="0 10" str="cimetidine" code="80061L1WGD"/>
<Mention id="M8" type="Trigger" span="22 4;79 9" str="Cmax | increased"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M6" precipitant="M9" effect="C54605"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M8" precipitant="M9" effect="C54602"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7147" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Cimetidine Plus Probenecid: Acyclovir Cmax and AUC following a single dose of VALTREX (1 gram) increased by 30% and 78%, respectively, after a combination of cimetidine and probenecid, primarily due to a reduction in renal clearance of acyclovir.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M10" type="Trigger" span="47 3;95 9" str="AUC | increased"/>
<Mention id="M15" type="Precipitant" span="143 40" str="combination of cimetidine and probenecid" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M12" type="Trigger" span="38 4;95 9" str="Cmax | increased"/>
<Mention id="M14" type="Trigger" span="204 28" str="reduction in renal clearance"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M10" precipitant="M15" effect="C54605"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M12" precipitant="M15" effect="C54602"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M14" precipitant="M15" effect="C54355"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7148" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Digoxin: The pharmacokinetics of digoxin were not affected by coadministration of VALTREX 1 gram 3 times daily, and the pharmacokinetics of acyclovir after a single dose of VALTREX (1 gram) was unchanged by coadministration of digoxin (2 doses of 0.75 mg).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7149" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Probenecid: Acyclovir Cmax and AUC following a single dose of VALTREX (1 gram) increased by 22% and 49%, respectively, after probenecid (1 gram).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M16" type="Trigger" span="31 3;79 9" str="AUC | increased"/>
<Mention id="M19" type="Precipitant" span="0 10" str="probenecid" code="PO572Z7917"/>
<Mention id="M18" type="Trigger" span="22 4;79 9" str="Cmax | increased"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M16" precipitant="M19" effect="C54605"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M18" precipitant="M19" effect="C54602"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7150" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Thiazide Diuretics: The pharmacokinetics of acyclovir after a single dose of VALTREX (1 gram) were unchanged by coadministration of multiple doses of thiazide diuretics.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7151" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Mechanism of Action: Valacyclovir is a nucleoside analogue DNA polymerase inhibitor.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7152" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Valacyclovir hydrochloride is rapidly converted to acyclovir which has demonstrated antiviral activity against HSV types 1 (HSV─1) and 2 (HSV─2) and VZV both in cell culture and in vivo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7153" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The inhibitory activity of acyclovir is highly selective due to its affinity for the enzyme thymidine kinase (TK) encoded by HSV and VZV.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7154" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This viral enzyme converts acyclovir into acyclovir monophosphate, a nucleotide analogue.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7155" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The monophosphate is further converted into diphosphate by cellular guanylate kinase and into triphosphate by a number of cellular enzymes.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7156" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In biochemical assays, acyclovir triphosphate inhibits replication of herpes viral DNA.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7157" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>This is accomplished in 3 ways: 1) competitive inhibition of viral DNA polymerase, 2) incorporation and termination of the growing viral DNA chain, and 3) inactivation of the viral DNA polymerase.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7158" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The greater antiviral activity of acyclovir against HSV compared with VZV is due to its more efficient phosphorylation by the viral TK.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7159" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Antiviral Activities: The quantitative relationship between the cell culture susceptibility of herpesviruses to antivirals and the clinical response to therapy has not been established in humans, and virus sensitivity testing has not been standardized.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7160" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Sensitivity testing results, expressed as the concentration of drug required to inhibit by 50% the growth of virus in cell culture (EC50), vary greatly depending upon a number of factors.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7161" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Using plaque-reduction assays, the EC50 values against herpes simplex virus isolates range from 0.09 to 60 μM (0.02 to 13.5 mcg/mL) for HSV─1 and from 0.04 to 44 µM (0.01 to 9.9 mcg/mL) for HSV─2.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7162" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The EC50 values for acyclovir against most laboratory strains and clinical isolates of VZV range from 0.53 to 48 µM (0.12 to 10.8 mcg/mL).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7163" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Acyclovir also demonstrates activity against the Oka vaccine strain of VZV with a mean EC50 of 6 µM (1.35 mcg/mL).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7164" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Resistance: Resistance of HSV and VZV to acyclovir can result from qualitative and quantitative changes in the viral TK and/or DNA polymerase.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7165" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Clinical isolates of VZV with reduced susceptibility to acyclovir have been recovered from patients with AIDS.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7166" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In these cases, TK-deficient mutants of VZV have been recovered.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7167" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Resistance of HSV and VZV to acyclovir occurs by the same mechanisms.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7168" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>While most of the acyclovir─resistant mutants isolated thus far from immunocompromised patients have been found to be TK─deficient mutants, other mutants involving the viral TK gene (TK partial and TK altered) and DNA polymerase have also been isolated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7169" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>TK─negative mutants may cause severe disease in immunocompromised patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="7170" LabelDrug="VALTREX" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The possibility of viral resistance to valacyclovir (and therefore, to acyclovir) should be considered in patients who show poor clinical response during therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="nephrotoxic drugs" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="14669001: Acute renal failure syndrome (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="nephrotoxic drugs" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cimetidine" precipitantCode="80061L1WGD" effect="C54602"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="cimetidine" precipitantCode="80061L1WGD" effect="C54605"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="combination of cimetidine and probenecid" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="combination of cimetidine and probenecid" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54602"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="combination of cimetidine and probenecid" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54605"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="probenecid" precipitantCode="PO572Z7917" effect="C54602"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="probenecid" precipitantCode="PO572Z7917" effect="C54605"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>