<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" setid="fbb6a064-59a6-4e1c-bbb6-5934c1505c4f">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
Pentazocine hydrochloride and acetaminophen tablets should not be administered to patients who are hypersensitive to either pentazocine or acetaminophen.</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
Adult. The usual adult dose is 1 tablet every 4 hours as needed for pain relief, up to maximum of 6 tablets per day. The usual duration of therapy is dependent upon the condition being treated but in any case should be reviewed regularly by the physician. The effect of meals on the rate and extent of bioavailability of both pentazocine and acetaminophen has not been documented.</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
Pentazocine is a mild narcotic antagonist. Some patients previously given narcotics, including methadone for the daily treatment of narcotic dependence, have experienced withdrawal symptoms after receiving pentazocine.</Section>
<Section name="PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="42232-9">
In prescribing pentazocine hydrochloride and acetaminophen tablets for chronic use, the physician should take precautions to avoid increases in dose by the patient. As with all drugs, pentazocine hydrochloride and acetaminophen tablets should be used with caution in patients with myocardial infarction who have nausea or vomiting. Although respiratory depression has rarely been reported after oral administration of pentazocine, the drug should be administered with caution to patients with respiratory depression from any cause, severely limited respiratory reserve, severe bronchial asthma and other obstructive respiratory conditions, or cyanosis. Decreased metabolism of the drug by the liver in extensive liver disease may predispose to accentuation of side effects. Although laboratory tests have not indicated that pentazocine causes or increases renal or hepatic impairment, the drug should be administered with caution to patients with such impairment. Since acetaminophen is metabolized by the liver, the question of the safety of its use in the presence of liver disease should be considered. Narcotic drug products are generally considered to elevate biliary tract pressure for varying periods following their administration. Some evidence suggests that pentazocine may differ from other marketed narcotics in this respect (i.e., it causes little or no elevation in biliary tract pressures). The clinical significance of these findings, however, is not yet known. Caution should be used when pentazocine hydrochloride and acetaminophen tablets are administered to patients prone to seizures; seizures have occurred in a few such patients in association with the use of pentazocine although no cause and effect relationship has been established. Since sedation, dizziness, and occasional euphoria have been noted, ambulatory patients should be warned not to operate machinery, drive cars, or unnecessarily expose themselves to hazards. Pentazocine may cause physical and psychological dependence when taken alone and may have additive CNS depressant properties when taken in combination with alcohol or other CNS depressants. Pentazocine is a mild narcotic antagonist. Some patients previously given narcotics, including methadone for the daily treatment of narcotic dependence, have experienced withdrawal symptoms after receiving pentazocine. Carcinogenesis, mutagenesis, and impairment of fertility studies have not been done with this combination product. Pentazocine, when administered orally or parenterally, had no adverse effect on either the reproductive capabilities or the course of pregnancy in rabbits and rats. Embryotoxic effects on the fetuses were not shown. The daily administration of 4 mg/kg to 20 mg/kg pentazocine subcutaneously to female rats during a 14 day pre-mating period and until the 13th day of pregnancy did not have any adverse effects on the fertility rate. There is no evidence in long-term animal studies to demonstrate that pentazocine is carcinogenic. Animal reproduction studies have not been conducted with pentazocine hydrochloride and acetaminophen tablets. It is also not known whether pentazocine hydrochloride and acetaminophen tablets can cause fetal harm when administered to pregnant women or can affect reproduction capacity. Pentazocine hydrochloride and acetaminophen tablets should be given to pregnant women only if clearly needed. However, animal reproduction studies with pentazocine have not demonstrated teratogenic or embryotoxic effects. There has been no experience in this regard with the combination pentazocine and acetaminophen. However, there have been rare reports of possible abstinence syndromes in newborns after prolonged use of pentazocine during pregnancy. Patients receiving pentazocine during labor have experienced no adverse effects other than those that occur with commonly used analgesics. Pentazocine hydrochloride and acetaminophen tablets should be used with caution in women delivering premature infants. The effect of pentazocine hydrochloride and acetaminophen tablets on the mother and fetus, the duration of labor or delivery, the possibility that forceps delivery or other intervention or resuscitation of the newborn may be necessary, or the effect of pentazocine hydrochloride and acetaminophen tablets on the later growth, development, and functional maturation of the child are unknown at the present time. It is not known whether this drug is excreted in human milk. Because many drugs are excreted in human milk, caution should be exercised when pentazocine hydrochloride and acetaminophen tablets are administered to a nursing woman. Safety and effectiveness in pediatric patients below the age of 12 have not been established. Clinical studies of pentazocine hydrochloride and acetaminophen tablets did not include sufficient numbers of subjects aged 65 and over to determine whether they respond differently from younger subjects. Other reported clinical experience has not identified differences in responses between the elderly and younger patients. In general, dose selection for an elderly patient should be cautious, usually starting at the low end of the dosing range, reflecting the greater frequency of decreased hepatic, renal, or cardiac function, and of concomitant disease or other drug therapy.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS SECTION" id="34071-1">
Head Injury and Increased Intracranial Pressure. As in the case of other potent analgesics, the potential of pentazocine for elevating cerebrospinal fluid pressure may be attributed to CO 2 retention due to the respiratory depressant effects of the drug. These effects may be markedly exaggerated in the presence of head injury, other intracranial lesions, or a pre-existing increase in intracranial pressure. Furthermore, pentazocine can produce effects which may obscure the clinical course of patients with head injuries. In such patients, pentazocine hydrochloride and acetaminophen tablets must be used with extreme caution and only if its use is deemed essential. Acute CNS Manifestations. Patients receiving therapeutic doses of pentazocine have experienced hallucinations (usually visual), disorientation, and confusion which have cleared spontaneously within a period of hours. The mechanism of this reaction is not known. Such patients should be closely observed and vital signs checked. If the drug is reinstituted, it should be done with caution since these acute CNS manifestations may recur. There have been instances of psychological and physical dependence on parenteral pentazocine in patients with a history of drug abuse, and rarely, in patients without such a history. (See DRUG ABUSE AND DEPENDENCE . ) Due to the potential for increased CNS depressant effects, alcohol should be used with caution in patients who are currently receiving pentazocine. Pentazocine may precipitate opioid abstinence symptoms in patients receiving courses of opiates for pain relief.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
Pentazocine hydrochloride and acetaminophen tablets are an analgesic possessing antipyretic actions. Pentazocine is an analgesic with agonist/antagonist action which when administered orally is approximately equivalent on a mg for mg basis in analgesic effect to codeine. Acetaminophen is an analgesic and antipyretic. Onset of significant analgesia with pentazocine usually occurs between 15 and 30 minutes after oral administration, and duration of action is usually three hours or longer. Onset and duration of action and the degree of pain relief are related both to dose and the severity of pretreatment pain. Pentazocine weakly antagonizes the analgesic effects of morphine, meperidine, and phenazocine; in addition, it produces incomplete reversal of cardiovascular, respiratory, and behavioral depression induced by morphine and meperidine. Pentazocine has about 1/50 the antagonistic activity of nalorphine. It also has a sedative activity. Pentazocine is well absorbed from the gastrointestinal tract. Plasma levels closely correspond to the onset, duration, and intensity of analgesia. The time to mean peak concentration in 24 normal volunteers was 1.7 hours (range 0.5 to 4 hours) after oral administration and the mean plasma elimination half-life was 3.6 hours (range 1.5 to 10 hours). The action of pentazocine is terminated for the most part by biotransformation in the liver with some free pentazocine excreted in the urine. The products of the oxidation of the terminal methyl groups and glucuronide conjugates are excreted by the kidney. Elimination of approximately 60% of the total dose occurs within 24 hours. Pentazocine passes the placental barrier. Onset of significant analgesic and antipyretic activity of acetaminophen when administered orally occurs within 30 minutes and is maximal at approximately 2 1 / 2 hours. The pharmacological mode of action of acetaminophen is unknown at this time. Acetaminophen is rapidly and almost completely absorbed from the gastrointestinal tract. In 24 normal volunteers the mean time to peak plasma concentration was 1 hour (range 0.25 to 3 hours) after oral administration and the mean plasma elimination half-life was 2.8 hours (range 2 to 4 hours). The effect of pentazocine on acetaminophen plasma protein binding or vice versa has not been established. For acetaminophen there is little or no plasma protein binding at normal therapeutic doses. When toxic doses of acetaminophen are ingested and drug plasma levels exceed 90 mcg/mL, plasma binding may vary from 8% to 43%. Acetaminophen is conjugated in the liver with glucuronic acid and to a lesser extent with sulfuric acid. Approximately 80% of acetaminophen is excreted in the urine after conjugation and about 3% is excreted unchanged. The drug is also conjugated to a lesser extent with cysteine and additionally metabolized by hydroxylation. If pentazocine hydrochloride and acetaminophen tablets are taken every 4 hours over an extended period of time, accumulation of pentazocine and to a lesser extent, acetaminophen, may occur.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="10305" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Pentazocine hydrochloride and acetaminophen tablets should not be administered to patients who are hypersensitive to either pentazocine or acetaminophen.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10306" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The usual adult dose is 1 tablet every 4 hours as needed for pain relief, up to maximum of 6 tablets per day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10307" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The usual duration of therapy is dependent upon the condition being treated but in any case should be reviewed regularly by the physician.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10308" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The effect of meals on the rate and extent of bioavailability of both pentazocine and acetaminophen has not been documented.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10309" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Pentazocine is a mild narcotic antagonist.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M1" type="Trigger" span="31 10" str="antagonist"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="22 8" str="narcotic" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M3" type="SpecificInteraction" span="17 24" str="mild narcotic antagonist" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M1" precipitant="M2" effect="M3" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10310" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Some patients previously given narcotics, including methadone for the daily treatment of narcotic dependence, have experienced withdrawal symptoms after receiving pentazocine.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M8" type="Trigger" span="115 11" str="experienced "/>
<Mention id="M9" type="Trigger" span="138 8" str=" symptoms"/>
<Mention id="M6" type="Precipitant" span="52 9" str="methadone" code="UC6VBE7V1Z"/>
<Mention id="M11" type="SpecificInteraction" span="127 19" str="withdrawal symptoms" code="363101005: Drug withdrawal (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M10" type="Precipitant" span="31 9" str="narcotics" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M8;M9" precipitant="M6" effect="M11" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M8;M9" precipitant="M10" effect="M11" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10311" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In prescribing pentazocine hydrochloride and acetaminophen tablets for chronic use, the physician should take precautions to avoid increases in dose by the patient.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10312" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>As with all drugs, pentazocine hydrochloride and acetaminophen tablets should be used with caution in patients with myocardial infarction who have nausea or vomiting.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10313" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Although respiratory depression has rarely been reported after oral administration of pentazocine, the drug should be administered with caution to patients with respiratory depression from any cause, severely limited respiratory reserve, severe bronchial asthma and other obstructive respiratory conditions, or cyanosis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10314" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Decreased metabolism of the drug by the liver in extensive liver disease may predispose to accentuation of side effects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10315" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Although laboratory tests have not indicated that pentazocine causes or increases renal or hepatic impairment, the drug should be administered with caution to patients with such impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10316" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Since acetaminophen is metabolized by the liver, the question of the safety of its use in the presence of liver disease should be considered.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10317" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Narcotic drug products are generally considered to elevate biliary tract pressure for varying periods following their administration.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10318" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Some evidence suggests that pentazocine may differ from other marketed narcotics in this respect (i.e., it causes little or no elevation in biliary tract pressures).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10319" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The clinical significance of these findings, however, is not yet known.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10320" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Caution should be used when pentazocine hydrochloride and acetaminophen tablets are administered to patients prone to seizures; seizures have occurred in a few such patients in association with the use of pentazocine although no cause and effect relationship has been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10321" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Since sedation, dizziness, and occasional euphoria have been noted, ambulatory patients should be warned not to operate machinery, drive cars, or unnecessarily expose themselves to hazards.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10322" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Pentazocine may cause physical and psychological dependence when taken alone and may have additive CNS depressant properties when taken in combination with alcohol or other CNS depressants.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M15" type="Trigger" span="90 8;114 10" str="additive | properties"/>
<Mention id="M13" type="Precipitant" span="156 7" str="alcohol" code="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M"/>
<Mention id="M17" type="SpecificInteraction" span="90 34" str="additive CNS depressant properties" code="418072004: Central nervous system depression (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M16" type="Precipitant" span="173 15" str="CNS depressants" code="N0000175758"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M15" precipitant="M13" effect="M17" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M15" precipitant="M16" effect="M17" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10323" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Carcinogenesis, mutagenesis, and impairment of fertility studies have not been done with this combination product.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10324" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Pentazocine, when administered orally or parenterally, had no adverse effect on either the reproductive capabilities or the course of pregnancy in rabbits and rats.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10325" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Embryotoxic effects on the fetuses were not shown.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10326" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The daily administration of 4 mg/kg to 20 mg/kg pentazocine subcutaneously to female rats during a 14 day pre-mating period and until the 13th day of pregnancy did not have any adverse effects on the fertility rate.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10327" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>There is no evidence in long-term animal studies to demonstrate that pentazocine is carcinogenic.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10328" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Animal reproduction studies have not been conducted with pentazocine hydrochloride and acetaminophen tablets.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10329" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>It is also not known whether pentazocine hydrochloride and acetaminophen tablets can cause fetal harm when administered to pregnant women or can affect reproduction capacity.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10330" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Pentazocine hydrochloride and acetaminophen tablets should be given to pregnant women only if clearly needed.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10331" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>However, animal reproduction studies with pentazocine have not demonstrated teratogenic or embryotoxic effects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10332" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>There has been no experience in this regard with the combination pentazocine and acetaminophen.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10333" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>However, there have been rare reports of possible abstinence syndromes in newborns after prolonged use of pentazocine during pregnancy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10334" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Patients receiving pentazocine during labor have experienced no adverse effects other than those that occur with commonly used analgesics.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10335" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Pentazocine hydrochloride and acetaminophen tablets should be used with caution in women delivering premature infants.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10336" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>The effect of pentazocine hydrochloride and acetaminophen tablets on the mother and fetus, the duration of labor or delivery, the possibility that forceps delivery or other intervention or resuscitation of the newborn may be necessary, or the effect of pentazocine hydrochloride and acetaminophen tablets on the later growth, development, and functional maturation of the child are unknown at the present time.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10337" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>It is not known whether this drug is excreted in human milk.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10338" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Because many drugs are excreted in human milk, caution should be exercised when pentazocine hydrochloride and acetaminophen tablets are administered to a nursing woman.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10339" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Safety and effectiveness in pediatric patients below the age of 12 have not been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10340" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Clinical studies of pentazocine hydrochloride and acetaminophen tablets did not include sufficient numbers of subjects aged 65 and over to determine whether they respond differently from younger subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10341" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>Other reported clinical experience has not identified differences in responses between the elderly and younger patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10342" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="42232-9">
<SentenceText>In general, dose selection for an elderly patient should be cautious, usually starting at the low end of the dosing range, reflecting the greater frequency of decreased hepatic, renal, or cardiac function, and of concomitant disease or other drug therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10343" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Head Injury and Increased Intracranial Pressure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10344" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>As in the case of other potent analgesics, the potential of pentazocine for elevating cerebrospinal fluid pressure may be attributed to CO2 retention due to the respiratory depressant effects of the drug.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10345" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>These effects may be markedly exaggerated in the presence of head injury, other intracranial lesions, or a pre-existing increase in intracranial pressure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10346" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Furthermore, pentazocine can produce effects which may obscure the clinical course of patients with head injuries.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10347" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>In such patients, pentazocine hydrochloride and acetaminophen tablets must be used with extreme caution and only if its use is deemed essential.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10348" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Patients receiving therapeutic doses of pentazocine have experienced hallucinations (usually visual), disorientation, and confusion which have cleared spontaneously within a period of hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10349" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>The mechanism of this reaction is not known.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10350" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Such patients should be closely observed and vital signs checked.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10351" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>If the drug is reinstituted, it should be done with caution since these acute CNS manifestations may recur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10352" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>There have been instances of psychological and physical dependence on parenteral pentazocine in patients with a history of drug abuse, and rarely, in patients without such a history.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10353" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Due to the potential for increased CNS depressant effects, alcohol should be used with caution in patients who are currently receiving pentazocine.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M18" type="Trigger" span="25 9;50 7" str="increased | effects"/>
<Mention id="M19" type="Precipitant" span="59 7" str="alcohol" code="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M"/>
<Mention id="M20" type="SpecificInteraction" span="25 32" str="increased CNS depressant effects" code="418072004: Central nervous system depression (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M18" precipitant="M19" effect="M20" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10354" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="34071-1">
<SentenceText>Pentazocine may precipitate opioid abstinence symptoms in patients receiving courses of opiates for pain relief.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M21" type="Trigger" span="16 11" str="precipitate "/>
<Mention id="M22" type="Trigger" span="46 8" str=" symptoms"/>
<Mention id="M23" type="Precipitant" span="88 7" str="opiates" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M24" type="SpecificInteraction" span="28 26" str="opioid abstinence symptoms" code="87132004: Opioid withdrawal (disorder)"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M21;M22" precipitant="M23" effect="M24" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10355" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Pentazocine hydrochloride and acetaminophen tablets are an analgesic possessing antipyretic actions.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10356" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Pentazocine is an analgesic with agonist/antagonist action which when administered orally is approximately equivalent on a mg for mg basis in analgesic effect to codeine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10357" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Acetaminophen is an analgesic and antipyretic.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10358" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Onset of significant analgesia with pentazocine usually occurs between 15 and 30 minutes after oral administration, and duration of action is usually three hours or longer.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10359" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Onset and duration of action and the degree of pain relief are related both to dose and the severity of pretreatment pain.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10360" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Pentazocine weakly antagonizes the analgesic effects of morphine, meperidine, and phenazocine; in addition, it produces incomplete reversal of cardiovascular, respiratory, and behavioral depression induced by morphine and meperidine.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M49" type="Trigger" span="19 11;45 7" str="antagonizes | effects"/>
<Mention id="M35" type="Precipitant" span="66 10" str="meperidine" code="9E338QE28F"/>
<Mention id="M51" type="SpecificInteraction" span="19 33" str="antagonizes the analgesic effects" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M46" type="Trigger" span="111 8" str="produces"/>
<Mention id="M42" type="SpecificInteraction" span="120 22;176 21" str="incomplete reversal of | behavioral depression" code="35489007: Depressive disorder (disorder)"/>
<Mention id="M45" type="SpecificInteraction" span="120 22;159 11;187 10" str="incomplete reversal of | respiratory | depression" code="80954004: Decreased respiratory function (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M48" type="SpecificInteraction" span="120 37;187 10" str="incomplete reversal of cardiovascular | depression" code="267037003: Cardiovascular symptoms (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M47" type="Precipitant" span="56 8" str="morphine" code="76I7G6D29C"/>
<Mention id="M50" type="Precipitant" span="82 11" str="phenazocine" code="J0ND6N0AQC"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M49" precipitant="M35" effect="M51" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M46" precipitant="M35" effect="M42" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M46" precipitant="M35" effect="M45" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M46" precipitant="M35" effect="M48" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M49" precipitant="M47" effect="M51" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M46" precipitant="M47" effect="M42" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M46" precipitant="M47" effect="M45" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M46" precipitant="M47" effect="M48" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M49" precipitant="M50" effect="M51" effectCodeMatch="NULL"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10361" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Pentazocine has about 1/50 the antagonistic activity of nalorphine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10362" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Pentazocine is well absorbed from the gastrointestinal tract.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10363" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Plasma levels closely correspond to the onset, duration, and intensity of analgesia.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10364" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The time to mean peak concentration in 24 normal volunteers was 1.7 hours (range 0.5 to 4 hours) after oral administration and the mean plasma elimination half-life was 3.6 hours (range 1.5 to 10 hours).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10365" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The action of pentazocine is terminated for the most part by biotransformation in the liver with some free pentazocine excreted in the urine.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10366" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The products of the oxidation of the terminal methyl groups and glucuronide conjugates are excreted by the kidney.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10367" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Elimination of approximately 60% of the total dose occurs within 24 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10368" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Pentazocine passes the placental barrier.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10369" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Onset of significant analgesic and antipyretic activity of acetaminophen when administered orally occurs within 30 minutes and is maximal at approximately 21/2 hours.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10370" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacological mode of action of acetaminophen is unknown at this time.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10371" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Acetaminophen is rapidly and almost completely absorbed from the gastrointestinal tract.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10372" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In 24 normal volunteers the mean time to peak plasma concentration was 1 hour (range 0.25 to 3 hours) after oral administration and the mean plasma elimination half-life was 2.8 hours (range 2 to 4 hours).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10373" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The effect of pentazocine on acetaminophen plasma protein binding or vice versa has not been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10374" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>For acetaminophen there is little or no plasma protein binding at normal therapeutic doses.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10375" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>When toxic doses of acetaminophen are ingested and drug plasma levels exceed 90 mcg/mL, plasma binding may vary from 8% to 43%.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10376" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Acetaminophen is conjugated in the liver with glucuronic acid and to a lesser extent with sulfuric acid.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10377" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Approximately 80% of acetaminophen is excreted in the urine after conjugation and about 3% is excreted unchanged.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10378" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The drug is also conjugated to a lesser extent with cysteine and additionally metabolized by hydroxylation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10379" LabelDrug="Pentazocine HCl and Acetaminophen" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>If pentazocine hydrochloride and acetaminophen tablets are taken every 4 hours over an extended period of time, accumulation of pentazocine and to a lesser extent, acetaminophen, may occur.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="narcotic" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="methadone" precipitantCode="UC6VBE7V1Z" effect="363101005: Drug withdrawal (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="narcotics" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="363101005: Drug withdrawal (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="alcohol" precipitantCode="N0000007432 | 3K9958V90M" effect="418072004: Central nervous system depression (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="cns depressants" precipitantCode="N0000175758" effect="418072004: Central nervous system depression (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="opiates" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="87132004: Opioid withdrawal (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="meperidine" precipitantCode="9E338QE28F" effect="267037003: Cardiovascular symptoms (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="meperidine" precipitantCode="9E338QE28F" effect="35489007: Depressive disorder (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="meperidine" precipitantCode="9E338QE28F" effect="80954004: Decreased respiratory function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="meperidine" precipitantCode="9E338QE28F" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="morphine" precipitantCode="76I7G6D29C" effect="267037003: Cardiovascular symptoms (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="morphine" precipitantCode="76I7G6D29C" effect="35489007: Depressive disorder (disorder)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="morphine" precipitantCode="76I7G6D29C" effect="80954004: Decreased respiratory function (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="morphine" precipitantCode="76I7G6D29C" effect="NO MAP"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="phenazocine" precipitantCode="J0ND6N0AQC" effect="NO MAP"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>