<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Label drug="MALARONE" setid="fc22e8d8-3bfb-4f70-a599-dd81262a4887">
<Text><Section name="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" id="34070-3">
• Known serious hypersensitivity reactions to atovaquone or proguanil hydrochloride or any component of the formulation. ( 4.1 ) • Prophylaxis of P. falciparum malaria in patients with severe renal impairment (creatinine clearance &amp;lt;30 mL/min). ( 4.2 ) MALARONE is contraindicated in individuals with known hypersensitivity reactions (e.g., anaphylaxis, erythema multiforme or Stevens-Johnson syndrome, angioedema, vasculitis) to atovaquone or proguanil hydrochloride or any component of the formulation. MALARONE is contraindicated for prophylaxis of P. falciparum malaria in patients with severe renal impairment (creatinine clearance &amp;lt;30 mL/min) because of pancytopenia in patients with severe renal impairment treated with proguanil [see Use in Specific Populations (8.6), Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)] .</Section>
<Section name="DOSAGE &amp;amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" id="34068-7">
The daily dose should be taken at the same time each day with food or a milky drink. In the event of vomiting within 1 hour after dosing, a repeat dose should be taken. MALARONE may be crushed and mixed with condensed milk just prior to administration to patients who may have difficulty swallowing tablets. • MALARONE should be taken with food or a milky drink. Prophylaxis ( 2.1 ): • Start prophylaxis 1 or 2 days before entering a malaria‑endemic area and continue daily during the stay and for 7 days after return. • Adults: One adult strength tablet per day. • Pediatric Patients: Dosage based on body weight (see Table 1). Treatment ( 2.2 ): • Adults: Four adult strength tablets as a single daily dose for 3 days. • Pediatric Patients: Dosage based on body weight (see Table 2). Renal Impairment (2.3 ): • Do not use for prophylaxis of malaria in patients with severe renal impairment. • Use with caution for treatment of malaria in patients with severe renal impairment. Start prophylactic treatment with MALARONE 1 or 2 days before entering a malaria‑endemic area and continue daily during the stay and for 7 days after return. Adults One MALARONE Tablet (adult strength = 250 mg atovaquone/100 mg proguanil hydrochloride) per day. Pediatric Patients The dosage for prevention of malaria in pediatric patients is based upon body weight (Table 1). Table 1. Dosage for Prevention of Malaria in Pediatric Patients Weight (kg) Atovaquone/ Proguanil HCl Total Daily Dose Dosage Regimen 11-20 62.5 mg/25 mg 1 MALARONE Pediatric Tablet daily 21-30 125 mg/50 mg 2 MALARONE Pediatric Tablets as a single daily dose 31-40 187.5 mg/75 mg 3 MALARONE Pediatric Tablets as a single daily dose &amp;gt;40 250 mg/100 mg 1 MALARONE Tablet (adult strength) as a single daily dose Adults Four MALARONE Tablets (adult strength; total daily dose 1 g atovaquone/400 mg proguanil hydrochloride) as a single daily dose for 3 consecutive days. Pediatric Patients The dosage for treatment of acute malaria in pediatric patients is based upon body weight (Table 2). Table 2. Dosage for Treatment of Acute Malaria in Pediatric Patients Weight (kg) Atovaquone/ Proguanil HCl Total Daily Dose Dosage Regimen 5-8 125 mg/50 mg 2 MALARONE Pediatric Tablets daily for 3 consecutive days 9-10 187.5 mg/75 mg 3 MALARONE Pediatric Tablets daily for 3 consecutive days 11-20 250 mg/100 mg 1 MALARONE Tablet (adult strength) daily for 3 consecutive days 21-30 500 mg/200 mg 2 MALARONE Tablets (adult strength) as a single daily dose for 3 consecutive days 31-40 750 mg/300 mg 3 MALARONE Tablets (adult strength) as a single daily dose for 3 consecutive days &amp;gt;40 1 g/400 mg 4 MALARONE Tablets (adult strength) as a single daily dose for 3 consecutive days Do not use MALARONE for malaria prophylaxis in patients with severe renal impairment (creatinine clearance &amp;lt;30 mL/min) [see Contraindications (4.2)] . Use with caution for the treatment of malaria in patients with severe renal impairment, only if the benefits of the 3-day treatment regimen outweigh the potential risks associated with increased drug exposure. No dosage adjustments are needed in patients with mild (creatinine clearance 50 to 80 mL/min) or moderate (creatinine clearance 30 to 50 mL/min) renal impairment. [See Clinical Pharmacology (12.3).]</Section>
<Section name="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" id="34073-7">
• Administration with rifampin or rifabutin is known to reduce atovaquone concentrations; concomitant use with MALARONE is not recommended. ( 7.1 ) • Proguanil may potentiate anticoagulant effect of warfarin and other coumarin-based anticoagulants. Caution advised when initiating or withdrawing MALARONE in patients on anticoagulants; coagulation tests should be closely monitored. ( 7.2 ) • Tetracycline may reduce atovaquone concentrations; parasitemia should be closely monitored. ( 7.3 ) Concomitant administration of rifampin or rifabutin is known to reduce atovaquone concentrations [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)] . The concomitant administration of MALARONE and rifampin or rifabutin is not recommended. Proguanil may potentiate the anticoagulant effect of warfarin and other coumarin-based anticoagulants. The mechanism of this potential drug interaction has not been established. Caution is advised when initiating or withdrawing malaria prophylaxis or treatment with MALARONE in patients on continuous treatment with coumarin-based anticoagulants. When these products are administered concomitantly, coagulation tests should be closely monitored. Concomitant treatment with tetracycline has been associated with a reduction in plasma concentrations of atovaquone [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)] . Parasitemia should be closely monitored in patients receiving tetracycline. While antiemetics may be indicated for patients receiving MALARONE, metoclopramide may reduce the bioavailability of atovaquone and should be used only if other antiemetics are not available [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)] . Concomitant administration of atovaquone and indinavir did not result in any change in the steady‑state AUC and C max of indinavir but resulted in a decrease in the C trough of indinavir [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)] . Caution should be exercised when prescribing atovaquone with indinavir due to the decrease in trough concentrations of indinavir.</Section>
<Section name="WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION" id="43685-7">
• Atovaquone absorption may be reduced in patients with diarrhea or vomiting. If used in patients who are vomiting, parasitemia should be closely monitored and the use of an antiemetic considered. In patients with severe or persistent diarrhea or vomiting, alternative antimalarial therapy may be required. ( 5.1 ) • In mixed P. falciparum and Plasmodium vivax infection, P. vivax relapse occurred commonly when patients were treated with MALARONE alone. ( 5.2 ) • In the event of recrudescent P. falciparum infections after treatment or prophylaxis failure, patients should be treated with a different blood schizonticide. ( 5.2 ) • Elevated liver laboratory tests and cases of hepatitis and hepatic failure requiring liver transplantation have been reported with prophylactic use. ( 5.3 ) • MALARONE has not been evaluated for the treatment of cerebral malaria or other severe manifestations of complicated malaria. Patients with severe malaria are not candidates for oral therapy. ( 5.4 ) Absorption of atovaquone may be reduced in patients with diarrhea or vomiting. If MALARONE is used in patients who are vomiting, parasitemia should be closely monitored and the use of an antiemetic considered. [See Dosage and Administration (2).] Vomiting occurred in up to 19% of pediatric patients given treatment doses of MALARONE. In the controlled clinical trials, 15.3% of adults received an antiemetic when they received atovaquone/proguanil and 98.3% of these patients were successfully treated. In patients with severe or persistent diarrhea or vomiting, alternative antimalarial therapy may be required. In mixed P. falciparum and Plasmodium vivax infections, P. vivax parasite relapse occurred commonly when patients were treated with MALARONE alone. In the event of recrudescent P. falciparum infections after treatment with MALARONE or failure of chemoprophylaxis with MALARONE, patients should be treated with a different blood schizonticide. Elevated liver laboratory tests and cases of hepatitis and hepatic failure requiring liver transplantation have been reported with prophylactic use of MALARONE. MALARONE has not been evaluated for the treatment of cerebral malaria or other severe manifestations of complicated malaria, including hyperparasitemia, pulmonary edema, or renal failure. Patients with severe malaria are not candidates for oral therapy.</Section>
<Section name="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" id="34090-1">
The constituents of MALARONE, atovaquone and proguanil hydrochloride, interfere with 2 different pathways involved in the biosynthesis of pyrimidines required for nucleic acid replication. Atovaquone is a selective inhibitor of parasite mitochondrial electron transport. Proguanil hydrochloride primarily exerts its effect by means of the metabolite cycloguanil, a dihydrofolate reductase inhibitor. Inhibition of dihydrofolate reductase in the malaria parasite disrupts deoxythymidylate synthesis. No trials of the pharmacodynamics of MALARONE have been conducted. Absorption Atovaquone is a highly lipophilic compound with low aqueous solubility. The bioavailability of atovaquone shows considerable inter‑individual variability. Dietary fat taken with atovaquone increases the rate and extent of absorption, increasing AUC 2 to 3 times and C max 5 times over fasting. The absolute bioavailability of the tablet formulation of atovaquone when taken with food is 23%. MALARONE should be taken with food or a milky drink. Distribution Atovaquone is highly protein bound (&amp;gt;99%) over the concentration range of 1 to 90 mcg/mL. A population pharmacokinetic analysis demonstrated that the apparent volume of distribution of atovaquone (V/F) in adult and pediatric patients after oral administration is approximately 8.8 L/kg. Proguanil is 75% protein bound. A population pharmacokinetic analysis demonstrated that the apparent V/F of proguanil in adult and pediatric patients older than 15 years with body weights from 31 to 110 kg ranged from 1,617 to 2,502 L. In pediatric patients 15 years and younger with body weights from 11 to 56 kg, the V/F of proguanil ranged from 462 to 966 L. In human plasma, the binding of atovaquone and proguanil was unaffected by the presence of the other. Metabolism In a study where 14 C‑labeled atovaquone was administered to healthy volunteers, greater than 94% of the dose was recovered as unchanged atovaquone in the feces over 21 days. There was little or no excretion of atovaquone in the urine (less than 0.6%). There is indirect evidence that atovaquone may undergo limited metabolism; however, a specific metabolite has not been identified. Between 40% to 60% of proguanil is excreted by the kidneys. Proguanil is metabolized to cycloguanil (primarily via CYP2C19) and 4-chlorophenylbiguanide. The main routes of elimination are hepatic biotransformation and renal excretion. Elimination The elimination half‑life of atovaquone is about 2 to 3 days in adult patients. The elimination half‑life of proguanil is 12 to 21 hours in both adult patients and pediatric patients, but may be longer in individuals who are slow metabolizers. A population pharmacokinetic analysis in adult and pediatric patients showed that the apparent clearance (CL/F) of both atovaquone and proguanil is related to the body weight. The values CL/F for both atovaquone and proguanil in subjects with body weight ≥11 kg are shown in Table 4. Table 4. Apparent Clearance for Atovaquone and Proguanil in Patients as a Function of Body Weight Body Weight Atovaquone Proguanil n CL/F (L/hr) Mean ± SD a (range) n CL/F (L/hr) Mean ± SD a (range) 11-20 kg 159 1.34 ± 0.63 (0.52-4.26) 146 29.5 ± 6.5 (10.3-48.3) 21-30 kg 117 1.87 ± 0.81 (0.52-5.38) 113 40.0 ± 7.5 (15.9-62.7) 31-40 kg 95 2.76 ± 2.07 (0.97-12.5) 91 49.5 ± 8.30 (25.8-71.5) &amp;gt;40 kg 368 6.61 ± 3.92 (1.32-20.3) 282 67.9 ± 19.9 (14.0-145) a SD = Standard deviation. The pharmacokinetics of atovaquone and proguanil in patients with body weight less than 11 kg have not been adequately characterized. Pediatrics The pharmacokinetics of proguanil and cycloguanil are similar in adult patients and pediatric patients. However, the elimination half‑life of atovaquone is shorter in pediatric patients (1 to 2 days) than in adult patients (2 to 3 days). In clinical trials, plasma trough concentrations of atovaquone and proguanil in pediatric patients weighing 5 to 40 kg were within the range observed in adults after dosing by body weight. Geriatrics In a single‑dose study, the pharmacokinetics of atovaquone, proguanil, and cycloguanil were compared in 13 elderly subjects (aged 65 to 79 years) with those of 13 younger subjects (aged 30 to 45 years). In the elderly subjects, the extent of systemic exposure (AUC) of cycloguanil was increased (point estimate = 2.36, 90% CI = 1.70, 3.28). T max was longer in elderly subjects (median: 8 hours) compared with younger subjects (median 4 hours) and average elimination half‑life was longer in elderly subjects (mean: 14.9 hours) compared with younger subjects (mean 8.3 hours). Renal Impairment In patients with mild renal impairment (creatinine clearance 50 to 80 mL/min), oral clearance and/or AUC data for atovaquone, proguanil, and cycloguanil are within the range of values observed in patients with normal renal function (creatinine clearance &amp;gt;80 mL/min). In patients with moderate renal impairment (creatinine clearance 30 to 50 mL/min), mean oral clearance for proguanil was reduced by approximately 35% compared with patients with normal renal function (creatinine clearance &amp;gt;80 mL/min) and the oral clearance of atovaquone was comparable between patients with normal renal function and mild renal impairment. No data exist on the use of MALARONE for long-term prophylaxis (over 2 months) in individuals with moderate renal failure. In patients with severe renal impairment (creatinine clearance &amp;lt;30 mL/min), atovaquone C max and AUC are reduced but the elimination half‑lives for proguanil and cycloguanil are prolonged, with corresponding increases in AUC, resulting in the potential of drug accumulation and toxicity with repeated dosing [see Contraindications (4.2)] . Hepatic Impairment In a single‑dose study, the pharmacokinetics of atovaquone, proguanil, and cycloguanil were compared in 13 subjects with hepatic impairment (9 mild, 4 moderate, as indicated by the Child‑Pugh method) with those of 13 subjects with normal hepatic function. In subjects with mild or moderate hepatic impairment as compared with healthy subjects, there were no marked differences (&amp;lt;50%) in the rate or extent of systemic exposure of atovaquone. However, in subjects with moderate hepatic impairment, the elimination half‑life of atovaquone was increased (point estimate = 1.28, 90% CI = 1.00 to 1.63). Proguanil AUC, C max , and its elimination half-life increased in subjects with mild hepatic impairment when compared with healthy subjects (Table 5). Also, the proguanil AUC and its elimination half-life increased in subjects with moderate hepatic impairment when compared with healthy subjects. Consistent with the increase in proguanil AUC, there were marked decreases in the systemic exposure of cycloguanil (C max and AUC) and an increase in its elimination half‑life in subjects with mild hepatic impairment when compared with healthy volunteers (Table 5). There were few measurable cycloguanil concentrations in subjects with moderate hepatic impairment. The pharmacokinetics of atovaquone, proguanil, and cycloguanil after administration of MALARONE have not been studied in patients with severe hepatic impairment. Table 5. Point Estimates (90% CI) for Proguanil and Cycloguanil Parameters in Subjects with Mild and Moderate Hepatic Impairment Compared with Healthy Volunteers Parameter Comparison Proguanil Cycloguanil AUC (0-inf) a mild:healthy 1.96 (1.51, 2.54) 0.32 (0.22, 0.45) C max a mild:healthy 1.41 (1.16, 1.71) 0.35 (0.24, 0.50) t 1/2 b mild:healthy 1.21 (0.92, 1.60) 0.86 (0.49, 1.48) AUC (0-inf) a moderate:healthy 1.64 (1.14, 2.34) ND C max a moderate:healthy 0.97 (0.69, 1.36) ND t 1/2 b moderate:healthy 1.46 (1.05, 2.05) ND ND = Not determined due to lack of quantifiable data. a Ratio of geometric means. b Mean difference. Drug Interactions There are no pharmacokinetic interactions between atovaquone and proguanil at the recommended dose. Atovaquone is highly protein bound (&amp;gt;99%) but does not displace other highly protein‑bound drugs in vitro. Proguanil is metabolized primarily by CYP2C19. Potential pharmacokinetic interactions between proguanil or cycloguanil and other drugs that are CYP2C19 substrates or inhibitors are unknown. Rifampin/Rifabutin: Concomitant administration of rifampin or rifabutin is known to reduce atovaquone concentrations by approximately 50% and 34%, respectively. The mechanisms of these interactions are unknown. Tetracycline: Concomitant treatment with tetracycline has been associated with approximately a 40% reduction in plasma concentrations of atovaquone. Metoclopramide: Concomitant treatment with metoclopramide has been associated with decreased bioavailability of atovaquone. Indinavir: Concomitant administration of atovaquone (750 mg twice daily with food for 14 days) and indinavir (800 mg three times daily without food for 14 days) did not result in any change in the steady‑state AUC and C max of indinavir but resulted in a decrease in the C trough of indinavir (23% decrease [90% CI = 8%, 35%]). Activity In Vitro and In Vivo Atovaquone and cycloguanil (an active metabolite of proguanil) are active against the erythrocytic and exoerythrocytic stages of Plasmodium spp. Enhanced efficacy of the combination compared with either atovaquone or proguanil hydrochloride alone was demonstrated in clinical trials in both immune and non-immune patients [see Clinical Studies (14.1, 14.2)] . Drug Resistance Strains of P. falciparum with decreased susceptibility to atovaquone or proguanil/cycloguanil alone can be selected in vitro or in vivo. The combination of atovaquone and proguanil hydrochloride may not be effective for treatment of recrudescent malaria that develops after prior therapy with the combination.</Section>
</Text><Sentences>
<Sentence id="9938" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Known serious hypersensitivity reactions to atovaquone or proguanil hydrochloride or any component of the formulation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9939" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>Prophylaxis of P. falciparum malaria in patients with severe renal impairment (creatinine clearance &lt;30 mL/min).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9940" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>MALARONE is contraindicated in individuals with known hypersensitivity reactions (e.g., anaphylaxis, erythema multiforme or Stevens-Johnson syndrome, angioedema, vasculitis) to atovaquone or proguanil hydrochloride or any component of the formulation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9941" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34070-3">
<SentenceText>MALARONE is contraindicated for prophylaxis of P. falciparum malaria in patients with severe renal impairment (creatinine clearance &lt;30 mL/min) because of pancytopenia in patients with severe renal impairment treated with proguanil.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9942" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>The daily dose should be taken at the same time each day with food or a milky drink.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9943" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>In the event of vomiting within 1 hour after dosing, a repeat dose should be taken.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9944" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>MALARONE may be crushed and mixed with condensed milk just prior to administration to patients who may have difficulty swallowing tablets.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9945" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>MALARONE should be taken with food or a milky drink.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9946" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Prophylaxis (2.1): Start prophylaxis 1 or 2 days before entering a malaria‑endemic area and continue daily during the stay and for 7 days after return.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9947" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Adults: One adult strength tablet per day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9948" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Pediatric Patients: Dosage based on body weight.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9949" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Treatment (2.2): Adults: Four adult strength tablets as a single daily dose for 3 days.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9950" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Renal Impairment (2.3): Do not use for prophylaxis of malaria in patients with severe renal impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9951" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Use with caution for treatment of malaria in patients with severe renal impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9952" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Start prophylactic treatment with MALARONE 1 or 2 days before entering a malaria‑endemic area and continue daily during the stay and for 7 days after return.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9953" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Adults One MALARONE Tablet (adult strength = 250 mg atovaquone/100 mg proguanil hydrochloride) per day.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9954" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Pediatric Patients The dosage for prevention of malaria in pediatric patients is based upon body weight (Table 1).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9955" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dosage for Prevention of Malaria in Pediatric Patients Weight (kg) Atovaquone/ Proguanil HCl Total Daily Dose Dosage Regimen 11-20 62.5 mg/25 mg 1 MALARONE Pediatric Tablet daily 21-30 125 mg/50 mg 2 MALARONE Pediatric Tablets as a single daily dose 31-40 187.5 mg/75 mg 3 MALARONE Pediatric Tablets as a single daily dose &gt;40 250 mg/100 mg 1 MALARONE Tablet (adult strength) as a single daily dose Adults Four MALARONE Tablets (adult strength; total daily dose 1 g atovaquone/400 mg proguanil hydrochloride) as a single daily dose for 3 consecutive days.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9956" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Pediatric Patients The dosage for treatment of acute malaria in pediatric patients is based upon body weight (Table 2).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9957" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Dosage for Treatment of Acute Malaria in Pediatric Patients Weight (kg) Atovaquone/ Proguanil HCl Total Daily Dose Dosage Regimen 5-8 125 mg/50 mg 2 MALARONE Pediatric Tablets daily for 3 consecutive days 9-10 187.5 mg/75 mg 3 MALARONE Pediatric Tablets daily for 3 consecutive days 11-20 250 mg/100 mg 1 MALARONE Tablet (adult strength) daily for 3 consecutive days 21-30 500 mg/200 mg 2 MALARONE Tablets (adult strength) as a single daily dose for 3 consecutive days 31-40 750 mg/300 mg 3 MALARONE Tablets (adult strength) as a single daily dose for 3 consecutive days &gt;40 1 g/400 mg 4 MALARONE Tablets (adult strength) as a single daily dose for 3 consecutive days Do not use MALARONE for malaria prophylaxis in patients with severe renal impairment (creatinine clearance &lt;30 mL/min).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9958" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>Use with caution for the treatment of malaria in patients with severe renal impairment, only if the benefits of the 3-day treatment regimen outweigh the potential risks associated with increased drug exposure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9959" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34068-7">
<SentenceText>No dosage adjustments are needed in patients with mild (creatinine clearance 50 to 80 mL/min) or moderate (creatinine clearance 30 to 50 mL/min) renal impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9960" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Administration with rifampin or rifabutin is known to reduce atovaquone concentrations; concomitant use with MALARONE is not recommended.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M3" type="Trigger" span="54 6;72 14" str="reduce | concentrations"/>
<Mention id="M2" type="Precipitant" span="32 9" str="rifabutin" code="1W306TDA6S | N0000007464"/>
<Mention id="M4" type="Precipitant" span="20 8" str="rifampin" code="VJT6J7R4TR | N0000006026"/>
<Interaction id="I1" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M3" precipitant="M2" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I2" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M3" precipitant="M4" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9961" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Proguanil may potentiate anticoagulant effect of warfarin and other coumarin-based anticoagulants.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M11" type="Trigger" span="14 10" str="potentiate"/>
<Mention id="M6" type="Precipitant" span="68 8" str="coumarin" code="A4VZ22K1WT"/>
<Mention id="M13" type="SpecificInteraction" span="14 31" str="potentiate anticoagulant effect" code="10191004: Anticoagulant effect (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M9" type="Precipitant" span="68 29" str="coumarin-based anticoagulants" code="A4VZ22K1WT"/>
<Mention id="M12" type="Precipitant" span="49 8" str="warfarin" code="5Q7ZVV76EI | N0000006403"/>
<Interaction id="I3" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M11" precipitant="M6" effect="M13" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I4" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M11" precipitant="M9" effect="M13" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I5" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M11" precipitant="M12" effect="M13" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9962" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Caution advised when initiating or withdrawing MALARONE in patients on anticoagulants; coagulation tests should be closely monitored.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M14" type="Trigger" span="0 7" str="Caution"/>
<Mention id="M15" type="Precipitant" span="71 14" str="anticoagulants" code="N0000029110 | N0000175980"/>
<Interaction id="I6" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M14" precipitant="M15"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9963" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Tetracycline may reduce atovaquone concentrations; parasitemia should be closely monitored.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M16" type="Trigger" span="81 9" str="monitored"/>
<Mention id="M20" type="Precipitant" span="0 12" str="Tetracycline" code="F8VB5M810T"/>
<Mention id="M18" type="SpecificInteraction" span="51 11" str="parasitemia" code="168253005: Animal inoculation: parasite (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M19" type="Trigger" span="17 6;35 14" str="reduce | concentrations"/>
<Interaction id="I7" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M16" precipitant="M20" effect="M18" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I8" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M19" precipitant="M20" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9964" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant administration of rifampin or rifabutin is known to reduce atovaquone concentrations.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M23" type="Trigger" span="64 6;82 14" str="reduce | concentrations"/>
<Mention id="M22" type="Precipitant" span="42 9" str="rifabutin" code="1W306TDA6S | N0000007464"/>
<Mention id="M24" type="Precipitant" span="30 8" str="rifampin" code="VJT6J7R4TR | N0000006026"/>
<Interaction id="I9" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M23" precipitant="M22" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I10" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M23" precipitant="M24" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9965" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The concomitant administration of MALARONE and rifampin or rifabutin is not recommended.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M27" type="Trigger" span="72 15" str="not recommended"/>
<Mention id="M26" type="Precipitant" span="59 9" str="rifabutin" code="1W306TDA6S | N0000007464"/>
<Mention id="M28" type="Precipitant" span="47 8" str="rifampin" code="VJT6J7R4TR | N0000006026"/>
<Interaction id="I11" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M27" precipitant="M26"/>
<Interaction id="I12" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M27" precipitant="M28"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9966" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Proguanil may potentiate the anticoagulant effect of warfarin and other coumarin-based anticoagulants.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M35" type="Trigger" span="14 10" str="potentiate"/>
<Mention id="M30" type="Precipitant" span="72 8" str="coumarin" code="A4VZ22K1WT"/>
<Mention id="M37" type="SpecificInteraction" span="14 35" str="potentiate the anticoagulant effect" code="10191004: Anticoagulant effect (finding)"/>
<Mention id="M33" type="Precipitant" span="72 29" str="coumarin-based anticoagulants" code="A4VZ22K1WT"/>
<Mention id="M36" type="Precipitant" span="53 8" str="warfarin" code="5Q7ZVV76EI | N0000006403"/>
<Interaction id="I13" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M30" effect="M37" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I14" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M33" effect="M37" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
<Interaction id="I15" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M35" precipitant="M36" effect="M37" effectCodeMatch="Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9967" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>The mechanism of this potential drug interaction has not been established.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9968" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Caution is advised when initiating or withdrawing malaria prophylaxis or treatment with MALARONE in patients on continuous treatment with coumarin-based anticoagulants.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M40" type="Trigger" span="0 7" str="Caution"/>
<Mention id="M39" type="Precipitant" span="138 8" str="coumarin" code="A4VZ22K1WT"/>
<Mention id="M41" type="Precipitant" span="138 29" str="coumarin-based anticoagulants" code="A4VZ22K1WT"/>
<Interaction id="I16" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M40" precipitant="M39"/>
<Interaction id="I17" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M40" precipitant="M41"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9969" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>When these products are administered concomitantly, coagulation tests should be closely monitored.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9970" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant treatment with tetracycline has been associated with a reduction in plasma concentrations of atovaquone.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M42" type="Trigger" span="67 34" str="reduction in plasma concentrations"/>
<Mention id="M43" type="Precipitant" span="27 12" str="tetracycline" code="F8VB5M810T"/>
<Interaction id="I18" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M42" precipitant="M43" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9971" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Parasitemia should be closely monitored in patients receiving tetracycline.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M44" type="Trigger" span="30 9" str="monitored"/>
<Mention id="M45" type="Precipitant" span="62 12" str="tetracycline" code="F8VB5M810T"/>
<Mention id="M46" type="SpecificInteraction" span="0 11" str="parasitemia" code="168253005: Animal inoculation: parasite (finding)"/>
<Interaction id="I19" type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" trigger="M44" precipitant="M45" effect="M46" effectCodeMatch="Close to Exact Match"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9972" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>While antiemetics may be indicated for patients receiving MALARONE, metoclopramide may reduce the bioavailability of atovaquone and should be used only if other antiemetics are not available.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M47" type="Trigger" span="87 26" str="reduce the bioavailability"/>
<Mention id="M48" type="Precipitant" span="68 14" str="metoclopramide" code="L4YEB44I46"/>
<Interaction id="I20" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M47" precipitant="M48" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9973" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Concomitant administration of atovaquone and indinavir did not result in any change in the steady‑state AUC and Cmax of indinavir but resulted in a decrease in the Ctrough of indinavir.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M49" type="Trigger" span="148 23" str="decrease in the Ctrough"/>
<Mention id="M50" type="Precipitant" span="45 9" str="indinavir" code="N0000005722 | 5W6YA9PKKH"/>
<Interaction id="I21" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M49" precipitant="M50" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9974" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34073-7">
<SentenceText>Caution should be exercised when prescribing atovaquone with indinavir due to the decrease in trough concentrations of indinavir.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M51" type="Trigger" span="82 33" str="decrease in trough concentrations"/>
<Mention id="M52" type="Precipitant" span="61 9" str="indinavir" code="N0000005722 | 5W6YA9PKKH"/>
<Interaction id="I22" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M51" precipitant="M52" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9975" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Atovaquone absorption may be reduced in patients with diarrhea or vomiting.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9976" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If used in patients who are vomiting, parasitemia should be closely monitored and the use of an antiemetic considered.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9977" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In patients with severe or persistent diarrhea or vomiting, alternative antimalarial therapy may be required.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9978" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In mixed P. falciparum and Plasmodium vivax infection, P. vivax relapse occurred commonly when patients were treated with MALARONE alone.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9979" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In the event of recrudescent P. falciparum infections after treatment or prophylaxis failure, patients should be treated with a different blood schizonticide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9980" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Elevated liver laboratory tests and cases of hepatitis and hepatic failure requiring liver transplantation have been reported with prophylactic use.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9981" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>MALARONE has not been evaluated for the treatment of cerebral malaria or other severe manifestations of complicated malaria.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9982" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Patients with severe malaria are not candidates for oral therapy.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9983" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Absorption of atovaquone may be reduced in patients with diarrhea or vomiting.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9984" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>If MALARONE is used in patients who are vomiting, parasitemia should be closely monitored and the use of an antiemetic considered.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9985" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Vomiting occurred in up to 19% of pediatric patients given treatment doses of MALARONE.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9986" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In the controlled clinical trials, 15.3% of adults received an antiemetic when they received atovaquone/proguanil and 98.3% of these patients were successfully treated.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9987" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In mixed P. falciparum and Plasmodium vivax infections, P. vivax parasite relapse occurred commonly when patients were treated with MALARONE alone.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9988" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>In the event of recrudescent P. falciparum infections after treatment with MALARONE or failure of chemoprophylaxis with MALARONE, patients should be treated with a different blood schizonticide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9989" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>Elevated liver laboratory tests and cases of hepatitis and hepatic failure requiring liver transplantation have been reported with prophylactic use of MALARONE.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9990" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="43685-7">
<SentenceText>MALARONE has not been evaluated for the treatment of cerebral malaria or other severe manifestations of complicated malaria, including hyperparasitemia, pulmonary edema, or renal failure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9991" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The constituents of MALARONE, atovaquone and proguanil hydrochloride, interfere with 2 different pathways involved in the biosynthesis of pyrimidines required for nucleic acid replication.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9992" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Atovaquone is a selective inhibitor of parasite mitochondrial electron transport.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9993" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Proguanil hydrochloride primarily exerts its effect by means of the metabolite cycloguanil, a dihydrofolate reductase inhibitor.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9994" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Inhibition of dihydrofolate reductase in the malaria parasite disrupts deoxythymidylate synthesis.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9995" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No trials of the pharmacodynamics of MALARONE have been conducted.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9996" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Absorption Atovaquone is a highly lipophilic compound with low aqueous solubility.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9997" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The bioavailability of atovaquone shows considerable inter‑individual variability.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9998" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Dietary fat taken with atovaquone increases the rate and extent of absorption, increasing AUC 2 to 3 times and Cmax 5 times over fasting.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M53" type="Trigger" span="34 9;67 10" str="increases | absorption"/>
<Mention id="M58" type="Precipitant" span="0 11" str="Dietary fat" code="NO MAP"/>
<Mention id="M55" type="Trigger" span="79 10;111 4" str="increasing | Cmax"/>
<Mention id="M57" type="Trigger" span="79 14" str="increasing AUC"/>
<Interaction id="I23" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M53" precipitant="M58" effect="C54355"/>
<Interaction id="I24" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M55" precipitant="M58" effect="C54602"/>
<Interaction id="I25" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M57" precipitant="M58" effect="C54605"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="9999" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The absolute bioavailability of the tablet formulation of atovaquone when taken with food is 23%.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10000" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Distribution Atovaquone is highly protein bound (&gt;99%) over the concentration range of 1 to 90 mcg/mL.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10001" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A population pharmacokinetic analysis demonstrated that the apparent volume of distribution of atovaquone (V/F) in adult and pediatric patients after oral administration is approximately 8.8 L/kg.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10002" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A population pharmacokinetic analysis demonstrated that the apparent V/F of proguanil in adult and pediatric patients older than 15 years with body weights from 31 to 110 kg ranged from 1,617 to 2,502 L. In pediatric patients 15 years and younger with body weights from 11 to 56 kg, the V/F of proguanil ranged from 462 to 966 L. In human plasma, the binding of atovaquone and proguanil was unaffected by the presence of the other.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10003" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Metabolism In a study where 14C‑labeled atovaquone was administered to healthy volunteers, greater than 94% of the dose was recovered as unchanged atovaquone in the feces over 21 days.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10004" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There was little or no excretion of atovaquone in the urine (less than 0.6%).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10005" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There is indirect evidence that atovaquone may undergo limited metabolism; however, a specific metabolite has not been identified.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10006" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Between 40% to 60% of proguanil is excreted by the kidneys.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10007" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Proguanil is metabolized to cycloguanil (primarily via CYP2C19) and 4-chlorophenylbiguanide.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10008" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The main routes of elimination are hepatic biotransformation and renal excretion.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10009" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Elimination The elimination half‑life of atovaquone is about 2 to 3 days in adult patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10010" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The elimination half‑life of proguanil is 12 to 21 hours in both adult patients and pediatric patients, but may be longer in individuals who are slow metabolizers.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10011" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>A population pharmacokinetic analysis in adult and pediatric patients showed that the apparent clearance (CL/F) of both atovaquone and proguanil is related to the body weight.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10012" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The values CL/F for both atovaquone and proguanil in subjects with body weight ≥11 kg are shown in Table 4.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10013" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Apparent Clearance for Atovaquone and Proguanil in Patients as a Function of Body Weight Body Weight Atovaquone Proguanil n CL/F (L/hr) Mean ± SDa (range) n CL/F (L/hr) Mean ± SDa (range) 11-20 kg 159 1.34 ± 0.63 (0.52-4.26) 146 29.5 ± 6.5 (10.3-48.3) 21-30 kg 117 1.87 ± 0.81 (0.52-5.38) 113 40.0 ± 7.5 (15.9-62.7) 31-40 kg 95 2.76 ± 2.07 (0.97-12.5) 91 49.5 ± 8.30 (25.8-71.5) &gt;40 kg 368 6.61 ± 3.92 (1.32-20.3) 282 67.9 ± 19.9 (14.0-145) a SD = Standard deviation.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10014" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacokinetics of atovaquone and proguanil in patients with body weight less than 11 kg have not been adequately characterized.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10015" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Pediatrics The pharmacokinetics of proguanil and cycloguanil are similar in adult patients and pediatric patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10016" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>However, the elimination half‑life of atovaquone is shorter in pediatric patients (1 to 2 days) than in adult patients (2 to 3 days).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10017" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In clinical trials, plasma trough concentrations of atovaquone and proguanil in pediatric patients weighing 5 to 40 kg were within the range observed in adults after dosing by body weight.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10018" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Geriatrics In a single‑dose study, the pharmacokinetics of atovaquone, proguanil, and cycloguanil were compared in 13 elderly subjects (aged 65 to 79 years) with those of 13 younger subjects (aged 30 to 45 years).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10019" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In the elderly subjects, the extent of systemic exposure (AUC) of cycloguanil was increased (point estimate = 2.36, 90% CI = 1.70, 3.28).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10020" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Tmax was longer in elderly subjects (median: 8 hours) compared with younger subjects (median 4 hours) and average elimination half‑life was longer in elderly subjects (mean: 14.9 hours) compared with younger subjects (mean 8.3 hours).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10021" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Renal Impairment In patients with mild renal impairment (creatinine clearance 50 to 80 mL/min), oral clearance and/or AUC data for atovaquone, proguanil, and cycloguanil are within the range of values observed in patients with normal renal function (creatinine clearance &gt;80 mL/min).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10022" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In patients with moderate renal impairment (creatinine clearance 30 to 50 mL/min), mean oral clearance for proguanil was reduced by approximately 35% compared with patients with normal renal function (creatinine clearance &gt;80 mL/min) and the oral clearance of atovaquone was comparable between patients with normal renal function and mild renal impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10023" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>No data exist on the use of MALARONE for long-term prophylaxis (over 2 months) in individuals with moderate renal failure.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10024" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In patients with severe renal impairment (creatinine clearance &lt;30 mL/min), atovaquone Cmax and AUC are reduced but the elimination half‑lives for proguanil and cycloguanil are prolonged, with corresponding increases in AUC, resulting in the potential of drug accumulation and toxicity with repeated dosing.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10025" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Hepatic Impairment In a single‑dose study, the pharmacokinetics of atovaquone, proguanil, and cycloguanil were compared in 13 subjects with hepatic impairment (9 mild, 4 moderate, as indicated by the Child‑Pugh method) with those of 13 subjects with normal hepatic function.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10026" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>In subjects with mild or moderate hepatic impairment as compared with healthy subjects, there were no marked differences (&lt;50%) in the rate or extent of systemic exposure of atovaquone.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10027" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>However, in subjects with moderate hepatic impairment, the elimination half‑life of atovaquone was increased (point estimate = 1.28, 90% CI = 1.00 to 1.63).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10028" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Proguanil AUC, Cmax, and its elimination half-life increased in subjects with mild hepatic impairment when compared with healthy subjects (Table 5).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10029" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Also, the proguanil AUC and its elimination half-life increased in subjects with moderate hepatic impairment when compared with healthy subjects.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10030" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Consistent with the increase in proguanil AUC, there were marked decreases in the systemic exposure of cycloguanil (Cmax and AUC) and an increase in its elimination half‑life in subjects with mild hepatic impairment when compared with healthy volunteers (Table 5).</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10031" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>There were few measurable cycloguanil concentrations in subjects with moderate hepatic impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10032" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The pharmacokinetics of atovaquone, proguanil, and cycloguanil after administration of MALARONE have not been studied in patients with severe hepatic impairment.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10033" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Point Estimates (90% CI) for Proguanil and Cycloguanil Parameters in Subjects with Mild and Moderate Hepatic Impairment Compared with Healthy Volunteers Parameter Comparison Proguanil Cycloguanil AUC(0-inf) a mild:healthy 1.96 (1.51, 2.54) 0.32 (0.22, 0.45) Cmax a mild:healthy 1.41 (1.16, 1.71) 0.35 (0.24, 0.50) t1/2 b mild:healthy 1.21 (0.92, 1.60) 0.86 (0.49, 1.48) AUC(0-inf) a moderate:healthy 1.64 (1.14, 2.34) ND Cmax a moderate:healthy 0.97 (0.69, 1.36) ND t1/2 b moderate:healthy 1.46 (1.05, 2.05) ND ND = Not determined due to lack of quantifiable data. a Ratio of geometric means. b Mean difference.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10034" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Drug Interactions There are no pharmacokinetic interactions between atovaquone and proguanil at the recommended dose.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10035" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Atovaquone is highly protein bound (&gt;99%) but does not displace other highly protein‑bound drugs in vitro.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10036" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Proguanil is metabolized primarily by CYP2C19.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10037" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Potential pharmacokinetic interactions between proguanil or cycloguanil and other drugs that are CYP2C19 substrates or inhibitors are unknown.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M61" type="Trigger" span="10 28" str="pharmacokinetic interactions"/>
<Mention id="M60" type="Precipitant" span="97 7;119 10" str="CYP2C19 | inhibitors" code="N0000182140"/>
<Mention id="M62" type="Precipitant" span="97 18" str="CYP2C19 substrates" code="NO MAP"/>
<Interaction id="I26" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M61" precipitant="M60"/>
<Interaction id="I27" type="Unspecified interaction" trigger="M61" precipitant="M62"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10038" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Rifampin/Rifabutin: Concomitant administration of rifampin or rifabutin is known to reduce atovaquone concentrations by approximately 50% and 34%, respectively.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M65" type="Trigger" span="84 6;102 14" str="reduce | concentrations"/>
<Mention id="M64" type="Precipitant" span="9 9" str="rifabutin" code="1W306TDA6S | N0000007464"/>
<Mention id="M66" type="Precipitant" span="0 8" str="rifampin" code="VJT6J7R4TR | N0000006026"/>
<Interaction id="I28" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M65" precipitant="M64" effect="C54356"/>
<Interaction id="I29" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M65" precipitant="M66" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10039" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The mechanisms of these interactions are unknown.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10040" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Tetracycline: Concomitant treatment with tetracycline has been associated with approximately a 40% reduction in plasma concentrations of atovaquone.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M67" type="Trigger" span="99 34" str="reduction in plasma concentrations"/>
<Mention id="M68" type="Precipitant" span="0 12" str="tetracycline" code="F8VB5M810T"/>
<Interaction id="I30" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M67" precipitant="M68" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10041" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Metoclopramide: Concomitant treatment with metoclopramide has been associated with decreased bioavailability of atovaquone.</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M69" type="Trigger" span="83 25" str="decreased bioavailability"/>
<Mention id="M70" type="Precipitant" span="0 14" str="metoclopramide" code="L4YEB44I46"/>
<Interaction id="I31" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M69" precipitant="M70" effect="C54356"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10042" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Indinavir: Concomitant administration of atovaquone (750 mg twice daily with food for 14 days) and indinavir (800 mg three times daily without food for 14 days) did not result in any change in the steady‑state AUC and Cmax of indinavir but resulted in a decrease in the Ctrough of indinavir (23% decrease [90% CI = 8%, 35%]).</SentenceText>
<Mention id="M71" type="Trigger" span="254 23" str="decrease in the Ctrough"/>
<Mention id="M72" type="Precipitant" span="0 9" str="indinavir" code="N0000005722 | 5W6YA9PKKH"/>
<Interaction id="I32" type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" trigger="M71" precipitant="M72" effect="C54358"/>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10043" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Activity In Vitro and In Vivo Atovaquone and cycloguanil (an active metabolite of proguanil) are active against the erythrocytic and exoerythrocytic stages of Plasmodium spp.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10044" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Enhanced efficacy of the combination compared with either atovaquone or proguanil hydrochloride alone was demonstrated in clinical trials in both immune and non-immune patients.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10045" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>Drug Resistance Strains of P. falciparum with decreased susceptibility to atovaquone or proguanil/cycloguanil alone can be selected in vitro or in vivo.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
<Sentence id="10046" LabelDrug="MALARONE" section="34090-1">
<SentenceText>The combination of atovaquone and proguanil hydrochloride may not be effective for treatment of recrudescent malaria that develops after prior therapy with the combination.</SentenceText>
</Sentence>
</Sentences>
<LabelInteractions><LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="rifabutin" precipitantCode="1W306TDA6S | N0000007464" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="rifabutin" precipitantCode="1W306TDA6S | N0000007464"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="rifampin" precipitantCode="VJT6J7R4TR | N0000006026" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="rifampin" precipitantCode="VJT6J7R4TR | N0000006026"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="coumarin" precipitantCode="A4VZ22K1WT" effect="10191004: Anticoagulant effect (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="coumarin" precipitantCode="A4VZ22K1WT"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="coumarin-based anticoagulants" precipitantCode="A4VZ22K1WT" effect="10191004: Anticoagulant effect (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="coumarin-based anticoagulants" precipitantCode="A4VZ22K1WT"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="warfarin" precipitantCode="5Q7ZVV76EI | N0000006403" effect="10191004: Anticoagulant effect (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="anticoagulants" precipitantCode="N0000029110 | N0000175980"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacodynamic interaction" precipitant="tetracycline" precipitantCode="F8VB5M810T" effect="168253005: Animal inoculation: parasite (finding)"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="tetracycline" precipitantCode="F8VB5M810T" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="metoclopramide" precipitantCode="L4YEB44I46" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="indinavir" precipitantCode="N0000005722 | 5W6YA9PKKH" effect="C54356"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="indinavir" precipitantCode="N0000005722 | 5W6YA9PKKH" effect="C54358"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="dietary fat" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54355"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="dietary fat" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54602"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Pharmacokinetic interaction" precipitant="dietary fat" precipitantCode="NO MAP" effect="C54605"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="cyp2c19 | inhibitors" precipitantCode="N0000182140"/>
<LabelInteraction type="Unspecified interaction" precipitant="cyp2c19 substrates" precipitantCode="NO MAP"/>

</LabelInteractions></Label>